<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CHAPTER XIX.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>1845</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed Lovers: a Milanese Story of the Seventeenth Century. With The Column of Infamy by Alessandro Manzoni. In Three Volumes</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
          <date>1845</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Henry Francis C. Logan</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="English_1845_cap19">
        <p n="1">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10047">Whosoever, chancing to see in an ill-cultivated field a plant, a fine plant of sorrel for example, should be desirous to know whether it had sprung up from a seed ripened in the field itself, was carried there by the wind or dropped by some bird, let him ponder ever so much, he will never arrive at a satisfactory conclusion. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10048" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10082">Thus we are unable to say whether it was from the natural depth of his wisdom, or from the insinuations of Count Attilio, that the noble uncle gained the idea of employing the Father Provincial to cut in twain, in the best manner, this entangled knot. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10083" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10130">Certain it is that Attilio had not given this advice merely by chance; and although he must have expected that the jealous self-love of the uncle would revolt at so undisguised a suggestion, he was determined, at all events, to lay before him the idea of this remedy, and put him in the path which he wished him to pursue. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10131" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10160">On the other hand, this expedient was so well adapted to the uncle's disposition, so naturally suggested by the circumstances, that one could have wagered anything that it had been his own idea. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10161" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10193">The affair was whether one of his name, his own nephew, in an open quarrel, should remain the vanquished party; this was a position nearly touching the reputation of that power which he had so near at heart. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10194" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10223">The satisfaction which his nephew could take himself, would be a remedy even worse than the evil, a sowing of fresh misfortunes; and it was necessary to prevent this in some way or other, and that without loss of time. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10224" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10252">Should he command him immediately to leave his castle, he would perhaps not be obeyed; and even should he be, this was surrendering the field of battle, a retreat of the palace before the convent. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10253" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10306">Commands, legal force, terrors of this nature, were of no value against an adversary of this description; both the regular and secular clergy were entirely placed beyond the power of any legal jurisdiction; and not only their persons, but their habitations also, enjoyed this privilege, as our reader must know, should he have perused no other history than ours. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10307" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10338">All, therefore, that could be done with such an adversary was to endeavour to remove him, and the means by which this was to be obtained was the Father Provincial, upon whose will his stay or departure depended. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="2">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10339" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10366">Now, there existed between the uncle the Count, and the Father Provincial, an old acquaintance; they saw each other rarely, but always met with a great demonstration of friendship, and with reiterated offers of service. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10367" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10436">At all times, it is better to have to do with a man who is placed above a number of individuals, than with a subordinate who only sees his own affair, only feels his own passion, and who only troubles himself about his own business; whilst the other discovers in a moment a hundred relationships, a hundred consequences, a hundred interests, a hundred things to avoid, a hundred means of salvation; and thus, can choose from a hundred different schemes. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="3">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10437" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10463">Having well considered everything, the uncle one day invited the Father Provincial to dinner, and arranged that he should meet a circle of guests chosen with the greatest discretion. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10464" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10597">There were relatives of the highest nobility, people whose very name was a title, and who alone by their behaviour, by a certain native confidence, by a lordly disdain, by speaking of great things in familiar terms, succeeded, even without intending it, in impressing and reviving every moment, in the minds of all present, the idea of their superiority and power; besides these nobles, there were also among the guests some clients, attached to the house by hereditary dependence, and to the host by a servitude of all their lifetime; who, beginning with the soup to express "Yes," with their mouths, their ears, their eyes, with their heads, with their bodies, and with all their soul, by the time dessert arrived, had caused one to forget how a man might say "No." At table, the noble host soon contrived that the discourse should turn upon his embassy to Madrid. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="4">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10598" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10610">One road leads to Rome; with him many led to Madrid. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10611" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10660">He spoke of the Court, of the Count-Duke, of the ministers, of the governor's family, of the bull-fights, which he could describe very well, having enjoyed a distinguished place, and of the Escurial, which he could render a minute account of, a servant of the Count-Duke's having conducted him through all its apartments. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10661" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10709">For some time all the guests remained a silent audience, attentive alone to him; afterwards, however, they divided themselves into separate groups; and he then continued to relate more of these fine things, as though in confidence, to the Father Provincial, who was seated near him, and let him talk, talk, talk. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10710" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10749">But at a certain point, he gave a turn to the discourse, passed on from Madrid, from court to court, from dignity to dignity, and at length spoke of Cardinal Barberini, who was a Capuchin, and nothing less than brother of the then Pope Urban VIII. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10750" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10779">The noble uncle was here obliged to allow others beside himself to talk, himself listen, and recollect that, after all, this company was not composed of people dependent upon him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10780" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10795">Shortly after, when they had risen from table, he begged the Father Provincial to step aside with him into another apartment. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="5">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10796" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10806">Two powers, two hoary-headed men of consummate experience, found themselves front to front. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10807" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10874">The magnificent Signor made the most reverend Father take a seat, then seated himself, and commenced in these words:—"Considering the old friendship which exists between us, I have thought I might speak to you of an affair of common interest to us both, which might be concluded between us, without having recourse to other means, which could— And therefore, frankly, with my heart in my hand, I will tell you what all this is about, and I am certain that in two words we shall be perfectly of accord. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10875" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10887">Tell me whether, in your convent of Pescarenico, there is not a Father Cristoforo da ——?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="6">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10888" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10893">The Father Provincial gave a sign of affirmation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10894" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10934">"Nay, I request your reverence to tell me frankly, as a friend,—whether this individual—this Father—I know nothing of him personally; it is true that I know divers Capuchin fathers, excellent men, zealous, prudent, humble;—I have been a friend to this order from my youth. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10935" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10974">But, in all rather large families, there is always some member, some individual — and I know from certain adventures that this Father Cristoforo is a man — rather a friend to disputes, — who has not all that prudence, all that reverence. — I would bet that more than once he has given your reverence something to think about." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="7">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10975" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11071">"I understand; there is another intrigue," thought the Father Provincial, "it is my fault. I knew that this blessed Cristoforo was the right sort of friar to send from pulpit to pulpit, and not the man to leave six months in one place, especially in a convent down in the country. Oh!" he pursued aloud, "really I am sorry to hear that your magnificence has formed such an idea of Father Cristoforo; for as much as I know, he is a religious man of the most exemplary conduct within the convent, and held in the highest esteem without." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="8">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11072" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11113">"I understand very well; your reverence must — however, as a sincere friend, I will inform you of a thing which it will be useful to you to know, and even should you already be informed, I can, without betraying my trust, lay before you certain consequences, certain — possibilities; I say nothing more. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11114" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11153">This Father Cristoforo we know has taken under his protection a man of that part of the country, a man — your reverence will have heard speak of him; the man who has caused so much talk by escaping from the officers of justice, after having done, that terrible day of San Martino, such things — things — Lorenza Tramaglino, in short!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="9">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11154" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11188">"Ahi!" thought the Father Provincial; but said, "this circumstance I was not aware of, but your magMagnificence knows very well that a part of our duty is to go in search of wanderers from the right path and bring them back—— </note>
        </p>
        <p n="10">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11189" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11198">"Good: but the protection of transgressors of a certain kind! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11199" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11244">These are difficult things—delicate affairs——" And here, instead of puffing out his cheeks and blowing, he pressed together his lips, and drew in as much air as he was usually in the habit of breathing forth; then he continued, "I have considered it, as well to give you an idea of this circumstance; for, if ever your Excellence—— Some step might be taken at Rome. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11245" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11258">I do not know anything—and from Rome something might arrive——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="11">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11259" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11304">"I am much obliged to your magnificence for this information; however, I am certain that, if inquiries were made regarding this affair, it would be found that Father Cristoforo has had no intercourse with the man of whom you spoke, except with the desire of recalling him to his duty. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11305" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11309">I know Father Cristoforo myself." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="12">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11310" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11327">"Such being the case, your reverence will know better than I what sort of a character this man bore when he belonged to the world, and also the frolics of his youth." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="13">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11328" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11361">"It is the glory of our habit, Signor Count, that a man, who in the world has made himself notorious, clothed with this garment becomes another being, and since Father Cristoforo wears this habit——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="14">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11362" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11381">"I should like to believe it; I say it from my heart, I should like to believe it; but sometimes, as the proverb says—the habit does not make the monk." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="15">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11382" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11415">The proverb did not seem very à-propos; but the Count had substituted it in haste in place of another which he had had upon his tongue's end — "the wolf changes his skin, but not his nature." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="16">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11416" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11422">"I have proofs," continued he, "I have testimonies —" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="17">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11423" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11447">"If you know positively," said the Father Provincial, "that this religious man has committed some error, and every one is liable to err, I shall consider it a real favour the being informed of it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11448" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11458">I am the Superior, unworthily certainly, but nevertheless I am the Superior, and as such it is precisely my duty to correct and to mediate." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="18">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11459" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11492">"I will tell you: there is connected with the unpleasant circumstance of the Father's open protection of the person of whom I have told you another vexatious thing which could — But between us we will settle all at once. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11493" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11510">And this is, I say, that this same Father Cristoforo has begun to wage war against my nephew Don Rodrigo" * * * </note>
        </p>
        <p n="19">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11511" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11519">"Oh, but I am sorry for this, I am sorry for this; really I am sorry for this!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="20">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11520" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11535">"My nephew is young, lively, feels keenly, and is unaccustomed to provocation —" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="21">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11536" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11545">"It shall be my duty to take cognizance of a fact like the present. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11546" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11586">As I have already said to your magnificence, and I speak with a Signor who has no less sense of justice than knowledge of the world, we are all flesh and liable to err — now in this way, now in another; and if Father Cristoforo should have failed in the fulfilment of his duty —" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="22">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11587" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11611">"But your reverence sees that these are affairs, as I have already said, which may be terminated between us, which may be kept secret here; things with which to meddle, would only be to make worse of the matter. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11612" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11686">You know how things will occur; these quarrels, these dissensions, given rise to in the commencement by some trifle, and which go on, and go on — and does one desire to get at the bottom of them, one either can never reach the end, or else a hundred fresh annoyances start forth, suppress, or put a stop to the affair; my very reverend Father, suppress, or put a stop to it; my nephew is young; the monk, from all we hear, has still all the spirits, all the inclinations of a youth; and it is for us, who have reached our years — only too many in number, eh, most reverend Father? </note>
        </p>
        <p n="23">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11687" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11735">Should any one have been present at this conversation, he would have stood in the position of a person at the theatre when, in the midst of an opera, through some blunder a scene is removed before its time, exposing a singer to view, who at this moment, never thinking of an audience, is conversing freely with his companion. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11736" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11767">The countenance and the manner of the noble uncle when he said, "only too many!" were entirely natural; this time he was no longer the politician; it was the pure truth that his many years caused him vexation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11768" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11781">Not that he wept over the times that were past, over the fire, the graces of his youth; — these were frivolities, follies, annoyances! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11782" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11810">The cause of his sorrow was a more solid and important one; it was that he hoped for a higher station when this should be vacant, and feared that he should not arrive in time. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11811" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11850">Having obtained which, one might be certain that he would no longer trouble himself about his years, he would have desired nothing beyond, and would have died content, as all people who very much desire a thing say they shall do when once they have attained their object. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11851" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11871">But let us leave him to speak for himself. "It is for us," he continued, "to have judgment for the young, and to repair their misdeeds. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11872" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11893">Fortunately we are yet in time; the affair has not yet made a noise, it is still the case of a good principiis obsta. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11894" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11898">Let us remove the fire from the straw. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11899" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11923">Sometimes an individual who does no good, or who might cause disturbances in one place, turns out well in another. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11924" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11934">Your reverence will know well where to find a convenient niche for the monk. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11935" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11979">There is also another circumstance, which is, that he, having become suspicious to a certain person, might himself desire to be removed; and thus by placing him in a situation some little way off, we give him a journey and render good service to two parties; and thus all is well arranged, or rather there is nothing done amiss." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="24">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11980" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12077">The Father Provincal had expected this conclusion from the very commencement of the conversation. "Ah, heaven!" thought he, "I see what thou wouldst drive at; as usual, when a poor Friar has a quarrel with some of you, or with only one, or gives you the slightest umbrage, the Superior, without seeking to learn whether he is in the right or in the wrong, must immediately have him removed." When the Count had ended, and sent forth a long-drawn breath, which was equivalent to a full-stop, the Father Provincal said, "I know very well what the Signor Count would say; but before taking a step——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="27">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12078" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12112">"It is a step, and it is not a step, very reverend Father; it is a natural thing, a common thing; and unless this expedient is adopted, and that too speedily, I foresee a mountain of irregularities, an Iliade of "woes. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12113" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12123">A folly—I will not believe my nephew would——I am here to prevent that. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12124" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12168">But at the point which the affair has now reached, unless we put an end to it, and that without loss of time, it is impossible that it should cease, or remain secret,—and then, it is no longer my nephew alone——A whole wasp's-nest is excited, my very reverend Father. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12169" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12175">You see we are a house, we have relatives——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="28">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12176" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12176">"That is manifest." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="29">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12177" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12193">"You understand me; they are all people who have blood in their veins, and that in this world——is something. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12194" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12229">Punctilio enters into the affair; it becomes of general interest, and then——even he, who is the friend of peace——It will be a real grief for me to be obliged to find myself.——I——who have always been so prepossessed in favour of the Capuchin fathers——! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12230" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12282">Your Fathers, in order to do good, as is their custom, to the great edification of the public, have need of peace, should avoid contention, and live harmoniously with those who——and then they have relatives in the world, — and these little points of honour, however important, extend, spread themselves, and involve—half the world. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12283" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12296">I find myself intrusted with this blessed charge, which obliges me to preserve a certain decorum. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12297" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12312">His Excellence—the Signori, my colleagues—it will become a party affair—all the more owing to the other circumstances. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12313" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12318">You know how such affairs proceed." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="30">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12319" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12377">"Certainly," said the Father Provincial, "Father Cristoforo is a preacher; and I had already some thought——I am asked——But at the present moment, in circumstances such as these, it might appear a punishment, and a punishment before having well brought to light——" "No punishment; O no! a prudent precaution, a simple means, to prevent the evils which could — I have explained myself." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="31">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12378" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12390">"Between the Signor Count and myself, the affair remains thus, I understand. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12391" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12411">But the facts being such as they have been reported to your Excellence, it appears to me impossible that something of all this should not have transpired in the country. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12412" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12441">There are everywhere instigators to mischief, busybodies — or at least idle malicious people who find extreme delight in seeing the nobles and the monks come to open strife; they follow the scent, they make malicious observations, they gossip. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12442" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12458">Every one has to observe a proper decorum; and I, as the Superior (unworthy though I be), have an express duty. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12459" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12497">The honour of my habit — is not my own affair — it is a trust which — The Signor, your nephew, being of so warm a temperament, as your Excellence says, might consider this as a satisfaction given him, — and I do not say glorify himself, and triumph in it, but —" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="32">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12498" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12502">"Does the very reverend Father jest? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12503" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12539">My nephew is a cavalier, who is of consideration in the world — according to his standing and his worth; but before me he is a child; and he will do neither more nor nor less than what I prescribe. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12540" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12549">I will tell you moreover, that my nephew shall know nothing of all this. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12550" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12556">What need have we to render him an account of our actions? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12557" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12573">These are affairs which, as good friends, we transact between ourselves, and between us they must remain. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12574" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12585">Give no thought about that; I should be accustomed to keep silence." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12586" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12587">And here he drew a deep breath. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12588" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12596">"And as to the gossips," he continued, "what would you have them say? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12597" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12610">It is such a common thing to "see a monk go to preach in another place! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12611" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12628">And then we who see—who foresee,—we who are concerned,—we ought not to trouble ourselves about these idle tales." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="33">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12629" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12657">"However, in order to prevent them, it would be as well on this occasion, that the Signor, your nephew, should make some demonstration, give some visible sign of friendship, of regard, not on our account, but for the habit ——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="34">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12658" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12661">"Certainly, certainly; this is but just. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12662" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12678">However, there is no necessity; I know that the Capuchins always meet with the reception they ought to do from my nephew. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12679" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12696">He does this from inclination; it is the humour of the family; and besides, he knows he is doing what is agreeable to me. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12697" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12707">For the rest, in this case—as it is somewhat an extraordinary one—it is but right. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12708" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12719">Leave me to act, very reverend Father, I will command my nephew. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12720" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12735">That is, it will be necessary to insinuate it to him with prudence, so that he may not learn what has passed between us. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12736" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12748">For I should not wish us to put on a plaster where there is no wound. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12749" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12773">And from what we have concluded, the sooner this takes place the better; and if some employment should be found for him at some distance—so as to remove every occasion ——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="35">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12774" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12791">"Precisely at this moment I have a request from Rimini for a preacher. Perhaps I should, even without any other motive, have cast my eyes upon ——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="36">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12792" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12797">"Very convenient, very convenient. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12798" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12799">And when ——?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="37">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12800" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12808">"Since the thing must be done, it shall be done speedily." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="38">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12809" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12817">"Speedily, speedily, my very reverend Father;" better to-day than to-morrow. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12818" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12839">And," he continued, rising from his seat, "if either I or my family could be of any service to our good Capuchin fathers----" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="39">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12840" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12861">"We know from experience the goodness of your house," said the Father Provincial, who had also risen, and followed his conqueror towards the door. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="40">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12862" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12878">"We have extinguished a spark," said the other, stopping for a moment; "a spark, very reverend Father, which could have caused a great conflagration. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12879" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12888">Between good friends, with a few words, mighty matters may be settled." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="41">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12889" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12911">When they had arrived at the door, the Count opened it, and would absolutely insist upon the Father going out first; they then entered the other apartment, and joined the rest of the company. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="42">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12912" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12932">A great deal of care, a great deal of art, and many important words, were employed by this Signor in a negotiation like the present; but he produced corresponding effects. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12933" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12955">In fact, by this conversation which we have reported, he succeeded in making Fra Cristoforo travel on foot from Pescarenico to Rimini, which is a good journey. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="43">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12956" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12971">One evening a Capuchin from Milan arrived at Pescarenico with a packet of letters from the Superior of the convent. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12972" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12985">Within them was contained the order for Fra Cristoforo to betake himself to Rimini, where he must preach during Lent. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12986" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13024">The letter addressed to the Superior brought instructions to insinuate to the aforesaid Friar, that he should lay aside every thought regarding affairs which he might perchance have begun in the place he must now leave, and that he should keep up no correspondence; the brother who officiated as porter should accomcompany him on his journey. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13025" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13070">The Superior said nothing that evening; but the next morning he ordered Fra Cristoforo to be called, shewed him the commands, and told him to go and take his basket, his staff, his towel, and his girdle, and to set forth immediately with the companion who was offered him. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="44">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13071" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13083">I leave it to my readers to think whether this was a blow for our Friar. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13084" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13131">Renzo, Lucia, and Agnese presented themselves immediately to his mind; and he exclaimed internally—"O God! what will these unfortunates do when I am no longer here!" But he raised his eyes to heaven, and accused himself of want of confidence, of having believed himself necessary to any one. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13132" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13170">He crossed his hands upon his breast in sign of obedience, and bowed his head before the Superior, who, drawing him aside, gave him the other piece of information, partly as advice, partly as a command. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13171" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13230">Fra Cristoforo went to his cell, took his basket, placed in it his breviary, his Lent sermons, and his bread of pardon, girded his robe with a leathern girdle, took leave of his brethren, who were then in the convent, and lastly went to receive a blessing from the Superior, after which, with his companion, he departed by the road he had been ordered to pursue. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="45">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13231" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13256">We have already said, that Don Rodrigo, more determined than ever to bring his fine enterprise to an issue, had resolved to seek the aid of a terrible man. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13257" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13298">We can give neither the name, the surname, nor the title of this personage, nor dare we even form any conjecture regarding him—a thing all the more strange, as we find mention of this individual in more than one book (we speak of printed books), in more than one book of this time. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13299" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13332">That this is the same personage, the identity of the facts leaves not the slightest doubt, but everywhere is observed a great care to avoid the name, as though this name must burn the pen and the hand of the writer. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13333" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13361">Francesco Rivola, in his life of Cardinal Federigo Borromeo, having to speak of this man, calls him, "a Signor, as powerful through his wealth, as illustrious from his birth;" and here he stops. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13362" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13462">Giuseppe Ripamonti, who, in the fifth book of the fifth decade of his Storia Patria, mentions him at greater length, speaks only of him, as *a certain person, a man, this man, this personage.* "I will relate," he says, in his beautiful Latin, "the deed of a certain man who, belonging to the very first nobility of the city, had fixed his abode in a certain part of the country near the frontiers; and there, insuring himself safety through his many crimes, set at nought judges, decrees, every manner of magistracy and sovereignty. He led a perfectly independent life. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13463" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13488">He offered an asylum to outlaws, having once himself been outlawed; afterwards returning, as though nothing had been—" We will, however, borrow from the author a few other passages, which will not only be found very à propos, as confirmation, but will also explain the recital of our Anonymous, with whom we still travel on. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="46">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13489" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13538">To do that which was prohibited by the laws, or was rendered difficult by any power whatsoever to be the arbitrator; the supreme judge in the affairs of others, without any other interest than the mere love of command; to be feared by all, even by those who made themselves feared by every one; such had always been the ruling passions of this man. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13539" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13565">From his earliest youth, seeing and hearing speak of so many oppressors, of so much contention, at the sight of so many tyrants, he had experienced a mingled sentiment of anger and impatient envy. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13566" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13603">Young, and living in a city, he allowed no occasion to pass by, or rather he went in search of such, in which he could contend with the most famous individuals of this profession, oppose them, measure his strength against theirs, make them subservient, or compel them to seek his friendship. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13604" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13659">Possessing greater wealth, and a more numerous retinue than most of the others, and superior to all, perhaps, in constancy and ardour, he obliged many to withdraw themselves from every species of rivalry, many he thoroughly chastised; in many he found his friends, not exactly friends on an equal footing with himself, but such as alone could please him, subordinate friends, friends who would recognise their own inferiority, and who would stand on his left hand. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13660" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13700">In truth, however, he came at length to be the active servant, the tool of all these men; they did not fail when in difficulty, to request the aid of so powerful an auxiliary; for him to have drawn back would have caused his reputation to decline, he would have been faithless to his undertaking. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13701" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13741">So that both on his own account, and on account of others, he had to commit such crimes, that, at length, neither his name, nor his parentage, nor his friends, nor his own audacity, were able longer to support him against the sentence of banishment pronounced upon him, or against the animosity of so many powers; and he was obliged to give way, and quit the state. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13742" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13755">I believe, that connected with this circumstance is a singular fact related by Ripamonti. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13756" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13803">"Once, when this man was obliged to fly his country, such was his secrecy, respect, and timidity, that he traversed the city on horseback, followed by a troop of dogs and accompanied by the sound of trumpets, and in passing before the palace, left with the guard an impertinent message for the governor. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="47">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13804" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13840">During his absence, he did not desist from his usual practices, or neglect to correspond with such of his friends as remained united with him—to translate literally from Ripamonti, "in a secret league of atrocious counsels and horrible deeds." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13841" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13863">It appears even that he then joined with still higher personages in certain new and terrible undertakings, of which the historian, whom we have already quoted, speaks with a mysterious brevity. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13864" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13895">"Foreign princes likewise had many a time recourse to his assistance in important homicides, and often they sent from far supplies of people to serve under his orders." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="48">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13896" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13949">At length (it is not known after what space of time), either the sentence of banishment having been removed through some powerful intercession, or the audacity of this man standing in place of freedom, he resolved to return home, and in fact, did return, not however to Milan, but to a castle situated on the frontiers of the Bergamascan territory, which then, as every one knows, belonged to the Venetian states. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13950" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13989">"This house," I again quote from Ripamonti, "was like an office for sanguinary warrants; you only saw domestics upon whose heads a price was set, and whose business was that of cutting off heads; neither the cook, nor even the scullion, were guiltless of murder; the very hands of the children were stained with blood." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13990" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14027">Besides this charming family, he had, the same historian affirms, another, composed of similar members, dispersed and as it were quartered at various places in the two states upon the limits of which he resided—a family always ready to obey his orders. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="49">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14028" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14055">All the tyrants who lived within a considerable distance had been obliged, either upon one occasion or another, to choose between the friendship or the enmity of this extraordinary tyrant. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14056" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14080">But things had gone so ill with the first who had attempted to resist him, that no one ever again desired to try the experiment. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14081" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14099">Yet, let you watch ever so much over your own affairs, let you stand alone, it was impossible to keep independent of him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14100" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14174">One of his messengers would arrive to intimate that you should abandon such an enterprise, that you should cease to molest such a debtor, or things similar to these; and it was necessary to reply either yes or no. When one party went with the homage of a vassal, to lay before him an affair, the other party would, find himself forced to the bitter alternative of choosing between submitting to his decision or of declaring himself this tyrant's enemy, which was equivalent to being, as was said in former times, consumptive in the last degree. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14175" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14210">Many people being in the wrong had recourse to him, in order effectually to be in the right; and others being in the right to gain so powerful a patronage, and thus prevent their adversaries from enjoying any means of access themselves; and thus all these became especially his dependents. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="50">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14211" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14274">Sometimes it happened that a defenceless man, oppressed and tormented by some noble, would fly to him, and he, taking the side of the oppressed, would force the oppressor to desist, to repair the evil he had done, and to sue for pardon; but should the noble stand firm, he would wage war against him, compel him to abandon the places in which he had tyranised, or even make him pay a more speedy and terrible homage. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14275" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14315">And, in these cases, this name so feared and abhorred has been for a moment blessed; for I will not say this justice, but this satisfaction, could not have been obtained in those times by any other power, either public or private. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14316" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14336">Oftener, nay generally, his power had been and was the servant of iniquitous desires, atrocious revenge, or of proud caprice. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14337" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14383">But the different uses he made of this power always produced the same effect—that of impressing in the minds of men a high idea of that which he could will and put in execution, spite of justice and injustice, those two great obstacles to the human will which so often cause men to retrace their steps. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14384" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14431">"The fame of ordinary tyrants generally was confined to their own neighbourhood, where they were the richest and most powerful of the inhabitants: each district had its own; and they all resembled each other so much, that there was no reason why people should occupy themselves about those which did not immediately concern themselves. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14432" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14470">But the fame of our tyrant had already for a long time been spread throughout the Milanese; everywhere his life was related by the populace, his name signified something irresistible, strange, and fabulous. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14471" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14494">The suspicion that his colleagues and assassins were everywhere, also contributed to keep alive the memory of him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14495" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14534">These were only suspicions, for who would have openly confessed to being one of his dependents? But every tyrant could be one of his colleagues, every robber belong to him; and the uncertainty itself rendered more vast the idea, more intense the terror of the thing. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14535" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14594">And every time that there appeared faces of unknown bravoes, more wicked than usual, and upon the occurrence of any enormous crime, the author of which, at first, could neither be indicated nor divined; there was murmured the name of him, whom we, thanks to the blessed circumspection of our author, shall be forced to call the Unknown. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="51">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14595" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14643">From the castle of this personage to the palace of Don Rodrigo it was not more than seven miles; and no sooner had the latter become lord and tyrant, than he had perceived that, living at this short distance from such a personage, it was impossible to carry on this trade without either coming to strife or living in peace with him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14644" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14684">Therefore he had offered himself, and had become one of his friends, after the same manner as all the others it is to be understood; had rendered him more than one service — the manuscript says nothing more regarding this circumstance — and had each time received promises of recompense and assistance when occasion for these should offer. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14685" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14706">He, however, took great care to conceal such a friendship, or at least to prevent its being seen how intimate and of what nature it was. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14707" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14805">Don Rodrigo certainly desired to play the tyrant, but not the lawless tyrant; the profession was for him a means not an end; he wished to reside at liberty in the city, to enjoy the comforts, the amusements, the honours of civilized life. And to do this it was necessary he should observe a certain respect, pay some regard to his relations, cultivate the friendship of high and mighty personages, and keep one hand upon the balance of justice, so as to cause it, when necessary, to sink on his side; to retard it, or even, on certain occasions, to let it fall upon the head of some one who, by this means, could be more easily reached than by the weapons of private violence. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14806" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14838">Now the intimacy, or it would be better to say a league, with a man of this description, with a declared enemy of legal power, would certainly have been of no service to him, particularly with the Count his uncle. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14839" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14912">As much of the friendship as could not be concealed might pass for an unavoidable connexion with a man whose ill-will was so dangerous, and thus he might be excused by his position; for he who has the care of providing for the general safety, but who either has not the desire, or does not find the means, ends by consenting that every one shall himself look after his own affairs; or if he does not expressly consent, he at least closes an eye. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="52">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap19-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14913" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14945">One morning Don Rodrigo set forth on horseback, equipped for the chase, accompanied by a small escort of bravoes on foot; Griso beside his stirrup, and four others behind, and in this manner he directed his course towards the castle of the Unknown. </note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>