<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CHAPTER XV.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>1845</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed Lovers: a Milanese Story of the Seventeenth Century. With The Column of Infamy by Alessandro Manzoni. In Three Volumes</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
          <date>1845</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Henry Francis C. Logan</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="English_1845_cap15">
        <p n="1">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10040">The host, perceiving that the game was being carried too far, approached Renzo, and, politely beseeching the others to leave him alone, shook him by one arm and endeavoured to make him understand that he had better go to bed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10041" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10093">But Renzo returned always to the same subjects, *to the name, the surname, to the proclamations, and to the good lads.* However, these words, *bed and sleep,* repeated so often in his ear, at length entered his head, they made him feel somewhat more distinctly the necessity of that which they signified, and procured a lucid interval. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10094" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10127">The little sense which returned to him, caused him, in a certain way, to remark that the greater portion had left him, in the same manner that the last expiring taper in an illumination shews the others already extinguished. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10128" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10152">He formed a resolution, he supported himself upon the table; attempted once or twice to rise; sighed, staggered, and, at the third attempt, aided by the host, was upon his feet. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10153" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10186">The host, supporting him all the time, made him come from between the table and the bench, and taking in one hand the light, with the other partly conducted and partly dragged him along, in the best manner he could, to the staircase door. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10187" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10246">There Renzo, hearing the uproar of salutations which the company shouted after him, hastily turned round; and if the one who supported him had not quickly seized him by the arm, he would have had a violent fall. He turned round, and then with the arm which remained at liberty he began tracing and writing in the air certain salutations, very much after the fashion of a Solomon's knot. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="2">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10247" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10278">"Come, to bed, to bed," said the host, dragging him along; he pushed him through the doorway, then, with still more fatigue, supported him to the top of the little staircase, and into the little chamber which he had destined for him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10279" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10328">At the sight of the bed which awaited him, Renzo rejoiced, and regarded his host most lovingly with two small eyes, which now gleamed brighter than ever, now vanished like two fire-flies; he endeavoured to balance himself upon his legs, and stretched forth his hand to caress the host's cheek in sign of friendship and gratitude, but he did not succeed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10329" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10367">"Excellent host!" he however managed to say, "now I see that thou art a worthy man, thus to give a poor lad a bed; but this nonsense about name and surname, that was not like a worthy man. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10368" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10377">Fortunately, however, I am also—" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="3">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10378" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10420">The host, who did not think that he could still be so collected in his ideas—the host, who knew from a long experience that men in this state are even more than usually liable to change their opinion, wished to profit by this lucid interval, and made another attempt. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10421" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10443">"My dear fellow," said he, with a very gentle voice and manner, "I have not, indeed, done this with the desire of troubling you, or of prying into your affairs. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10444" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10459">What would you have me do? It is the law; we also are obliged to obey it; besides, we are the very first who suffer the penalty imposed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10460" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10463">It is better to conform. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10464" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10468">After all, what is all this?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10469" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10473">A mighty affair! The saying two words. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10474" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10506">Not in the least important on their own account, but merely to do me a favour; come—here, alone with me, under four eyes, we will transact our business; tell me your name, and then go to bed with a quiet mind. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="4">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10507" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10524">"Ah, rascal!" exclaimed Renzo; "knave! Thou art returned again into the field with thy infamous name, surname, and business!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="5">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10525" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10532">"Hush! you fool; and go to bed," said the host. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="6">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10533" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10544">But Renzo continued even more loudly, "I understand thou art also in this league. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10545" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10549">Wait, wait, I will settle thee, I will." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10550" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10566">And turning his head towards the staircase, he shouted as loud as he could, "Friends! the host is in the ——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="7">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10567" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10590">"I have said this in jest," cried the other in Renzo's face, and pushed him towards the bed; "in jest; didst thou not understand it was only in jest?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="8">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10591" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10596">"Ah! in jest! now thou speakest well. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10597" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10604">Since thou hast spoken in jest —— These are proper things to jest about." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10605" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10610">And he fell prostrate on the bed. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="9">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10611" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10624">"Come, undress yourself quickly," said the host, and to his advice he added his assistance, of which there was much need. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10625" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10651">When Renzo had pulled off his doublet, he seized it suddenly, and felt with his hands in the pockets, to see whether there was any little hoard there. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10652" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10701">He found it; and thinking that the following day his guest would have to account with quite other people than he, and that most probably this hoard would fall into hands out of which a host would never again be able to get it, he wished to see, at least, whether he would not now settle his little affair. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="10">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10702" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10711">"You are a good fellow, an honest man, are you not?" said he. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10712" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10731">"Good fellow, honest man," replied Renzo, his fingers busied with the buttons of his hose, which he had not yet taken off. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="11">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10732" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10749">"Well," said the host, "settle with me now my little bill, for to-morrow I am obliged to leave home on account of certain affairs of mine—" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="12">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10750" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10766">"That is but just," returned Renzo; "I am a rogue, yet an honest man—But where is my money—Go and search for the money, now!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="13">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10767" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10797">"There it is," said the host; and, putting into operation all his practice, all his patience, all his skill, he succeeded in making out his reckoning with Renzo, and in paying himself. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="14">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10798" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10818">"Lend me a hand to finish undressing," said Renzo; "I also know, as well as you, that I have a heavy sleep upon me." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="15">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10819" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10841">The host gave him the required assistance; and more than that he drew the coverlid over him, and roughly wished him "good-night;" but our Renzo snored already. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10842" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10940">Then, governed by that species of attraction which sometimes induces us to gaze upon an object of hatred, as well as of love, and which is, perhaps, no other than the desire of knowing that which operates so strongly upon our soul,—he stopped a moment to contemplate this guest, who had caused him such vexation; and, raising the light above the sleeper, and with his outstretched hands casting the rays full upon his face, much in the same attitude that Psyche is painted when she stands contemplating the form of her unknown consort,—"great ass!" he said, mentally apostrophising the poor unconscious sleeper, "thou hast properly gone in search of thy own misfortune. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10941" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10950">To-morrow thou canst tell me how it pleases thy own taste. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10951" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10971">Clowns who wander through the world, without knowing in which quarter the sun rises, with no other aim than that of getting yourselves and your neighbours into trouble. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="16">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10972" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10988">This said, or thought, he drew back the light, moved away, went out of the chamber, and locked the door. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10989" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11016">Arrived on the landing-place, he called the hostess, whom he told to leave her children in the care of one of her servants, and descend to the kitchen, there to preside in his stead. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11017" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11042">"I am obliged to go out, thanks to a stranger who has arrived here for my misfortune," he added; and related in a few words this vexatious accident. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11043" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11056">Then he again added— "Have an eye upon every thing; but above all, be prudent in this cursed business. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="17">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11057" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11079">Down stairs, we have a handful of dissolute fellows, who, partly through drinking, and partly because they are naturally vile, say all manner of things. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11080" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11083">Enough, if any foolhardy——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="18">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11084" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11095">"O! I am no child; I know well enough myself, what must be done. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11096" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11103">Until now, it does not seem to me it can be said——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="19">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11104" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11196">"Good, good,—and take care that they pay; and as to their discourses about the Superintendent of Provisions, about the Governor Ferrer, and the Council of Ten, and the knights of Spain and France, and about all such nonsense, do not seem to pay any attention; because if thou shouldst contradict them, that might bring forth immediate evil, and if thou shouldst agree with them that could occasion evil in the future; and thou knowest that those who sometimes speak the strongest—enough; when certain questions are asked, turn aside thy head, and say, 'I am coming,' as though some one called thee from some other part of the room. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11197" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11204">I will try and return as soon as possible." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11205" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11250">Having said this, he descended with her into the kitchen, cast a glance around to see that there was nothing fresh, and taking down from a peg his hat and cloak, took his stick out of a corner, repeated by an expressive glance towards his wife the instructions he had just given, and set forth. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11251" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11332">But, whilst busied with these operations, he had resumed in his mind the apostrophe commenced at poor Renzo's bed, and pursued it whilst he walked on through the streets. "Blockhead of a mountaineer!" For, however much Renzo had desired to conceal the fact, this characteristic had shewn itself in his every word, in his pronunciation, in his appearance, in his manners. "On a day like this, by force of policy, by force of judgment, I had got off well; and then thou must needs come at the end, and spoil my egg in the basket! </note>
        </p>
        <p n="20">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11333" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11343">Is there a dearth of inns in Milan, that thou must precisely stumble upon mine? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11344" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11362">If thou hadst only come alone, I should have closed my eyes for this evening, and to-morrow I would have made thee hear reason. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11363" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11395">But no, my gentleman came in company, and in the company of an informer, to make the matter better!" At each step which he took the host encountered solitary passengers, or troops and companies of people, who murmured among themselves as they passed by. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="21">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11396" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11429">At this point in his silent discourse he saw a patrole of soldiers approach; and drawing himself aside, so as to let them pass by, he glanced at them out of the corner of his eye, and said to himself, — "there go fool-punishers! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11430" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11456">And thou great donkey! because thou hast seen a few people in movement making a noise, hast got it into thy head, that the world was about to change itself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11457" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11474">And upon this good foundation thou hast ruined thyself, and hast wished also to ruin me; which is not just. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11475" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11494">I did all in my power to save thee; and thou fool, in exchange, hast wanted but little to turn my hostel topsy-turvy. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11495" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11506">Now it will be for thee to extricate thyself from this troublesome business; as for myself, I shall think about my own affairs. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11507" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11518">As though I wanted to know thy name out of curiosity! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11519" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11529">What does it matter to me whether thou art called Taddeo, or Bartolommeo? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11530" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11554">And what a great pleasure I must have in taking a pen in my hand! But you are not the only people who desire that things should go on after your own fashion. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11555" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11574">I know very well myself that there are proclamations which are counted as nothing; a fine piece of news this, for a mountaineer to come and tell you! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11575" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11585">But thou dost not know, perhaps, that the proclamations against landlords count for something. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11586" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11615">And thou wilt endeavour to change the world, and wilt speak; and yet thou dost not know that when one wishes to do as the world does, and to have the proclamations in one's pocket, the first thing is to speak of them with great respect. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11616" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11642">And dost thou know, great simpleton, dost thou know what would happen to a poor landlord who should be of thy opinion, and should not demand the name of those who do him the favour to stay at his house? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11643" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11691">'Under penalty, of whoever of the aforesaid hosts, keepers of taverns, of three hundred scudi;' yes, here are three hundred scudi hatched, and a very good way to spend them too; 'to be applied, the two-thirds to the use of the royal chamber, and the other third to the use of the accuser or informer.' This beautiful swan! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11692" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11710">"And, in case of inability, five years of the galleys, or greater punishment, pecuniary or corporal, according to the will of his Excellency.' </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11711" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11726">A thousand thanks for his kindness!" And saying these words, the host touched the threshold of the hall of justice. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="23">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11727" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11775">Here, as in all other public offices, there was a great bustle; everywhere were persons occupied in issuing such orders as appeared calculated to ensure the peace of the day following, so as to remove all pretext for revolt, and cool the minds of those who desired fresh disorders, and also to establish power in those hands accustomed to exercise it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11776" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11793">The number of soldiers was increased at the Superintendent's house; the ends of the streets were barricaded with beams of wood, and blocked up with carts. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11794" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11848">The bakers were ordered to make bread without intermission; couriers were despatched into the neighbouring villages, with orders to send grain into the city; nobles were deputed to attend at each bake-house from the early morning, to watch over the distribution of bread, and to keep by their fine speeches and their authority the unquiet spirits in check. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11849" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11925">But to give, as the saying is, a blow to the hoop and another to the cask, and to render these arrangements still more efficacious, by infusing a little terror into them, they even set about thinking how they should lay hands upon some of the seditious; and this was the principal care of the Capitano di Giustizia. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11926" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11978">This bloodhound had been in the field from the commencement of the tumult; and this seducing Ambrogio Fusella was, as our host had said, a disguised informer, sent out to seize some unfortunate wretch in the fact, thus be enabled to recognise him, watch him secretly, and then deliver him up at night when quiet should have returned, or on the morrow. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="24">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11979" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12004">Having heard four words of Renzo's sermon, he immediately calculated upon him, our hero appearing an excellent criminal and exactly a fit subject for him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12005" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12035">Finding that he was newly arrived from the country he had attempted the grand stratagem of conducting him directly to the prison, as to the surest lodging in the city, but this failed, as we have seen. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12036" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12072">However, he could carry home with him certain information regarding his name, surname, and country, besides a hundred other conjectures; so that when the host arrived there to say what he knew about Renzo, they already knew more than he. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12073" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12099">He entered the accustomed chamber and made his report; said how a stranger was come to lodge at his house, and how this same stranger would not give up his name. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="25">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12100" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12154">"You have done your duty in informing us," said a notary, laying down his pen; "but we already know this." "A fine secret," thought the host; "that requires a mighty genius!" "And we know also," continued the notary, "this much respected name." "The devil! the name also; how have they managed?" thought the host again to himself. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="29">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12155" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12166">"But," replied the notary, with a serious countenance, "but you do not tell us all candidly." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="30">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12167" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12171">"What ought I to say more?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="31">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12172" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12198">"Ah, ah! we know very well that this person brought into your hostel a quantity of bread which he had stolen, stolen by violence, became possessed of by pillage and sedition." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12199" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12211">"A man comes with a cake in his pocket; I am very likely to know where he has taken it from. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12212" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12229">And to speak as though at the point of death, I can only say I saw him with one small loaf." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="32">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12230" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12240">"Always the way with you! Always excusing yourselves—always defending yourselves! To hear you, these fellows are all honest men. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12241" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12250">How can you prove that this loaf was honestly acquired?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="33">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12251" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12261">"What have I to prove? I do not enter into the affair; I was the host." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="34">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12262" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12293">"You cannot however deny that this fellow, your customer, has had the audacity to pronounce words injurious to the proclamations, and to make indecent and irreverent jokes about the armorial bearings of his Excellency." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="35">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12294" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12310">"Pardon me, your lordship; but how can he be one of my customers if I now see him for the first time? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12311" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12339">It is the devil—speaking with all due respect—who has sent him to my house. If I had known him, your lordship sees I should not have needed to ask his name." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="36">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12340" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12359">"However, in your hostel, in your presence, have been spoken terrible things: audacious words, seditious proposals; murmurings, shouts, clamour, have been heard." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="37">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12360" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12375">"How? Would your lordship have me pay attention to nonsense which so many drunkards bawl all at once? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12376" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12385">I am a poor man, I must attend to my own interest. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12386" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12411">And then, your lordship knows that those who have a free tongue have generally a nimble hand, and all the more so when they are in a body, and—" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="38">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12412" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12426">"Yes, yes; let them do and say what pleases them;" to-morrow, to-morrow, you will see whether this wantonness has left him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12427" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12428">What do you think?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="39">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12429" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12432">"I do not think anything." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="40">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12433" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12440">"That the mob will have made itself master of Milan?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="41">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12441" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12442">"Oh, certainly!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="42">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12443" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12444">"You shall see, you shall see." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="43">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12445" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12470">"I understand very well. The king will always be the king; but whoever has taken anything will keep it, and naturally a poor father of a family will not desire to deliver it up. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12471" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12479">Your lordships have the power, and it is your lordships' business." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="44">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12480" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12485">"Have you still many people in your house?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="45">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12486" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12487">"A considerable quantity." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="46">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12488" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12493">"And what is your customer doing? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12494" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12506">Is he still shouting, exciting the people, and preparing seditions for the morrow?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="47">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12507" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12515">"This stranger, your lordship would say; he is gone to bed." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="48">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12516" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12542">"You have then a considerable number of people — enough; take care and do not let him escape." "Am I then to play the turnkey?" thought the host, but he said neither no nor yes. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="50">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12543" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12552">"Return home, and be prudent," resumed the notary. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="51">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12553" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12557">"I have always been prudent. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12558" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12568">Your lordship can say whether I ever have been brought up to justice." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="52">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12569" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12579">"And do not think that justice has lost its power." "I? Good heavens! </note>
        </p>
        <p n="53">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12580" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12590">I do not think anything. I am careful to act the landlord." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="54">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12591" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12599">"The old song; have you nothing more to say?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="55">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12600" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12604">"What else have I to say? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12605" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12609">Is not truth one." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="56">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12610" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12635">"Good! what you have deposed is sufficient for to-day. The case will be seen to; to-morrow you will inform us minutely regarding every thing that will be demanded of you." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="57">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12636" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12652">"How can I inform you of anything? I know nothing; I have scarcely head-piece enough to attend to my own affairs." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="58">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12653" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12657">"Take care, and do not let him depart." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="59">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12658" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12672">"I hope that the illustrious Signor Capitano will know that I came immediately to fulfil my duty. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12673" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12677">I kiss your lordship's hands." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="60">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12678" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12712">At break of day, Renzo had been snoring for seven hours, and was yet, poor fellow, in his deepest sleep, when two violent shakes by the arm, and a voice which proceeded from the bed's-foot, shouting, "Lorenzo Tramaglino!" woke him all of a sudden. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12713" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12744">He returned to consciousness, stretched out his arms, opened his eyes with difficulty, and saw standing at the foot of the bed a man clothed in black, and two armed attendants, one on either side of his bolster. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12745" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12782">Renzo, what between the surprise, the sleep, and the fumes of the wine, remained a moment like one enchanted. Believing that he still dreamed, and not finding the dream very agreeable, he moved as though to awake himself thoroughly. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="61">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12783" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12800">"Ah, you have heard at last, Lorenzo Tramaglino," said the man in the black cloak, the notary of the preceding evening. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12801" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12807">"Come, then, get up, and come with us." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="62">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12808" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12816">"Lorenzo Tramaglino!" said Renzo Tramaglino; "what is the meaning of this? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12817" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12820">What do you want with me? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12821" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12826">Who has told you my name?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="63">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12827" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12845">"Chatter less, and make haste," said one of the constables who stood at his side, taking him again by the arm. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12846" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12855">"Oh, oh! What outrage is this?" cried Renzo, drawing away his arm. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12856" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12858">"Host! oh, host!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="64">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12859" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12870">"Shall we carry him off in his shirt?" asked the other constable, turning towards the notary. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="65">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12871" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12889">"Do you understand?" returned the latter, addressing Renzo. "This shall be done, unless you get up very quickly and come along with us." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="66">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12890" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12893">"And wherefore?" demanded Renzo. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="67">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12894" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12902">"The wherefore you shall hear from the Signor Capitano di Giustizia." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="68">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12903" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12914">"If I am an honest man, I have done nothing; and I am astonished——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="69">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12915" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12933">"All the better for you, all the better for you; with two words you will be set free, and can go about your business." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="70">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12934" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12948">"Let me go now," said Renzo; "I have nothing to do with justice." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="71">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12949" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12953">"Come, let us have done with it!" said a constable. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="72">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12954" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12959">"Let us carry him away!" said the other. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="73">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12960" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12964">"Lorenzo Tramaglino!" said the notary. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="74">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12965" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12970">"How does your lordship know my name?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="75">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12971" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12993">"Do your duty," said the notary to the constable, who immediately laid hands upon Renzo to draw him out of bed. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="76">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12994" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13006">"Ah, don't touch an honest man's body—for—I know how to dress myself." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="77">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13007" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13012">"Then dress yourself quickly," said the notary. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="78">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13013" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13036">"I am dressing myself," replied Renzo; and in fact set about collecting the various garments which lay scattered over the bed, like the fragments of a shipwreck upon a coast. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13037" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13053">And beginning to put them on, he continued, all the time saying, "but I do not wish to go to the Capitano di Giustizia. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13054" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13071">I have nothing to do with him; since this unjust affront has been offered me, I wish to be conducted to Ferrer. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13072" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13082">I know this, I know that he is an honest man, and he is somewhat indebted to me." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="79">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13083" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13092">"Yes, yes, my son, thou shalt be conducted to Ferrer," replied the notary. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="80">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13093" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13109">Under other circumstances he would have laughed heartily at such a proposition; but this was not a moment in which to laugh. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13110" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13151">Already in coming along he had seen in the streets a certain commotion, but he had not been able to decide whether this were the remains of a revolt which had not yet entirely subsided, or the commencement of a fresh one; there was a rushing in of people, a meeting, a marching in companies, a collecting in knots. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13152" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13173">And now, without appearing, or at least striving not to appear to do so, he was busied listening, and it seemed to him that the noise increased. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13174" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13209">He was, therefore, desirous of making as much speed as possible; but he would also have wished to conduct Renzo away quietly, and with his own consent; for, should he come to open war with him in the street, he could not be certain whether he should find them still three to one. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13210" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13232">Therefore, he gave the constables to understand by a glance that they should have patience, and not exasperate the young man; and himself sought to persuade him by gentle speeches. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13233" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13279">The youth, whilst he dressed himself very slowly, recalled to mind, as well as he could, the events of the past day, and pretty nearly guessed that the proclamation, and the name, and the surname, must be the cause of all; but how the devil did this fellow know his name? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13280" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13334">And what the devil could have happened in the night, to make officers of justice courageous enough thus to come boldly, and lay hands upon one of these brave lads, whose voice but the preceding day had been of so much weight in the assembly? And yet they could not all be asleep, since Renzo also perceived an increasing noise in the street. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13335" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13356">At length, looking into the notary's countenance, he discovered the agitation which the other endeavoured in vain to keep concealed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13357" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13427">Then, as though to throw some light upon these conjectures, and to reconnoitre the country, to gain time, and even to attempt a bold stroke, he said, "I see well what is the cause of all this; it is from love of the name and surname; truly, last night I was somewhat gay; these hosts have sometimes certain very treacherous wines; and sometimes, I say, it is well known that when wine is in the body, it is the wine that speaks. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13428" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13449">But, if this concerns nothing else, I am ready to give you every satisfaction: Besides, you already know my name. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13450" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13454">Who the devil has told it you?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="81">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13455" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13480">"Bravo, my fine fellow, bravo!" replied the notary, with a very polite air. "I see that you are right, and you may believe me, who am of the profession, that you are gentler than all the others. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13481" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13501">This is the best way to get off quickly and well; with this good disposition, you will be dismissed with two words, and set at liberty. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13502" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13515">But see, my son, I have my hands bound, and cannot release you here, as I should like. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13516" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13539">Come, make haste, and only come on without fear; when they see who you are — and then I will say — Allow me to act — enough; make haste, my son." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="82">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13540" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13568">"Ah! you cannot; I know how," said Renzo; and be continued to dress himself, pushing back the constables, who endeavoured to lay hold of him so as to hasten his operations. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="83">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13569" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13577">"Shall we pass through the Cathedral-square?" he at length demanded of the notary. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="84">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13578" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13696">"Any way you like, the shortest way, so as to get you the sooner liberated," said our notary, tormenting himself inwardly, whether he ought to let this mysterious demand of Renzo, which might become the subject of a hundred questions, fall to the ground. "What a thing it is to be born unfortunate!" thought he. "Only see! A fellow falls into my hands, who, it seems, will do nothing but chatter; if one had only breathing time, thus *extra formam*, speaking academically, in the way of friendly discourse, one could make him confess anything that one liked, without using the rope; he is a man to conduct into prison and examine well, without he himself having any idea of what is going on; and that a man of this description must needs fall into my hands precisely in a moment of anxiety like the present. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13697" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13751">Ah! there is no means to escape," continued he, listening and inclining his head; "there is no remedy, the day promises to be even stormier than yesterday." What caused him to think this, was an extraordinary noise which was heard in the street; and he could not refrain from opening the window and casting a glance below. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13752" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13796">He saw that there was a company of citizens, who, when commanded by the patrole to disperse, had, in the beginning, replied with violent language; but who, nevertheless, at last separated themselves, murmuring loudly; and what particularly appeared to the notary a fatal sign, was that the soldiers were full of politeness towards the populace. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13797" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13854">He closed the window, and hesitated a moment whether he ought to carry out the enterprise, or, leaving Renzo in the care of the two constables, hasten to inform the Capitano di Giustizia of what had happened. "But," thought he immediately to himself, "they will tell me I am a coward, that I am good for nothing, that I ought to execute the orders given me. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13855" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13859">I am in for it; so I may as well proceed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13860" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13862">Cursed crowd! cursed trade!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="85">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13863" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13876">Renzo was already on his legs, the two satellites stood on each side of him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13877" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13896">The notary signed to them not to offer him too much violence, and said to his prisoner, "Come, my brave lad, make haste!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="86">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13897" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13902">Renzo also heard, saw, and thought. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13903" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13919">He was now entirely dressed, with the exception of his doublet, which he held in one hand, feeling with the other in the pockets. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13920" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13938">"Oh!" said he, looking at the notary with a very significant expression of face, "there was money and a letter here, Signor mio!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="87">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13939" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13952">"Every thing shall be punctually returned when all these little formalities are executed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13953" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13954">Let us go, let us go." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="88">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13955" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13972">"No, no, no," said Renzo, shaking his head; "this won't do for me. I will have my property, Signor mio. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13973" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13982">I will render account of my actions; but I will have my property." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="89">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13983" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14010">"I wish to shew you how much I confide in you; here they are, and make haste," said the notary, taking out of his bosom, and consigning into Renzo's hands, the sequestered articles. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14011" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14031">Our hero, replacing them where they had been before, muttered between his teeth, "You hold so much converse with thieves," that you have learned some little of their trade!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14032" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14109">The constables could no longer contain themselves, but the notary held them in check with his eyes, saying to himself meantime, "If thou set foot beyond this threshold, thou shalt pay for this with usury—thou shalt pay for it!" Whilst Renzo put on his doublet, and took his hat, the notary signed to one of the constables to proceed down stairs, sent the prisoner after him, then the other of these good friends, and then followed himself. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="90">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14110" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14159">When they were in the kitchen, whilst Renzo said, "Where has this blessed host hid himself?" the notary gave another sign to the constables, who, seizing hold of Renzo one on either hand, fastened his wrist with certain machines, which, by this hypocritical figure of speech, are called handcuffs. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14160" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14204">They consisted (we regret thus to be obliged to descend to particulars so unworthy the gravity of history, but perspicuity demands it), they consisted in a small cord, a little longer than would go round an ordinary wrist, with small pieces of wood, like pegs, at the two ends. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n189" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14205" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14261">This cord went round the patient's wrist; and the bits of wood passed between the middle and third finger of the captor's hand, remaining in his grasp, so that, in turning them, he tightened the cord according to his pleasure; and by this means he was enabled, not only to insure the safety of the captured, but also to torture one who might be stubborn; and to this end the cord was full of knots. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="91">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n190" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14262" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14292">Renzo struggled, and cried out, "What treachery is this? to an honest man ——" But the notary, who had his fine speeches ready for every unpleasant event, said, "Have patience. They are only doing their duty." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n191" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14293" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14310">What would you have? These are all formalities. We even are not able to treat people as our hearts dictate. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n192" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14311" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14326">If we did not do that which we are ordered to do, we should be prettily off, worse even than you! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n193" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14327" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14328">Have patience." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="92">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n194" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14329" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14342">Whilst he spoke thus, the two whose business it was to operate upon him gave a twist to the bits of wood. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n195" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14343" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14360">Renzo plunged like a fiery horse which feels his mouth pressed by his bit, and cried, "Patience!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="93">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n196" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14361" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14373">"But, my good fellow," said the notary, "this is the true way to get yourself liberated. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n197" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14374" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14390">What would you have? It is a tedious affair, I see that myself; but behaving yourself well, you will have done with it in a moment. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n198" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14391" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14413">And then I see that you are well disposed, and I feel inclined to assist you; I wish to give you yet another piece of advice for your good. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n199" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14414" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14453">Believe me, who am practised in these affairs; go straightforward on your way, without looking here or there, without making yourself remarked; thus no one will attend to you, no one will perceive who it is, and thus you will preserve your honour. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n200" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14454" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14492">In an hour, from this time, you will be at liberty. There is so much to be done, that they will also be in haste to set you free; and then I will speak — you will go about your affairs, and no one will know that you have been in the hands of justice. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n201" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14493" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14547">And you," he continued, turning to the constables with a severe air, "take great care to do him no ill, for he is under my protection; it is necessary that you perform your duty; but recollect that he is an honest and a civil youth, who, in a short time, will again be at liberty, and that he is likely to feel regard for his honour. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n202" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14548" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14564">Proceed in such a manner that no one shall perceive anything, as though you were three gentlemen going a walk." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n203" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14565" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14620">And in an imperative tone, and with threatening brows, he concluded, "You have understood;" then turning himself to Renzo with a calmed brow, and with a countenance suddenly become smiling, which seemed to say, "Oh, but really we are great friends!" he again whispered to him, "Be prudent, follow directions: proceed collected and calm, confide in those who wish you well; let us be going." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n204" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14621" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14624">And the train moved off. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="94">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n205" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14625" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14693">Renzo, however, did not believe one word of all these beautiful speeches; neither that the notary wished more good to him than to the constables, neither that he had his reputation so much at heart, neither that he felt any inclination to assist him; but he understood very well that this excellent man, fearful that some good occasion of escaping from their hands might present itself in the streets, made these fine proposals, in order to deter him from watching for and profiting by it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n206" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14694" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14716">Therefore all these exhortations were of no use, except to confirm him in the designs which he had in his head, and to make him do precisely the contrary. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="95">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n207" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14717" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14731">Let no one however conclude from this that the notary was an inexperienced knave and a novice, because he would thus be under a mistake. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n208" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14732" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14758">He was, on the contrary, an arch knave, says our historian, who appears to have been one of his friends, but in this moment his mind was in a state of agitation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n209" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14759" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14800">I can assure you that in this ordinary state of mind he would have ridiculed any one who, to induce another to commit himself, should have gone and suggested the means, and counselled him so warmly with the miserable feint of giving him, as a friend, a disinterested piece of advice. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n210" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14801" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14850">But there is a general tendency in men when they are agitated and anxious, and observe that another is able to extricate them from their embarrassment, to demand this assistance earnestly and repeatedly, and under every sort of pretence; and knaves also, when they are in agitation and anxiety, become subject to this general law. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n211" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14851" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14864">Therefore it happens that they in circumstances like the present mostly make such a poor figure. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n212" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14865" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14988">These masterly stratagems, this beautiful cunning with which they are accustomed to come off victorious, which are become to them like a second nature, and which, employed in time, and conducted with presence of mind, with the necessary calmness, succeed so well and so secretly,—this cunning which, after a successful result calls forth such universal applause, is adopted in all haste by these poor wretches when they are in great straits, madly, without cleverness or grace; in such a manner too as to cause those who see them thus struggling and striving, to pity and laugh at them; and the one whom they would make their victim, although less crafty than they, discovers their plot, and from their own artifices receives light and turns it against them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n213" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14989" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15017">Therefore it can never be sufficiently recommended to knaves by profession to preserve always their *sang froid*, or if possible always to remain the stronger party, which after all is the safest plan. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="96">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n214" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15018" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15047">Renzo, therefore, was scarcely arrived in the street, than he began to look about him here and there, to waver his body to the right and left, to listen with both ears. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n215" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15048" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15085">There was not, however, any extraordinary concourse of people in the streets, and yet in the countenance of more than one passer-by, it was easy to read an indescribable seditious expression, yet every one pursued their way, and properly speaking there was no sedition. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="97">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n216" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15086" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15099">"Be prudent, be prudent!" muttered the notary behind his back; "remember your honour, your honour, my son!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n217" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15100" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15142">But when Renzo, listening to three men who came up with inflamed countenances, heard them speak of a bakehouse, of concealed flour, of justice, he also began making signs to them, and coughing in a manner which announces quite another thing than a cold. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n218" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15143" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15172">These men regarded this little troop with more attention, and stopped; with them also some others who had just then come up, and others who had gone on before, began to whisper, and turning back brought up the rear. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="98">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n219" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15173" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15194">"Take care of yourself; be prudent, my son, do not spoil your affairs; think of your honour, of your reputation," murmured the notary. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n220" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15195" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15197">Renzo behaved in a still worse manner. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n221" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15198" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15219">The constables after having consulted each other by glances, thinking to do wisely (every one is liable to err), drew tight the handcuffs. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="99">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n222" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15220" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15242">"Ahi! ahi! ahi!" cried the tortured one; at this cry the people crowded round, they hastened from all sides; the convoy found itself perplexed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n223" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15243" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15261">"He is a profligate fellow," whispered the notary to those who surrounded him; "he is a thief, caught in the fact. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n224" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15262" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15267">Retire, allow the officers of justice to pass on." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n225" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15268" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15307">But, Renzo perceived this fine opportunity, he saw the constables become white, or at least pale. "If I don't assist myself now, all the worse for me," thought he. And suddenly he raised his voice. "Good people! they are taking me to prison, because yesterday I shouted, "bread and justice." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n226" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15308" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15317">I have done nothing else. I am an honest man; assist me, do not abandon me, good people!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="100">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n227" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15318" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15354">A favourable murmur ran through the crowd, then protecting voices raised themselves in reply; at first the constables commanded, then requested, then besought those who were nearest to move away, and make an opening; the mob, however, crowded and pressed round them all the more. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n228" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15355" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15377">The constables, at sight of danger, loosened the handcuffs, and only thought how they might lose themselves among the crowd, and get off unobserved. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n229" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15378" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15424">The notary desired ardently to do the same, but this was difficult on account of his black cloak; the poor man, pale and desponding, endeavoured to make himself very, very small. He moved along bending his body, so as to escape out of the crowd; but he could not raise his head without seeing twenty eyes fixed upon him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n230" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15425" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15482">He studied in every possible manner to appear a stranger, who, passing by on his way home, had found himself as fast in the crowd as a straw in the ice; and meeting face to face with a man who gazed at him intently, with a frown even more threatening than that of the others, he composed his mouth to a smile, and with a silly air demanded, "What has happened?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="101">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n231" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15483" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15486">"Ah, raven!" replied he. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n232" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15487" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15490">"Raven, raven!" resounded from all sides. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap15-n233" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15491" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15526">Blows were now added to the cries, so that in a short time, partly by his own legs, partly by the elbows of others, he obtained that which was in this moment the most important to him — a release from this crush. </note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>