<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CHAPTER XIV.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>1845</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed Lovers: a Milanese Story of the Seventeenth Century. With The Column of Infamy by Alessandro Manzoni. In Three Volumes</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
          <date>1845</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Henry Francis C. Logan</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="English_1845_cap14">
        <p n="1">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10020">The crowd which remained behind began to disperse, and to withdraw to the right and to the left, by this and by that street. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10021" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10054">Some returned home to look to their affairs; some departed to breathe at large after having passed so many hours in this terrible crush; some in search of friends, with whom to chat over the events of the day. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10055" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10086">The same scene took place at the other end of the square, where now the people were so thinly scattered that the detachment of Spanish soldiers was able, without meeting any resistance, to approach and post itself before the Superintendent's house. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10087" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10149">Near to this house remained yet assembled, the dregs, so to say, of the tumult; a band of scoundrels, who, discontented with so cold and therefore so unsatisfactory an ending of so grand and brilliant a commencement, murmured, cursed, held counsel whether anything might yet be attempted; and, in order to essay this, commenced assaulting and shaking this poor door which had again been barricadoed as well as might be. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10150" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10188">On the arrival of the detachment, all these people, with an unanimous resolve and without stopping to consult, moved off in the opposite direction, leaving the field clear to the soldiers, who immediately took possession of it, and posted themselves there to guard the house and the street. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10189" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10254">But through all the neighbouring streets were scattered groups of people; wherever two or three individuals stopped, there stopped also three, four, twenty others; here some one would detach himself, there a whole knot of people would move away together, like those little clouds which sometimes after a tempest float through the azure of heaven, and say to those who gaze upwards, "the weather is not yet settled." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10255" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10260">Only imagine, then, what a chattering of tongues there must have been! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10261" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10345">One narrated with emphasis the particular events which he himself had witnessed; another related what he himself had done; this one congratulated himself that all had ended so well, praised Ferrer, and prognosticated serious woes for the Superintendent; another, with a laughing air, said, "Do not be afraid; they will not kill each other, the wolf does not devour the flesh of the wolf;" whilst a fifth, more angrily murmured, that the thing had not been done as it ought to have been, that it was as thunder, and that it had been a folly to make so much noise, only to let themselves then be decoyed in this manner. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="2">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10346" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10371">Meanwhile the sun had set, and all objects were clothed in the same sombre hue; many, wearied from the exertions of the day and tired of thus gossiping in the twilight, returned home. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10372" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10433">Our youth, after he had aided the progress of the carriage as far as assistance was necessary, after he had followed close behind it, between these files of soldiers, as though in triumph, had congratulated himself, when he saw the coach drive on freely and out of danger, had proceeded a short way along the street with the mob, and then had issued forth through the first opening to which he came, in order himself to breathe a little free air. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10434" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10484">Scarcely had he taken a few steps at his ease, than, in the midst of so much agitation, of so many sentiments of so many recent and confused images, he felt a strong desire for food and repose; and he began looking about him on every side in search of some public-house sign, for it was already too late to return to the Capuchin convent. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10485" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10511">Walking along with his gaze thus directed upwards, he found himself close upon one of these knots of people. He stopped and listened how they discoursed upon their conjectures and designs for the day following. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10512" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10538">Having remained one moment to listen, he could not preserve himself from delivering his opinion, and it appearing to him that he who had done so much might certainly without presumption say something. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10539" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10582">Persuaded from all he had seen to-day, that, in order to make any enterprise succeed, it was only necessary to bring it into favour with those who wander about the streets, "Gentlemen!" he cried in a tone of exordium, "gentlemen! May I also give my humble opinion? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10583" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10640">My humble opinion is this: that it is not alone in the affair of bread that knavish tricks are played; and since to-day it has been clearly seen that one has only to make oneself heard to obtain justice, it is necessary to proceed in this manner until a remedy has been found for all the other wickedness, and until the world goes on in a more Christian style." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="3">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10641" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10704">And is it not true, gentlemen, that there is a handful of tyrants who think proper to break the Ten Commandments, and seek out quiet people who never think about them, in order to injure them in a thousand ways, and yet who at the end are always in the right? Even when they have committed a greater villany than usual, they walk along holding their heads higher than ever. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10705" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10714">In Milan itself, there must be a certain quantity of these men. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="4">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10715" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10719">"Only too many," said a voice. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="5">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10720" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10732">"I say it, I do," replied Renzo; "already histories are related among us. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10733" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10739">And then the thing speaks for itself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10740" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10772">Let us suppose, for example, one of these men who stands as it were with one foot in the country and one in Milan; if he be a devil there, he will not be an angel here, it appears to me. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10773" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10790">Then tell me, gentlemen, have you ever seen one of these people with the countenance of a Ferrer? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10791" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10857">And then what makes this conduct even worse, and this I can tell you as a certainty, is that there are proclamations printed for their chastisement, and they are not all proclamations founded on nothing; their crimes are clearly enumerated, just as they happen, and to each one its good punishment, and it is written, 'Whosoever he be, ignoble and plebeian, etc.' </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10858" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10893">Now, go and desire the doctors, the scribes, and the pharisees, to cause justice to be done you, according to the command of the proclamation, and they will pay you as much attention as the Pope does to rogues; this is enough to turn an honest man's brain. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10894" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10920">One sees then clearly that the king and those who are in command desire that these scoundrels should be chastised; but nothing is done, because there is a law. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10921" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10966">There fore, it is necessary to break this law; it is necessary to go to-morrow to Ferrer, who is a brave gentleman, a worthy Signor; and to-day, we have been able to see how happy he was to find himself among poor people, and how he sought to hear their arguments, and with what a good grace he answered. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10967" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11093">We must go to Ferrer, and tell him how affairs stand; and I, for my own part, can recount to him very fine things. I who have seen with my own eyes a proclamation, with lots of coats-of-arms at the top, and which had been made by three of those who are at the head of affairs, and underneath their names beautifully printed, and one of these names was Ferrer, this I have seen with my own eyes: now this proclamation was just applicable to my case; but to a Doctor, to whom I in consequence applied for justice, according to the intention of these three Signors, among whom was Ferrer, to this Signor Doctor, who himself had shewn me the proclamation, this is the best of all, ah, ah! it seemed that I talked like a madman. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11094" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11129">I am certain that did this dear old man hear all these fine things — for he cannot know them all, especially those belonging to the country — he would not wish that the world should go on in this manner, and would apply some good remedy. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11130" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11155">And then, besides, those who make these proclamations must have pleasure in seeing them obeyed; for it is an insult, an epitaph with their names, to count them as nothing. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11156" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11177">And if the nobles will not lower their heads, and listen to reason, we are here to assist them, as we have done to-day. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11178" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11201">I do not say he ought to drive about in his coach to catch all the villains, nobles and tyrants; if he did, he would require Noah's Ark. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11202" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11276">He should command those whose duty it is, and not alone those in Milan, but also those in the country, to do all things conformable to the instructions laid down in these proclamations; and commence a good law-suit against those who have committed these iniquities; and where it says, "prison," let us have the prison,—where it says, "the galleys," let us have the galleys; and say to the Podestà that he shall do all these things truly; if not, send him about his business, and place a better in his stead; and then, as I said before, we should be also here, to lend him a helping hand. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11277" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11292">And order the doctors also to listen to the poor, and speak in defence of their right. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11293" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11296">Have I said well, gentlemen?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="6">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11297" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11328">Renzo had spoken so entirely from his heart, that, from the commencement, a considerable number of those assembled had suspended all other discourse, and had turned towards him; and, at a certain point, all had become his auditors. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11329" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11346">A confused shout of applause, of "bravo, certainly, he has reason, it is only too true," were the answers of his audience. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11347" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11351">But critics were not wanting. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11352" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11366">"O yes!" said one, "listen to these mountaineers! They are all lawyers!" and he went his way. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11367" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11399">"Now," muttered another, "every bare-legged fellow will have his say; and, with this rage to busy themselves about every thing, we never shall have cheap bread; is it on this account we have put ourselves in motion?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11400" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11415">Renzo, however, only heard the compliment; some took him by one hand, some seized him by the other, "until we meet to-morrow!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11416" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11437">"Where? In the Cathedral square.—Yes, good.—Very good. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11438" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11441">And something will be done?—And something will be done!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="7">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11442" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11462">"Which of these good gentlemen would tell me where I may find a hostel, where a poor lad could eat a mouthful, drink a glass, and sleep?" said Renzo. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="8">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11463" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11484">"I am at your service, my good youth," said one who had attentively listened to this sermon, and as yet had said nothing. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11485" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11503">"I know an hostel which will suit you precisely; I will recommend you to the host, who is my friend, and an excellent man." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="9">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11504" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11507">"Here, in the neighbourhood?" Renzo demanded. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="10">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11508" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11511">"A short distance off," replied the former. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="11">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11512" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11531">The assembly dissolved, and Renzo, after many pressures of unknown hands, moved off with the unknown, thanking him for his courtesy. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="12">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11532" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11546">"It is nothing, it is nothing," returned the stranger; "one hand washes the other, and both wash the face. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11547" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11554">Ought we not to oblige our neighbour?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11555" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11568">And pursuing their road, he asked of Renzo, by way of discourse, now one question, now another. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11569" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11584">"It is not from any impertinent curiosity to know your affairs; but you appear to me much wearied. From what part of the country do you come?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="13">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11585" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11591">"I come all the way from Lecco—all the way." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="14">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11592" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11594">"All the way from Lecco? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11595" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11597">You are from Lecco?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="15">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11598" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11602">"From Lecco—that is, out of the district." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="16">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11603" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11617">"Poor youth! From what I have been able to understand of your discourse, you have been shamefully treated there." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="17">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11618" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11661">"Ah, my dear, worthy sir! I have been obliged to be rather politic so as not to speak of my private affairs in public; but — enough, some day this will be known, and then — But I see an inn sign; and, by my faith, I have no desire to go farther." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="18">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11662" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11677">"No, no; come where I have told you, it is only a short way from here," said his guide; "here, you will not be comfortable." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="19">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11678" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11714">"O yes!" replied the youth; "I am no fine gentleman accustomed to be wrapt up in cotton-wool; something good to put into my stomach, and a straw-bed, will suffice for me. And what particularly concerns me is to find quickly both one and the other. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11715" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11716">God preserve me!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11717" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11729">And he entered the large portal over which hung the sign of the Full Moon. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="20">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11730" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11744">"Well, I will conduct you there, since you wish it," said the unknown, and he followed him. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="21">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11745" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11752">"There is no need that you trouble yourself farther," replied Renzo. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11753" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11765">"However," added he, "if you would come in and take a glass with me, you would do me a pleasure." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="22">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11766" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11799">"I accept your kind offer," replied the stranger; and preceding Renzo, like one better acquainted with the localities, he passed through a little court and approached a door which led into the kitchen, lifted up the latch, opened it, and went in with his companion. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11800" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11817">Two small lamps, suspended from the beam of the ceiling, cast below a half light. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11818" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11866">Many people, none of them however in idleness, were seated upon two benches placed on each side a long and narrow table, which occupied a considerable portion of the apartment. Here and there, at intervals, napkins and plates were laid; cards were to be seen lying in confusion, dice thrown down or again collected together; everywhere large flasks and glasses. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11867" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11921">There were also to be seen many berlinge, reali, and parpagliole, rolling about on the table, which, could they have spoken, would most probably have said, "this morning we were in a baker's till, or in the pocket of some spectator among the mob, who, all intent upon watching the course of public events, forgot to watch over his own little private affairs." The confusion was great. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11922" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11980">A boy wildly rushed backwards and forwards to wait upon the revellers and the gamesters; the host was seated upon a small bench within the wide chimney, apparently occupied in tracing and again effacing with the tongs certain figures among the ashes; but, in reality, he was attending to all that passed around him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11981" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11990">He rose when he heard the raising of the latch, and advanced towards the newly arrived guests. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11991" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12080">As soon as he perceived who was the guide, "Cursed fellow!" he exclaimed to himself, "why must thou always come under my feet when I have the least wish for thee!" He then cast a glance at Renzo, saying again to himself, "I do not know thee; but coming with such a hunter, thou must needs be either dog or hare; I shall know which of the two thou art, when thou hast said two words." However, not one of these reflections could be traced in the host's countenance, which remained as motionless as that of a portrait; it was a countenance plump and shiny, with a small thick beard of a reddish colour, and with two small sharp clear eyes. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="23">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12081" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12088">"What do these gentlemen command?" said he aloud. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="24">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12089" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12103">"First of all a good flask of good wine," said Renzo, "and then a mouthful of something." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12104" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12141">And saying this, he seated himself upon a bench towards the upper end of the table, and sent forth a sonorous "Ah!" as if to say, "It does one good to rest upon a bench, after one has been such a long time busy on one's legs." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12142" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12168">But suddenly there occurred to his mind that bench and that table to which he had sat for the last time with Lucia and Agnese, and he heaved a sigh. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12169" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12183">He shook his head, however, as though to drive away this thought, and saw the host arrive with the wine. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12184" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12193">The unknown companion had placed himself on the bench facing Renzo. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12194" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12204">Our good youth immediately poured him out some wine, saying, "So, wet your lips!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12205" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12213">And having filled the other glass, he emptied it in a moment. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="25">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12214" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12221">"What can you give me to eat?" he then demanded of the host. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="26">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12222" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12228">"I have a piece of stewed meat; does this please you?" replied the other. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="27">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12229" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12232">"Yes, excellently; let us have some of the stewed meat." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="28">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12233" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12249">"You shall be served," said the host to Renzo; and to the waiter, "serve this stranger;" and then moved off towards the chimney. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12250" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12263">"But,"—he continued, turning to Renzo, "but, bread I have not to-day." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="29">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12264" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12277">"As for bread," said Renzo, laughing, "Providence has thought of that." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12278" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12303">And he drew forth the third and last of the little loaves of bread picked up under the cross of San Dionigi, and raised it on high, crying, "Here is the bread of Providence!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="30">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12304" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12321">At this exclamation, many of the guests turned round, and seeing this trophy in the air, one of them cried, "Bread for ever at a cheap rate!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="31">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12322" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12329">"At a cheap rate!" said Renzo, "gratis et amore." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="32">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12330" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12331">"Better, still better." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="33">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12332" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12343">"But," added Renzo immediately, "I do not wish these Signors to think ill of me. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12344" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12367">I have not, as one might say, stolen it; I have found it lying on the ground, and if the owner could be found, I am ready to pay him for it." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="34">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12368" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12389">"Bravo, bravo!" shouted the guests, laughing still louder; and it occurred to not one of them that these words were said in earnest. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="35">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12390" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12420">"You imagine I am joking, but this is really what I mean," said Renzo to his guide; and turning the cake round in his hand, added, "you see how it has been treated; it looks as flat as a pancake; but there was such a crowd! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12421" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12435">If any one had been there with tender bones, he would have come badly off! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12436" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12463">And immediately he devoured three or four mouthfuls of this bread, bending after them a second cup of wine, adding, 'This bread will not go down by itself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12464" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12471">I never have had my throat so dry. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12472" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12476">That was a grand shout we gave.'" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="36">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12477" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12493">"Prepare a good bed for this worthy young man," said the guide, "for he intends to sleep here." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="37">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12494" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12503">"You will sleep here?" demanded the host, approaching the table. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="38">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12504" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12525">"Certainly," replied Renzo, "I can put up with any sort of a bed; it is sufficient if the sheets are only clean; for, although I am a poor fellow, I am accustomed to cleanliness." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="39">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12526" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12559">"Oh! as to that ——," said the host, going to his counter, which stood in one corner of the kitchen, from whence he brought in one hand an inkstand and a small piece of paper, and in the other a pen. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="40">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12560" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12589">"What does this mean?" cried Renzo, swallowing a piece of the stewed meat which the boy had placed before him, and then, smiling in amazement, added, "Is this then the clean sheet?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="41">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12590" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12637">The host, without replying, placed upon the table the inkstand and the paper; then supported his left arm and right elbow upon the same table, and then, with the pen in the air, and his face raised towards Renzo, he said, "Do me the favour to tell me your name, surname, and country." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="42">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12638" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12646">"What is this?" said Renzo. "What has all this to do with the bed?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="43">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12647" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12699">"I do my duty," said the host, gazing into the guide's face: "we are obliged to render an account of all those persons who come to lodge with us,—'name and surname, of what country he is, upon what business he is come, whether he has arms with him, how long he may remain in this city.' </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12700" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12703">These are the very words of the proclamation." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="44">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12704" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12726">Before answering, Renzo emptied another glass; this was the third; and henceforth I fear we shall no longer be able to enumerate them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12727" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12733">"Ah, ah!" he cried, "you have your proclamation! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12734" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12751">I pride myself upon being a doctor of laws, and therefore I know immediately how much importance is attached to these proclamations." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="45">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12752" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12789">"I speak the truth," said the host, still gazing at Renzo's mute companion; and he again went to the counter, drew forth a large sheet of paper, a copy of the proclamation, which he unfolded before Renzo's eyes. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="46">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12790" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12823">"Ah, here it is," said our friend; raising with one hand the glass which he had again emptied, and stretching out his other hand, with one finger pointing towards the proclamation. "Ah, here it is; this beautiful sheet of paper. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12824" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12827">I rejoice myself extremely on its account. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12828" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12842">I know these coats-of-arms; I know what is the meaning of this Pagan face, with this cord round his neck." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12843" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12879">At the head of proclamations were then placed the Governor's armorial bearings; and in those of Don Gonzalo Fernandez de Cordova was seen a Moorish king, chained by the throat. "This face signifies—command who can, obey who will. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12880" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12941">When this face shall have sent to the galleys the Signor Don ----, enough, I know what I would say; as it says in another scrap of paper similar to this, when he shall have taken such measures that an honest young man can marry an honest young woman who is happy to marry him, then I will tell my name to this face. I will even moreover give it a kiss. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12942" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12952">I can have very good reasons for not telling it my name. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12953" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12954">This would be fine, indeed! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12955" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13000">And if a great villain who might have a handful of other villains under his command, because if he should be alone ----" here he finished his phrase by a gesture; "if a great villain should wish to know where I am, in order to do me a bad turn, I ask, would this face ever bestir itself to assist me? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13005">Ought I to tell it my affairs? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13006" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13009">This is certainly something new. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13010" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13032">And even suppose I were come to Milan to confess myself, I would rather confess myself to a Capuchin father than to a host." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="47">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13033" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13049">The host remained silent, and continued to regard the guide, who did not exhibit the slightest intention to depart. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13050" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13071">Renzo, we are grieved to say it, drained another glass and continued; "I will give thee a reason, my dear host, which will convince thee. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13072" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13092">If the proclamations which speak in favour of good Christians count for nothing, all the less should those which speak ill of them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13093" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13107">Therefore, remove all these annoyances, and bring instead another flask, for this is broken." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13108" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13122">Saying this, he struck it lightly with his knuckles, and added, "listen, listen, host; how cracked it sounds!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="48">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13123" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13148">This time also, Renzo, by little and little, had attracted the attention of those who surrounded him; and also this time he was applauded by his auditory. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="49">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13149" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13162">"What ought I to do?" said the host, looking at the unknown, who, however, was not unknown to him. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="50">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13163" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13183">"Come, come," cried many of these merry companions, "this youth is right; they are all oppressions, snares, annoyances; let us have to-day a new law—a new law!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="51">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13184" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13210">In the midst of these cries, the unknown, casting a reproving glance at the host for this too open interrogation, said, "let him follow his own course; do not make a scene." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="52">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13211" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13249">"I have done my duty," said the host aloud; and then thought to himself, "Now I have put myself under shelter." He took up the paper, the pen, the inkstand, the proclamation, and the empty flask, to consign them to the boy. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="53">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13250" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13290">"Bring me some more of the same wine," said Renzo, "and we will send him to bed without demanding from him his name, his surname, and of what country he is, and for what he is come here, and whether he has to stay a little while in this city." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="54">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13291" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13326">"Of the same," said the host to the boy; giving him the flask at the same time, and he returned to seat himself under the wide chimney.—"Nothing less than a hare," thought he, again playing with the ashes; "and into what hands art thou fallen, thou "great ass! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13327" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13361">If thou wilt strangle thyself, why strangle thyself; but the landlord of the Full Moon will not get into trouble through thee." Renzo thanked his guide, and all those who had taken his part. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="55">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13362" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13377">"Brave friends!" he said; "now I clearly see that gentlemen give each other their hands and sustain each other." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13378" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13413">Then flourishing his right hand in the air, and again assuming the attitude of a preacher, "it is a fine thing," he exclaimed, "that those who rule the world will always make paper, pens and ink, enter into every thing whatsoever! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13414" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13418">Always the pen in the hand! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13419" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13427">What a madness all these Signors have for using the pen!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="56">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13428" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13444">"Eh, good country youth! Would you know the reason of this?" said, laughing, one of the gamesters who had just been victorious. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="57">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13445" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13449">"Let us hear," replied Renzo. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="58">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13450" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13477">"The reason is this; because these Signors eat the geese, and find upon them so many, many quills, that it becomes quite necessary to do something with them." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="59">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13478" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13488">All began to laugh, except the companion who lost. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="60">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13489" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13495">"Oh, oh!" said Renzo, "this good fellow is a poet. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13496" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13506">You have poets here also; they spring up everywhere now. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13507" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13523">I myself also have the vein, and sometimes say curious things—— but when affairs are better." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="61">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13524" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13587">In order to understand poor Renzo's nonsense, it is necessary to know that among the lower class in Milan, and even more particularly in the surrounding country, *Poet* does not signify as among the educated, a sacred spirit, an inhabitant of *Pindus*, a pupil of the *Muses*,—but rather a whimsical and giddy-brained fellow, who, in his words and in his deeds, has more of wit and singularity than of reason. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13588" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13611">So great is the inclination of the vulgar to alter the true meaning of words, and to make them express ideas the farthest from their legitimate signification! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13612" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13624">For, I ask, what in the world has the word poet to do with this giddy-brain?' </note>
        </p>
        <p n="62">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13625" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13683">"But I will tell you the real reason, that I will," added Renzo; "it is because it is they who hold the pen—the words which they themselves say fly away and disappear; on the contrary, they are very attentive to the words of a poor lad, and quickly they empale these words during their flight with this pen, and fasten them down upon paper, to make use of when time and place shall present themselves. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13684" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13751">They have also another crafty scheme; when they wish to embarrass a poor lad who has not studied, but who nevertheless has a little—I know very well what I mean," and to make himself understood he struck his forehead with the tip of his first finger. "And when they perceive that he begins to comprehend this confused business, they throw into the discourse some Latin words, so as to make him lose the thread of their argument, and puzzle his brains; enough—this practice ought to be discountenanced. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13752" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13797">To-day, everything has been well managed after the manner of the people, without pen, ink, or paper; and to-morrow, if the people will only know how to govern themselves, even better things will be done, and this without hurting the hair of a single head, and all in the way of justice." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="63">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13798" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13836">In the meantime some of his companions had again returned to their gaming, others to their eating, others to their shouting; some departed, others arrived; the host was attentive to one and all; but these are affairs which have nothing at all to do with our story. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13837" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13869">Still the unknown guide did not seem inclined to take his departure; he had, as it appeared, no other affair in this place, yet he would not depart before having gossiped a little more with Renzo. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13870" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13900">He turned round to him, and renewed the conversation regarding bread; and after a few of those phrases which already for some time had been in all mouths, he put forth one of his own projects. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="64">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13901" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13915">"Ah! if I commanded, I would discover the way to make affairs go on well!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="65">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13916" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13939">"How would you manage?" demanded Renzo, gazing at him with eyes more brilliant than usual, and twisting his mouth somewhat, as though he would remain particularly attentive. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="66">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13940" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13959">"How I would manage? I should wish there to be bread for every one; as much for the poor as for the rich." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="67">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13960" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13965">"Ah! that is very good," said Renzo. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="68">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13966" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13976">"This is what I would do: I would fix an honest price, so that every one should be able to buy. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13977" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14011">And then bread should be distributed according to the number of mouths, for there are thoughtless gluttons who desire all for themselves, scramble for all they can get, and seize upon all that comes in their way, and thus the poor want bread. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14012" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14015">Therefore, the bread must be divided. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14016" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14019">And how is this to be done? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14020" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14039">In this manner; give a ticket to each family, in proportion to the number of mouths, so that they may go and fetch bread from the bakers. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14040" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14077">To myself, for example, they ought to deliver a ticket after this form — Ambrogio Fusella, sword-cutler by profession, with a wife and four children, all old enough to eat bread, pay attention to this; he shall be given bread to a considerable amount, and pay a considerable amount. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14078" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14087">But justice must be done, always with regard to the number of mouths. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14088" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14098">And to you, for example, they ought to give a ticket for——what is your name?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="69">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14099" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14136">"Lorenzo Tramaglino," said the youth; who, quite enchanted with this project, no longer remarked that all this had to do with pens, ink, and paper, and that to bring it into operation, the first thing must be the collecting people's names. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="70">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14137" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14145">"Very good," said the unknown; "but have you a wife and children?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="71">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14146" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14161">"I ought certainly to have — not children — that would be too soon — but a wife — if the world were as it ought to be——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="72">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14162" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14164">"Ah! you are alone. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14165" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14172">Therefore have patience, they will give you a smaller portion." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="73">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14173" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14189">"That is just; but if soon, as I hope — and with the aid of God — but if I should also have a wife myself?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="74">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14190" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14211">"Why then the ticket would be changed, and your portion increased, as I have said, always with regard to the number of mouths," said the unknown, rising. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="75">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14212" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14233">"This is excellent," cried Renzo, continuing to shout and strike his fist upon the table; "and wherefore have they not made such a law?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="76">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14234" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14238">"What would you have me say? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14239" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14260">In the meantime, I wish you a good-night, and take my leave; for I think my wife and the children will have been expecting me for some time." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="77">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14261" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14292">"Another drop, another drop," said Renzo, filling in haste the other's glass, and suddenly rising and seizing him by a fold of his doublet, pulled him down, in order to force him to seat himself again. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14293" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14299">"Another drop, another drop, do not do me this affront." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="78">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14300" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14324">But the friend with one jerk liberated himself, and leaving Renzo to pour forth a torrent of entreaties and reproaches, he again said, "good-night," and departed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14325" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14340">Renzo continued to address him, when he was already in the street, and then fell again heavily upon the bench. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14341" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14405">He fixed his eyes upon the glass which he had again filled, and seeing the waiter pass by the table, he signed to him to stop, as though he had something to communicate to him, and pointing to the glass, in a solemn and slow tone, pronounced these words: "Behold, I had prepared this for that gentleman; only see, it is full measure, just right for a friend; but he would not have it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14406" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14412">Sometimes people have curious ideas. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14413" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14424">I am not to blame; I have shewn my good heart. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14425" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14436">Well, since the thing has been done, there is no need that it should be lost." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14437" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14446">And saying this, he took it and emptied it at one draught. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="79">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14447" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14452">"I understand," said the boy going. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14453" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14462">"Ah! you understand, you also," resumed Renzo. "Then it is true. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n189" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14463" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14467">When the reasons are just ——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="80">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n190" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14468" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14501">All our love of truth is here necessary to enable us to continue faithfully a narrative which does so little honour to so important a character, nay, we might say, to the hero of our history. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n191" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14502" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14542">However, this same impartiality which we profess obliges us to inform the reader that this was the first time such a thing had happened to Renzo; and precisely, because he was not accustomed to such carousals, did this first one succeed so fatally. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n192" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14543" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14597">These few glasses which he had swallowed one after the other in the commencement, contrary to his usual custom, partly owing to the burning heat which he felt, partly owing to his excitement of mind, which allowed him to do nothing by halves, had quickly mounted to his head. With an experienced drinker this would have only excited his thirst. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n193" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14598" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14614">Here, our Anonymous makes an observation which we shall repeat, let it be worth what it may. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n194" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14615" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14661">Temperate and moderate habits, says he, possess also this advantage, that the older they have grown, and the deeper they are rooted in a man, the sooner he finds himself, when wishing to deviate from them, inconvenienced, thus suffering from his fault for some time, his fault even becomes a lesson. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="81">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n195" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14662" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14701">However this might be, when the first fumes had mounted to Renzo's brain, wine and words continued to flow without either measure or rule, and at the point where we left him, he was about as tipsy as he could be. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n196" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14702" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14743">He felt a strong desire to speak; listeners, or at least people around him, whom he could consider as such, were not wanting; and for a certain time his words also had presented themselves without being sought for, and had allowed themselves to be arranged in a certain order. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n197" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14744" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14759">But by little and little the ending of his phrases began to be terribly difficult. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n198" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14760" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14792">The thought which had presented itself clear and strong in his mind became cloudy and vanished all on a sudden; and a word, after having made itself waited for some time, was not the one after all applicable to the case in question. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n199" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14793" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14813">In these perplexities, by one of those fatal instincts which in so many things ruin men, he had recourse to this blessed flask. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n200" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14814" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14833">But of what assistance could the flask be to him under these circumstances? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n201" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14834" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14871">We will only report a few of the many words he spoke this unfortunate evening; those which we omit are too extravagant, for not only they had no sense, but they had not even the appearance of having any, a necessary condition in a printed book. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="82">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n202" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14872" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14905">"Ah, host! host!" recommenced Renzo, following him round the table with his eyes, and even until he had returned to his seat under the chimney; sometimes fixing them where he was not, and always speaking in the midst of the clamour made by the company. "Host, that thou art! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n203" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14906" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14916">I cannot possibly swallow this—this demanding the name, surname, and business. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n204" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14917" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14921">From a lad such as I! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n205" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14922" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14926">No, thou hast not acted well. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n206" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14927" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14939">What satisfaction, what advantage, what pleasure—to put a poor lad like me upon paper! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n207" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14940" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14942">Am I right, gentlemen? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n208" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14943" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14951">The host ought to be on the side of honest lads. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n209" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14952" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14962">Listen, listen, host; I wish to make you a comparison—for the argument. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n210" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14963" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14964">They laugh, eh? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n211" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14965" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14976">I am a little gay;—but I give very just reasons. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n212" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14977" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14987">Tell me a little, who is it who keeps the shop a-going? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n213" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14988" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14994">Poor lads, is it not? Am I not right? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n214" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14995" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15010">Only see whether these Signors of the proclamations ever come to thee to drink a little glass of wine?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="83">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n215" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15011" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15020">"They are all people who drink water," said one of Renzo's neighbours. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="84">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n216" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15021" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15034">"They wish to keep in their senses," added another, "so as to be able to tell lies cleverly." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="85">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n217" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15035" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15044">"Ah!" said Renzo, "now it is the poet who has spoken. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n218" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15045" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15052">Listen, therefore, you others, to my reason. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n219" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15053" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15077">Answer, host. And Ferrer, who is the best of them all, has he ever come here to drink a health, or to spend the half of a quattrino? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n220" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15078" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15083">And this dog of an assassin, this Don — ? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n221" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15084" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15091">I remain silent, for I am not cool enough. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n222" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15092" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15107">Ferrer and the Father Cur—, I know, are two honest men. But there are very few honest men. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n223" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15108" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15119">The old men worse than the young ones, and the young ones—even still worse than the old. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n224" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15120" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15135">However, I am glad that no blood has been spilt; oh, these are horrors to leave to the executioner. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n225" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15136" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15139">Read, oh! as to that, yes! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n226" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15140" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15149">I have received terrible blows, but—then I have also given in return. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n227" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15150" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15152">Make way! Abundance! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n228" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15153" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15164">Hurrah!—And yet, even Ferrer—these few words in Latin—*sies baraos trapolorum.*—Cursed fault! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n229" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15165" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15172">Vivat! Justice! Bread! Ah, here are the just words! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n230" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15173" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15191">There it was these honest men—when this cursed ton, ton, ton, was heard, and then again, ton, ton, ton. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n231" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15192" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15207">The question was not then to fly, but to keep the Signor Curato there—I know what I am thinking about! </note>
        </p>
        <p n="86">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n232" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15208" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15256">With these words he bowed his head and remained some time as though absorbed in thought; then he heaved a deep sigh, and raised a countenance and two such sparkling eyes full of so severe an anguish, that it would have been woe unto the author of this excitement had he been there to witness it but for one moment. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n233" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15257" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15301">But these men, who had already begun to amuse themselves with his impassioned and confused eloquence, were now still more amused by his emotion. Those who were nearest him said to the others, "look;" and all turned round, so that he became the laughing-stock of the whole company. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n234" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15302" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15337">Not because the others were in their right senses, but, to say the truth, no one had so entirely lost his as poor Renzo, and then, besides, he was a peasant. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n235" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15338" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15353">They began first one and then another to excite him, by asking foolish and impertinent questions with a mock ceremony. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n236" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15354" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15387">Renzo now appeared to grow angry, now would treat the thing as a joke; again, without paying attention to these questions, would speak about quite different subjects, would reply, or again in his turn would question, always, however, in the wrong place, and in a most senseless manner. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap14-n237" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15388" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15453">Fortunately, however, in the midst of this folly he had retained a kind of instinct which preserved him from pronouncing the names of certain persons, so that the one which must have been the most deeply engraven in his memory did not pass his lips. It would have displeased us too much, had this name, for which we even feel a little love and respect, been defiled by these disgusting mouths, and had become the amusement of these vile tongues. </note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>