<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CHAPTER XVII.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>1845</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed Lovers: a Milanese Story of the Seventeenth Century. With The Column of Infamy by Alessandro Manzoni. In Three Volumes</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
          <date>1845</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Henry Francis C. Logan</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="English_1845_cap17">
        <p n="1">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10020">One desire is often sufficient to torment a man; imagine then, what he must suffer subjected to two at once, each one at war with the other! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10021" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10058">Poor Renzo, already for many hours, had been possessed by two such desires — the desire of flight and the desire of keeping himself concealed, and the unfortunate words of this merchant had strangely increased both one and the other. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10059" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10095">His adventure then had excited attention, they desired to get hold of him by any means: who knew how many constables were ready to give chase to him? Who knew how many orders had been given to search after him in the villages and inns, and on the roads? </note>
        </p>
        <p n="2">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10096" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10148">At length, however, he thought that the only constables who knew him were two, and that fortunately he did not carry his name written on his brow; but many stories, which he had heard related of fugitives stopped and discovered through strange combinations of circumstances, by their gait, their suspicious air, and other unimagined signs, passed through his mind; all this excited his uneasiness. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10149" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10196">Although the *Ave Maria* rang as he left Gorgonzola, and the increased darkness diminished these dangers still more and more, he chose, much against his will, the high-road, proposing to himself to strike into the first path which should seem to conduct him to the point he desired to reach. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10197" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10247">At first, he encountered a few travellers; but, his imagination filled with these ugly apprehensions, he had not the courage to stop any one and inquire his way. "He said six miles—this man!" thought he to himself; "if out of the regular road these six should become eight or ten, these legs which have walked thus far will walk the rest of the way. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10248" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10257">I am not going towards Milan, that is certain; therefore I am going towards the Adda. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10258" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10265">Travel on and on, and sooner or later I shall arrive there. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10266" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10282">The Adda has a loud voice; and when I shall have arrived in her neighbourhood, I shall no longer require any one to direct me. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10283" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10324">If there happen to be any boat in which I can cross the river, I will cross immediately; should it be otherwise, I will wait until morning, in a field, on the grass, like the sparrows; better lie on the grass than in prison." Very soon he saw a small pathway open to the left; he entered it. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="3">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10325" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10348">Had he met any one at this hour, he would no longer have been so ceremonious about inquiring his way, but he saw no living soul. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10349" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10362">He therefore went where the path conducted him, and thought— *I play the devil! </note>
        </p>
        <p n="4">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10363" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10367">I assassinate all the Signori! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10368" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10372">A packet of letters! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10373" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10382">My companions who were keeping watch! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10383" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10415">I would give something to find myself face to face with this merchant on the other side of the Adda (ah, when I shall only have crossed this blessed Adda!), then to stop him, and demand politely where he had obtained all this beautiful information. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10416" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10509">Know now, my dear sir, that it happened so and so, and that my playing the devil consisted in my assisting Ferrer, as though he had been my brother; know that these rogues, who to* believe you were my friends, wished to play me an ugly trick, because I, in a certain moment, spoke to them like a good Christian; know that, whilst you were busy guarding your shop, I got my ribs squeezed in order to save your Signor Vicar of provisions, whom I had before neither seen nor known. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10510" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10518">You may wait for my putting myself out of the way to assist Signori again. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10519" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10529">It is true, one must do this to save one's soul; they are also our neighbours, these Signori. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10530" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10564">And as to the great packet of letters about which there was all this stir, and which you know for certainty is now in the hands of the officers of justice, let us bet that I make it appear here, without the help of the devil? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10565" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10570">Are you curious to see this packet? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10571" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10572">Here it is. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10573" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10575">One single letter! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10576" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10632">Yes, sir, one single letter; and this letter, if you wish to know it, was written by a religious man who could instruct you in every kind of learning whatsoever; a religious man, a single hair of whose beard is worth more than the whole of yours; and this letter is written, as you see, to another religious man, also a man who </note>
        </p>
        <p n="5">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10633" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10640">"Only see now who are the rascals, my friends. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10641" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10674">Learn how to speak another time, particularly when it concerns your neighbour." But after some time, these thoughts and similar ones entirely ceased; present circumstances wholly occupied the faculties of the poor pilgrim. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="6">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10675" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10703">The fear of being pursued and discovered, which during the day had embittered his journey so much, no longer annoyed him; but how many other things rendered this nocturnal journey still more wearisome! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10704" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10775">The gloom, the solitude, and his ever-increasing and painful fatigue. There blew a chill breeze, steady and keen; a breeze not very likely to be agreeable to one who still wore the same garments he had put on to be married in, intending immediately after the ceremony to return home in triumph. This was certainly not very agreeable, but to increase his miseries, there was this travelling on as chance directed, or rather this groping about, in search of a place of repose and security. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="7">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10776" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10810">When he passed through a village, he walked on very, very slowly, looking about, however, to see whether there were any door still open, but the only sign he perceived of people being yet up was here and there some light streaming through a window. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10811" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10831">When he had left the hamlet behind him, he would stop every now and then, and listen if he could hear the voice of the Adda, but in vain. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10832" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10853">He heard no other sound than the yelling of dogs which proceeded from some solitary cottage, travelling through the air at once plaintive and menacing. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10854" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10903">Upon his approach to some one of these cottages, this yell would change itself into an animated and furious bark, and passing before the door he heard, and almost saw, the animal with his nose at the sill of the door, redoubling his noise—a circumstance which removed the temptation of knocking and demanding shelter. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10904" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10925">And perhaps even without the dogs, he would not have been able to resolve upon this step. "Who is there?" will be the answer, he thought; "what do you want at this hour? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10926" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10929">How are you come here? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10930" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10931">Let us know who you are? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10932" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10936">Are there no inns where you could pass the night?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10937" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10962">This is the best answer I shall receive if I knock; even should no coward sleep there, who should immediately commence crying, 'help, thieves!' </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10963" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10976">One must have something explicit to give in reply—and what reply can I give? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10977" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11045">People who hear a noise at night never imagine anything but thieves, profligates, ambuscades; they never think that an honest man may find himself on the highway at night, unless he be a gentleman in his carriage. On this account, therefore, he determined only to have recourse to this at the very last extremity, and pushed forward in the hope of at least discovering the Adda, if not of crossing it this same night, and thus not be again obliged to seek the river in broad daylight. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="8">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11046" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11062">He walked on and on, and arrived where the cultivated country died away into a plain, scattered over with fern and broom. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11063" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11084">This appeared to him, if not a sign, at least an argument in favour of his approach to the river; he advanced along the plain, following a path which traversed it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11085" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11094">Having taken a few steps, he stopped to listen, but again in vain. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11095" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11131">The weariness of the journey was increased by the savage character of the scenery, where no longer was seen a single walnut-tree, a vine, nor any one of those other signs of cultivation which in the commencement of his journey had been for him a kind of half companionship. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11132" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11169">He continued still to advance, and as certain images and apparitions began to haunt him, apparitions called forth by the tales he had heard related when a child, he, in order to expel or pacify them, commenced reciting the prayers for the dead; and thus he pursued his way. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="9">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11170" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11185">By degrees he found himself among shrubs of a greater height, among plum-trees and dwarf-oaks. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11186" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11220">Still advancing, and lengthening his strides with more impatience than joy, he began to perceive among the low bushes, here and there, a tree, and pursuing the same path, he reached a wood. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11221" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11247">He felt a certain repugnance to advance into it, but conquering the sentiment, he proceeded much against his will, but the farther he advanced, the more his repugnance increased, the more did every object excite his uneasiness. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11248" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11296">The trees which he saw in the distance presented to his excited imagination strange, deformed, and monstrous shapes; the shadows of the agitated tree-tops, which trembled on the pathway, illuminated, as it was, here and there, by the moonlight, annoyed him; even in the rustling of the dry leaves which he trampled under foot, there was for his ear something indescribably hateful. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11297" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11318">His legs were impelled forward, whilst, at the same time, they appeared scarcely able to support his body. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11319" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11359">He felt the night-breeze blow still more cold and sharp against his brow and cheeks, he felt it penetrate between his garments and his flesh, stiffening them, and reaching even his bones, which already ached with weariness, thus extinguishing the last remains of vigour. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11360" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11380">At one moment this antipathy, this indefinite horror, against which his mind had combated some time, appeared as though it would at once overpower him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11381" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11405">He was on the point of losing his senses; but terrified by his own fear more than by anything else, he recalled his former courage, and was determined that this should rule him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11406" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11447">Thus having for a moment strengthened himself, he stood still to deliberate, and resolved immediately to leave this wood by the path along which he had just come, to return straight to the last village through which he had passed, to find himself again among human beings, and to seek shelter even at the inn. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11448" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11474">Whilst he thus stood deliberating, the rustling of his feet among the leaves ceased, all was silent around him, and he for the first time heard a sound, a murmuring of flowing water. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11475" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11482">He listened, was certain; and exclaimed, "It is the Adda!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11483" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11491">It was to him like the discovery of a friend, of a brother, of a saviour. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11492" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11538">His weariness vanished, his pulse returned, he felt his blood flow freely and warmly through all his veins, he felt his confidence increase, and in a great degree the uncertainty and horror of the surrounding objects vanished, he no longer hesitated to advance farther into the forest, and pressed on towards this friendly murmur. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="10">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11539" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11565">He arrived in a few moments at the extremity of the plain, upon the edge of a steep precipice; and looking below, he saw between the bushes which clothed the shore, the waters sparkling and flowing onward. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11566" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11602">Then raising his eyes he perceived the vast plain of the opposite shore, scattered over with hamlets, and beyond, the hills, upon one of which he distinguished a large whitish spot which seemed to him must be a town, no doubt Bergamo. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11603" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11641">He descended the declivity a little way, and separating the bushes and brambles with his hands and arms, he looked below whether any friendly bark were moving on the river; he listened for the stroke of oars, but he neither heard nor saw anything. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11642" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11668">Had this been a river less considerable than the Adda, Renzo would immediately have descended and attempted to ford it; but he knew very well that the Adda was not a stream to be too confidently trusted in. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="11">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11669" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11683">Therefore he began deliberating with great coolness upon the course to pursue. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11684" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11717">To lie down on the grass and wait there for the dawn, for the next six hours perhaps, with this breeze, with this hoar frost, and thus lightly clothed, was certainly more than sufficient to benumb him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11718" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11752">To walk to and fro all this time, besides being but a poor defence against the rigour of the night air, was demanding too much from those poor legs which had already done more than their duty. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11753" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11804">He recollected to have seen in one of the fields nearest to the heath, one of those huts covered with straw, constructed of branches and tree trunks, and then plastered over with mud, in which the Milanese peasants are accustomed in summer to deposit their harvest, and whither they repair to watch it; during the remainder of the year these huts are abandoned. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11805" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11826">This then he immediately chose as his hostel; he again struck into the pathway, traversed again the wood, the thicket, the heath, and walked on towards the hut. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11827" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11863">A worm-eaten and disconnected door, without either key or bolt, had fallen backwards; Renzo pulled it aside, entered, and saw a hurdle suspended in the air, supported by boughs, after the fashion of a hammock, but he did not trouble himself to mount up into it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11864" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11880">He saw some straw lying upon the ground, and thought that even there a quiet sleep would be very delightful. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="12">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11881" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11913">Before he lay down upon this bed which Providence had prepared for him, he fell upon his knees to return thanks for this blessing, and for all the assistance he had received throughout this terrible day. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11914" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12031">He then repeated his customary prayers, and besought pardon from God for not having said them the night before; or, to use his own words, for having gone to sleep like a dog, and even worse than a dog. "And it was for this," added he, then to himself, preparing to lie down, "it was for this that I had such a beautiful awakening this morning." He collected all the straw which lay around him and covered himself with it, making of it as well as he could a sort of coverlet, so as to protect himself from the cold, which even within the hut made itself pretty sharply felt, and then huddled himself together under this straw with the intention of enjoying a good sleep, which it appeared to him he had bought more dearly than was needful. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="13">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12032" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12068">But scarcely had he closed his eyes, than in his memory, or in his imagination—I am unable to indicate the precise spot—there commenced such a coming and going to and fro of people, in such crowds, and so incessantly, that it was adieu to sleep. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12069" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12102">The merchant, the notary, the constables, the sword-cutler, the host, Ferrer, the vicar, the company in the inn, the tumult in the street, then Don Abbondio, then Don Rodrigo; in short, all people with whom Renzo had something to do. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="14">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12103" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12141">Three figures alone presented themselves unaccompanied by any bitter memory, free from every suspicion, amiable in every respect; and two images in particular, though differing much from each other, were closely united in the young man's heart—a tress of black hair and a white beard. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12142" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12160">But the pleasure which this thought excited was far from being pure and calm. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12161" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12207">Thinking of the good Friar, he felt still more acutely shame, for his escapades, for his disgusting intemperance, for the fine use he had made of the fatherly advice this good man had given him; and contemplating Lucia's image, we will not attempt to say what he felt; the reader knows the circumstances, he can imagine his feelings. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12208" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12215">And this poor Agnese, how could he have forgotten her? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12216" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12255">This Agnese who had chosen him, who had already considered him as one with her daughter, and who, since she had received from him the title of mother, had assumed a mother's language and heart, demonstrating her earnestness by deeds. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12256" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12316">But another sorrow, and not the least bitter one, was the thought that precisely owing to these kind intentions, to her having wished so well to him, the poor woman should now find herself driven from her home, a fugitive and uncertain of the future; and that she should now, by the very circumstance from which she had hoped to derive the repose and comfort of her last years, draw upon herself toil and suffering. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12317" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12320">Poor Renzo, what a night! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12321" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12329">This which should have been the fifth after his marriage! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12330" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12331">What a chamber! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12332" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12334">What a nuptial couch! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12335" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12338">After what a day! </note>
        </p>
        <p n="15">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12339" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12368">"God's will be done," exclaimed he, as his thought became ever more sorrowful and vexatious—"God's will be done. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12369" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12377">He knows what happens. He watches over us. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12378" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12384">I accept all as penance for my sin. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12385" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12440">Lucia is so good! the Almighty will not permit her to suffer long, very long!" Occupied with these thoughts he despaired of ever falling asleep, and the cold becoming insupportable, he shivered, and his teeth chattered; he sighed for the approach of day, and measured with impatience the slow course of the hours. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="16">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12441" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12462">I say measured, because he heard every half-hour the striking of a distant clock resounding through the vast silence; I imagine this must have been the clock at Trezzo. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12463" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12505">The first time that this sound fell upon his ear, thus unexpectedly, and without his being able to form any idea from whence it came, it caused a mysterious and solemn sensation, like an admonition proceeding from an unseen person, in an unknown voice. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="17">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12506" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12615">When the hammer had struck eleven strokes, which was the hour Renzo had fixed upon for his departure, he rose benumbed, fell upon his knees, and repeated with more than customary fervour his morning devotions, then stood up, stretched his arms and legs, shook his person, as though to put together all his members, which seemed inclined each one alone to act for itself, blew first into one hand, then into the other, rubbed them, and opened the door of the hut; gave a glance here and there, to see whether there were any one about, and seeing no one, sought with his eye the pathway of the evening before, immediately recognised it, and set forth. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="18">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12616" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12650">The sky gave promise of a fine day; the setting moon, pale and without beams, shone in the immense field of grey azure, which gradually towards the horizon faded away into a pale rose. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12651" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12721">Along the horizon in irregular masses extended clouds of brown and azure hues, the lower ones edged with a streak of fire, which every moment became brighter and more distinct; towards the south, other heaped-up clouds, light, and ever changing, illuminated the heavens with a thousand nameless colours; it was in short this heaven of Lombardy, so beautiful when it is beautiful, so splendid, so calm. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12722" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12764">If Renzo had been there walking for his pleasure, he would most certainly have looked upwards, and admired this dawn, so different from that which he was accustomed to see among his mountains; but he gazed upon his road, and hastened on with long strides, in order to warm himself, and arrive quickly. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12765" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12822">He again passed the field, the heath, the bushes; he traversed the wood, looking around him, laughing at himself, and feeling at the same time inwardly ashamed of the terror he had experienced there but a few hours before; he is now arrived upon the river's edge, he looks below; and between the branches he perceives a fisher's little boat, which slowly moves forward against the stream, keeping close to this bank. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12823" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12866">He immediately descends by the shortest path through the brambles, and now stands close to the river; he calls in a low voice to the fisherman, and intending merely to appear as though he asked but a favour of small moment, he, without being aware of it himself, signs to him to approach with a half-supplicating air. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12867" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12898">The fisher casts a glance along the shore, gazes attentively along the water which flows towards him, turns round to gaze along the water which has hastened past him, directs his prow towards Renzo, and reaches him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12899" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12929">Renzo, who stood on the edge of the shore, almost with one foot in the water, seized the prow of the boat, leaped in and said: "Will you do me the favour of putting me over to the other side? I will pay you for it." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="20">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12930" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12939">The fisher having divined his desire, had already turned his boat in this direction. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12940" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12952">Renzo perceived another oar lying in the boat, and stooped to take it. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="21">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12953" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12981">"Gently, gently," said the fisher, but then observing with what address the youth had seized upon the instrument, and with how much skill he was preparing to manage it, he added, "ah, ah! you understand the trade." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="22">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12982" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13000">"A little," replied Renzo; and he commenced rowing with a vigour and skill which was that of no amateur. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13060">Without ever slackening his exertions he cast every now and then a gloomy glance towards the shore from which they were hastening, and a glance of impatience towards the one whither they were borne. Renzo was in an agony at not being able to proceed more quickly, for the current was in some places too rapid for them to pass straight across; and the boat, partly opposing, partly following the stream of water, was obliged to pursue a diagonal course. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13061" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13116">In all affairs which are somewhat perplexing, the difficulties present themselves at first in a mass; but when the time for action arrives, they start up one by one in an endless succession. Thus it was with Renzo. Now that the Adda might almost be said to be passed, his being uncertain whether here the river served as the boundary line between the two states caused him much uneasiness, as did also the fear that even should this obstacle be overcome, there might still remain for him some other to surmount. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13117" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13146">He called therefore to the fisherman, and motioning with his head towards this white spot which he had perceived the preceding night, and which now was much more distinct, he said, "Is that place Bergamo?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="23">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13147" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13153">"The town of Bergamo," replied the fisherman. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="24">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13154" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13159">"And this shore, does it belong to Bergamo?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="25">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13160" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13163">"It is the territory of San Marco." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="26">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13164" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13168">"Long live San Marco!" exclaimed Renzo. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13169" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13173">The fisherman said nothing. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="27">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13174" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13268">At length they touch this shore; Renzo throws himself out of the boat; he inwardly returns thanks to God, and with his lips expresses his gratitude to the boatman. He puts his hand into his pocket and draws forth a berlinga, which, considering the circumstances, was no small generosity, and offers it to this brave man, who, having again cast a glance towards the Milanese shore, and looked up and down the river, stretches forth his hand, takes the money, puts it into his pocket, then compresses his lips and places his forefinger across them, accompanying this gesture with an expressive glance, and then saying, "a good journey to you," he turns back. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="28">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13269" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13326">In order that the ready and obliging courtesy of this man towards a stranger should not be unintelligible to the reader, we must inform him that this man, often besought by smugglers and outlaws, was accustomed to render them similar services, not so much on account of the small and uncertain profit that might thus accrue to him, as through fear of making himself enemies among these two classes. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13327" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13345">He rendered this service, I say, whenever he could be sure of not being seen by custom-house officers, constables, or spies. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13346" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13381">Thus, without wishing more good to one class than to the other, he endeavoured to satisfy all, by exercising that impartiality which is the usual characteristic of those who are obliged to act with one party and render account of their actions to another. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="29">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13382" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13428">Renzo stopped a moment to contemplate the opposite shore, that earth which but so short a time before had seemed to burn under his feet. "Ah! here I am, safely out of it," was his first thought. "Rest there, "cursed land," was his second, his farewell to his country. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13429" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13438">But his third carried him back to those he left behind. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13439" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13480">Then he folded his arms upon his breast, heaved a sigh, cast his eyes upon the water which flowed at his feet, and thought—"it has passed under the bridge!" For thus, according to the manner of his country, he called the one at Lecco. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13481" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13516">"Ah, infamous world! enough; God's will be done!" He turned his back upon these sorrowful objects, and set forth on his farther travel, taking for his guiding point the whitish spot upon the mountain slope, until he should find some one from whom he might inquire the proper road. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="30">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13517" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13537">You really ought to have seen with what an easy air he accosted the passers-by, and how he named, without any evasion, the village in which his cousin resided. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13538" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13552">From the first traveller to whom he referred, he had learned that there yet remained nine miles for him to walk. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="31">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13553" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13557">This journey was not agreeable. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13558" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13594">Without speaking of the woes which Renzo carried along with him, sorrowful objects excited his sympathy every moment, objects which must have informed him that he would find in this country which he was about to enter, poverty such as he had left in his own. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13595" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13643">All along the road, and even still more in the villages and hamlets, he encountered beggars at every step, not beggars by profession, but from necessity, and they exhibited misery more in their countenances than in their garments; there were peasants, mountaineers, artisans, whole families together; and there was heard a confused hum of prayers, lamentations, and cries. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13644" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13678">This sight, besides exciting his compassion and melancholy, recalled his own affairs. "Who knows," he meditated, "whether I shall find anything to do? Whether there will be work as in the past years? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13679" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13696">But enough, Bortolo wishes me well; he is a good fellow; he has made money, he has often invited me to come to him, he will not abandon me. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13697" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13769">And then Providence has assisted me until the present time; Providence will assist me in the future." Meanwhile his appetite, which had already been aroused some time, was increased by every mile; and although Renzo felt, as soon as he began to pay any attention to it, that he should be able, without great inconvenience, to restrain it during the two or three miles which yet remained, still he considered that it would not be well to present himself before his cousin like a beggar, and say to him, as his first compliment, "Give me to eat." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="32">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13770" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13786">He drew forth from his pocket all his fortune, and counted it in his hand. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13787" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13803">This was no account to require a great arithmetician; however, there was enough wherewith to make a little feast. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13804" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13821">He entered a public-house to refresh himself; and in fact, having paid his bill, there still remained a few pence over. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="33">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13822" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13890">Going forth, he saw, so close to the door that he had nearly stumbled over them, two women reclining rather than sitting on the earth, one aged, the other younger, with an infant which, after in vain having sucked first at one breast and then at the other, cried most bitterly; all bore the hue of death; near them stood a man, in whose countenance and limbs might still be discovered the traces of former vigour; a vigour now humbled and exhausted by long fasting. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13891" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13915">All the three stretched out their hands towards Renzo, who issued forth with a free step and reanimated air; not one spoke; what more could a prayer have said? </note>
        </p>
        <p n="34">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13916" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13948">"Here is an alms," said Renzo, and thrust his hand into his pocket, brought forth these pieces of money, placed them in the hand nearest to him, and pursued his way. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="35">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13949" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13968">This repast, and this good action (for we are composed both of soul and body) had comforted him, and enlivened his thoughts. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13969" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13993">In truth, after having been thus dispossessed of his last remaining money, he was inspired with a greater confidence in Providence than if he had found ten times the sum. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13994" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14057">For, if, in order this day to support these unfortunate people, Providence had held in reserve the last pence of a stranger, of a fugitive, who himself was also uncertain of his means of livelihood, how could he then believe that Providence would abandon the one she had thus made use of, the one whom she had inspired with such a lively confidence in herself, with such a resolute and beneficial confidence? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14058" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14077">Such were pretty nearly the thoughts of our youth, although perhaps even less clearly expressed than we have here given them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14078" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14089">During the remainder of his journey, meditating upon his affairs, all seemed to explain itself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14090" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14123">The famine must have an end; there is a harvest every year; in the meanwhile, he had his cousin Bortolo and his own skill; and besides, at home he had a little money which he would have sent immediately to him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14124" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14210">With this, even at the worst, he could exist from day to day until abundance should return. "And then abundance having at length returned," continued Renzo in his imagination, "the heat of trade recommences; the masters contend with each other in procuring Milanese workmen, for it is they who best understand their business; the Milanese workmen hold their heads high; those who will have able workmen must pay for them; there may be earned more than enough for one person, there will be something that may be laid aside; and I can get some one to write the women word to come — And then, why wait at all? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14211" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14227">Is it not true that with this little hoard we should have managed to exist together at Lecco, even through this winter? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14228" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14230">We can exist here just as well. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14231" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14236">There are curates everywhere. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14237" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14245">Then let these two dear women come; we will keep house here. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14246" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14343">What pleasure it would be to walk along this road all together! To go as far as the Adda in a cart, to take some refreshment on the bank, upon the bank itself, to shew these dear creatures the place where I have embarked, the wild plum-tree by which I descended, the point where I stood to look out for a boat." At length he arrived at his cousin's village. Entering, nay, even before he had set foot in the street, he observed a very tall house with a more than usual number of very high windows; he recognised in it a silk-manufactory, entered it, and amidst the roar of wheels and falling water, demanded in a loud voice whether a certain Bortolo Castagneri lived there. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="37">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14344" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14346">"The Signor Bortolo? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14347" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14361">There he is." "Signor? a good sign," thought Renzo; he sees his cousin, he flies towards him. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="38">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14362" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14372">The cousin turns round, recognises the youth, and says, "Here I am." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14373" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14385">There is an "Oh!" of surprise, a raising of arms, a falling on each other's neck. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14386" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14418">After this reception, Bortolo draws aside our youth into a chamber, far from the noise of the machinery and the eyes of the curious, and says to him, "I am most happy to see thee, but thou art a strange fellow. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14419" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14435">I have invited thee so often, and thou wouldst never come; now thou art arrived in a somewhat critical moment." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="39">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14436" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14465">"Why, if I must tell thee, I am not come away now by my own free will," said Renzo; and then with much brevity, but not without much emotion, he recounted his sad history. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="40">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14466" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14473">"That's another affair," said Bortolo. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14474" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14476">"O poor Renzo! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14477" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14487">But thou hast counted on me, and I will not abandon thee. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14488" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14517">Truly at the present time no one runs after workmen; people can scarcely keep on their own, in order not to lose them and interrupt business; but our master wishes me well, and has money. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14518" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14537">And in great part he owes it to me, I can tell thee, without praising myself; he has capital, and I have ability. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14538" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14550">Dost thou know I am his first workman? And then I must tell thee I am his factotum. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14551" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14553">Poor Lucia Mondella! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14554" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14577">I recollect her as though it were but yesterday — a good girl! Always the most modest in the church; and when one passed by her little cottage — </note>
        </p>
        <p n="41">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14578" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14595">I seem to see this little cottage just out of the village, with a beautiful fig-tree growing beside the wall —" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="42">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14596" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14600">"No, no, don't let us speak of it." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="43">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14601" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14617">"I would say that whenever one passed this cottage one always heard her reel, which spun round, and round, and round. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14618" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14649">And this Don Rodrigo! Already in my time he had commenced his evil courses. But now, for as much as I see, he will play the devil outright, until God shall lay the bridle on his neck. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14650" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14666">As I have told thee we begin to suffer here somewhat from famine,—and by-the-bye, how is it with thy appetite?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="44">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14667" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14672">"I have eaten a short time since on my way." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="45">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14673" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14677">"And how is it with thy money?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="46">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14678" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14692">"Renzo opened one hand, brought it near his mouth and blew into it." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="47">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14693" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14720">"That does not matter," said Bortolo; "I have plenty. Very soon things will alter, God willing thou canst repay me, or lay by for thyself." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="48">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14721" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14729">"I have something at home, and I will have it sent." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="49">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14730" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14737">"That is good. In the meantime draw upon me. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14738" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14760">God has been good towards me, in order that I may do good; and if I do not do good to my relations and friends, to whom ought I?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="50">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14761" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14774">"Have I not said that Providence would assist me!" exclaimed Renzo, pressing affectionately his good cousin's hand. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="51">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14775" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14784">"Well then," replied the other, "they have made all this uproar in Milan. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14785" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14790">They seem to me rather like fools, these people. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14791" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14808">The report had already reached us. But I should like thee to relate me the affair more minutely. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14809" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14814">Ah! we have plenty to talk about. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14815" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14832">Here, however, thou seest things go on somewhat better, and affairs are managed with more judgment. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14833" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14866">The town has purchased two thousand some of corn from a merchant who is at Venice. This is corn which comes from Turkey; but when eating is concerned, people are not so dainty. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14867" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14891">Now hear what happened, it happened that the governors of Verona and Brecia closed the means of communication, and said; no grain shall be exported from here. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14892" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14896">What do the people of Bergamo? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14897" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14906">They send to Venice, Lorenzo Torre, a doctor, but one good for something! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14907" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14925">He set off in haste, and presented himself to the Doge, and said, "only think what an idea is this that the governors have got in their heads?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14926" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14935">It is such a speech they say, such a speech, a speech to be printed! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14936" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14944">That is having a man who knows how to speak. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14945" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14970">And immediately an order was issued that the corn should be allowed to pass; and the governors not only allow it to pass, but are obliged to give it escort, and the corn is now on its way. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14971" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14976">And the country has also been considered. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14977" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15010">Giovanbatista Biava, ambassador from Bergamo at Venice (an excellent man also), has given the senate to understand that the famine is felt in the country; and the senate has granted us four thousand staia of millet. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15011" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15016">Even this helps to make bread. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15017" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15029">And then, if we cannot eat bread, we will live upon meat. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n189" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15030" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15038">The Lord has given me property, as I have told thee. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n190" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15039" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15056">Now I will conduct thee to my master; he has often heard thee spoken of, and will give thee a good reception. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n191" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15057" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15065">He is a thorough Bergamascan of the old sort, a man with a large heart. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n192" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15066" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15090">Certainly he did not expect thee just now; but when he has heard thy story — and then he knows how to value workmen, for the famine passes away, and business lasts. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n193" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15091" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15099">But first of all, I must inform thee of something. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n194" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15100" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15112">Dost thou know what they call us Milanese in this country?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="52">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n195" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15113" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15115">"What do they call us?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n196" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15116" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15118">"They call us baggiani" (simpletons). </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n197" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15119" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15123">"That is not a nice name." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n198" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15124" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15139">"What matters it? Whoever is born in the Milanese, and desires to live in the territory of Bergamo, must receive it quietly. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n199" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15140" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15155">For these people address simpleton to a Milanese, as we should illustrissimo to a gentleman." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="53">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n200" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15156" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15165">"They say it, I imagine, to those who will allow them." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="54">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n201" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15166" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15186">"My good lad, if thou art not disposed to endure the simpleton, thou hadst better not count upon living here. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n202" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15187" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15225">Thou wouldst always be obliged to carry thy knife in thy hand, and even; let us suppose that thou hast killed two, three, or even four fellows, one would come at last and kill thee; and then what a pleasure it would be to appear before God's tribunal with three or four homicides upon thy soul!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="55">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n203" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15226" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15247">"And a Milanese, who should have a little——" and here he struck his forehead with his finger, as he had done in the full moon. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n204" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15248" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15256">"I would say one who knows something of his business?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="56">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n205" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15257" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15263">"All the same, here he is also a simpleton. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n206" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15264" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15301">Dost thou know how my master speaks of me when he talks with his friends? This simpleton has been sent by God to benefit my business; if I had not this simpleton I should be badly off. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n207" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15302" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15304">This is the custom." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="57">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n208" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15305" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15330">"It is a foolish custom, and particularly when they know what we can do. And after all, who is it that has brought here these arts, and set them going? No one but us. Is it possible that this has not brought them to reason?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="58">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n209" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15331" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15356">"At present it has not; with time, perhaps it may. The children perhaps may change; but for the men grown there is no remedy; they have contracted the bad habit; they will not lay it aside. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n210" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15357" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15359">After all, what is it? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n211" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15360" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15380">The trifles thy country people have done and would do for thee, is quite another thing." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n212" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15381" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15389">"Certainly, that's true; if there is no other evil—" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="59">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n213" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15390" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15398">"Well, now that thou art persuaded of this, all will go on well. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n214" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15399" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15403">Come to the master, and be of good courage." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="60">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n215" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15404" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15422">And in fact all did go on well; the promises of Bortolo were realised. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap17-n216" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15423" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15446">There was really Providence at work, for we shall see directly how little was to be hoped from the property and money which Renzo had left at home. </note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>