<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CHAPTER I.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>1845</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed Lovers: a Milanese Story of the Seventeenth Century. With The Column of Infamy by Alessandro Manzoni. In Three Volumes</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
          <date>1845</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Henry Francis C. Logan</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="English_1845_cap1">
        <p n="1">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10111">That branch of the lake of Como which flows towards the south between two uninterrupted chains of mountains, full of creeks and bays, according to their advance and retreat, compresses itself almost at once, and takes the course and form of a river, between a promontory on the one hand, and a wide coast on the other; and the bridge which here connects the two shores, appears to render this transformation still more sensible to the eye, and marks the point where the lake ceases and the Adda recommences to take again the name of the lake, where the shores stretching out anew allow the water to extend and develope itself in new gulfs and bays. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10112" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10203">The shore formed from the deposit of these great torrents, ascends, supported by two contiguous mountains, one called San Martino, the other, in the dialect of Lombardy, il Resegone, from its many summits in a line, which, in truth, make it resemble a saw, so that one seeing it for the first time, provided this were from the front, as, for example, from the ramparts of Milan on the northern side, would recognise immediately by this denomination, this long and vast ridge, from among the other mountains, of names more obscure and forms more common. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10204" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10238">For a considerable distance the coast descends with a gentle and continuous declivity, then breaks itself into hills and dales, descents and levels, according to the formation of the two mountains and the work of the waters. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10239" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10275">The extreme edge, torn by the mouths of the torrents, is scarcely anything but sand and pebbles; the rest fields and vineyards, scattered over with hamlets, towns, and villages; and in some parts are woods, which stretch themselves up the mountains. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10276" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10320">Lecco, the principal of these hamlets, and the one which gives its name to the territory, lies not far distant from the bridge on the shore of the lake, and even finds itself partly in the lake when the waters increase; it is at the present day a large village, and seems in a fair way to become a town. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="2">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10321" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10403">At the time the events occurred which we undertake to relate, this village, already important, was moreover a fortress, and therefore had the honour of lodging a commandant, and the advantage of possessing a stationary garrison of Spanish soldiers, who taught the girls and the women of the country modesty, who, from time to time, saluted the shoulders of some husband or father, and who, at the end of summer, never failed to employ themselves in the vineyards, thinning the grapes, and relieving the peasants of the fatigues of the vintage. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10404" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10505">From one to the other of these hamlets, from the heights to the shores, from hill to hill, ran and yet run roads and by-roads, more or less steep or level; some very deep, buried between two walls, whence, raising your eyes, you only perceive a piece of sky and some mountain summit; others elevated upon open terraces; and here the eye wanders over prospects more or less extensive, but always rich and always new, according as the different points take in more or less of the vast surrounding scene, and according as this or that part of the landscape foreshortens itself, stands forth, or disappears by turns. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10506" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10597">Here one picturesque bit, there another; here a long extent of this vast and varied mirror of water. On this hand the lake shut in at the extremity, or rather losing itself among the windings of a group of mountains, and then gradually extending itself among others, which present themselves, one by one, to the view, reflected in the water upside-down, with lovely landscapes upon the shores. Here the arm of the river, there the lake; then again the river, losing itself in lucid windings between two chains of mountains, which accompany it, fade away in the distance, and lose themselves in the horizon. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10598" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10683">The place itself, whence you contemplate these varied visions, presents every where wonders and beauties; the mountain, whose side you traverse, unfolds itself above and around; its summit and cliffs, distinct and erect, change at every step, opening and forming into many peaks that which at first had appeared only one, and present that effect in mountain tops which we have just observed in the shores; the soft and domestic character of the mountain slopes tempers gradually what is savage, and adorns still more the magnificence of the other scenes. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="3">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10684" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10732">By one of these pathways returned home very leisurely from a walk, on the evening of the 7th of November of the year 1628, Don Abbondio, curate of one of the above-mentioned hamlets. Neither the name of this hamlet, nor the surname of this personage, is to be found in the manuscript, either in this place or elsewhere. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10733" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10831">He repeated tranquilly the divine service, and each time between one psalm and another closed his breviary, keeping in it as a mark the first finger of his left hand, and placing then the right hand behind him, pursued his way, gazing on the ground, and kicking with his foot towards the wall the pebbles which obstructed the path. Now he raised his head, and casting his eyes idly around him, fixed them on that part of a mountain which the light of the already sunken sun, escaping through the clefts of the opposite chain of hills, had coloured here and there with unequal streaks of purple. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10832" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10866">Now he again opened the breviary, and reciting another passage, arrived at a turn of the road where he was always accustomed to raise his eyes from the book and look around him, — on this day he did as usual. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10867" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10919">After this turn, the road ran straight forwards, perhaps sixty paces, and then divided itself into two little paths, in the form of a Y: the one to the right ascended towards the mountain, and led to the curacy; the other descended into the valley until it reached a torrent; at this part the wall did not reach above the waist of the passer-by. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10920" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10995">The inner walls of these two pathways, instead of uniting at the angle, terminated in a little chapel, upon which were depicted certain long, winding figures, terminating in points, which, according to the intention of the artist, to the eyes of the inhabitants of the neighbourhood should represent flames; and, alternating with these flames, certain other figures imposable to describe, which should be souls in purgatory; souls and flames brick colour, upon a greyish ground, with plaster here and there. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10996" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11020">The curate took this road, and directing his looks as usual towards the little chapel, saw something he did not expect, and most certainly would not have wished to see. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11021" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11070">Two men stood, one opposite the other, at the confluence, so to say, of the two paths; one of them astride upon the low wall, one leg dangling outwards, the other placed on the road; his companion stood leaning against the wall, with his arms crossed upon his breast. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11071" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11093">Their dress, their deportment, and what the curate could perceive of their appearance from the spot where he had arrived, left no doubt regarding their condition. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11094" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11193">They had each of them round their heads a little green net, which fell back upon the left shoulder, and terminated in a large tassel; out of this net protruded upon the forehead an enormous tuft of hair. A large moustache curling in points, a shining leathern girdle to which were attached two pistols, a little horn full of powder hanging upon the breast like a necklace, the handle of an immense knife peeping forth from the pocket of the ample and full breeches, and a large sword, with a heavy handle richly open-worked with plates of brass, polished and bright, made them known as individuals of the class of bravoes. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="4">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11194" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11208">This class, now entirely lost, was then very flourishing in Lombardy, and already very ancient. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11209" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11238">For those who have no idea of this class, here are some authentic sketches, which will be able to give a sufficiently good one of its principal characteristics, of the endeavours made to destroy it, and of its audacious existence. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="5">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11239" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11307">On the 8th of April 1583, the very illustrious and excellent Signor don Carlo of Arragon, Prince of Castelvetrano, Duke of Terranuovo, Marquis of Avola, Count of Burgeto, Grand-Admiral and Grand-Constable of Sicily, Governor of Milan, and Captain-General of His Catholic Majesty in Italy, "fully informed of the intolerable misery in which the city of Milan has lived, and still lives, by reason of bravoes and vagabonds," publishes a proclamation against them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11308" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11371">"He proclaims and defines all those to be included in this proclamation, and liable to be imprisoned as bravoes and vagabonds, who, being foreigners, or belonging to the country, have no occupation, or, having one, do not employ themselves therewith, but without a salary, or with one, depend upon some cavalier or gentleman, officer or merchant, to aid and favour him, or really, as may be presumed, to do injury to others." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="6">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11372" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11409">To all these he orders, that within the term of six days they shall remove themselves out of the country, intimates the galleys to the stubborn, and gives to the officers of justice the most ample and unlimited power for the execution of these orders. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11410" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11546">But in the following year, April the 12th, this Signor, "seeing that the city is still full of the said bravoes, returned to live as they lived at first, their customs not in the least changed, nor their numbers diminished," puts forth another proclamation still more vigorous and worthy of notice, in which, among other ordinances, he prescribes— "That whatsoever person, either of this city, or a foreigner, who by two witnesses shall be believed and commonly reputed a bravo, and bear this name, even although he shall have done offence to no one, for this sole reputation of bravo, without other proof, may, by the aforesaid judges, or by any one of them, be delivered over to the rack and torture, in order to procure information; and still not confessing himself guilty of any crime, may be sent to the galleys for the space of three years, for the sole reputation and name of bravo as above." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="7">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11547" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11566">All this, and still more before the end, "since his Excellence is resolved to make himself obeyed by every one." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="8">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11567" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11599">Hearing from so great a lord, words thus bold and confident, accompanied by such orders, one is tempted to believe, that, alone at their very sound, all the bravoes have disappeared for ever. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11600" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11619">But the testimony of a lord, not less to be credited, nor less endowed with names, obliges us to believe to the contrary. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11620" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11732">This is the very illustrious and excellent Signor Juan Fernandez de Velasco, Constable of Castile, Grand-Chamberlain to his Majesty, Duke of the town of Frias, Count of Flaro and of Castelnovo, Signor of the house of Velasco, and of the Seven Infants of Lara, Governor of the State of Milan, etc. On the 5th of June 1593, he also, fully informed of how much misery and ruin is occasioned by these bravoes and vagabonds, and of the very great evil done by this kind of people to the public good, in despite of justice, intimates to them again, that within the term of six days they have to quit the country, and repeating very nearly the same ordinances, and the same menaces as his predecessor. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11733" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11816">Then the 23d of May 1598, being informed with no small grief, that in this city, each day, the number of these same bravoes and vagabonds continues to increase, and that nothing is heard of them, either day or night, but relations of premeditated assassinations, homicides, robberies, and all other manners of crime; this being rendered all the more easy, through the bravoes being confident of the assistance of their superiors and protectors,—prescribes again the same remedy; increasing the dose, as is customary in obstinate disorders. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11817" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11859">"Every one, therefore," he then concludes, "shall guard himself from infringing in the slightest degree the present proclamation, otherwise instead of experiencing the clemency of his Excellence, he will experience his rigour and anger, he being resolved and determined that this shall be a last, and enduring admonition." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11860" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12072">But the very illustrious and excellent Signor don Pietro Enriquez de Ecevedo, Count di Fuentes, Captain and Governor of the State of Milan, was not of this opinion; he was not of this opinion, and that for very good reasons. *Being fully informed of the misery in which the city and state of Milan exists, by reason of the number of bravoes which there abounds, he is determined totally to exterminate this most pernicious race, and publishes, on the 5th December 1600, a new proclamation, full also of the most severe measures, with the firm intention that they shall, with every rigour, and without the hope of remission, be fully put in execution.* One is led to believe, however, that in this again he did not apply himself with the same good will, which he knew how to make use of in planning a cabal, or in exciting enemies against his great enemy Henry IV.; since upon this point, history attests to his success in arming against the Duke of Savoy, whom he caused to lose more than one city, and to his success also in exciting the Duke di Biron to join in a conspiracy, whom he caused to lose his head; but what concerns this most pernicious race of bravoes, certain it is that it still continued to increase to the 22d of September 1612, on which day the very illustrious and excellent Signor don Giovanni de Mendoza, Marquis de la Hynojoosa, gentleman, etc., governor, etc., thought seriously about extirpating it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12073" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12097">To this effect he sent to Pandolfo and Marco Tullio Malatesti, royal printers, the customary proclamation, corrected and enlarged, in order that it should be printed for the extermination of the bravoes. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12098" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12191">But these still lived on to receive the 24th of December, of the year 1618, the same and still stronger blows from the very illustrious and excellent Signor Don Gomez Suarez de Figueroa, Duke de Feria, etc., governor, etc. However, they still not being dead, the illustrious and excellent Signor Gonzalo Fernandez di Cordova, under whose government the walk of Don Abbondio took place, had found himself obliged to recorrect and republish the customary proclamation against the bravoes, the 5th of October 1627; that is, a year, a month, and a day, before this memorable event which we relate. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="9">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12192" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12215">Neither was this the last publication; but we do not believe ourselves bound to mention the later ones. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12216" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12253">We will only hint that on the 15th February 1632, in which year the very illustrious and excellent Signor the Duke of Feria was for the second time governor; he informs us that *the greatest acts of wickedness proceeded from those called bravoes*. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12254" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12268">This assures us sufficiently that in the time of which we treat there were bravoes everywhere. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="10">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12269" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12302">That the two described above, stood here expecting some one, was a thing very evident; but what most displeased Don Abbondio was his being led to perceive by certain actions that the expected one was himself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12303" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12355">Since, when he appeared, these two glanced at each other, raising their heads with a movement, which shewed that both exclaimed, "It is he." The one who was astride, rose, placing one leg upon the road; the other moved away from the wall, and both came towards him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12356" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12389">He, still holding his breviary open, as though he read, glanced over it, to watch the motions of these two, and seeing them come directly towards him, was assailed at once with a thousand thoughts. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12390" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12451">He quickly questioned himself in great fear, as to whether between himself and the bravoes there were at the right or the left any outlet from the road, and as quickly recollected that there was none. He then made a rapid examination as to whether he had sinned against any powerful or vindictive noble; but still, in the midst of this tumult, the consoling testimony of his conscience reassured him somewhat. The bravoes, however, advanced towards him, their eyes fixed upon him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12452" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12497">He placed the first and second finger of his left hand in his collar, as though he would arrange it, and moving the two fingers round the collar, turned at the same time his face over his shoulder, twisting his mouth about, and glancing with the corner of his eye to see whether any one arrived. But he saw no one. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12498" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12517">He gave a glance over the little wall into the fields,—no one;—another more modest one on to the road before him; no one, except the bravoes. What was to be done? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12518" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12536">Turn back? For that there was no time. Run away? That was the same as to say follow me, or worse. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12537" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12561">Not being able to escape the danger, he rushed to meet it, since the moments of this uncertainty were so painful to him that he desired only to shorten them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12562" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12607">He hastened his step, recited a little verse with a louder voice, composed his countenance to as much quietness and hilarity as he could, and made every effort to prepare a smile. When he found himself in front of these two gentlemen, he said mentally, "here we are," and stood still. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12608" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12619">"Signor Curato," said one of these two, fixing his eyes upon him. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="11">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12620" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12640">"What do you command?" replied immediately Don Abbondio, raising his eyes from the book, which rested open in his hands as upon a desk. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="12">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12641" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12670">"You have the intention," pursued the Bravo, with the menacing and angry manner of one who surprises an inferior in a villanous undertaking, "you have the intention of marrying to-morrow Renzo Tramaglino and Lucia Mondella!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="13">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12671" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12691">"That is to say" — answered Don Abbondio, with a tremulous voice; "that is to say — you gentlemen are men of the world, and know very well how these things are managed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12692" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12724">The poor curate does not enter into the business. They lay their plans among themselves, and then — and then they come to us as they would go to a bank, — and we, we are every one's servants." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="14">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12725" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12748">"Well," said the Bravo in his ear, with a solemn tone of command, "this marriage is not to take place, neither to-morrow, nor ever." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="15">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12749" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12776">"But, my good gentlemen," replied Don Abbondio with a meek and gentle voice, as though he would persuade an impatient listener, "but, my good gentlemen, only deign to place yourselves in my shoes. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12777" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12811">If the thing depended upon me — you see very well that nothing falls into my pocket ——" "Come," interrupted the Bravo, "if the thing were to be decided by gossip, you would have the best of the argument. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12812" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12820">We don't know anything of it, neither do we wish to know more. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12821" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12824">A man who is warned—you understand us." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="16">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12825" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12832">"But you, gentlemen, are too just, too reasonable——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="17">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12833" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12872">"But," interrupted this time the other companion, who until now had said nothing; "but the marriage is not to take place, or"—and here a terrible oath—"or he who performs the marriage will never repent it,—because he will not have time, and," here another oath. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="18">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12873" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12903">"Hush, hush!" replied the first orator, "the Signor Curato is a man who knows the ways of the world; and we are gentlemen, who do not wish to do him any harm, provided he will have judgment. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12904" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12914">Signor Curato, the very illustrious Signor Don Rodrigo, our patron, greets you most cordially." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="19">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12915" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12942">This name was to the mind of Don Abbondio like a lamp, which in a tempestuous night for a moment illuminates confusedly the surrounding objects, increasing the horror. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12943" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12954">He made, as by instinct, a low bow, and said, "If you knew how to suggest to me——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="20">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12955" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12975">"O, to suggest to you, who know Latin!" interrupted the Bravo again, with a laugh between the awkward and the ferocious. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12976" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13006">"That concerns you, and above all, don't let one word escape you regarding the advice we have given you for your own good; otherwise—hem—it will be the same as performing the marriage. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13007" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13019">Well, what do you wish we should say in your name, to the illustrious Signor, our master?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="21">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13020" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13022">"My respects." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="22">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13023" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13026">"Explain yourself better?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="23">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13027" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13045">"I am disposed—disposed always to obedience;" and in proffering these words, he did not know whether he made a promise or merely a compliment. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="24">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13046" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13057">The Bravos received this message, and appeared to take it in its most serious signification. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="25">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13058" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13071">"Well, good night to you, Signor Curato," said one of them, in the act of departing with his companion. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="26">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13072" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13092">Don Abbondio, who a few moments before would have give an eye to have escaped them, would now have liked to prolong the conversation and the transaction. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13093" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13122">"Gentlemen," he began, closing the book with both hands,—but they, without listening longer to him, took the path by which he had arrived, and walked away singing a song, which we will not transcribe. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13123" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13156">Poor Don Abbondio remained some moments with his mouth open, like one enchanted; then took that one of the little roads which led to his house, dragging with difficulty one leg after the other, for his poor legs appeared benumbed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13157" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13180">How it was with him internally will be better understood when we have said something of his character, and of the times in which he lived. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="27">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13181" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13196">Don Abbondio (as the reader has already perceived) was not born with the heart of a lion. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13197" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13230">But from his earliest years he had been forced to comprehend that the very worst condition in those times was that of an animal without claws and without teeth, but which, nevertheless, feels no inclination to be devoured. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13231" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13251">The legal power did not in any instance protect the quiet and inoffensive man who had no means of causing fear to others. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13252" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13262">Not that laws and punishments for private violence were wanting. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13263" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13333">There was a deluge of laws; crimes were enume- rated and particularised with the most minute tediousness; punishments were foolishly extravagant; and if they were not sufficient, might be augmented by the arbitrary will of the legislator himself, or by the hundred other ministers of the law. The law proceedings studied only to free the judge from every thing which might be an impediment to him in pronouncing a sentence of condemnation. The sketches which we have extracted from the laws against the bravoes give a slight but faithful example of this. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13334" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13396">With this, or in great measure caused by this, these proclamations, republished and recorrected by each succeeding governor, served only to attest most amply to the impotence of their authors; or if they produced any immediate effect, it was principally to add to the many torments which the weak and peaceful already suffered from these disturbers, and to increase their violence and cunning. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13397" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13411">Impunity was organised, and had roots which the laws could neither touch nor move. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13412" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13454">Such were the asylums, such the privileges of each individual class, in part recognised by the law, in part tolerated in envious silence or attacked by vain protests; but sustained, in fact, and defended by these classes themselves, with the activity of interest and the jealousy of punctilio. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13455" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13481">Now, this impunity, menaced and insulted by these proclamations, must naturally at each menace and each insult make use of fresh strength and fresh inventions in order to preserve itself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13482" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13516">This happened in effect; and at the appearance of proclamations intended to restrain these violences, they sought, in their real strength, new means more opportune for continuing to do that which these proclamations wished to prohibit. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13517" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13562">They could fetter at every step and molest the innocent man, who was without power of his own and without protection, since, in order to prevent or punish every offence, each man was under their power, and the actions of every private individual were subjected to the arbitrary will of every description of law-officer. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13563" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13628">But he who before committing a crime took means to shelter himself in a convent or in a palace, where the officers of justice would never dare to set foot,—or he who without any other protection than a livery which engaged the vanity and interest of a powerful family to defend a whole caste, was free in his operations, and could laugh at all this noise of proclamations. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13629" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13681">Of those even who were deputed to put these laws into execution, some belonged by birth to the privileged classes, others depended upon patronage; all of them, by education, by interest, by habit, by imitation, had embraced these maxims, and would have taken great care not to offend against them merely through love to a bit of paper pasted up on the corners of the streets. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13682" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13741">If the men charged with the execution of these proclamations had been enterprising as heroes, obedient as monks, and as ready to sacrifice themselves as martyrs, they would not have been able to accomplish their purpose, inferior as they were in numbers to those who were to be subdued, and with the great probability of being abandoned by those who, in abstract, and, so to say, in theory, had imposed this work upon them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13742" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13776">But, besides this, these were generally the vilest wretches of their time; their office was despised even by those to whom it should have inspired terror, and their title was a reproach. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13777" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13837">It was, therefore, very natural that these wretches, instead of risking their lives in a desperate undertaking, should sell their inaction and connivance to the powerful, and reserve the execution of the detestable authority and power which they possessed for those occasions where there was no danger, that is, when they could oppress and torment peaceable men who were without means of defence. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="28">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13838" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13853">The man who wishes to injure, or who fears every moment to be himself injured, seeks naturally allies and companions. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13854" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13886">Hence, in those times the tendency of individuals to keep themselves knit together in classes, to form new associations, and to strive each one to increase the power of that particular class to which he belonged, was carried to the very greatest extent. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13887" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13907">The clergy sought to extend and sustain their immunities, the nobles their privileges; the military their exemptions. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13908" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13928">The merchants and artizans were enrolled in guilds and brotherhoods, the lawyers formed an alliance, the physicians even a corporation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13929" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13963">Each one of these little oligarchies had its own peculiar power; in each one the individual found the advantage of employing for himself, in proportion to his authority or his cleverness, the united strength of the many. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13964" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13999">The more honest availed themselves of this advantage for defence only, the crafty and villanous made use of it to assist their wicked purposes, for which their own private means would not have sufficed, and to insure to themselves thereby, impunity. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14000" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14060">The strength, however, of these various alliances was very unequal; and particularly in the country, the rich and violent noble, surrounded by a troop of bravoes and a population of peasantry, accustomed by family tradition, or obliged, to consider themselves as subjects or soldiers of the master, exercised a power which it would have been difficult for any alliance to resist. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="29">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14061" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14101">Our Abbondio, neither noble nor rich, still less courageous, had perceived himself, ever since his arrival at years of discretion, to be in this society, like an earthen vessel constrained to travel in company with many vessels of iron. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14102" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14114">He had, therefore, with sufficient willingness obeyed his parents, who wished him to become a priest. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14115" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14162">To say the truth, he had never reflected very seriously upon the obligations and noble object of the ministry to which he dedicated himself. To procure for himself the means of living quietly, to place himself in a revered and powerful class, appeared to him two reasons more than sufficient for such a choice. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14163" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14188">But, however powerful the class may be, it does not protect the individual, does not preserve him from danger beyond a certain point; no one dispensed with forming for himself a particular system of defence. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14189" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14215">Don Abbondio, absorbed continually in thoughts regarding his own quiet, did not trouble himself much about those advantages for the obtaining of which it would be necessary to exert himself, and to be rather bold. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14216" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14284">His system consisted principally in avoiding all quarrels, and in yielding to those which he could not avoid, in unarmed neutrality, in all the wars which raged around him, in the contests then very frequent between the clergy and the secular power, between the military and the civil power, between noble and noble, nay, even in the disputes between two peasants, given rise to by a word, and decided by their fists or their knives. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14285" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14336">If he found himself absolutely obliged to take part between two combatants, he always stood by the strongest; always, however, in the rear, and always took care to make the other perceive that he was not voluntarily his enemy, seeming to say, But why have you not managed to be the strongest, so that I might have placed myself on your side? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14337" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14396">Holding himself aloof from the powerful, appearing not to notice their capricious and wanton insults, bearing with submission those which were of a more serious intention, and forcing, by dint of bows and cheerful respect, even the most surly and disdainful to smile upon him when they met upon the road, the poor man had succeeded in passing through sixty years without great tempests. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="30">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14397" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14456">Not but that he had also his portion of gall and bitterness: this continual exercise of patience, this giving up of his will to others, these many bitter mouthfuls swallowed in silence, had irritated him to such a pitch, that had he not been able from time to time to relieve himself, his health would certainly have suffered. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14457" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14503">But still there were in the world, and near him too, persons whom he knew very well were quite unable to molest him, and upon these he would sometimes wreak his long repressed ill-humour, and satisfy himself by being a little fanciful, and scolding in the wrong. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14504" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14527">He was a rigid censor of those who did not conduct themselves in the same manner as he did, provided this censure could be exercised without even the most distant personal danger. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14528" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14541">With him the one who remained vanquished was always at least an imprudent fellow; the one who was assassinated, a busybody. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14542" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14589">Did any one maintaining his rights against a powerful man, remain with a broken head, Don Abbondio always knew how to prove that he had been in the wrong; a thing not very difficult, since right and wrong are not divided by so fine a line that to either party belongs exclusively either the one or the other. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14590" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14611">But above every thing else, he declaimed against those of his brethren who, to their own personal danger, took part with an oppressed poor man against a powerful oppressor. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14612" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14641">This he called buying trouble with ready money, trying to make dogs' legs straight. He said also very severely, that he was a medler in profane matters, very prejudicial to the dignity of the sacred ministry. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14642" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14674">And against these he preached,—always, however, in a *tête-à-tête*, or in a very small company, with so much the more vehemence as his auditors were known to be unfavourable to the resenting of injuries which regarded themselves personally. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14675" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14709">He had a favourite sentence, with which he always closed his discourses upon this subject, which was, "that such rude encounters never happened to a gentleman who took care of himself, and who was contented with his condition." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14710" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14726">Consider, my five-and-twenty readers, what impression the circumstances we have related must have made upon the mind of this poor creature! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14727" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14809">The fright of these terrible visages and terrible words, the menace of a signor noted for never menacing in vain, a system of quiet existence which had cost so many years of study and patience, destroyed at one blow! And a step taken, from which he could see no means of escape. All these thoughts buzzed tumultuously in the shallow brain of Don Abbondio. If Renzo could be sent away with a quiet no; but then he will want reasons — and what in the name of heaven have I to answer him? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14810" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14829">And, and, and he has such a spirit! A lamb, if you don't meddle with him, but if you will contradict him — ah! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14830" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14867">Then he has quite lost his head about this Lucia, he is in love like — Foolish young people, who not knowing what to do, fall in love, and wishing to marry, never trouble themselves about all the vexation they occasion a poor gentleman. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14868" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14885">Ah, poor unfortunate that I am! Why should these ugly faces just place themselves in my path, and seize upon me? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14886" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14888">What have I to do with this? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14889" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14893">Is it I who wish to marry? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14894" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14923">Why did they not sooner go and speak — Oh, only see what a fine destiny is mine, the right thing never comes into my mind until a moment after it is wanted! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14924" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14975">If I had only thought of suggesting to them to carry their embassy — But at this point he perceived that to repent of not having been counsellor and co-operator in this wickedness was a thing very sinful, and he turned the anger of his thoughts against him who was thus come to disturb his peace. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14976" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15019">He did not know Don Rodrigo, except by sight and fame; neither had he ever had anything to do with him, beyond touching his breast with his chin, and the earth with the point of his hat, the few times they had happened to meet on the road. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15020" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15057">He had chanced on more than one occasion to defend the reputation of the Signor against those who in a low voice, sighing and raising their eyes towards heaven, cursed some of his deeds. He had said a thousand times, "he was an honourable cavalier." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="31">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15058" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15084">But in this moment he conferred upon him, in his heart, all those titles which he had never heard applied to him by others without interrupting them in haste, with a "fie on't!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="32">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15085" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15146">Arrived in the tumult of these thoughts at the door of his house, which stood at the further end of the village, he put, in haste, the key which he already held in his hand, into the key-hole, opened the door, entered, closed it carefully behind him, and anxious to find himself in confidential company, called quietly, "Perpetua, Perpetua!" advancing then towards the little parlour where this personage ought certainly to be, preparing the table for supper. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15147" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15233">Perpetua was, as every one perceives, the servant of Don Abbondio; an affectionate and faithful creature, who knew how to obey and command according as occasion served; tolerating now the grumbling and whims of her master, now making him tolerate her own, which became every day more frequent, since she had passed the synodal age of forty and still remained single, having refused every offer of marriage which had been made her, as she said, or never having found a dog who could fancy her, as her friends said. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="33">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15234" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15304">"I am coming," she answered, placing at its accustomed spot on the table, a small flask of Don Abbondio's favourite wine, and then moving away very slowly; but she had not yet reached the threshold of the little parlour, when her master entered, with so constrained a step, so gloomy an air, so distorted a countenance, that no one would have required the experienced eyes of Perpetua to perceive at the first glance that something truly extraordinary had happened to him. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="34">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15305" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15308">"Mercy! what is the matter with my master?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="35">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15309" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15320">"Nothing, nothing;" returned Don Abbondio, letting himself sink panting into his great chair. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="36">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15321" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15332">"How, nothing! you wish to make me believe that,—gloomy as you are? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15333" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15337">Some great accident has happened." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="37">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15338" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15342">"Oh, for the love of heaven! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15343" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15355">When I say nothing, it is either nothing, or something which I cannot tell you." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="38">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15356" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15362">"Which you cannot tell even to me? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15363" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15369">Who then will take care of your health? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15370" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15374">Who then will give you counsel?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="39">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15375" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15386">"Ah, alas! be silent; and don't prepare anything more for me for supper. Give me a glass of my wine." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="40">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15387" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15420">"And yet you will maintain that nothing is the matter with you!" said Perpetua, filling the glass, and then holding it in her hand as though she would only give it him as a reward for the confidence which was so much expected. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="41">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15421" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15446">"Give it here, give it here," said Don Abbondio, taking the glass from her with no steady hand, and then swallowing its contents in haste, as though this were a dose of medicine. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="42">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15447" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15488">"You wish then to see me obliged to demand what has happened to my master?" said Perpetua, who stood straight before him, her arms a-kimbo, regarding him fixedly, as though she would suck his secret out of his eyes. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="43">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15489" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15504">"For the love of heaven, do not gossip so! Do not make such an uproar. Life, life is at stake." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="44">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15505" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15508">"Life?" "Life!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="46">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15509" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15526">"You know very well that every time you have told me anything in confidence, I have never ——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="47">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15527" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15529">"How, how? when?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="48">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15530" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15574">Perpetua observed she had touched a wrong note, when changing quickly her tone, "Signor," she said, with a voice of emotion, and which was intended to move him, "I have always been full of affection towards you, and if now I desire to know this, it is through eagerness to assist you, to give you counsel, to comfort your mind ——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="49">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15575" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15633">The fact is, that Don Abbondio had perhaps as strong a desire to unburden himself of his secret as Perpetua had to know it, since after having resisted each time more weakly the new and still more persecuting assaults of Perpetua, after having made her swear, more than once, never to breathe a word concerning the matter, finally, with many delays, and with many an 'alas!' he related the miserable affair. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15634" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15684">When he arrived at the terrible name of the signor who sent the message, it was necessary that Perpetua should bind herself to a new and still more solemn oath; and Don Abbondio pronouncing this name, threw himself back in his chair with a great sigh, raising his hands, in an attitude of command, and yet at the same time of supplication, said, "for the love of heaven!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="50">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15685" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15701">"Mercy!" exclaimed Perpetua; "oh, the villain! the cunning one! Oh, what a man without the fear of God!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="51">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15702" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15708">"Will you be silent? or will you completely ruin me?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="52">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15709" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15716">"Oh! we are here where no one can hear us. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15717" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15722">But what will you do with Signor Padrone?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="53">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15723" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15738">"Only see," said Don Abbondio, with an angry voice, "only see the fine counsel which this creature can give me. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15739" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15755">She comes to me and asks me, 'what shall I do—what shall I do?' It might be she who was in a difficulty, and I the one to help her out of it!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="54">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15756" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15767">"But I certainly should like to give you my poor counsel, but then ——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="55">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15768" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15770">"But then let us hear." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="56">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15771" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15829">"My poor counsel would be, that as every one says our Archbishop is a holy man, and a man of power, and that he fears no one, and is quite delighted when he can make one of these powerful nobles keep to his duty, in order to assist a curate, I should say, and I say that you ought to write a beautiful letter to him, to inform him how ——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="57">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15830" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15833">"Will you be silent, will you be silent? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15834" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15841">Are such counsels to be given to a wretched man? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15842" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15855">When I shall feel a musket-ball in my back—God help me—will the Archbishop remove it?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="58">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15856" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15876">"Ah, musket-balls! no, they do not disappear like comfits; and woe to us if their dogs should bite every time they bark! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15877" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15916">I have always seen that respect is shewn to him who can shew his teeth, and make himself thought of; and precisely because you will never speak out your opinion, we are brought to such a pass that every one comes licensed to ——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="59">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15917" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15918">"Will you be silent?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="60">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15919" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15941">"I am silent; but it is however certain, that when the world perceives a person always, on every occasion, ready to give way ——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="61">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15942" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15943">"Will you be silent? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15944" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15950">Is this a time for such nonsense?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="62">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15951" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15971">"Enough: you will think of this to-night; but in the mean time do not begin to injure yourself by ruining your health; eat a mouthful." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="63">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15972" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15987">"I will think of this," muttered Don Abbondio, "certainly, I will think of this, and here I have something to think about." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15988" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_16007">He rose, continuing, "I will take nothing, nothing; I have other things to occupy me. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_16008" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_16015">I also know it concerns me to think about this; but why must it happen precisely to me?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="64">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_16016" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_16032">"Swallow at least this other drop," said Perpetua, pouring out some wine, "you know it always does your stomach good." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="65">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_16033" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_16042">"I require something else, something else, something else." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_16043" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_16070">Thus saying, and still muttering, "a small trifle to a gentleman like me; how will it be to-morrow?" and, with similar lamentations, prepared to ascend to his chamber. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap1-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_16071" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_16096">Arrived at the threshold, he turned round towards Perpetua, placed his finger upon his lips, and saying, in a slow and solemn tone, "for the love of heaven!" disappeared. </note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>