<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CHAPTER XII.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>1845</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed Lovers: a Milanese Story of the Seventeenth Century. With The Column of Infamy by Alessandro Manzoni. In Three Volumes</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
          <date>1845</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Henry Francis C. Logan</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="English_1845_cap12">
        <p n="1">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10007">This was the second year that the crops had been bad. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10008" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10047">The preceding year, the provisions which remained over from the former harvests had to a certain degree supplied the deficiency, and the populace had lived on until 1628, the time of our history, neither entirely satiated nor famished, but certainly entirely destitute of resources. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10048" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10085">Now this much-desired harvest was even more miserable than the preceding one,—partly owing to the seasons being still more adverse (and this not alone in the states of Milan, but also in a considerable tract of the surrounding country), partly the fault of man. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="2">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10086" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10146">The havoc and spoil of the war, of the beautiful war, which we have already mentioned, were such, that, in those parts of the state nearest the scene of action, more farms than usual remained uncultivated and abandoned by the peasantry, who instead of procuring bread by their labour, both for themselves and for others, were obliged to gain it by charity. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10147" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10229">I have said more than usual, because the insupportable taxes imposed with an unexampled greediness and stupidity, the habitual behaviour of the troops quartered in the villages even in time of peace,—behaviour which the sorrowful documents of this time compare to that of an invading enemy, and other causes which are not for us to mention, had already been long slowly producing this bad effect in the Milanese States; the particular circumstances of which we speak, were like the sudden irritation of a chronic disease. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10230" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10278">And scarcely was the harvest got in, when the provisions for the multitude, and the waste which always accompanies them, caused such a dearth, that famine, and with it its salutary as well as inevitable concomitant, dearness of food, made itself soon felt. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="3">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10279" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10317">But when the dearness reaches a certain point, there rises always—or at least has always risen until now; and if still this is the case at the present day, spite of the writings of so many excellent men, only think what it must have been in those times!—there rises, I say, an opinion among the multitude that this dearth is not the cause of the high price of provisions. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10318" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10365">People remember to have feared and predicted it; people imagine all at once that there is grain enough, and that the evil arises from not selling sufficient for consumption: a supposition which is entirely unfounded, but which flatters for a while their anger and their hope. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10366" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10430">The corn-dealers, real or imaginary, the possessors of estates who would not sell their corn all in one day, the bakers who bought it,—all those, in short, who had crops, little or much, or who were reported to have, were considered as the authors of the misery and the dearth; they were the object of the universal complaint—the abomination of both the well and ill-dressed multitude. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10431" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10483">They could say with certainty where were the magazines, heaped up, overflowing with grain, and crowded with sacks; they even mentioned the number of the sacks—a surprising number! they spoke with certainty of the immense quantity of grain which was secretly exported; and in other states, people probably exclaimed with equal certainty and warmth, that the corn of their country went to Milan. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10484" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10521">They implored from the magistrates those measures which always appear, or at least have always in the eye of the multitude appeared, so simple, so just, and so well adapted to bring forth the grain, which as they said lay concealed, walled-up, or buried; those measures which should cause the return of plenty. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10522" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10547">The magistrates did something; they fixed the exact price of each article, and intimated punishment to those who refused to sell, with several other things of the same kind. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10548" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10600">Yet all precaution in this world, let it be ever so efficacious, is unable to diminish the necessity for food, or to cause crops to spring up out of season; and as unfortunately those who exercised power were not possessed of any means by which to bring forth corn from those places in which there might be a superabundance, the evil still remained, and even increased. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10601" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10624">The multitude attributed this to the weakness of the remedies applied, and solicited, with loud cries, more vigorous and decisive measures. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10625" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10634">And as ill-luck would have it, they found the very man after their own heart. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="4">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10635" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10662">In the absence of the Governor, Don Gonzalo Fernandez de Cordova, who was commanding at the siege of Casale, in Montserrat, the High-Chancellor Antonio Ferrer, also a Spaniard, supplied his place at Milan. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10663" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10699">He perceived—and who could not have perceived?—that the having bread at a just price, was in itself a very desirable thing; and he thought—and here is the absurdity—that an order from his hand would be sufficient to produce this effect. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10700" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10740">He fixed the *meta* (this is the name given at Milan for the tariffs for food); he fixed the meta of bread at the price which would have been just, had grain then been generally sold at thirty lire the bushel, but it sold even as high as eighty. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10741" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10756">He acted like a lady who has been young, and who hopes to make herself young again by altering her certificate of baptism. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="5">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10757" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10797">Orders, less absurd and less unjust, had, more than once, remained unexecuted, owing to the very impossibility of their execution; but the multitude, who saw their desire at length converted into law, watched over its execution, and would not have suffered that it should remain merely a joke. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10798" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10829">They ran immediately to the bakehouses to demand bread at the taxed price; and they demanded it with that air of resolution and menace which is given by passion, by strength, and by the law, when all three are united in one. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10830" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10836">If the bakers make loud outcries, do not demand the bread, said they. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10837" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10882">To mix the flour, work the dough, put into the oven, and take out again without pausing (for the people, having a confused idea that the whole thing was violent, besieged the bakehouses continually, so as to enjoy this good fortune as long as it lasted), to fatigue yourself, I say, nay, almost kill yourself, only in the end to be the loser, how great must have been the pleasure? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10883" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10938">But on one hand, the magistrates threatened punishment; on the other, the people who wished to be served urged on, and grumbled in their coarse voices, whenever a baker delayed, ever so little, menacing him with one of their acts of justice, which are among the worst of acts perpetrated in this world: there was no remedy; they were obliged to knead, to put in and take out of the oven, and to sell. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10939" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10970">However, to insure the continuance of this occupation, it was not sufficient merely to command the bakers, neither sufficed it that the bakers should stand in great fear of this command, it was necessary that they should be able to obey; and although the state of affairs had continued only a short time longer, this they would not have been able to do. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10971" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11011">They shewed the magistrates how unjust and insupportable was this burden imposed upon them; they protested that they were willing to fling their shovels into the oven, and leave the city; in the meanwhile they dragged on, hoping and ever hoping, that sometime the Grand-Chancellor would have his eyes opened. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11012" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11065">But Antonio Ferrer, who was what would now be called a man of character, replied, that the bakers had gained a great deal by the past, and would again gain a great deal by the future, when times should again be better; that it would be seen how he, perhaps, thought of making them some compensation, and that in the meantime they should continue to carry on as well as they could. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11066" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11116">Was he really himself persuaded of these reasons which he gave; or knowing by its effect the impossibility of maintaining his edict, did he wish to leave to others the odium of revoking it? Who now can fathom the intentions of Antonio Ferrer? The fact is, that he continued steadfast to that which he had ordained. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11117" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11153">In the end, the Council of Ten (a municipal magistracy formed from the nobility, which lasted until the year 1796,) informed the Governor, by letter, of the state in which affairs were, and prayed him to discover some remedy. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="6">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11154" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11197">Don Gonzalo, immersed in the affairs of the war, did what the reader will readily imagine; he named a Junto, upon whom he conferred authority to fix a reasonable price upon bread, this was just towards both parties. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11198" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11256">The deputies met, or, as they said in the diplomatic jargon of that time, borrowed from the Spaniards; they assembled in Junto, and after a thousand reverences, compliments, penalties, sighs, doubts, vain propositions, and tergiversations, drew towards a determination of which they all felt the necessity, and knowing well that they played an important card, but convinced they could do no less, they raised the price of bread. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11257" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11263">The bakers breathed again, but the populace were infuriated. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="7">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11264" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11312">The evening preceding the day of Renzo's arrival the streets and the squares had been stirring with men, who, transported by a common rage, governed by a common thought, acquaintances or strangers, had assembled in knots, without at first any common intention, almost without being aware of it themselves. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11313" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11328">Each oration increased the conviction and passion of its auditors, as well as the passion of its deliverer. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11329" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11387">Among so many impassioned men, there were, nevertheless, some who were cool and calm enough to observe with pleasure how the water continued to trouble itself; they amused themselves with troubling it still more by those arguments and stories which knaves know so well how to fabricate, and which excited minds are so prone to believe; and they proposed to themselves not to let this water repose before having caught some good fish. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11388" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11405">Thousands of men went to sleep with the confused idea that it was necessary to do something, and that something would be done. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11406" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11479">Before day the streets were again filled with knots and little gatherings of people, children, women, men, old men, artisans, beggars,—all met by chance. Here was a confused din of a thousand voices, here some one harangued the people, whilst others applauded; this one asked his neighbour the same thing which had just been asked of him; the other repeated the exclamation which he had heard resounding in his ears; everywhere were heard lamentations, threats, cries of surprise; a very small number of words was the material of many discourses. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="8">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11480" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11499">Nothing was wanting but an occasion, an impetus, to turn these words into deeds; and this was not long wanting. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11500" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11523">At break of day, boys were accustomed to leave the bakers' shops with baskets filled with bread, which they went to deliver at the houses of their customers. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11524" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11546">The first appearance of one of these unlucky boys in one of these knots of people was like the falling of a lighted squib into a gunpowder-mill. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="9">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11547" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11555">"Only see, if there is not bread!" cried a hundred voices at once. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="10">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11556" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11587">"Yes, for our tyrants who swim in abundance, and who wish that we should die of hunger," said one. He approached the lad, placed his hand upon the edge of the basket, drew it towards him, and said, "Let me see." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11588" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11615">The little lad coloured, turned pale, trembled; wished to say, "let me go forward," but the words died in his mouth; he loosened his arms, and endeavoured to liberate himself in haste from the leathern straps. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="11">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11616" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11621">"Down with this basket," was heard from all sides. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11622" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11645">Many hands seized upon it; the basket is on the ground, the cloth which covers it is thrown into the air; a tepid fragrance diffuses itself around. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="12">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11646" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11681">"We also, are Christians; we also "ought to eat bread," said the first. He takes a loaf, lifts it on high, shews it to the crowd, and bites it; hands in the basket; bread in the air; in less time than it takes to relate, the basket was emptied. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11682" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11711">Those who had got nothing, irritated at the sight of the others' gain, and animated by the facility of the enterprise, move off in troops in search of other baskets; so many met—so many pillaged. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11712" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11742">However, it was no longer needful to assault those who carried them; they who unhappily found themselves in the street, saw which way the wind blew, willingly set down their burdens, and scampered off. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11743" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11788">Nevertheless, those who remained with unsatisfied stomachs were, without comparison, the most numerous; thus the conquerors themselves were not satisfied with so small a prey; and there were to be found among them those who had counted upon a much better arranged assault. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11789" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11794">"To the bakehouse!" cried they. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="13">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11795" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11853">In the street called the Corsia de' Servi, there stood at the time of our story a bakehouse, and even at the present day there is one of the same name. This name, which in Tuscan signifies the Bakehouse of the Crutches, is composed in Milanese of such extravagant, strange, savage words, that the alphabet of the Italian language has not characters wherewith to indicate the sound. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11854" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11859">Here, rushed the crowd. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11860" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11897">The people of the shop were busied questioning the boy who was returned unladen, who, all out of breath and in trouble, recounted stammering his sad adventure, when suddenly they heard a sound of people in movement; the noise increases, approaches, they perceive the forerunners of the troop. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11898" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11921">"Shut up the shop! shut up the shop! quick! quick! Some one runs to demand assistance from the sheriff; the others close in haste the shop, and barricade the doors. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11922" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11935">The people begin to crowd outside, and cry, "bread! bread! open! open!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="14">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11936" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11948">In a few moments the sheriff arrives with a piquet of halberdiers. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11949" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11966">"Make way, make way, my children! home, home, make way for the sheriff!" cried he, with his halberdiers. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11967" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11995">The people, who at present were not very numerous, made way a little; the soldiers were enabled to draw themselves up, and post themselves before the closed shop door, somewhat pressed together, although in good order. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="15">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11996" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12005">"But, my children!" cried the sheriff, "what are you doing here? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12006" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12009">Return home, return home! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12010" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12014">Where is then your fear of God? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12015" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12020">What will our lord the king say? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12021" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12030">We do not wish to hurt you, but return home; behave like honest men! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12031" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12037">What the devil will you do here, thus crowding one upon the other! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12038" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12047">No good either to soul or body. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12048" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12051">Home, home!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12052" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12102">But those who saw the face of the speaker, and who heard his words, even had they wished to obey, could not, pushed about as they were, and pressed upon by those behind—as one man is hurried on by another, on, on, even to the extremity of the crowd, which still kept increasing. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12103" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12109">The sheriff began to lose his breath. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12110" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12125">"Make them give way, that I may regain my breath," said he to the halberdiers; "but do not hurt any one. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12126" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12133">Endeavour to enter the shop; knock, make them stand back." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="16">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12134" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12149">"Back, back!" cried the halberdiers, throwing themselves upon the foremost ranks of the multitude, and repulsing them with the butt-end of their halberds. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12150" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12198">The people gave a yell, and drew back as well as they were able, pushing their backs into the chests, their elbows in the stomachs, their heels into the feet of those behind them; there was such a press, such a crowd, that those who found themselves in the midst would have given something to have been out of it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12199" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12247">In the meantime a small opening was made before the door; the sheriff knocked, and knocked again, shouting that they should open; the people of the house look out from the windows, they descend in haste, they open the door. The sheriff enters, he calls the halberdiers, who enter one by one, those who were last keeping back the crowd with their halberds. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12248" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12268">When they are all entered, they draw the bolt, the sheriff mounts up stairs in haste, he appears at a window. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12269" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12271">Good heavens! what a tumult! </note>
        </p>
        <p n="17">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12272" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12282">"My children!" he cried. Many looked upward. "My children! return home. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12283" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12290">A general pardon to whomsoever returns immediately home." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="18">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12291" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12307">"Bread, bread! Open, open!" were the words most distinctly heard in the horrible yell by which the crowd answered him. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="19">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12308" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12315">"Be wise, my children! Give heed! You have yet time! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12316" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12320">Go; return, return home! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12321" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12329">You shall have bread, but this is not the way to get it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12330" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12334">Ah, ah! what are you doing down there? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12335" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12338">Ah! at this door? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12339" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12340">Oh! oh!—I see, I see. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12341" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12349">Be reasonable! Give heed! This is a great crime you are committing. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12350" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12353">I am going to descend immediately. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12354" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12362">Ah, ah! leave those irons there! down with those hands. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12363" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12363">Shame! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12364" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12376">You Milanese, who for your goodness are celebrated throughout the world! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12377" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12383">Listen, listen! You have always been good children. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12384" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12385">Ah! canaille!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="20">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12386" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12417">This sudden change of style was occasioned by a stone which, proceeding from the hand of one of these good children, struck the sheriff's forehead. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12418" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12429">"Canaille! canaille!" continued he, hastily closing the window and retiring. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12430" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12458">But loud as he had cried, his words, both good and bad, had vanished, and were lost in the air, in the tempest of sound which came from below. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12459" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12501">What he had referred to was a great labouring with stones and iron bars (the first which they had been enabled to procure in the street) at the door and the windows, in order to burst in the said door and tear away the bars from the windows; and already was the work far advanced. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="21">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12502" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12550">In the meantime the masters and apprentices of the shop who were at the windows of the upper stories, armed with a provision of stones (which probably they had torn up from the paving of the court-yard), shouted to those below, and made threatening gestures, in order to deter them; they exhibited the stones, and gave the crowd to understand that these they would fling down; but soon seeing that this was only lost time, they began to hurl the stones in good earnest. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12551" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12575">Not one fell in vain; so great was the concourse that, as the saying is, not a grain of millet could have fallen to the ground. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="22">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12576" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12579">"Ah, rogues! ah, rascals! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12580" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12588">Is this the bread you will give the poor? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12589" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12591">Ah, ah! Oh, oh! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12592" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12596">On, on!" yelled the mob. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12597" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12606">More than one was wounded,—two lads remained dead on the spot. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12607" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12627">Rage increased the strength of the multitude; the door was driven in; the iron bars from the windows were wrenched out, and the tumult penetrated through the openings thus made. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12628" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12662">Those within the house, seeing this disastrous issue, escaped to the garrets. The sheriff and the halberdiers remained lying under the tiles; others, escaping through the skylights, wandered about the roofs like cats. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="23">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12663" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12675">The sight of the booty made the conquerors forget their designs of sanguinary vengeance. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12676" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12685">They throw themselves upon the troughs, the bread is pillaged. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12686" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12716">Others, on the contrary, hasten to break open the lock of the counter, seize handfuls of money, pocket it, and depart, loaded with quattrini, to return afterwards to steal bread, should any yet remain. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12717" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12722">The crowd streams into the magazines. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12723" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12835">They seize upon the sacks of flour, they drag them along, they pour out their contents; one man holds a sack between his legs, loosens its mouth, and, to reduce it to a portable size, throws away a portion of the flour; another, crying, "wait, wait," places himself behind him, so as to receive in his apron, in his handkerchief, in his hat, this gift of God; one runs to a trough, and seizes upon a piece of dough, which lengthening itself out, escapes his grasp; another, who has possessed himself of a bolting-cloth, carries it off high in the air; they come, they go; men, women, and children, push, pull, and yell; a white dust which settles everywhere, and rises from all sides, covers and whitens every thing. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12836" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12864">Outside is a crush, formed by the two opposing processions of those who depart with the booty, and others who wish to enter with the same desire of pillage,—these dash against each other, alternately embarrassing one another. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="24">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12865" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12880">Whilst this bakehouse was being thus devastated, not one in the whole city was quiet and out of danger. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12881" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12932">But before the others, the crowd did not assemble sufficient to dare every thing; some shops the masters had called in assistance, and stood on the defensive; whilst some other poor bakers, less strong in numbers, or more intimidated, endeavoured to compromise matters; they distributed bread to those who began to assemble before their shops, on condition that these should take their departure. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12933" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12976">And they departed, at length, not so much because they were satisfied, with what they had gained, as because the halberdiers and officers of justice, keeping away from this terrible bakehouse of the Crutches, shewed themselves everywhere else with sufficient strength to awe these little troops of mutineers. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12977" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13011">Thus the tumults continued always increasing before the first unfortunate bakehouse; all those who longed to lay a hand to this beautiful work, hastened where the friends were the strongest, and impunity the most sure. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="25">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13012" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13043">Things had arrived at this point, when Renzo, having, as we have said, finished eating his bread, came from the suburb of the Eastern-gate, and, without being aware of it, reached the very centre of the tumult. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13044" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13073">He walked on, now quickly, now retarded by the crowd, making good use of both his eyes and ears, so as to gain from the confused hum of voices some more positive notion of the state of things. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13074" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13092">And here are pretty nearly the words which he succeeded in overhearing during his walk. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="26">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13093" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13113">"It is discovered now," said one; "the infamous imposture of these rascals, who said that there was neither bread, nor flour, nor grain. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13114" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13130">Now we clearly see how the thing is, and they can no longer make us believe any such stories. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13131" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13132">Hurrah! abundance!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="27">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13133" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13159">"I tell you that this will help nothing," said another; "it is only a hole in the water; it will be worse than ever, unless they do us thorough justice. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13160" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13178">Bread will be cheap, but they will poison it, to kill the poor like so many flies. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13179" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13215">They say already there are too many of us; this has been said in the council. I know this for certain, having heard it with these ears of mine, from one of my gossips, who is the friend of a relation of one of these gentlemen's scullions." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="28">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13216" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13250">Another foaming at the mouth, and holding with one hand a ragged handkerchief upon his thin and bloody hair, said words which are not to be repeated, and his neighbour, to console him, echoed them back. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="29">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13251" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13289">"Make way! make way! gentlemen, I beseech. Let a poor father pass, who carries food to his five little children," said one staggering under the weight of a great sack of flour; and every one endeavoured to make way for him. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="30">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13290" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13303">"'I,' said another, almost in an under-tone, to his companions, 'I shall go. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13304" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13313">I am a man of the world, and I know how these things go on. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13314" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13333">These brawlers who now make such an uproar, to-morrow, or soon after, will keep in their houses, all trembling with fear. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13334" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13366">I have already perceived certain faces, certain gentlemen, who are skulking about spying out the land; and they note well, who is, and who is not here. When all is ended, they will make up their accounts, and every one will have his bill.'" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="31">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13367" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13385">"'The one who protects the bakers,' said a sonorous voice, which attracted Renzo's attention, 'is the Superintendent of provisions.'" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="32">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13386" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13391">"'They are all villains,' cried another." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13392" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13400">"Yes, but he is the chief of them," replied the first speaker. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="33">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13401" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13441">The Superintendent of provisions, elected every year by the Governor from among six nobles proposed by the Council of Ten, was the president of this council and of this tribunal of provisions; the tribunal had several duties, but principally the one of providing corn and provisions. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13442" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13482">The one occupying such a post must necessarily in times of famine and of ignorance be considered as the author of these evils; unless he acted differently to Ferrer, but even had such been his intention, it would not have been in his power. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="34">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13483" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13511">"The villains!" exclaimed another, "could they have done anything worse? They have even gone so far as to say that the High-Chancellor was an old man in his dotage, so as to discredit him, and get the command to themselves. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13512" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13530">One ought to make a large coop and put them in, to live on dry peas and cockle-weed, as they would have treated us." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="35">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13531" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13552">"Is it bread?" said one, who sought to pass on in haste; "blows from stones of a pound weight—stones of such a size, which came down like hail! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13553" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13557">And what bruised ribs I have! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13558" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13564">I do not see how I am to get home!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="36">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13565" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13589">In the midst of such discourses, from which it would be difficult to say whether he gained most information or most terror, and in the midst of blows, Renzo arrived at length before this bakehouse. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13590" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13643">The populace had already begun to disperse themselves, so that he could contemplate this sad ruin; the walls — dilapidated and bruised from the blows of stones and bricks, the windows torn from their frames, the door broken. This, however, is no beautiful thing, thought Renzo to himself. If they treated all bakehouses after this manner, where will they make bread? </note>
        </p>
        <p n="37">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13644" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13692">In the wells? From time to time some one would issue forth from the shop carrying a piece of a trough, or of a sieve, a bench, a basket, a ledger, some thing, in short, from this poor bakehouse, and crying, "Make way! make way!" passed on through the crowd. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="38">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13693" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13764">All these people took the same direction, and stopped at a place agreed upon by all. What is this other affair? thought Renzo to himself, and he placed himself behind one of these individuals, who having made a bundle of broken boards and chips of wood, placed it upon his shoulders, and went on like the others through the street which runs along the northern side of the cathedral, and which takes its name from the flight of steps* which used to be there, but which, since a short time, is there no longer. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="39">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13765" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13794">The desire of seeing what was about to happen, could not, however, prevent our mountaineer, now arrived before this grand pile of building, from stopping for a moment to gaze upwards, open-mouthed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13795" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13839">He redoubled his pace to rejoin the one whom he had chosen as his guide. He turned the corner, casting another glance at the façade of the cathedral, the greater part of which was still in the rough, and very far from being completed, keeping constantly behind the one who directed his steps towards the (marked in the text with an asterisk) middle of the square. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="40">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13840" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13872">The farther one advanced the denser became the crowd, but all made way for the bearer of the wood. He passed through the mob, and Renzo, insinuating himself into the opening which he made, arrived with him at the centre of the crowd. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13873" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13890">Here was a large open space, and in the midst a bonfire, a heap of embers, relics of the utensils mentioned above. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13891" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13908">All around was a clapping of hands, a stamping of feet, a din of a thousand cries of triumph, and of a thousand imprecations. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="41">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13909" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13946">The man of the bundle flung it upon the embers; another, with a piece of a half-consumed shovel, stirred up the fire; the flame rises and condenses itself, the flame ascends, and with it the cries arise still stronger: "Hurrah! abundance! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13947" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13949">Death to the tyrants! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13950" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13952">Perish the famine! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13953" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13958">Perish the tribunal! Perish the council! Abundance! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13959" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13961">Hurrah! Bread! Hurrah!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="42">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13962" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14003">Certainly, the destruction of the bolters and the troughs, the pillaging of the bakehouses, the ruining and terrifying the bakers, are not the most efficacious means of causing an abundance of bread; but this is one of those metaphysical niceties which do not strike the mind of the multitude. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14004" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14054">However, without being a very great metaphysician, Renzo, who did not partake in the general delirium, made this reflection. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14055" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14078">He kept it prudently to himself, however, because among so many countenances there was not one which did not seem to say, "Brother, if I am wrong thou canst try to correct me, but thou shalt pay dearly for it." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="43">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14079" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14124">The flame was again extinguished; no one was seen to arrive with other combustibles, and the troop were beginning to grow weary, when the report spread that at the Cordusio (a small square or street not far distant), they were laying siege to another bakehouse. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14125" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14134">In circumstances like this, the mere announcement of a fact is often sufficient to occasion it in reality. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14135" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14165">Together with this report a desire diffused itself through the crowd to hasten to the scene of action. "I am going there; art thou going?—Come. Let us go," was heard on all sides; the mob moved off and formed a procession. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14166" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14205">Renzo remained behind without stirring, except when hurried along by this torrent, and held counsel with himself whether he should extricate himself from this rabble-rout, and return to the convent in search of Father Bonaventura, or go on and see what yet remained to be seen. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14206" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14210">Curiosity again prevailed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14211" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14237">However, he resolved not to get mixed up with the fray, not to get his bones broken, or even risk something still more; but to keep himself at some distance and be a mere spectator. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14238" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14260">This resolution taken, and already finding himself somewhat at liberty, he drew forth his second little loaf, and having bitten it, commenced his march with this tumultuous army. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="44">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14261" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14285">The multitude having left the square, had entered the narrow and straight street, the Pescheria-Vecchia, and from thence reached the square de Mercanti. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14286" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14359">There were few who, passing the niche in the gallery of the edifice, then called the College of Doctors, did not cast a glance towards the grand statue which occupied it, towards the serious, haughty, ferocious countenance of Don Philip the Second, who, even in marble, imposed a sentiment of respect; and who, stretching forth his arm, seemed to say, "I am here, scum of the earth." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="45">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14360" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14368">This statue is no longer there, owing to a singular circumstance. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14369" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14404">A hundred and sixty years after the events of our story, his head was, one morning removed, his sceptre taken from his hand, a dagger substituted in its stead, and to the statue was given the name of Marcus Brutus. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14405" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14476">Thus metamorphised, it remained standing a few years, when another morning, certain individuals who had not much sympathy with Marcus Brutus, who even must have had a secret hatred against him, threw a cord round the statue and dragged it down, insulting it in a hundred ways; and thus mutilated and reduced to a shapeless trunk, they drew it through the streets with yells and wild gestures, and when they were thoroughly wearied they cast it I know not where. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14477" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14485">Who could have foretold this to Adrea Biffi when he sculptured it? </note>
        </p>
        <p n="46">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14486" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14506">From this square de' Mercanti, the noisy rabble rushed through the street de Fustagnai, and thus arrived at the Cordusio. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14507" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14518">Every one on entering the square, immediately glanced towards the bakehouse which had been indicated. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14519" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14559">But instead of the crowd of friends which they expected to find there already at work, they saw only a few who stood there undecided, at some distance from the shop which was closed, and at the windows appeared armed men ready to defend the house. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14560" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14590">At this sight some were amazed, some laughed, some turned back to inform those who were arriving every moment; some stood still, some wished to return, some cried, "On, on!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14591" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14609">There was a running about, a holding of people back, a pause, an uncertainty, a confused murmur of debate and consultation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14610" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14637">In the midst of this confusion an ill-starred voice cried out, "The house of the Superintendent is near here! Let us do ourselves justice! Let us pillage it!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14638" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14649">This seemed rather the recollection of a resolution already formed, than the receiving of a new proposal. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap12-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14650" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14679">"To the Superintendent's! to the Superintendent's!" was the only cry to be heard, and the crowd rushed on towards the street, where the house thus unfortunately mentioned stood. </note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>