<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CHAPTER XIII.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>1845</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed Lovers: a Milanese Story of the Seventeenth Century. With The Column of Infamy by Alessandro Manzoni. In Three Volumes</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
          <date>1845</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Henry Francis C. Logan</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="English_1845_cap13">
        <p n="1">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10045">The unfortunate Superintendent was digesting a dinner, eaten without an appetite, and without fresh bread; he awaited in great suspense the termination of this hurricane; far, however, from imagining that it would burst thus terribly over his head. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10046" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10059">A gentleman hastened on before the crowd to inform him of the peril which he saw in staying in this house. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10060" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10079">The domestics attracted to the door by the voice, looked affrighted down the street towards the quarter from whence the noise proceeded. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10080" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10115">Whilst he listened to this advice, he perceived the vanguard arrive; in haste and in terror the domestics hasten to inform their master; and now, whilst the master thinks about flight and how he shall escape, another arrives to tell him that for this there is no longer time. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10116" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10127">The domestics were scarcely able to close the door. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10128" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10154">They put up the bars; they barricade it well; they run to close the windows, as people do when the heaven is overcast, and they expect every moment a hail-storm. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10155" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10189">The increasing yell sounds like thunder echoing in the empty court-yard, every corner of the house resounds with it; and in the midst of this vast and deafening noise are heard loud and heavy blows of stones thrown against the door. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="2">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10190" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10191">"The Superintendent! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10192" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10193">The tyrant! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10194" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10194">The author of the famine! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10195" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10199">We will have him, alive or dead!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10200" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10230">The unfortunate man rushed from chamber to chamber, pale, breathless, clasping his hands, recommending himself to God, conjuring his domestics to stand firm, and to discover for him some means of escape. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10231" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10235">But how and where? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10236" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10277">He ascends to the garret; through a skylight, from whence he cannot be seen, he gazes anxiously down into the street; he sees it filled with madmen, he hears the voices which demand his death; and, more terrified than ever, he retires to seek a more secure and secret hiding-place. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10278" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10323">Here he lurks, he listens, he listens again, with agony, whether this terrible uproar calm itself, whether this tumult grow somewhat quieter; but, on the contrary, hearing the roar arise more loud and fierce than ever, and the blows increase, he hastily covers his ears with his hands. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10324" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10349">Then, as though out of himself, setting his teeth together and contracting his countenance, he stretches out his arms and presses wildly with his hands against the door, as though he would hold it firm. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10350" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10369">What exactly happened afterwards cannot be known, as he was by himself; this our history can only divine. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="3">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10370" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10390">Renzo found himself in the thickest of the fray; he had not been carried there by the torrent, he had run there. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10391" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10428">At this first proposal to spill blood, he had felt his blood all on fire. As to the plundering, he had not been quite sure whether this were good or bad, under the present circumstances; but the idea of homicide caused him to feel a sudden and intense horror. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10429" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10502">And, although owing to the terrible facility which lively imaginations possess of believing everything, he was persuaded by the impassioned words of so many people, that the Superintendent was the principal cause of the famine and the enemy of the poor; yet, having heard by chance in the commencement of the attack some words which indicated the desire of making some attempt to save him, he had suddenly proposed to himself to assist such a work, and with this intention he had arrived near the door which was attacked in a hundred ways. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10503" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10556">Some with stones knocked upon the nails which held the lock, so as to break it; others, with chisels and hammers, endeavoured to work more methodically; others, even with stones, with blunted knives, with nails, with sticks, nay, having nothing but their finger-nails, broke the walls and tore off the plaster, and tried to raise the bricks and make a breach. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10557" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10612">Those who could not assist the work itself inspired courage by their cries; yet at the same time, by their pressing round, they interrupted the work still more, already interrupted as it was by the disorderly emulation of the labourers: for, by the grace of heaven, it happens sometimes, in evil as well as in good, that the most ardent assistants become an impediment. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="4">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10613" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10679">The magistrates who were the earliest informed of what had happened, sent immediately to demand succour from the commandant of the castle, then called after the gate Giovia—he sent some soldiers; but what between the giving of the information and the orders, the assembling themselves and putting themselves in march, and the time required to make the journey, the house was already encompassed by the besiegers, and the soldiers were obliged to remain at a distance, at the outskirts of the crowd. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10680" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10688">The commanding officer knew not what course to pursue. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10689" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10708">Here was nothing but an assemblage of people, of all ages and of both sexes, which had nothing to do but to stand and look on. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10709" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10729">To the orders given to make way and separate themselves, they returned only a dull and protracted murmur; no one moved. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10730" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10763">To fire upon the mob appeared to the officer not only a cruel but also a dangerous thing—a thing, which offending the least terrible party, would have irritated the more violent; and then, besides, he had received no such order. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10764" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10794">To break through the first crowd, disperse it right and left, and carry war to those who were waging war, would have been the best; but how to succeed thus far?—There was the point. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10795" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10828">Who knows whether the soldiers would have been able to advance united and in good order; and whether, instead of breaking through the crowd, they would not have found themselves dispersed among the mob, and left to its discretion, after having irritated it? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10829" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10842">The irresolution of the commander and the immobility of the soldiery were regarded, either with or without reason, as occasioned by fear. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10843" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10914">The people who surrounded the soldiers contented themselves with gazing into their faces with an expression which said, "I laugh at you," those who stood somewhat farther off did not even content themselves with provoking them alone by gestures and with cries of scorn; nay, there were but few who knew of their presence, or troubled themselves about them; the besiegers continued their work of demolition without any other thought than that of speedily succeeding in their enterprise; the spectators did not cease to animate them by their cries. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="5">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10915" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10977">There was seen among the rabble, a spectacle in himself, an ill-looking old man, who, opening two sunken and flaming eyes, contracting his wrinkles into a smile of diabolical pleasure, raised with his two hands above his dishonoured grey hairs, and agitated in the air, a hammer, a cord, and four large nails, with which, as he said, he would crucify the Superintendent upon his own door, as soon as he should have given up the ghost. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="6">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10978" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11014">"Shame, shame!" escaped from Renzo's lips, who was seized with horror at these words, and at the sight of so many other countenances which seemed to give an approving sign, and encouraged also, perhaps, by some others upon which, although silently, there depicted itself the same horror with which he himself was seized. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11015" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11025">"Shame! shall we take upon ourselves the executioner's office? Assassinate a Christian? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11026" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11038">How will you that God should give us bread, if we commit such crimes? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11039" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11046">He will send us his thunders, and not bread!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="7">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11047" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11074">"Ah, dog! Ah, traitor to his country!" cried, turning round to Renzo, one of those who in the midst of the tumult had heard these holy words. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11075" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11076">"Wait, wait! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11077" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11089">It is one of the Superintendent's domestics disguised as a peasant; it is a spy! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11090" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11094">Fall upon him! fall upon him!" burst forth a hundred voices around him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11095" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11098">"What is he? Where is he? Who is he? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11099" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11102">A servant of the Superintendent's. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11103" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11104">A spy. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11105" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11111">The Superintendent himself, who disguised as a peasant, is escaping. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11112" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11115">Where is he? Where is he? Upon him! Upon him!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="8">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11116" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11143">Renzo remained silent; he drew himself together and made himself very small; he wished to disappear. Some of his neighbours aided our hero in concealing himself; they send forth loud cries; they endeavour to stifle and confound these hostile and blood-thirsty voices. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11144" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11167">But what assisted him more than all the rest was the cry of "Make way! make way!" which resounded near him. "Make way! Here is our succour! Make way, ohe!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="9">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11168" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11168">What was this then? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11169" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11186">It was a long ladder which some people were carrying towards the house in order to enter by the window. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11187" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11206">But happily this means, which would have rendered the thing so easy, was not easily to be put in operation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11207" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11271">Those who bore it at the ends, and here and there on each side of the machine, knocked about and separated by the crowd, staggered at every step; one with his head imprisoned between two staves of the ladder, the two supports resting upon his shoulders, as though under a moving yoke, sent forth miserable groans; another was separated from his burden by a blow; and the ladder fell upon shoulders, arms, and ribs; and only think, good reader, what must have been the cries of the victims! </note>
        </p>
        <p n="10">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11272" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11290">Others raised it again, placed themselves underneath, and laid it upon their shoulders, crying, "Come, let us on!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11291" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11297">The fatal machine proceeded along, leaping and winding. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11298" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11361">It arrived in time to divert the attention of Renzo's enemies; he profited by this confusion risen out of confusion. He at first concealed himself; then, plying his elbows as much as he could, he withdrew from this spot where the air was no longer wholesome for him, with the intention of escaping as quickly as possible out of the tumult, and of really going to find or to wait for the Father Bonaventura. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="11">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11362" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11387">Suddenly an extraordinary movement commenced at one extremity, and spread through the crowd; a voice is heard, and is repeated, from mouth to mouth, the name of "Ferrer! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11388" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11388">Ferrer!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11389" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11418">An astonishment, a joy, a madness, an inclination, a repugnance, arises wherever this name arrives; some shout the name, some wish to stifle it; some affirm, some deny; some bless, some curse. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="12">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11419" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11427">"Ferrer is here!—It is not true, it is not true!—Yes, yes! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11428" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11448">Long live Ferrer! Ferrer who gives us cheap bread!—No, no!—He is here; he is here in his carriage.—What does that matter? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11449" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11476">What has he to do with this? We will have no one!—Ferrer! Long live Ferrer!—the friend of the poor! He comes to conduct the Superintendent to prison!—No, no; we will execute justice ourselves; back, back!—Yes, yes: Ferrer! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11477" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11485">Let Ferrer come! Throw the Superintendent into prison!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="13">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11486" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11503">And all, standing on tip-toe, turned their gaze towards that side from whence was announced this unexpected arrival. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11504" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11524">But by all standing on tip-toe, they saw neither more nor less than if they had remained with their feet flat on the ground; but so it was, they all raised themselves on their toes. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="14">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11525" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11592">In fact, at the outskirts of the crowd, on the opposite side to where the soldiers stood, Antonio Ferrer, the High-Chancellor, had arrived in his carriage; he, his conscience probably tormenting him for having by his propositions and obstinacy been the cause, or at least, the occasion of this uproar, was now come endeavouring to appease, or at least to prevent, its most terrible and irreparable consequences; he was come to spend worthily an ill-acquired popularity. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="15">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11593" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11666">In all popular tumults there is always a certain number of men who, either through the violence of their passions, through a fanatical persuasion, or through a criminal design, or an infernal love of destruction, do all that lies in their power to drive things to the most fearful extremity. They propose or support the most barbarous projects; they stir the fire each time it commences to languish; nothing is ever too violent for them; — they desire that the tumult should have neither end, nor limit. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11667" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11716">But, as counterpoise, there is also always a certain number who apply themselves, perhaps with the same ardour and the same obstinacy, to obtain the contrary effect: some are influenced by friendship or partiality for the persons menaced; others, without any other impulse than a pious and spontaneous horror of bloodshed and atrocious deeds. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11717" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11720">May heaven bless them! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11721" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11742">In each of these opposing parties, although at first there are never any concerted measures, the uniformity of their wishes creates an instantaneous harmony in their operations. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11743" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11836">Thus what composes the mass, and even the material of the tumult, is an accidental mingling of men who, more or less, by indefinite gradations, hold to one or the other extreme; somewhat hot-headed, somewhat of rogues, somewhat inclined towards a certain species of that justice which they can comprehend, desirous of seeing some grand example of this same justice; disposed to ferocity, to compassion, to adoration, or execration, according as the occasion presents itself for experiencing either one or the other of these sentiments in its fullest extent; every moment eager to know, to believe something extraordinary; feeling the necessity of shouting, of applauding, or of yelling against some one. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11837" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11923">Let him live! let him die! are the words which they pronounce most willingly; and if any one has succeeded in convincing them that such a one does not deserve to be hanged, drawn, and quartered, it is not needful to expend many more words to convince them that he is worthy to be borne in triumph; they are actors, spectators, tools, obstacles, according to the way the wind blows; they are ready to remain silent when they no longer hear a cry to repeat, ready to desist when the instigators are wanting, ready to disband when, without one dissenting voice, the cry is, "Let us depart!" Ready to return to their homes, demanding one from the other "What is all this, then?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11924" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11967">Always, in circumstances of this kind, the mass having the greatest power, because the mass is in itself the power, each of the two active parties employs all its ability to win the mass over to its side, to render itself master of the popular mind. These two parties are like two hostile souls which struggle to enter into this vast body and put it in motion. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="16">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11968" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12042">It is for them to strive who can best circulate reports the most calculated to excite the passions, to direct the movements of the populace in favour of either one or other of the parties; it is for them to discover news the most likely to call forth their indignation or appease it, to awaken their hopes or their fears; for them to know where to find that shout which, repeated from mouth to mouth, expresses, affirms, and creates at the same time the wish of the greater number for either one side or the other. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12043" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12111">All this gossip has merely been to preface the fact, that, in the combat of these two parties assembled before the Superintendent's house, the appearance of Antonio Ferrer gave immediately a decided advantage to the more moderate party, who were visibly the losing party. If this succour had arrived but a very little later, this party would neither have had the strength nor a motive to combat for. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12112" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12138">This man was agreeable to the multitude on account of the tariff of his own invention, which was so favourable to purchasers, and on account also of his heroic resistance to all the arguments brought forward by the opposing party. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12139" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12168">The minds of those already favourably prepossessed were still more influenced by the courageous confidence of this old man, who, without guards, and without display, was thus come to meet and expose himself to an irritated and stormy populace. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12169" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12234">Thus, the hearing that he was come to carry the Superintendent off to prison produced an admirable effect. The fury against this unfortunate man would have arisen with twofold violence had he come to oppose it, had he conceded nothing; but with this promise of satisfaction, or as they say in the Milanese, "with this bone in the mouth," their fury somewhat calmed itself, and gave way to the sentiments of an opposite nature, which sprang up in the hearts of a considerable number. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="17">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12235" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12312">The partisans of peace, having recovered breath, seconded Ferrer in a hundred ways: those who were near him, exciting by their applause the applause of the people, and endeavouring at the same time to induce the crowd to stand back and open a way for the carriage; others, in applauding, repeating, and circulating his words, or those which appeared to them the best which he could possibly have said,—imposing silence upon the furious and obstinate,—and in turning against them the new passion of this fickle assembly. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12313" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12322">"Who is there who desires we should not shout—live Ferrer! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12323" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12333">Thou dost not then wish that bread should be cheap? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12334" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12356">These are the villains who do not desire an act of Christian justice; and there are among them those who bawl louder than the others to save the Superintendent. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12357" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12360">"Throw the Superintendent in prison! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12361" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12362">Long live Ferrer! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12363" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12365">Make way for Ferrer!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12366" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12409">The number of those who spoke thus continued to increase; the numbers of the opposite party were on the decrease; so that the one party, excited by the sermon, threw themselves upon those who were still busied with their work of demolition, ill-used them, and tore their tools out of their hands. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12410" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12431">The latter, fuming with rage and menacing, sought to revive their interest; but the cause of blood was lost: the cry which now predominated was, "Prison! Justice! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12432" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12493">Ferrer!" After a short struggle these were vanquished; the others made themselves masters of the door, in order to defend it from fresh assault, and to prepare an entrance for Ferrer. One of them, shouting to the people of the house through the wall, — fissures were not wanting, — informed them that he was come with succour, and that the Superintendent should hold himself in readiness, "to go immediately — to prison. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12494" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12530">Do you understand?" "Is this the Ferrer who helped to make the edicts?" demanded our Renzo of one of his new neighbours, remembering the vidit Ferrer which the Doctor had shouted into his ear, and shewn him at the bottom of a certain famous edict. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="19">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12531" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12537">"Precisely so, the High-Chancellor," — was the reply. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="20">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12538" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12542">"He is a brave gentleman, is he not?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="21">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12543" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12579">"He is more than a brave gentleman! It is he who has lowered the price of bread; the others did not wish it; and now he is come to fetch the Superintendent to carry him to prison, because he has not acted justly." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="22">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12580" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12590">It is not needful to say that Renzo was for Ferrer. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12591" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12624">He wished to go straightway to meet him; the thing was not easy; but by certain kicks of his feet, and blows with his elbows, wherein he exercised his mountaineer's strength, he succeeded in making way for himself, and arrived in the first rank, beside the carriage. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="23">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12625" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12650">The carriage had already just entered the crowd; and at this moment was stopped by one of those obstacles so inevitable and so frequent in a progress of this description. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12651" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12693">The old High-Chancellor presented first at one window of his coach, and then at the other, a countenance, all humility, all smiles, all amiability—a countenance which he had always held in reserve for the day when he should find himself in the presence of Don Philip IV., but which he was constrained to employ on this occasion. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12694" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12723">He spoke also, but the noise and hum of so many voices, the vivats, even which were shouted in his honour, allowed but a few of his words to be heard by a very few. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12724" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12778">He then aided himself by gestures, now placing the tip of his fingers upon his lips to receive a kiss, which his hands immediately distributed to the right and the left, in acknowledgment of the benevolence of the public; now, he stretched forth his hand from the carriage window and moved slowly; as to beseech the people to make way; now, he lowered it gracefully, as requesting a moment's silence. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12779" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12804">When he had obtained this, those nearest to him heard and repeated his words,—"bread, abundance. I come to execute justice; make way a little, if you please." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12805" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12851">At length, however, as though overpowered by the hum of so many voices, by the sight of so many wild countenances, and so many eyes fixed upon him, he drew himself back for a moment, swelled out his cheeks, sending forth a great breath, and said to himself; — *Por mi vida, que de gente!* "Live, Ferrer! </note>
        </p>
        <p n="24">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12852" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12854">Do not be afraid! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12855" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12858">He is a gentleman. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12859" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12860">Bread! bread!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="25">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12861" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12875">"Yes, bread, bread!" replied Ferrer. "Abundance, I promise you," and he placed his hand upon his breast. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="26">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12876" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12914">"A little space," he added immediately. "I am to conduct him to prison, to inflict upon him the just chastisement which he merits;" and he added in an under tone — "*Si es culpable!*" Then, bending forward towards his coachman, he said hastily, "*Adelante, Pedro, si puedes.*" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="27">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12915" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12959">The coachman also smiled upon the multitude with an affectionate politeness, as though he also were some great personage; and with an ineffable grace he agitated his whip very slowly to the right and the left, beseeching his inconvenient neighbours to press themselves together, and retire a little. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12960" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12977">"A little space, if you please, gentlemen," said he also, "a very little; as little as possible, only just enough to let us pass." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="28">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12978" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12991">Meanwhile, the most active of the benevolent party occupied themselves in causing that way to be made, which was requested with so much politeness. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12992" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13055">Some going before the horses made the people retire by certain sweet words, by placing their hands upon their chests, by gently pushing them: "There, there, make way a little, gentlemen." Others were busied in the same manner on each side of the carriage, in order that it should pass on without bruising their feet or crushing the countenances of the multitude; an accident which, besides the immediate evil which could have resulted, would have fearfully risked the popularity of Antonio Ferrer. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="29">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13056" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13112">Renzo, who had regarded this interesting old man some moments, disturbed by vexation, tormented by fatigue, yet, at the same time, animated by solicitude, which so to say was embellished by the hope of delivering a human being from this mortal agony—Renzo, I say, laid aside all thoughts of departure, and resolved to assist Ferrer, and not to abandon him until he had obtained his object. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13113" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13130">No sooner said than done; he placed himself with the others who busied themselves in causing the crowd to make way, and he was certainly not one of the least active. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13131" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13153">The opening was made. "Only advance," said more than one to the coachman, drawing back, or hastening forward to make way further on. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13154" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13167">"Adelante presto, con juicio," said the master also; and the carriage put itself in motion. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="30">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13168" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13232">In the midst of the salutations which he lavished promiscuously upon the populace, he had addressed also certain other thanks accompanied by a smile of intelligence to those whom he saw employed for him; more than one of these smiles were bestowed upon Renzo, who, in truth, well merited them, for he, this day, served the High-Chancellor better than the most intrepid of his secretaries could have done. To the </note>
        </p>
        <p n="31">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13233" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13248">On quickly, with precaution. young mountaineer, on fire with this charming politeness, it appeared as though he had thus formed a friendship with Antonio Ferrer. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="32">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13249" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13265">The carriage, once put in motion, continued its course with more or less slowness, and not without pausing from time to time. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13266" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13297">The distance was not more than a musket-shot; but, to judge from the time employed in making it, it would have seemed a little journey, even to those who were not inspired with the holy haste of Ferrer. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13298" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13326">The people moved, before and behind, on the right hand and on the left, like billows on either side a vessel which drives into the tempest. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13327" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13339">More piercing, more discordant, more deafening, than a tempest, was the present uproar. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13340" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13391">Ferrer, gazing now on this side, now on the other; moving and gesticulating, sought to hear something upon which to frame a suitable reply; he wished to hold a dialogue with this little troop of friends, but it was a difficult, perhaps the most difficult, thing he had yet encountered in all the long years of his High-Chancellorship. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13392" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13425">From time to time, however, some word, some phrase repeated by the assembly during his progress, made itself heard, as the explosion of a squib will often rise above the deafening crush of fireworks. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13426" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13464">And he, endeavouring to answer these shouts in a satisfactory manner, now shouting himself with all the strength of his lungs those words which he knew would be the best received, or which some sudden necessity seemed to demand, addressed the people, as he traversed the street, in words such as these: </note>
        </p>
        <p n="33">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13465" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13468">"Yes, gentlemen; bread; abundance. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13469" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13479">I myself will conduct him to prison; he shall be chastised — si es culpabile. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13480" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13488">Yes, yes; I will command; cheap bread. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13489" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13508">Asi es — it is so, I would say. The king, our lord and master, does not wish that his faithful subjects should suffer famine. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13509" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13517">Oz, oz! guardaro: Take care, that they do not hurt you, gentlemen. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13518" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13521">Pedro, adelante con juicio. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13522" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13529">Abundance, abundance! make way a little, for charity. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13530" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13531">Bread! bread! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13532" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13535">In prison! in prison! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13536" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13558">"What is this?" he demanded of a man who had already protruded more than half his body through the coach-window, to shout to the old man, a counsel, a prayer, a commendation, or whatsoever it might be. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13559" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13583">But he, without being able to hear the "what is this?" had been roughly drawn back by another who saw him in danger of being crushed under the wheels. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13584" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13622">Thus, in the midst of these questions and answers, these incessant acclamations, surrounded by the murmurs of opposition, which here and there made themselves heard, but which were speedily stifled, Ferrer, at length, arrived at the house, owing, however, his success principally to the assistance of his good auxiliaries. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="34">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13623" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13648">Those of the mob who, as we have already said, were stationed here with the same good intention, had, in the meantime, busied themselves in clearing and recreating a little space. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13649" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13714">They prayed, they exhorted, they threatened; they pushed, they pressed, they trampled with their feet, on this side and on that, with the redoubled ardour and strength which the approach of a desired end always calls forth; and they had at length succeeded in dividing the mob into two crowds, and in pressing back the two divisions, so that between the carriage and the door, before which it had stopped, there was a little free space. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13715" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13756">Renzo, who, acting as scout and guide, had arrived with the carriage, was able to find place in one of the two ranks of these good people, who formed, at the same time, a protection for the carriage and two banks to keep within bounds these two overpowering waves of the populace. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13757" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13776">And, assisting to keep back one of these waves with his powerful shoulders, he found himself very well placed to see everything. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="35">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13777" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13791">Ferrer drew a long breath when he saw the small opening which was cleared, and that the door was yet closed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13792" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13840">It would be better to say, not yet opened; for the hinges were unnailed from the door-posts, the panels shivered, bruised, forced in and broken in the middle, allowing a piece of a bolt to be seen through a large aperture, which twisted, loosened, and almost torn out of its socket, still, however, held all together. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13841" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13882">One of these good men had placed himself at this opening, and shouted that they should open the door; another ran to open the carriage-door; the old man put out his head, rose, and, supporting himself with his right hand upon this excellent fellow's arm, he issued forth and placed his foot upon the step. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="36">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13883" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13914">The crowd, on all sides, stood on tiptoe to see; there are a thousand faces, a thousand beards, raised in the air; the general curiosity and attention create a moment of general silence. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13915" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13958">Ferrer, resting a moment upon the step, casts a glance around him, salutes with an inclination of his body the multitude, as though from a pulpit, places his left hand upon his breast, and cries, "Bread and justice!" and then, bold, upright, and clothed in his robe, he descends midst the acclamations which mount to heaven. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13959" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13992">Meanwhile those within had opened the door, or rather had completed the opening, by drawing away the bolt, together with the rings, already unnailed; and widening the aperture only just enough, however, to allow this desired guest to enter. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13993" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14018">"Quick, quick!" said he, "open wide, so that I can enter, and you, like brave fellows, keep back the people; and let none follow me—for the love of heaven! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14019" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14026">Open a way for us presently. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14027" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14053">Eh! eh! gentlemen, a moment," he said, at length, to those within, "gently with this door, allow me to pass; ah! my ribs; I beg you to be careful of my ribs. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14054" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14062">Now close it again; no, eh! eh! my robe! my robe!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14063" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14091">It would, in fact, have remained shut in between the door and the door-post had he not with much dexterity drawn in his train after him,—it disappeared like the tail of a serpent which hides itself in its hole. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="37">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14092" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14099">The door, closed again as well as it could be, was again propped up. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14100" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14134">Outside, those who had constituted themselves Ferrer's body-guard laboured with their shoulders, their arms, and their cries, to maintain the space clear, praying in the bottom of their hearts that he would make haste. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="38">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14135" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14162">"Quick! quick!" exclaimed Ferrer, also within, to the domestics, who crowded round him, crying, "Blessings be upon you! Ah, your Excellence! Oh, your Excellence! Praised be your Excellence!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="39">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14163" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14169">"Quick! quick!" replied Ferrer, "where is this blessed man?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="40">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14170" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14188">The Superintendent descended the stairs, half dragged, half carried by his other servants, pale as death. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14189" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14231">When he saw his saviour, he drew a long breath, his pulse began again to beat, a little life flowed into his legs, a little colour into his cheeks, and he ran as well as he could towards Ferrer, saying, "I am in the hands of God, and of your Excellency. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14232" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14236">But how to escape from here? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14237" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14244">On all sides are people who desire my death!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="41">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14245" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14262">"Venga usted con migo,"* and take courage; outside is my carriage, quick, quick!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14263" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14312">He seized him by the hand, and conducted him towards the door, encouraging him all the time, but saying to himself, "Aquí está el busilis: Dios nos valga!"† The door opened: Ferrer issued forth the first; the other followed behind, shrinking together, and clinging fast to this toga of deliverance, as a child does to its mother's petticoat. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="42">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14313" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14356">Those who had maintained the space clear now raised their hands and waved their hats, and made, in fact, a species of veil—a cloud so as to screen the Superintendent from the dangerous gaze of the multitude: the unfortunate man entered the carriage the first, and there concealed himself in one of the corners. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14357" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14363">Ferrer then mounted, and the door was shut. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14364" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14380">The multitude sees something confusedly, knows what has taken place, and yells forth a torrent of applause and imprecation. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="43">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14381" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14397">The portion of the journey yet to be made might appear the most difficult and the most dangerous. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14398" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14455">But the desire of the people that the Superintendent should be conducted to prison had sufficiently manifested itself; and whilst the carriage had been waiting, many of those who had favoured Ferrer's arrival, had occupied themselves in keeping open the passage through the crowd; the carriage upon its return The Spanish phrase means "Come with me." The exclamation expresses: "Here is the difficult point: God preserve us!" could thus proceed faster and continuously. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="44">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14456" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14476">Gradually, as it advanced, the two crowds, ranged along the narrow passage, mingled together and united behind. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="45">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14477" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14504">Ferrer, scarcely seated, had bent forward to advise the Superintendent to keep himself concealed as far back in the carriage as possible, and not to show himself for the love of heaven; but this piece of advice was needless. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14505" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14522">The High-Chancellor, on the contrary, was obliged to exhibit himself, so as to occupy and draw upon himself all the public attention. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14523" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14572">During this journey, as well as during the former one, he held, with his fickle auditory, a discourse, the most continuous as far as time was concerned, and yet the most disconnected with regard to sense, which ever was heard; he interrupted it, however, every now and then, by some Spanish words which he turned round to whisper into his companion's ear. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="46">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14573" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14596">"Yes, gentlemen; bread and justice; in the castle, in the prison, under my custody. — Thanks, thanks, many thanks. — No, no, he shall not escape! — *Por ablandarlos.* — It is too just. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14597" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14617">He shall be examined; it shall be seen that I myself wish you well, gentlemen. — A severe chastisement. — *Esto lo digo por su bien.* A just tariff, an honest tariff, and punishment for those who will starve the people. — Retire a little, if you please. — Yes, yes. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14618" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14651">I am a gentleman, a friend to the people. — He shall be punished; it is true, he is a villain, a rogue. — *Pardone, usted.* He will pass a miserable quarter of an hour — he will pass a miserable quarter of an hour — *si es culpable.* Yes, yes, we will make the bakers keep to a straight path. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14652" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14682">Long live the King, and the good Milanese, his faithful vassals!—He is badly off—he is badly off.—Animo; estamos ya quasi fuera. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="47">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14683" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14709">They had, in fact, passed through the greater crowd, and were already on the point of issuing forth and pursuing their way in peace. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14710" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14764">There, whilst Ferrer commenced reposing his lungs, he perceived this succour from Pisa; these Spanish soldiers who, however, towards the end, had not been totally useless, because, supported and directed by some citizens, they had co-operated in keeping the people quiet, and in preserving the way clear at the farther extremity. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14765" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14829">On the arrival of the carriage, they drew themselves up in line, and presented arms to the High-Chancellor, who returned also a salutation to the right and to the left; and to the officer who came nearer to present his salutation, he said, accompanying the words with a movement of the right hand, "Beso a usted las manos;" words, which the officer understood as they were really meant; that is,—you have afforded me a fine assistance! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14830" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14840">In reply, he made another sign, and shrugged his shoulders. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14841" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14875">This was really the opportunity to say, Cedant arma togae; but Ferrer, at this moment, had not his head running upon quotations; and, besides, it would have been throwing away words, for the officer did not understand Latin. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="48">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14876" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14898">Pedro, passing between these two files of muskets thus respectfully raised, felt his old courage return. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14899" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14939">He recovered immediately from his confusion; he recalled who he was, and whom he was driving, and cried, "Ohe! ohe!" without adding any other ceremonious words, for the people were now scattered thinly enough to be thus treated with impunity, he whipped his horses and made them take the road towards the castle. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="49">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14940" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14984">"*Levántese, levántese; estamos ya fuera,*" said Ferrer to the Superintendent, who, assured by the cessation of cries, and by the rapid movement of the carriage, and by these words, drew himself out of his corner, rose, and, recovering his voice, began returning thanks without end to his liberator. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14985" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_15065">The latter, after having condoled with him in danger, and rejoiced with him in his salvation, exclaimed, striking his smooth head, "Ah! *¿qué dirá de esto su Excelencia,*" who is already almost mad with this cursed Casale which will not surrender? "*¿Qué dirá el conde Duque,*" who is alarmed if a leaf makes more noise than usual! "*¿Qué dirá el rey nuestro señor,*" who will not fail to learn something regarding an uproar such as this? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_15066" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_15073">And, even now, will this be at an end? *Dios lo sabe.*" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="50">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_15074" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_15115">"Ah, for myself, I desire to meddle no more in it!" said the Superintendent. "I wash my hands of it. I resign my post into your Excellency's hands, and shall go and live in a cave upon a mountain, a hermit, far away from these ferocious people." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="51">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_15116" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_15135">"*Usted,*" "you will do what is most proper *por el servicio de su Magestad,*" replied the High-Chancellor, gravely. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_15136" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_15154">"His Majesty will not desire my death," replied the Superintendent; "in a cave, in a cave, far, far from these people." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="52">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap13-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_15155" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_15183">Our author does not tell us what became of his proposition, for, after having accompanied the poor man to the castle, he no longer makes mention of his affairs. </note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>