<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CHAPTER X.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>1845</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed Lovers: a Milanese Story of the Seventeenth Century. With The Column of Infamy by Alessandro Manzoni. In Three Volumes</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
          <date>1845</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Henry Francis C. Logan</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="English_1845_cap10">
        <p n="1">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10055">There are moments, particularly in youth, when the soul is disposed in such a manner that the least solicitation is sufficient to obtain anything which has the appearance of sacrifice; as a flower, scarcely opened, droops upon its fragile stem, ready to abandon its fragrance to the first breeze which caresses it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10056" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10086">These moments, which one ought to admire with a timid respect, are precisely those which interested, cunning spies spy out attentively and seize, to bind an unguarded wish. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="2">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10087" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10104">On reading this letter, the Prince — saw suddenly the loophole open to his old and constant views. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10105" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10123">He sent to inform Gertrude that she should come to him; and expecting her, he disposed himself to strike the iron. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10124" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10147">Gertrude appeared, and without raising her eyes to her father's face, threw herself on her knees before him, and had scarcely breath to say "pardon!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10148" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10193">He signed to her to rise; but, with a voice little calculated to reassure her, he replied, that it was not sufficient either to desire or to crave pardon; that this was a thing but too easy and too natural in every one who found themselves guilty, and who feared punishment; that, in short, it was necessary to merit pardon. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10194" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10202">Gertrude demanded submissively and tremblingly, what she ought to do. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10203" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10247">The Prince (one has not the heart to give him in this moment the title of father) did not directly reply to this, but began talking tediously about Gertrude's fault; and these words made the soul of the poor girl smart, as does a wound under the touch of a rude hand. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10248" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10299">He continued, saying, that—when even—in case,—he should have had at first the intention of establishing her in the world, she herself had now placed an insurmountable obstacle in the way, since a man of honour, like himself, could never be audacious enough to present to a gentleman a young lady who had given such a proof of her disposition. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10300" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10365">The miserable listener was annihilated; then the Prince, softening by degrees his voice and words, continued saying, that, however, for every fault there was a remedy and mercy; and that hers was one of those for which the remedy was most clearly indicated; that she must see from this sad accident, that the life of the world was too full of dangers for her. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="3">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10366" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10384">"Ah, yes!" exclaimed Gertrude, overcome by fear and shame, and moved in this moment by an instantaneous tenderness. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="4">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10385" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10393">"Ah! you also comprehend this," replied the Prince immediately. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10394" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10457">"Well, the past shall be spoken of no more,—all is cancelled; you have taken the only honourable and convenient course which remained to you; but since you have chosen it by your own free will, and with so good a grace, it is for me to render it agreeable in every thing to you,—it is for me to cause you to enjoy all the advantage and merit of this action; I will take charge of this." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10458" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10501">Saying these words, he rang a little bell which stood upon a small table, and said to the servant who entered, "the Princess and the young Prince immediately;" and then continued, turning to Gertrude, "I wish to make them participate in my joy; I wish that they should commence immediately to treat you in a manner suitable to the occasion. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10502" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10517">You have until now experienced what is a severe father, but henceforth you shall only know the affectionate parent." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="5">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10518" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10524">At these words, Gertrude remained confounded. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10525" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10578">Now, she thought how this yes, which had escaped her lips, could have been able to signify so much; now she sought whether there were any means of contracting and restraining its sense; but the persuasion of the Prince appeared so entire, his joy so jealous, his amiability so conditional, that Gertrude dared not proffer a word which could trouble him the least in the world. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="6">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10579" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10596">After a few moments, the Princess and the young Prince came, and seeing Gertrude there, looked in her face uncertain and full of wonder. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10597" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10625">But the Prince, with a gay and amiable air, which prescribed to them also a similar one, said, "Behold the stray sheep; let this be the last word which recalls this sad memory. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10626" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10630">Behold the joy of the family! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10631" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10648">Gertrude has no longer need of counsel, that which we desired for her good she has done spontaneously. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10649" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10686">She is resolved, she makes me understand—" Here Gertrude raised towards her father a look half-astonishment, half-supplication, as though begging him to desist, but he continued, "that she is resolved to take the veil." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="7">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10687" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10717">"Well done! Excellent!" exclaimed with one voice the mother and son, and both embraced Gertrude, who received these embraces with tears, which were interpreted as tears of joy. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10718" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10736">Then the Prince was diffuse in explaining what he would do to render his daughter's fate gay and splendid. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10737" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10776">He spoke of the distinction which she would enjoy in the convent and in the country; that she should be like a Princess, like the representative of the family, that, as soon as her age should permit, she should be raised to the first dignity, and that in the meantime she should be only subject in name. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10777" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10796">The Princess and young Prince renewed every moment their congratulations and applause—Gertrude was as possessed by a dream. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="8">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10797" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10817">"It will be proper then to fix the day for going to Monza, to make the request to the Abbess," said the Prince; "how pleased she will be! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10818" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10831">I can say that all the convent know well how to appreciate the honour which Gertrude does it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10832" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10837">And even—why not go to-day? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10838" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10843">Gertrude will willingly take the air." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="9">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10844" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10848">"Let us go then," said the Princess. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="10">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10849" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10856">"I will go and give orders," said the young Prince. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="11">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10857" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10860">"But——," proffered Gertrude, submissively. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="12">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10861" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10884">"Gently, gently," replied the Prince, "we will leave it to her to decide; perhaps to-day she does not feel herself sufficiently disposed, and she would rather wait till to-morrow. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10885" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10891">Say, would you rather go to-day or to-morrow?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="13">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10892" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10910">"To-morrow," replied Gertrude, in a weak voice to whom it appeared something, having only gained a little time. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="14">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10911" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10921">"To-morrow," said the Prince solemnly, "she has fixed that it shall be to-morrow. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10922" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10934">Meanwhile I will go to the vicar, to arrange a day for the examination. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10935" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10959">Without farther being said, the Prince left the house, and really went (which was no small honour) to the vicar, and there concerted that he should come in two days. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="15">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10960" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10973">All the rest of this day, Gertrude had not a moment of comfort. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10974" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11025">She would have wished to repose her soul after so much agitation, to allow, so to say, her thoughts to clear themselves, to render account to herself of that which she had done, and of that which still remained to do; to know what she desired; to retard a moment this machine which, scarcely set in motion, hurried on with such precipitation; but there was no means of doing this. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11026" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11034">The occupations which succeeded each other without interruption entirely prevented all reflection. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11035" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11058">Immediately after the Prince's departure, she was conducted into the cabinet of the Princess, there to be dressed and adorned under her direction, by the hands of her own women. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11059" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11072">They had not yet given the finishing touch, when it was announced that dinner was served. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11073" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11116">Gertrude passed on through the respectful bows of the servants, who seemed to felicitate themselves upon her cure, and she found some of her nearest relations, who had been invited in haste to do honour to her, to congratulate her upon these two happy events, the recovery of her health, and the declaration of her determination. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="16">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11117" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11156">The *Sposina* (it is thus they call young girls destined to the cloister, and Gertrude at her entrance was saluted by all with this name), the Sposina had enough to do to answer all the compliments which were made her on all hands. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11157" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11173">She was well aware that each of her answers was like a new consent and a confirmation, but how to answer differently? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11174" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11182">Directly after leaving the table came the hour of the drive. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11183" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11197">Gertrude went in the carriage with her mother, and two uncles, who had been at dinner. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11198" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11233">After the ordinary tour, they drove into the Strada Marina, which covered then the space occupied at the present day by the public gardens; it was the place where the Signori came in their carriages to refresh themselves after the fatigues of the day. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11234" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11321">Gertrude's uncles spoke also to her as was proper on such a day, and one of them, who appeared to know better than the other every body, every carriage, every livery, and who had every moment something to say of Signor this, or of Signora that, interrupted himself all at once, and turning round to his niece, said,—"Ah, you little rogue! you turn your back upon all this idle nonsense. You are a little sly puss; you leave all of us poor worldlings in our embarrassments, you retire to lead a holy life, and drive comfortably to paradise in your carriage!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="17">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11322" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11342">In the evening they returned home, and the domestics, descending in haste with torches, announced that many visiters were expected. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11343" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11358">The news had spread, and friends came to pay their respects. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11359" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11363">They entered the conversation-hall. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11364" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11372">Here the Sposina was the idol, the amusement, the victim. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11373" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11417">It was who should have her most to herself, who should give her sweetmeats, who should promise to go and see her, who should speak to her of the mother such-a-one her relation, or the mother such-a-one an acquaintance of hers, who should vaunt the air of Monza, who should paint an enchanting picture of the high rank she would enjoy there. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11418" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11447">Others, who had not yet been able to approach Gertrude thus besieged, stood waiting for an occasion to present themselves, and felt a certain remorse, until they had acquitted themselves of this duty. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11448" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11469">By degrees the company withdrew; all left with an easy conscience, and Gertrude remained alone with her parents and her brother. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="18">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11470" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11485">"At length," said the Prince, "I have had the pleasure of seeing my daughter treated according to her rank! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11486" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11514">One must, however, confess that she has behaved admirably. She has shewn that she will not be in the least embarrassed, in assuming the first place, and in maintaining the honour of the family." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="19">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11515" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11528">They supped in haste, in order to retire immediately, and thus be ready early the next morning. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="20">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11529" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11585">Gertrude, saddened, provoked, and yet at the same time a little vain of all these compliments, remembered at this moment all she had suffered from her gaoleress; and seeing her father thus disposed to gratify her in every thing, with but one exception, she desired to profit by the prosperity in which she found herself, and appease one of the passions which tormented her. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11586" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11599">Therefore she shewed a great repugnance to be with this woman, and complained strongly of her behaviour. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="21">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11600" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11608">"How?" said the Prince, "has she been wanting in respect towards you? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11609" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11616">To-morrow, to-morrow, I will give her something which she shall remember long. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11617" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11631">Leave it to me, I will make her know who she is, and who you are. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11632" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11651">And, in any case, a daughter with whom I am contented, ought not to see near her a person who displeases her." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11652" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11688">Saying this, he had another woman called, whom he ordered to wait upon Gertrude; who, however, deliberating upon the satisfaction she had received, was astonished to find in it so little savour, in comparison with the desire for it which she had experienced. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="22">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11744" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11788">The woman who accompanied Gertrude to her apartment was an old servant of the family, formerly governess of the young Prince, whom she had received from the arms of his nurse; educated almost to adolescence, and upon whom she had placed all her joys, all her hopes, all her glory. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11789" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11872">She was as happy about the decision made this day, as though it were one influencing her own fortune; and Gertrude, for the last diversion of the day, had to submit to the congratulations, the praises, the counsels of the old woman, and to hear her speak of certain aunts and great aunts who had been enchanted with the life of a nun; since being of this family they had enjoyed always the highest honours, had known how to keep one hand without the convent, and thus in their parlours had obtained things which the greatest ladies in their halls could never have attained. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11873" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11911">She spoke of the visits she would receive; one day she would see the young Prince with his bride, who would certainly be some very great lady; and then not only the convent, but also all the country would be in movement. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11912" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11928">The old woman spoke while assisting Gertrude to undress, she spoke when Gertrude was already in bed, and she still spoke when Gertrude slept. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11929" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11939">Youth and fatigue had been more powerful than sorrow. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11940" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11970">Her sleep was unquiet, agitated, full of painful dreams, and was only broken by the screaming voice of the old woman who came to wake her, in order to prepare her for the journey to Monza. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="23">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11971" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11988">"Rise, rise, Signora Sposina, it is broad day, and another hour will have passed at least before you are dressed and have finished your toilet. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11989" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12001">The Princess is dressing; she has been wakened four hours earlier than usual. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12002" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12021">The young Prince has already descended to the stables, he will return directly, and will be ready to set out when you are. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12022" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12043">He is as lively as a hare--the little rogue! But he has always been so from quite a little child, and I can say so, who have carried him in my arms. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12044" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12062">But when he is ready one must not make him wait, because, although he is of the best temper in the world, he gets impatient then, and grows very angry. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12063" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12083">Poor little fellow! one must please him; it is his disposition; and then this time he has a little reason for it, since he puts himself out of the way for you. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12084" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12114">Woe to him who provokes the young Prince in these moments! He has regard for no one excepting the Prince, but one day he will also be Prince himself; let that day be, however, as far off as possible! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12115" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12117">Quick, quick, Signora Sposina. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12118" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12122">Why do you look at me so amazed? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12123" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12129">By this hour you ought to be out of your nest. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="24">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12130" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12156">At the image of the young Prince impatient, all the other ideas which had crowded the awakened mind of Gertrude dispersed themselves like a troop of sparrows at the sight of a kite. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12157" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12176">She obeyed, dressed herself in haste, let her hair be arranged, and appeared in the hall where her parents and brother were assembled. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12177" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12209">They made her seat herself in a large arm-chair, and brought her a cup of chocolate: taking the veil was the same thing as among the Romans assuming the vestal robe. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="25">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12210" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12237">When it was announced that the carriage was ready, the Prince drew aside his daughter and said to her, "Now, Gertrude, yesterday you did yourself honour, to-day you must even surpass yourself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12238" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12258">You have to appear at the convent, and in the country, where you are destined to play the first character." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12259" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12282">They expect you there (it is needless to say the Prince had sent notice of this to the Abbess the day before), and all eyes will be upon you. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12283" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12285">Have dignity and be skilful. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12286" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12322">The Abbess will demand what is your desire, this is a mere formality; you can answer that you ask permission to be admitted to take the veil in the convent where you have been educated with so much love, where you have received so many favours; which is the pure truth. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12323" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12345">Say these few words with an independent air, so that it may not be said they have been whispered to you, and that you do not know how to speak by yourself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12346" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12375">There, the good mothers know nothing of what has happened; it is a secret which shall rest buried in the family, and therefore do not make a contrite and doubtful face which could cause suspicion. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12376" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12399">Shew from what blood you spring; be polite and modest, but remember that in this place, excepting your family, no one is higher than you. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="26">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12400" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12422">Without waiting for an answer, the Prince moved away, the Princess and the young Prince followed him; they descended all four the staircase, and got into the carriage. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12423" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12449">The embarrassments and the annoyances of the world, and the holy life of the cloister, particularly for young women of noble blood, were the themes of conversation during the drive. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12450" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12468">Towards the end of their journey the Prince renewed his instructions to his daughter, and repeated many times the form of the response. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12469" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12501">Entering Monza, Gertrude felt her heart ache, but her attention was attracted by I do not know what Signor, who stopped the carriage, repeating I do not know how many compliments. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12502" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12523">They recommenced their way, moving along at a foot's pace towards the convent, between the regards of the curious who rushed from all sides into the street to gaze at them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12524" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12543">When the carriage paused before this wall, before this door so well known of old, Gertrude's heart ached still more. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12544" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12556">She descended from the carriage between two rows of people, whom the domestics ordered to stand back. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12557" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12618">All these eyes riveted upon the poor child obliged her continually to study her countenance; but what more than all the rest held her in subjection was the eyes of her father, towards which, although she feared them so much, she could not avoid turning hers every moment; these eyes governed her movements and her countenance as by means of invisible reins. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12619" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12641">They crossed the first court, entered another, and there saw the door of the inner cloister open and crowded with nuns. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12642" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12666">In the first row was the Abbess, surrounded by the elders; behind them, other nuns, pêle-mêle, some on tip-toe, and last of all the lay sisters standing on benches. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12667" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12714">You saw here and there gleam some little eye, peep forth some little face, between the black robes; these were the wildest and most courageous among the pupils, who introduced themselves, and penetrating between nun and nun, had succeeded in making a little hole for themselves so as to see something. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12715" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12730">From the multitude went forth many an acclamation; you saw many arms wave themselves in sign of welcome and joy. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12731" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12744">Arrived at the door, Gertrude found herself face to face with the Lady Abbess. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12745" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12773">After the first compliments, this one with a manner half-joyous, half-solemn, demanded what she desired in this place, since there was nothing which they could refuse her. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="27">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12774" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12808">"I am here——" commenced Gertrude, but at the moment of pronouncing the words which decided thus irrevocably her fate, she hesitated an instant, and remained with her eyes fixed upon the crowd before her. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12809" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12839">She saw in this moment one of her most intimate companions, who regarded her with an air of compassion, and yet at the same time of malice, and who seemed to say, — "Ah, there is our brave one fallen at last!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12840" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12935">This sight woke again more livingly than ever in her soul old feelings, and restored also a little of her former courage; and she sought an answer somewhat different from the one which had been told her. When, raising her eyes towards the countenance of her father, as though to essay her strength, she perceived there a disgust so deep, an impatience so menacing, that, resolved by fear, with the same speed with which she would have fled a terrible object, she continued, — "I am here beseeching to be admitted to take the veil in this convent, where I have been brought up with so much love." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="28">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12936" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13017">The Abbess quickly replied that it pained her much upon such an occasion, that the rules did not permit her to give an immediate reply; this reply must come from the united voices of the sisters, and must precede the permission of the superiors; but that Gertrude, knowing the sentiments which they entertained for her there, could foresee with certainty what this answer would be; and that in the meantime no rule prohibited the Abbess and sisters from manifesting the joy which they felt at this request. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13018" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13026">A confused murmur of congratulations and acclamations arose. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13027" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13043">Great baskets, filled with sweetmeats, were presented first to the Sposina, and then to her parents. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13044" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13072">Whilst some of the nuns fondled her, others complimented the mother, others the young Prince, the Abbess prayed the Prince that he would come to the grate of the parlour, where she expected him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13073" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13136">She was accompanied by two elders, and when she saw him appear, "Signor Prince," she said, "in obedience to the rules, to accomplish an indispensable form—although in this case—nevertheless I am obliged to tell you—that every time a daughter asks to be admitted to take the veil—the Superior, who I am unworthily—is obliged to inform the parents—that if by chance—they may have forced the will of their daughter—they will incur excommunication. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13137" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13138">But you will excuse me——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="29">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13139" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13142">"Very good, very good," reverend Mother. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13143" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13149">I praise your exactitude, it is too just. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13150" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13154">But you cannot doubt—— </note>
        </p>
        <p n="30">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13155" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13165">"Oh! I think Signor Prince—I have spoken to fulfil precisely—as for the rest——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="31">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13166" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13169">"Certainly, certainly, Lady Abbess." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="32">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13170" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13207">Having exchanged these few words, the two interlocutors bowed to each other, and separated as though both one and the other were desirous to end the tête-à-tête, and each one went to rejoin the party awaiting them, one within, the other without, the convent. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="33">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13208" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13231">"Come!" said the Prince, "Gertrude will soon be able to enjoy, at her leisure, the company of these good mothers. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13232" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13237">For this time we have wearied them enough." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13238" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13255">Thus saying, he saluted the Lady Abbess, the family followed his example; they renewed their compliments, and again set forth. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="34">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13256" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13264">Gertrude, in returning, had no great desire to talk. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13265" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13318">Frightened at the step she had taken, ashamed of her weakness, vexed with others and with herself, she sorrowfully counted over the occasions in which it yet remained for her to say no, and promised weakly and confusedly to herself that she would have more address and courage. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13319" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13377">All these thoughts, however, had not entirely dispelled her fears of the frowns of her father; so little so indeed, that when by a glance cast secretly she saw in his countenance that there remained no longer any trace of anger, but that, on the contrary, he appeared very well satisfied with her, this seemed so great a happiness that she was for a moment quite joyful. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="35">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13378" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13398">As soon as they arrived it was necessary to change her dress, then came the dinner, then other visits, then the promenade, then the *conversazione*, then the supper. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13399" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13414">Towards the end of which, the Prince brought into the field another affair, the selection of the godmother. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13415" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13485">Thus is a lady called, who, at the request of the parents, becomes guardian and conductress of the young Sposina during the time which elapses between the supplication and the entrance into the convent,—time employed in visiting the churches, the public places, societies, villas, sanctuaries, every thing, in short, most remarkable in the town and its neighbourhood, to the end that the young girls, before pronouncing an irrevocable vow, may know what they renounce. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13486" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13517">"It is necessary to think about a godmother," said the Prince, "since to-morrow the Nuns' Vicar will come for the formality of the examination, and immediately afterwards Gertrude will be proposed in the chapter to be accepted by the Mothers." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13518" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13579">Saying these words, he had turned towards the Princess, and she, believing that this was an invitation to propose, commenced, "It would be—" But the Prince interrupted, "No, no, Signora; the godmother must, before every thing, please the Sposina; and although general custom gives the choice to the parents, still Gertrude has so much judgment, so much caution, that she really deserves that an exception should be made in her favour." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13580" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13631">And then, turning to Gertrude with an air of one who announces a particular favour, he continued, "Every one of those ladies who have been here this evening has the necessary qualifications for being godmother to a daughter of our house; there is not one, believe me, who will not consider this selection as a great honour: select." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="36">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13632" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13666">Gertrude saw well that to make this selection was to give a fresh consent; but the proposition had been made with so much ceremony, that the refusal, however humble this were, would appear disdainful, or at least capricious and ungrateful. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13667" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13716">She took also this step, and named the lady who all the evening had pleased her the most; that is, the one who had lavished the most caresses upon her, praised her the most, treated her with those familiar, affectionate, and earnest manners which, in the first moments of an acquaintance, counterfeit an old friendship. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13717" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13727">"An excellent choice!" exclaimed the Prince, who desired and expected precisely this. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13728" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13772">Were it art or chance, there had now happened to Gertrude that which often arrives when a card-player, passing quickly before your eyes a pack of cards, tells you to think of one which he will guess; but, in fact, he has made them all pass before your eyes in such a manner that you have only seen one. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13773" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13800">This lady had been beside Gertrude all the evening, she had occupied herself so much with her, that it would have required a good effort of the imagination for Gertrude to have thought of another. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13801" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13850">So much eagerness had not been without a motive; the lady had fixed her eyes for a long time upon the young Prince as her son-in-law; therefore she regarded the affairs of the house as her own, and it was very natural that she should interest herself about this dear Gertrude no less than the nearest relations. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="37">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13851" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13885">The next morning Gertrude woke with the thought of the Nuns' Vicar who should come, and whilst she was reflecting whether she could avail herself of this desired opportunity and draw back, the Prince sent for her. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="38">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13886" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13900">"Well, my daughter," he said, "so far you have conducted yourself admirably; to-day you will crown the work. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13901" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13911">All that has hitherto been done has been done by your consent. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13912" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13944">If during this time any doubt, any little feeling of repentance, any youthful whims should have arisen, you ought to have expressed them; but at the point at which things now are, it is no longer time to play the child. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13945" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13976">The excellent man who comes this morning will ask you a hundred questions regarding your vocation; whether you are entering the convent by your own free-will, the why and the wherefore, and many other things. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13977" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13988">If you waver in your answer, who knows how long he may keep you on the rack? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13989" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14004">It would be a weariness and torment for you; but a more serious misfortune could arise from it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14005" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14051">After all the public demonstrations which have been made, the smallest hesitation that is seen in you might endanger my honour, might cause people to believe that I had mistaken one of your youthful caprices for a firm resolution," that I had precipitated the affair,—that I had—done more things than I can tell. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14052" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14145">In this case I should find myself under the necessity of selecting between two sad alternatives, either to let the world form a false conjecture regarding my conduct, and this cannot possibly agree with what I owe to myself, or to reveal the true motive of your resolution, and ——" But here, seeing that Gertrude was become scarlet, that her eyes grew large, and her face contracted itself, like the leaves of a flower in the sultry heat which precedes a tempest, he cut short his discourse, and, with a severe air, replied, "Come, come; all depends upon yourself, upon your judgment. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14146" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14168">I know that you have a deal, and that you are not a girl to spoil at the end, an affair so well begun; but I must foresee every possibility. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14169" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14193">This shall not be spoken of any more, and we rest agreed that you will reply with frankness, and in such a manner as not to give rise to doubts in the mind of this good old man. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14194" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14201">In this manner you will get out of the affair much sooner." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14202" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14240">And here, after having suggested some answers to the most probable questions, he began the usual discourse regarding the peace and joys which were prepared for Gertrude in the convent, and he conversed about this until a servant announced the Vicar. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14241" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14258">The Prince renewed, in haste, the most important instructions, and left his daughter alone with him, as was prescribed. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="39">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14259" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14287">The good man arrived with the opinion already formed that Gertrude had a strong inclination for the cloister, because the Prince had said so when he came to invite him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14288" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14354">It is true that the good priest, knowing that distrust was one of the most necessary virtues of his office, held it for a maxim to give but little belief to similar protests, and to be on his guard against preoccupation; but it rarely happens that the affirmative and confident words of a person full of authority of whatsoever kind, do not tinge with their colour the mind of the one who hears them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14355" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14400">After the usual compliments, "Signora," he said, "I am come to play the part of the devil; I come to make doubtful that which in your supplication you have given as a certainty. I come to lay before your eyes the difficulties, and to assure myself that you have well considered them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14401" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14407">Permit me to put these questions." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="40">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14408" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14411">"Speak," replied Gertrude. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="41">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14412" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14423">The good priest then began to question her according to the prescribed form of his rules. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14424" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14435">"Do you feel in your heart a free spontaneous resolution to become a nun? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14436" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14442">Have not menaces or flatteries been adopted? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14443" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14453">Has no authority been made use of to induce you to this? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14454" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14483">Speak without fear, and with sincerity, to a man whose duty it is to know your true desire, so as to prevent any violence being used towards you." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="42">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14484" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14499">The true answer to such a question presented itself suddenly in Gertrude's mind, with a terrible evidence. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14500" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14517">But, in order to give this answer, it was necessary to come to an explanation, to say with what she had been menaced, relate a long history. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14518" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14546">The unfortunate shrunk back from this idea, terrified; sought in haste another answer; she only found one which could liberate her quickly and securely from this torture—the one the most opposed to the truth. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14547" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14561">"I take the veil," she said, hiding her confusion, "I take the veil by my own desire—freely." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14562" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14574">"Since when has this thought come into your mind?" again demanded the good priest. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="43">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14575" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14591">"I have always had it," replied Gertrude, become, after the first step, more bold in lying against herself. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="44">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14592" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14603">"But what is the principal motive which induces you to turn nun?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="45">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14604" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14632">The good priest did not know what a terrible note he touched; and Gertrude made a great exertion to prevent the effect which these words produced in her soul being visible in her countenance. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14633" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14647">"The motive," she said, "is to serve God, and fly the dangers of the world." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="46">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14648" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14656">"But may not this be some disgust,—some, pardon me, some caprice? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14657" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14681">Often a momentary cause can make an impression which seems as though it would endure for ever, and then when the cause ceases, and the heart changes, then——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="47">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14682" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14694">"No, no!" returned Gertrude in haste; "the cause is such as I have told you." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="48">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14695" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14721">The Vicar, rather entirely to fulfil his duty than from persuasion that the thing was necessary, persisted in his questionings; but Gertrude was determined to deceive him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14722" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14776">Besides the shame which she felt at acquainting this grave and good priest with her weakness, who also appeared so far from suspecting such a thing from her, the poor girl thought that, although he could certainly prevent her entering the convent, there his authority and protection would cease. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14777" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14843">That, when he was gone, she should remain alone with the Prince, and of what she should then have to endure in this house the good priest would know nothing; or even did he know, he could only, with all his good intentions, feel compassion for her, —that compassion, tranquil and measured, which is generally as though courtesy felt for those who have given cause, or at least a pretence, for the injury which is done them. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="49">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14844" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14904">The Vicar was weary of questioning sooner than the unfortunate was of lying; and hearing answers always suitable, and having no reason to doubt their candour, he changed at length his language, congratulated her, demanded, in a certain way, pardon for having in the performance of his duty delayed her thus long, adding what he considered most fitting to confirm her in this good resolution, and took his leave. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="50">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14905" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14937">Crossing the apartments on his way out, he met the Prince, who appeared to be there by chance, and congratulated him moreover on the happy disposition in which he had found his daughter. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14938" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14992">The Prince, until that moment, had been in the most painful suspense; at this news he breathed again, and forgetting his accustomed gravity he almost ran towards Gertrude, lavished upon her praises, caresses and promises, with a cordial joy, with a tenderness for the most part sincere. Such a strange medley is the human heart. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="51">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14993" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15038">We will not follow Gertrude in this continual whirl of spectacles and amusements, neither will we describe minutely and in order the sentiments of her mind during this time; it would be a history of sorrows and fluctuations too monotonous, and too much like what we have already described. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15039" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15076">The pleasantness of the country, the variety of the objects, this wandering here and there in the fresh air, rendered still more odious to her the idea of the place which she should enter for the last time and for ever. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15077" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15088">Still more poignant were the impressions which she received in societies and in fêtes. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n189" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15089" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15133">The sight of each wife to whom this title was given in the most common and familiar sense caused her an intolerable envy and anguish; and sometimes the sight of other persons made her think that the hearing this title from their lips must be the height of happiness. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n190" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15134" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15178">At other times, the pomp of palaces, the splendour of their furniture, the hum and bustle of festivals, would communicate to her such an intoxication, such a desire to live joyously, that she promised herself to break her word, and suffer every thing sooner than return to the cold and deathlike gloom of the cloister. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n191" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15179" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15198">But all these resolutions vanished upon a calmer consideration of the difficulties, and at one glance towards the countenance of the Prince. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n192" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15199" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15238">Sometimes also the thought that she must abandon for ever these enjoyments rendered bitter and sad this short experience of them, as an invalid suffering from thirst regards with hatred and even thrusts aside with disdain the spoonful of water which the physician has granted to his earnest prayers. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="52">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n193" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15239" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15259">In the meantime the Vicar has given the necessary attestation, and the permission to hold the chapter for the admission of Gertrude has arrived. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n194" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15260" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15281">The chapter met; two-thirds of the secret votes which were required, agreed, as one might expect, and Gertrude was accepted. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n195" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15282" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15298">She, wearied of this long martyrdom, desired to enter the convent as soon as possible. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n196" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15299" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15307">Certainly there was no one who would curb such an impatience. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n197" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15308" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15320">Her desire was therefore attended to, and conducted with pomp to the convent, she took the veil. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n198" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15321" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15369">After twelve months noviciate full of repentance, she found herself arrived at the moment of profession, at that moment when it was necessary to pronounce a no, more strange, more unexpected, more scandalous, than ever; or repeat a yes, already repeated so many times. She repeated it, and was a nun for ever. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="53">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n199" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15370" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15394">It is one of the singular and incommunicable privileges of the Christian religion, to be able to direct and console every human being, who, under any circumstance, or guided by any motive, has recourse to her. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n200" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15395" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15437">If for the past there is any remedy, she prescribes it, furnishes it, gives knowledge and strength to bring it into operation, let this be at whatever price it may; if there is none, she gives the means to realise in effect what is taught in the proverb, that is, make necessity a virtue. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n201" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15438" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15487">She teaches to continue with wisdom that which has been undertaken with levity, inclines the soul to embrace with willingness the yoke imposed by arbitrary power, and gives to a choice which was rash, but irrevocable, all the holiness, all the prudence, nay, we say it frankly, all the joys of the religious life. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n202" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15488" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15526">It is a path so constructed that, by whatsoever labyrinth or precipice a man arrives there and takes one step, he can henceforth travel on with security and faith, and reach joyously a peaceful goal. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n203" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15527" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15542">By this means, Gertrude could have been a holy and contented nun, spite of the manner in which she had become one. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n204" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15543" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15562">But the unhappy girl struggled vainly under her yoke, and thus only felt the more its weight and pressure. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n205" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15563" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15590">An incessant regret for her lost liberty, abhorrence of her present state, and a toilsome pursuit after desires, which could never be satisfied, were the principal occupations of her mind. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n206" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15591" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15631">She thought over the bitter past, she recalled to her memory all the circumstances by which she found herself in her present position, and vainly a thousand times destroyed in thought that which she herself had constructed; she accused herself of cowardice; others, of tyranny and perfidy,—and eternally tormented herself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n207" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15632" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15668">She idolized, and at the same time wept over, her beauty; deplored her youth, destined to struggle in a slow martyrdom; and envied in certain moments the first woman who presented herself,—were she of the lowest condition, were she of the worst fame,—who could freely enjoy these gifts in the world. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="54">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n208" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15669" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15685">The sight of those nuns who had stretched forth a hand to draw her in was odious to her. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n209" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15686" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15710">She remembered the arts and subterfuges which had been put into operation, and paid them back with rudeness, caprice, and sometimes even with open reproach. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n210" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15711" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15779">The nuns were many times obliged to swallow this and be silent, because the Prince, although he had willingly tyrannised over his daughter so far as was necessary to make her enter the cloister, having now obtained his desire, would not have suffered so easily that others should oppose one of his blood; and the slightest noise made by her would cause them to lose powerful protection, or change peradventure the protector into an enemy. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n211" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15780" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15830">It seems as though Gertrude ought to have felt a certain affection towards the other sisters who had taken no part in these intrigues, and who, without having desired her as a companion, loved her as such, and who, pious, occupied, and gay, shewed her by their example how even there it were not only possible to live, but also possible to be happy. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n212" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15831" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15840">But these even were hateful to her, but hateful from another reason. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n213" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15841" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15878">Their air of piety and contentment appeared to her a reproach for her disquiet and whimsical conduct, and she allowed no opportunity to escape her of ridiculing them behind their backs as bigots, and of slandering them as hypocrites. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n214" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15879" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15909">Perhaps she would have felt less aversion towards them had she divined that the small black-balls found in the urn, which should decide her acceptation, had been precisely put in by them. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="55">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n215" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15910" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15948">She seemed sometimes to find pleasure in being able to command, in being courted within the convent, and in receiving visits from without; in making some undertaking succeed; in bestowing her protection; in hearing herself called the Signora,—but what pleasure? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n216" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15949" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16009">The heart, finding in these things so little satisfaction, would have rushed from time to time to join with them, and enjoy at the same time the consolations of religion; but these consolations do not come, unless the others are abandoned: like the shipwrecked mariner, who, if he wish to grasp the plank which can conduct him in safety to the shore, must first open his hand and let go the sea-weed which he has seized with a mad instinct. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n217" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16010" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16030">A short time after her profession, Gertrude had been nominated instructress of the pupils; you can well imagine how these young girls must have gone on under such discipline. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n218" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16031" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16060">All her former confidants had left, but she had preserved the passions of that time, and in one manner or another the poor scholars must bear their weight. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n219" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16061" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16111">When it came into her mind that many of them were destined to live in this world from which she was for ever excluded, she felt towards them hatred, nay, even a desire of revenge; she kept them under, ill-treated them, and deducted, in anticipation, from the pleasures which they should one day enjoy. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n220" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16112" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16136">Who had heard in these moments with what mighty anger she scolded them for any trifling fault would have believed her a lady of an indiscreet and savage austerity. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n221" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16137" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16156">On other occasions, her horror of the cloister, of the rules, and of obedience, burst forth in accents of quite an opposite character. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n222" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16157" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16198">Then she not only supported the clamorous diversions of her pupils, but even excited them; she joined in their games, and rendered them still more disorderly; she took part in their discourses, and led them further than had been the intention of those who commenced them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n223" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16199" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16241">If one among the scholars said a word regarding the gossip of the Lady Abbess, the preceptress imitated it at a great length, and made of it quite the scene of a comedy; she mimicked the face of one nun, the manner of another, and would then laugh like a mad creature,—but this was laughter which left her no gayer than before. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n224" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16242" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16264">Thus she had lived for several years, neither having the means nor the opportunity to do more, when, as her misfortune would have it, an opportunity presented itself. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="56">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n225" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16265" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16291">Among the other distinctions and privileges which had been granted her, in order to compensate for her not yet being Abbess, was that of having an apartment to herself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n226" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16292" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16336">This part of the convent was continuous to a house inhabited by a young man, a scoundrel by profession, one of the many who, in those times, with their followers, and with the alliance of other scoundrels, could, to a certain extent, laugh at the laws and public power. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n227" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16337" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16346">Our manuscript calls him Egidio, without speaking of his surname. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n228" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16347" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16384">He, from one of his upper windows, which looked into a little court in this quarter of the convent, had seen Gertrude sometimes walking to and fro in idleness, and, excited sooner than deterred by the daring and impiety of such an enterprise, he ventured one day to address her. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n229" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16385" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16387">The unfortunate replied. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n230" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16388" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16400">In the commencement she felt a contentment, not pure certainly, but very lively. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n231" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16401" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16442">In the shady void of her soul, an occupation strong and continuous, nay, one could almost say a powerful life, had infused itself, but this contentment resembled the restorative which the ingenious cruelty of the ancients poured out to the condemned, to give them strength to sustain their torments. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n232" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16443" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16506">In this time a great change was perceptible in her conduct, she became suddenly more regular, more tranquil, no longer gave way to her raillery and her murmurs; she shewed herself even affectionate and polite, so much so that the sisters congratulated each other on this happy transformation, so far were they from suspecting the true motive, and from comprehending that this new virtue was nothing else than hypocrisy added to her ancient vices. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n233" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16507" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16563">This appearance, this so to say exterior whitewashing, however, did not last long, at least not with this continuity and uniformity,—her customary disdain and caprices soon returned, her imprecations and raillery against the conventual imprisonment, expressed each time in a language unusual in such a place and in such a mouth, soon again made themselves heard. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n234" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16564" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16586">However, after each of these flights came repentance, and a great anxiety to make all forgotten by means of endearments and coaxing words. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n235" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16587" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16604">The sisters supported as well as they could these sudden changes, and attributed them to the Signora's whimsical and frivolous nature. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n236" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16605" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16678">For some time it appeared no one suspected anything; but one day, when the Signora had come to high words with a lay sister, about I do not know what trifle, and permitted herself to ill-treat her beyond all measure, the sister, after having suffered and bitten her lips sometime in silence, losing at length her patience, let fall that she also knew something, and in time and place could speak. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n237" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16679" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16689">From this moment the Signora had no more rest. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n238" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16690" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16743">Not many days, however, passed over, before the lay sister was in vain expected one morning to her accustomed devotions. They sought her in her cell, but they did not find her; they called her at the pitch of their voices, but she did not reply; they sought her here, they sought her there; they hunted the house through from the garrets to the cellars, she was nowhere. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n239" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16744" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16776">And who knows what conjectures might have been formed, had they not discovered a hole in the garden wall, which circumstance made every one think she had escaped this way. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n240" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16777" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16806">Great search was made after her in Monza, in the neighbourhood, and particularly in Meda, the native town of the lay sister; they wrote to various quarters, but not the slightest intelligence was gained. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n241" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16807" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16824">Perhaps they would have been able to know something regarding her, had they, instead of seeking far away, dug the earth in the neighbourhood. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n242" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16825" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16878">After a deal of astonishment, for no one could have thought her capable of such a thing, and after a deal of talking, it was concluded that she must have gone a long, long way off; and as one of the sisters said, without hesitation, "She had taken refuge in Holland," it was immediately repeated, and held as certain, both within and without the convent, that there she had taken refuge. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n243" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16879" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16888">It does not, however, appear that the Signora was of this opinion. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n244" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16889" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16941">Not that she expressed disbelief or combated this idea by her own private reasonings; if she had such, certainly never were reasons better dissimulated. There was nothing she abstained from so willingly as any reference to this history, nothing she troubled herself less about than sounding this mystery. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n245" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16942" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16950">But the less she spoke about it the more she thought. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n246" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16951" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16973">How many times in the day would the image of this woman come suddenly into her mind, plant itself there, and never move! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n247" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16974" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17005">How many times she would have desired to see her alive in reality, sooner than have her always fixed in her thoughts, sooner than be obliged day and night to find herself in company with this vain, terrible, insufferable form! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n248" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17006" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17051">How many times wished to hear her real voice, whatever it might pronounce, rather than hear always, in the depth of her soul, the fantastic murmur of this same voice, repeating words with a pertinacity, with an unmeaning obstinacy, which are never found in a living being! </note>
        </p>
        <p n="57">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n249" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17052" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17077">About a year had elapsed since this event, when Lucia was presented to the Signora, and had with her the conversation with which our relation terminated. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n250" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17078" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17123">The Signora multiplied her questions regarding the persecutions of Don Rodrigo, and entered into certain particulars with an intrepidity which appeared, and must appear, more than strange to Lucia, who had never imagined that the curiosity of nuns could exercise itself upon such subjects. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n251" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17124" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17138">The judgments with which she intermingled these questions on what transpired, were not less strange. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n252" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17139" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17199">She appeared to laugh at the great terror which Lucia had always had of this Signor, and demanded whether he were a monster to cause such fear; it was easy to be seen that she would have considered the coyness of the young girl foolish and unreasonable, had it not been for the preference given to Renzo; and regarding him she demanded questions which amazed Lucia, and made her blush. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n253" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17200" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17240">Perceiving, then, that she had let her tongue follow too freely the wanderings of her mind, she endeavoured to correct her foolish gossip, and interpret it to the best advantage. But she could not prevent an unpleasant astonishment, and a confused terror remaining in Lucia's mind. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="58">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n254" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17241" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17269">Scarcely was she alone with her mother, than she opened her heart; but Agnese, as having more experience, despatched with a few words these doubts, and cleared up the mystery. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="59">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n255" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17270" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17290">"Do not be astonished," she said; "when thou hast known the world as well I do, thou wilt see these are not things to wonder at. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n256" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17291" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17310">These gentlefolks, more or less, for one thing or another, have all a grain of folly. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n257" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17311" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17330">One must let them say what they like, particularly when one has need of them, and appear to listen to them seriously, as though they said what was just. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n258" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17331" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17344">Hast thou heard how she cut me short, as though I had said some folly? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n259" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17345" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17352">I did not appear to be astonished. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n260" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17353" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17355">They are all in this manner. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n261" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17356" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17377">But with all this, heaven be praised, that this Signora appears to have taken so to thee, and will really protect us. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n262" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17378" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17399">And for the rest, if thou canst but escape; and it should happen to thee ever to have to do with gentlefolks—thou wilt see, thou wilt see, thou wilt see." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="60">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n263" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17400" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17460">The desire of obliging the Superior, the pleasure of protecting, the thought of the good reputation which a protection thus piously employed could gain her, a certain inclination for Lucia, and even a certain consolation in doing good to an innocent creature, in the succouring and consoling the oppressed, had really disposed the Signora to take the fate of these two poor fugitives to heart. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n264" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17461" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17486">At her request, and through her care, they were lodged in a quarter of the fattoressa, near the cloister, and treated as though they were attached to the service of the convent. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n265" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17487" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17503">The mother and daughter rejoiced together in having thus quickly found a secure and honourable asylum. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n266" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17504" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17557">They would have been well satisfied to remain entirely unknown, but this was no such easy matter in a convent, particularly as there was a man very much interested in having intelligence regarding one of them, and in whose soul, anger, at thus having been outwitted and deluded, had now united itself to the ancient passions and pique. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="61">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap10-n267" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17558" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17580">Here we will leave the women in their retreat, and return to Don Rodrigo's palace, at the time when he was awaiting the issue of this criminal expedition. </note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>