<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CHAPTER XI.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>1845</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed Lovers: a Milanese Story of the Seventeenth Century. With The Column of Infamy by Alessandro Manzoni. In Three Volumes</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
          <date>1845</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Henry Francis C. Logan</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="English_1845_cap11">
        <p n="1">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10037">As a pack of hounds, after having in vain followed a hare, return home to their master mortified, their noses touching the earth, their tails between their legs, so in this night of alarms returned the bravoes to the palace. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10038" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10054">Don Rodrigo was pacing in the gloom up and down a vast and uninhabited apartment of the upper story, which overlooked the esplanade. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10055" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10100">Sometimes he paused, listened, looked through the half-opened window-shutters, full of impatience, and with some uneasiness; not alone on account of the uncertainty of this enterprise, but also on account of its possible consequences, for this was the most important and daring undertaking which this brave man had yet attempted. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10101" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10126">He, however, reassured himself, thinking of the precautions taken to prevent all traces, if not all suspicions. "As to suspicions," thought he, "I can laugh at them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10127" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10146">I should like to see who would come to look whether there were or were not a young girl here. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10147" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10154">Let him come, let him come; the boor, he shall be well received! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10155" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10158">Let the Friar come! let him come! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10159" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10160">The old woman? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10161" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10165">Let her go to Bergamo, the old soul. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10166" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10167">The law! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10168" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10170">Pah, the law! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10171" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10179">The Podesta! he's neither a child nor a fool. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10180" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10182">And at Milan? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10183" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10193">Who will listen to them at Milan? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10194" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10198">Who knows that there are such people? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10199" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10213">They are like lost people on the earth—they have not even a patron—they are people who are nothing. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10214" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10217">Come, come, there is no cause for fear. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10218" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10221">How astonished Attilio will be to-morrow! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10222" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10228">He shall see whether I only talk, or whether I act. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10229" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10353">And then—if any embarrassment should arise—how do I know?—some enemy who should seize upon this occasion. Attilio will know how to counsel me; the honour of the whole family will be at stake." But the thought with which he most occupied himself, since in it were combined a calm for his doubts and food for his principal passion, was the thought of what flatteries and promises he should make use of in order to appease Lucia. "She will be very much frightened," thought he, "at finding herself here alone in the midst of these ruffians, with faces which—I am the only one here with a human countenance—by Bacchus! she will be forced to fly to me; she will supplicate, and if she supplicates—" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="2">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n21" type="comm" status="insertion">Whilst he imagined these fine things, he hears a sound of footsteps, he goes to the window, opens it a little, puts out his head,—it is they! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n22" type="comm" status="insertion">"And the litter." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10354" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10357">"Diavolo, where is the litter? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10358" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10420">Three—five—eight—they are all there. There is Griso himself; but the litter is not with them,—diavolo! diavolo! Griso shall account to me for this." When they had entered, Griso placed in a corner of a room on the ground-floor, his staff, took off his large hat, and his frock; and then, as summoned to the performance of his office, which at this moment no one envied, he ascended to render to Don Rodrigo an account of what had happened. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="3">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10421" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10450">This impatient master, who expected him at the head of the staircase, seeing him appear with the foolish and stupid air of an outwitted knave, said, or rather cried,— "Well, Signor Bully, Signor Captain, Signor Leave-all-to-me?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="4">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10451" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10484">"It is hard," replied Griso, resting one foot on the first step, "it is hard only to receive reproaches, after having laboured faithfully, endeavoured to fulfil one's duty, and even risked one's life." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="5">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10485" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10486">"How has it gone on? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10487" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10545">Let us hear, let us hear," said Don Rodrigo, and led the way to his chamber whither Griso followed him, and immediately related what he had arranged, done, seen or not seen, heard, feared, repaired; and all this with that confusion, with that doubtfulness and wildness, which must necessarily have reigned together in his ideas. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="6">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10546" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10573">"Thou art not in fault, and thou hast conducted thyself well," said Don Rodrigo; "thou hast done all that was possible, but under this roof there must be a spy—! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10574" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10601">If there is—if I discover him,—and I will discover him if there is one,—I can tell thee, Griso, that he shall be properly dealt with." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="7">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10602" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10639">"Such a suspicion," said Griso, "has passed also through my mind; and should it be true, and should such a rogue be discovered, the Signor Padrone ought to place him in my hands. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10640" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10658">A fellow who has found amusement in making me pass a night such as this! It is for me to pay him off for it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10659" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10680">However, from various circumstances, the idea has occurred to me that there must still be some other intrigue which just at the present moment we cannot understand. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10681" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10688">To-morrow, Signor, to-morrow, we will bring it to light." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="8">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10689" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10693">"At all events you have not been recognised?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="9">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10694" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10726">Griso replied that he hoped they had not been; and the conclusion of the discourse was, that Don Rodrigo ordered three things to be done on the morrow, three things which Griso would have been very well able to think of himself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10727" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10817">To send very early the next morning two men to intimate certain things to the Consul,—which was done, as we have already seen; to despatch two others to the ruinous old house to watch round it, and keep away any idler who might direct his steps thither, and conceal from every eye the litter until the following night, when it should be sent for; the third command was to go himself, and send also some of the most cunning and clever bravoes to mingle with the populace, and thus discover something regarding the confusion of the night. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10818" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10851">Having given these orders, Don Rodrigo retired to rest, and allowed Griso to do the same, dismissing him with many words of praise, in which might be observed an ardent desire to make up for the hasty reproaches with which he had received him. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="10">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10852" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10862">Go to sleep, poor Griso, for thou must, indeed, stand in need of it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10863" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10864">Poor Griso! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10865" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10910">Busied all the day, busied half the night, without counting the danger of falling into the clutches of these villains, or drawing upon thy head a reward *for the rape of an honest woman,* to add to those which are already set upon thee,—and to be received in this manner? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10911" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10916">But, alas! it is only too often that the world thus repays good services. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10917" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10943">But thou, however, hast been able to see, in this instance, that sometimes justice, if not at first, arrives sooner or later, even in this world. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10944" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10962">Go to sleep for the present; a day will come when thou, perhaps, wilt have to give another proof of thy attachment and prowess,—a proof even still more remarkable than the one thou hast just given. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10963" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10977">The following morning, when his master arose, Griso was already busied in fresh affairs. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10978" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_10999">Don Rodrigo went immediately in search of the Count Attilio, and the Count, seeing him appear, assumed an air of raillery, and cried, "San Martino!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="11">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11000" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11021">"I do not know what to say," replied Don Rodrigo, approaching him; "I will pay the wager, but it is not this that troubles me the most. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11022" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11033">I have told you nothing, because I had thought of giving you a little surprise this morning. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11034" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11039">But enough—I will now tell you all." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="12">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11040" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11068">"The Friar has had a hand in this affair," said the cousin, after listening to the recital with more gravity than one would have expected from such a giddy brain. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11069" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11093">"The Friar," he continued, "with his innocent face, and his silly maxims, I hold to be an old hypocrite and an old rogue. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11094" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11135">And you have never confided in me, never told me clearly about what he came bothering you the other day!" — Don Rodrigo here related the conversation. — "And you had all this patience!" exclaimed Attilio; "and you have let him depart as freely as he came?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="13">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11136" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11145">"How! would you have me draw down upon myself the wrath of all the Capuchins in Italy?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="14">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11146" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11185">"I do not know," said the Count, "whether in this moment I should have recollected that there were other Capuchins in the world, than this daring rascal; but come,—following the rules of prudence, are the means wanting by which you can demand satisfaction from a Capuchin's arm? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11186" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11209">You have only at the proper time to redouble your attentions towards the whole body, and then you can with impunity chastise one of its members. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11210" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11239">But enough,—he has" escaped a punishment which he so well merited, but I will take him under my protection, and have the pleasure of teaching him how to speak to such as me." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="15">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11240" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11243">"Do not make matters worse." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11244" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11254">"Confide for once in me, I will serve you both as a relation and a friend." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11255" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11258">"What do you think of doing?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11259" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11270">"I do not yet know; but most assuredly I shall pay the Friar. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11271" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11288">I will think about it,—and—the Signor Uncle of the Secret Council is the man who must render me this service. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11289" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11292">Dear Signor Uncle! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11293" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11309">How much I amuse myself whenever I make a politician of this class work for me! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11310" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11325">The day after to-morrow I shall be in Milan, and in one way or another the Friar shall be dealt with as he deserves." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="16">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11326" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11339">The breakfast here made its appearance, but did not interrupt the discussion of so important an affair. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11340" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11389">The Count Attilio spoke with vivacity, although he took the side which his friendship for his cousin and their common honour demanded; according, at least, to his idea of honour and friendship, he could not prevent himself from laughing at the misadventure of his relation and friend. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11390" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11423">But Don Rodrigo, who discussed his own cause, and who, thinking of quietly gaining an important point, had failed most signally, was agitated by more serious passions, and occupied with more vexatious thoughts. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="17">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11424" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11434">"These fellows," said he, "will gossip finely in the neighbourhood. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11435" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11437">But what does that matter to me? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11438" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11473">As to the law, I laugh at it. There are no proofs, and even were there, I should equally scorn them. I have intimated this morning to the Consul that he shall take good care and not make his deposition regarding this event. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11474" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11495">Nothing disagreeable to me will result from the affair; but such gossiping, when it continues, annoys me; it is already too much to have been so barbarously joked with. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="18">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11496" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11543">"You have done extremely well," replied the Count Attilio; "your Podestà—your brutal—your wearisome—your foolish Podestà—is a gentleman—a man who knows his duty, and when one has to do with such a person, it is necessary to use a deal of caution to prevent him getting into difficulty. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11544" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11561">If a rogue of a Consul makes a deposition, the Podestà, however well inclined he may be, is obliged——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="19">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11562" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11590">"But you," interrupted Don Rodrigo, with a little anger, "you spoil my affairs by your foolish habit of contradicting him in everything, and ridiculing him upon every occasion. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11591" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11607">Diavolo! why may not a Podestà be stupid and obstinate, if for the rest he is a worthy man." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="20">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11608" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11626">"Do you know, cousin," said the Count Attilio, "do you know I begin to think you are a little afraid? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11627" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11633">You treat as serious even the Podestà——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="21">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11634" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11645">"Come, come, have not you yourself said that it is necessary to pay attention to this?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="22">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11646" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11662">"I have; and when an affair of importance is at stake, I will let you see that I am no child. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11663" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11671">Do you know what I will do for you? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11672" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11683">I am the man to go in person and pay the Podestà a visit. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11684" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11687">Ah! will he not be charmed with this honour? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11688" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11718">I am the man to let him talk of the Count-Duke and the Spanish Castellan by the half-hour, and let him always be right, should he even say the most extravagant things in the world. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11719" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11740">I will throw in a word regarding my "uncle the Count of the Secret Council, and you know what effect these words will produce in the ears of a Podestà. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11741" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11756">And then, after all, he really has more need of our protection than we of his condescension. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11757" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11770">I will do good: I will go there and leave him better disposed towards you than ever." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="23">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11771" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11806">After these and similar words, the Count Attilio went forth to the chase, and Don Rodrigo awaited with impatience the return of Griso, who at the hour of dinner at length arrived to make his relation. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="24">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11807" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11860">The tumult of the night had been so noisy, and the disappearance of these people from the little village was such a great event, that the inquiries, whether instigated by interest or curiosity, had been naturally many, warm, and incessant; and those informed of these things were by far too numerous to agree all to be silent. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11861" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11919">Perpetua could not shew herself at the door without being assailed by people to relate who it was that had caused her master this great fright; and Perpetua, considering all the circumstances, and seeing how she had been taken in by Agnese, felt such rage against her perfidy, that she was forced to relieve her mind. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11920" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11978">Not that she went and complained to people of the means employed to impose upon her — no, regarding this she did not breathe a word; but she could not entirely pass over in silence the trick played upon her poor master, and above all that this trick had been concerted and put in execution by this innocent girl, by the good young man, and by this excellent widow. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_11979" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12081">Don Abbondio might indeed command her resolutely, and pray her affectionately, to keep silent; she might indeed tell him that it was unnecessary to recommend to her a thing thus clear and natural,—but it is certain that so great a secret in the mind of this poor woman, was like new wine in an old and badly hooped cask, which works, ferments, and boils, and even if it does not send the bung into the air, trickles about, oozes out in froth, leaks between the staves, and drops here and there, so that any one may taste it, and tell pretty nearly what wine it is. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12082" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12132">Gervaso, who could scarcely believe it true, that for once he was better informed than other people, did not think it a slight honour to have experienced so great a fright; and who, having co‑operated in an affair which appeared criminal, seemed all at once to have become a man like the others, was ready to burst with his desire to boast of it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12133" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12171">But although Tonio, who thought seriously of the possible investigation and law‑suits, and of the account he had rendered, might command him, holding his clenched fist before his face, yet he could not stifle every word. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12172" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12218">And even Tonio himself, having been out of the house at an unusual hour, returning home with an unusual step and appearance, and suffering an agitation of mind which disposed him to sincerity, could not refrain from telling his wife, who also was not mute. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12219" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12269">The one who spoke the least was Menico, because scarcely had he recounted his history and the object of his expedition to his parents, than their son's having taken part in an attempt to frustrate any scheme of Don Rodrigo's seemed to them so terrible a thing that they would scarcely allow the child to finish his relation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12270" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12314">They then commanded him in the strongest and most menacing terms not to let fall the slightest hint; and the following morning, not believing themselves sufficiently secure, they resolved to keep him shut up in the house for that day, and perhaps for even longer. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12315" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12373">But what happened? They themselves gossiping with the villagers, even without wishing to appear better informed than they, when it came to the obscure point of the flight of our three poor friends, of the hour, and the wherefore, and whither,—they added, as a thing already well known, that they had taken refuge at Pescarenico; thus this circumstance also entered with the general discourse. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="25">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12374" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12414">With all these pieces of information joined together, and united as one is accustomed to do, and with the fringe which one naturally adds in the sewing, there was enough to make out a history of such certainty and clearness, that even the most critical intellect must have been satisfied. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12415" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12447">But this invasion of the bravoes, an event which was too grave, and had made too much noise to be forgotten, but of which no one had any positive knowledge, was the event of all others which rendered the whole history confused. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12448" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12467">The name of Don Rodrigo was murmured everywhere, about this name every one was of accord; the rest was all strange conjecture. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12468" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12499">A deal was spoken about the two great bravoes who had been seen in the street when evening closed in, and of the others who had stood at the entrance of the hostel; but what light could be gained from this meagre fact? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12500" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12537">They certainly questioned the host as to who had been at his house the preceding evening, but the host did not recollect whether he had seen any one that evening, and always ended by saying that an inn was like a sea-port. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12538" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12578">Above all, this pilgrim, seen by Stefano and Carlandrea, confounded them, and confused their conjectures; this pilgrim, whom the ruffians wanted to murder, who was gone off with them, or whom they had carried off,—what was he come to do? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12579" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12683">It was a soul escaped from purgatory to succour the two women—it was a damned soul—the soul of a scoundrel—of an imposter pilgrim which returned at night to unite itself to those who did such deeds as it had been accustomed to do when in the body,—it was a living and veritable pilgrim, whom these braves wished to murder, fearing lest he should cry out and alarm the whole village,—it was (only see what people will imagine!) one of these villains disguised as a pilgrim! It was this, it was that,—in short, it was so many things, that all the sagacity and experience of Griso would have been insufficient to have discovered who this really was, had Griso been obliged to learn this part of the history from the people's discourse. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12684" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12731">But, as the reader knows, what rendered it confused to others was precisely the most clear to him. Making use of this fact as a key to the other information gained by himself and by means of other inferior spies, he could on the whole make a sufficiently distinct relation to Don Rodrigo. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12732" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12775">He shut himself up immediately with his master, and informed him of the deed attempted by the two unfortunate betrothed, which naturally explained the empty cottage and the sound of the bell, without making it necessary to suppose traitors in the house, as these two gentlemen had imagined. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12776" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12809">He informed him of the flight, and even for this it was easy to find a reason; the fear of the two betrothed discovered in their enterprise, or some news of the invasion given when this became known and the village was in an uproar. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12810" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12824">He said, finally, that they had taken refuge at Pescarenico; farther than there his knowledge did not extend. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12825" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12852">It was agreeable to Don Rodrigo to be certain that no one had betrayed him, and to see that no traces remained of his deed; but this was only a fugitive and slight pleasure. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12853" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12860">"They have fled together!" he cried; "together!—And this rogue of a Friar—this Friar!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12861" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12886">These words issued hoarsely from his throat; he ground his teeth and bit his nails, whilst his whole aspect became as hideous as his passions. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12887" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12891">"This Friar shall pay for this! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12892" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12906">Griso—I know not who I am—I will know—I will find them—this very evening I will know where they are. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12907" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12909">I shall have no peace until then. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12910" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12927">To Pescarienico—quick—to know, to see, to find—four scudi immediately, and my protection for ever! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12928" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12932">This very evening I will know. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12933" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12937">And this rascal!—this Friar!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="26">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12938" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12965">Griso was again in the field; and in the evening of the same day was able to give his patron the desired information; and these are the means he employed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12966" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12987">One of the greatest pleasures of this life is friendship, and one of the greatest pleasures of friendship is having some one in whom to confide a secret. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_12988" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13018">Now friends are not divided into couples, like husbands and wives; every one generally speaking has more than one friend, and thus is formed a chain, of which no one has ever been able to discover the end. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13019" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13046">Therefore, when a friend procures himself this pleasure by depositing a secret in the bosom of another, he gives to this one the desire of procuring for himself in his turn the same pleasure. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13047" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13074">It is true that he beseeches him to say nothing of this to any one; but whoever should receive this condition in its most rigorous sense, would immediately cut short the course of this pleasure. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13075" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13102">But general practice has willed that he shall oblige himself only to confide it to a friend equally trustworthy, imposing upon him the same conditions. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13103" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13139">Thus from one confidential friend to another the secret rolls on and on by this immense chain, until at length it reaches the ears of him or her to whom the first who spoke intended it should never arrive. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13140" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13169">The secret would, however, generally remain a long time on the road, had every one only two friends; the one who confides it to him, and the one to whom he repeats it under condition of his silence. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13170" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13208">But there are privileged men who relate it to a hundred, and when the secret has reached one of these, its course becomes so rapid and multiplied, that one is unable to follow its track. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13209" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13319">Our author has never been able to ascertain by how many mouths the secret which Griso was ordered to discover had passed; the fact is, that the good man who had conducted the women to Monza, returning towards evening to Pescarenico with his cart, met by chance a confidential friend to whom he related in great confidence the good work which he had done, and its consequences; and Griso, upon his return to the palace two hours after, could inform Don Rodrigo, that Lucia and her mother were concealed in a convent at Monza, and that Renzo had pursued his way to Milan. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="27">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13320" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13341">Don Rodrigo experienced a wicked joy at hearing of this separation, and felt again rise within him something of the wicked hope of gaining his end. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13342" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13358">He reflected upon the means of attaining this a great part of the night, and rose the next morning with two designs—the one formed, the other merely imagined. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13359" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13384">The first was to send Griso immediately to Monza, there to obtain clearer information regarding Lucia, and to learn whether it were possible to attempt anything there. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13385" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13415">He, therefore, had Griso summoned, and placing the four scudi in his hand, praised him again for the ability with which he had gained them, and gave him the order he had just premeditated. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="28">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13416" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13420">"Signor----" said Griso, with hesitation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13421" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13426">"How! Have I not spoken clearly?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13427" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13432">"If you could only send some one else----" "How?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13433" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13463">"Illustrious Signor, I am ready to risk my life for my master,—it is my duty; but I know also that my master does not wish thus heedlessly to risk the lives of his subjects." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13464" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13464">"Well?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13465" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13512">"Your most illustrious lordship knows very well that a great price is set upon my head;—and—here I am under the protection of your lordship; we are a band; the Signor Podestà is a friend of the house; the constables treat me with respect, and I also—it is a thing which does one but little honour; but to live, quietly, I treat them as friends. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13513" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13552">In Milan, the livery of your lordship is known; but in Monza, it is I, on the contrary, who am known; and does your lordship know—I do not say this to boast of myself—that he who delivers me up to justice does a good deed? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13553" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13563">He receives a hundred scudi, and the permission to free two outlaws." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="29">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13564" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13601">"Diavolo!" exclaimed Don Rodrigo, "thou art like a yard-dog which has scarcely the courage to attack the legs of those who pass before the door, looking all the time behind him, whether the house"hold will support him, and never daring to move from the house." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="30">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13602" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13607">"I believe, Signor Padrone, that I have given proof that—" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="31">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13608" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13608">"Well?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="32">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13609" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13636">"Well!" replied Griso boldly, thus taken at his word, — "well, your lordship will not consider what I have spoken; lion's heart, and hare's legs, and I am ready to set forth." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="33">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13637" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13645">"I have not said that thou shouldst go alone. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13646" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13666">Take with thee a couple of the boldest men. Spegiato and Tira-dritto; be courageous, and be Griso. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13667" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13689">Who, thinkest thou, would not be glad to let three such faces as yours pass by quietly, when they are going about their own affairs. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13690" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13713">The constables of Monza must be very much wearied of life, if they would for a hundred scudi risk it in so perilous a game. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13714" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13737">And then, and then, — I do not believe I am so unknown there, that the quality of my servant counts for nothing." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="34">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13738" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13751">After having thus piqued Griso, he gave him more ample and particular instructions. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13752" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13864">Griso took with him his two companions, and departed with a bold and joyous air, cursing, however, in his heart, Monza, and the rewards, and the women, and the caprices of his master; he pursued his way like a wolf, which, driven on by famine, his sides shrunk in, and with ribs which might be counted, descends from the mountains where there is nothing but snow, advances with suspicion into the plain, and stops at every step with one paw raised, shaking his skinny tail, With raised snout, snuffing in the tainted air, to discover whether the wind bear to him the scent of man or steel, pricks up his sharp ears, and rolls his bloody eyes from which gleam at once the love of prey and terror of the chase. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="35">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13865" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13946">For the rest,—should any one desire to know whence cometh this beautiful verse,—it is taken from an unedited *diablerie* concerning the Crusades and the Lombards, which soon will no longer be unedited, and will make a fine noise. I have taken it, because it happened to come *à propos*; and I say this, in order not to make myself fine in the robes of another; let no one, however, think that this is a scheme of mine, to make known to the public that I and the author of this *diablerie* are like brothers, and that I grope among his manuscripts as much as it pleases me. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="36">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_13947" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14002">The other thing which concerned Don Rodrigo was to discover the means by which to prevent Renzo from returning to Lucia, or from setting foot again in his native village. And to promote this end, he contrived to spread reports of menaces and snares which had been lain for him, reports which reaching his ear, by means of some good friend, would take away his desire to return to those parts. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14003" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14032">He thought, however, the surest way would be to have him banished out of the state; but to succeed in this enterprise, he perceived that law would have been more able to serve him than violence. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14033" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14072">If he could only, for example, give a little colouring to the attempt made in the Curate's house, painting it is a seditious act, and by means of the Doctor Azzecca-Garbugli give the Podestà to understand that this was a sufficiently grave offence for him to issue against Renzo a good warrant of arrest. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14073" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14198">But he considered that it was not proper for him to meddle in this ugly business; and therefore he, without longer puzzling his brain, resolved to disclose his intentions to the Doctor Azzecca-Garbugli, should this be necessary, and thus make him comprehend his desire. "The edicts are many," thought he; "the Doctor is no goose; he will know how to find something for my case; he will know how to seek some quarrel with this fellow, otherwise I will change his name;" but (only see how things happen in this world!) whilst he thought of the Doctor, as the man the most able to serve him in this affair, another man, the man one should least have imagined, Renzo himself, so to say, was working with all his heart to serve Don Rodrigo, in a manner more certain and more speedy than any one which the Doctor would have been able to imagine. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="37">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14199" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14253">I have many a time seen a dear child who is more lively to confess the truth, than is necessary, but who, nevertheless, by every token, promises one day to become a clever man; I have seen him, very often, I say, very busy towards evening, endeavouring to drive home to their resting-place his troop of Guinea-pigs, which he allowed during the day to run about in a small garden. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14254" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14324">He would have liked them to enter their den altogether; but he fatigued himself in vain, one scampered off to the right, and whilst our little herdsman ran to drive him back to the troop, another, two, three, would run away in every direction, so that, at length, after growing somewhat impatient, he was forced to adapt himself to their humour, push in those which happened to be nearest, and afterwards the others, by ones, by twos, or by threes, as they might chance to be. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14325" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14355">We are obliged to play a similar game with our personages: having placed Lucia in safety, we ran to Don Rodrigo, and now we must leave him to follow Renzo, of whom we have lost sight. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="38">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14356" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14377">After the sorrowful separation, which we have related, Renzo travelled on from Monza to Milan in that state of mind which every one may easily imagine. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14378" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14409">To abandon his house, to leave his trade, and what was more than all the rest, to remove himself from Lucia, to travel along a strange road without knowing where to repose himself,—and all this on account of this scoundrel! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14410" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14494">When he touched in thought upon one or other of these things, he became possessed by rage and the desire for vengeance; but then he remembered the prayer which the good Friar had recited with him in the church of Pescarenico, and his thoughts amended themselves,—then his anger would again awaken, but seeing a saint painted upon the wall, he raised his hat, paused a moment, and prayed again; so that, during this journey, he had murdered Don Rodrigo in his heart, and brought him to life again, at least twenty times. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14495" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14531">The road was buried between two high banks—muddy, stony, ploughed up by deep ruts, which after rain became perfect brooks; and at certain places, where the road lay even still lower, it was entirely flooded, so that you might have gone over it in a boat. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14532" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14552">At such places a little steep path, after the manner of stairs, up the bank, would indicate that other pedestrians had made themselves a road in the fields. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14553" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14612">Renzo ascended by one of these paths to the higher ground, and saw the immense mass of the cathedral isolated in the plain, as though it rose not out of the heart of a city, but sprang up in a desert: he suddenly paused, forgetting all his woes, to contemplate thus from far this eighth wonder of the world, of which he had heard so much said from his earliest childhood. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14613" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14659">But after a few moments he turned round and saw those indented mountain summits, he saw distinctly his Resegone elevated, he felt his blood boil, he gazed sorrowfully in this direction, and then sorrowfully turned his back, and pursued his road. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14660" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14708">By little and little he began to distinguish the spires, towers, cupolas, and roofs; he descended again into the high road, and continued walking along it for some time, then, perceiving that he approached the city, he accosted a passer-by, and bowing as politely as he possibly could, said, "Will you be so good, sir——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="39">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14709" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14712">"What do you wish, my good youth?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="40">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14713" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14729">"Could you direct me the shortest road to the Capuchin monastery, where Father Bonaventura is?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="41">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14730" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14777">The man whom Renzo addressed was a rich inhabitant of one of the suburbs, who, having gone this morning to Milan about certain affairs, was returning home in great haste, without having transacted any of his business; and, fearing he should not arrive in time, he could very well have dispensed with this interruption. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14778" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14847">Spite, however, of this, without giving any sign of impatience, he replied very sweetly, "My dear sir, there is more than one monastery; you should tell me more clearly which is the one you seek." Renzo then drew from his bosom Father Cristoforo's letter, and showed it to the Signor, who, having read upon it "Porte Orientale," gave it back to him, saying, "You are fortunate, my good youth, the monastery you seek is but a short distance from here. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="42">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14848" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14882">Take this little path to the left, it is the shortest; in a few minutes you will reach the corner of a long low building, it is the lazzaretto, follow the ditch which surrounds it, and you will arrive at the Eastern-gate. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14883" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14903">Enter, and, after three or four hundred steps, you will see before you an open space in which grow some beautiful elm-trees; there is the monastery, you cannot mistake it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14904" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14919">"God be with you, my good youth!" and accompanying these last words with a graceful motion of the head, he took leave of Renzo. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="43">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14920" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14951">Renzo remained astonished and edified by the politeness of these citizens towards country-people; but he did not know that to-day was an extraordinary day, a day when the cloaks humbled themselves before the jackets. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14952" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14965">He followed the road which had been indicated to him, and soon found himself at the Eastern-gate. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14966" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14985">It is not, however, necessary that at this name, the reader should picture to himself the images which now are associated with it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_14986" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15014">When Renzo entered Milan by this gate, the road beyond it ran only in a straight line, the length of the lazzaretto, and then prolonged itself, winding and narrow, between two hedges. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15015" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15037">The gate itself consisted of two pillars, with a pent-house to shelter these two pillars, and on one side a small house for the custom-house officers. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15038" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15061">The bastions descended in an irregular descent, and the ground presented a rough and uneven surface, strewn with rubbish which had been thrown there. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15062" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15088">The road which opened itself before him, as he entered by this gate, was not very unlike that which now presents itself to those who enter by the Tosa-gate. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15089" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15117">A small ditch ran through the middle of the road to within a short distance of the gate, dividing it thus into two little paths covered with dust or mud, according to the season. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15118" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15135">At the spot where was, and still is, the lane called the Borghetto, the little ditch loses itself in a common-sewer. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15136" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15167">Here stood a column with a cross upon it, called the column of San-Dionigi; on the right and left were gardens surrounded by hedges, and, at intervals, little houses, mostly inhabited by washerwomen. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15168" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15212">Renzo entered the gate, and passed on, not one of the custom-house officers took notice of him,—a circumstance which seemed to him very strange, since he had heard such of his countrymen, who could boast of having been at Milan, relate extraordinary things of the searching and questioning which those who arrived from the country were subjected to. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15213" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15237">The street was deserted, and had it not been for a distant hum which indicated some great movement, it would have appeared to him an uninhabited city. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15238" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15272">He went on, not knowing what to think of all this, and saw upon the earth certain banks, white and soft, like snow, but snow it could not be, since snow does not fall in straight lines, nor generally at this season. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15273" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15304">He stoops down, looks at, and touches it, and finds that it is—flour! "There must, indeed, be a great abundance at Milan," said he to himself, "if they can thus squander away the gifts of God. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15305" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15315">They, nevertheless, give it out that the famine is everywhere. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n189" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15316" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15375">Only see what they say to keep the poor quiet, down in the country!" But after taking a few more steps, he arrived at the column, and saw at its base something still stranger; he saw upon the steps of the pedestal certain things scattered about, which certainly were not stones, and which, had they been in a baker's-shop, he would not have hesitated a moment to have called bread. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n190" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15376" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15464">But Renzo did not dare thus readily to believe his eyes, because, good heaven! this was not the place for bread. "Let us see what all this is," said he to himself; he went towards the column, stooped down, took up one of these things, and it was truly a little cake of bread, round and very white, of that kind which Renzo was only accustomed to eat on holidays. "Is it really bread!" he exclaimed aloud, so great was his astonishment. "Is it thus they sow this year? and in this country? and do they not even take the trouble to pick them up when they fall? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n191" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15465" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15513">This must be the country of Green Ginger!" After a journey of ten miles in the morning air, this bread, together with his astonishment, awoke his appetite. "Shall I take it?" he deliberated with himself; "pooh! they have left it here to the discretion of dogs, it is equally good that a Christian should enjoy it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n192" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15514" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15563">After all, if the master comes I will pay him." Thus thinking, he put into one pocket the cake he had in his hand, took a second and put it into the other, a third and began to eat, pursuing his way more uncertain than ever, and desiring to understand what all this might be. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n193" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15564" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15581">Scarcely had he taken two steps, before he saw people approach from the city, and he gazed most attentively at those who first made their appearance. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n194" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15582" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15611">There were a man and a woman, and rather behind them a little boy; all three bore loads upon their backs, which seemed beyond their strength, and all three presented a strange sight. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n195" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15612" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15644">Their clothes, or rather their rags, were covered with flour, their countenances also covered with flour, distorted and inflamed, they moved along, not only bent down by the weight, but also as though they were in pain, as though their bones had been bruised. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n196" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15645" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15672">The man carried upon his shoulders, with great difficulty, a sack of flour, which, pierced with holes here and there, sowed some of its contents on the ground each time he met with any obstacle in his way, and at each false step that he took. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n197" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15673" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15716">But still more singular was the figure of the woman; a huge fat body, which two extended arms seemed with difficulty to sustain, resembled a large earthen pot with two handles; and below this huge body issued forth two legs, naked to the knees, which came along staggering. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n198" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15717" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15759">Renzo regarded her attentively, and perceived that this huge body was formed by her petticoat which the woman held up by the hem, within which petticoat was placed as much flour as it could contain, and even rather more, so that at each step she took she was enveloped in a white cloud. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n199" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15760" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15807">The little boy supported with his hands upon his head a basket heaped up with bread, but he, having shorter legs than his parents, remained a little behind, and hastening his pace to rejoin them, the basket lost its balance, and some of the bread fell out. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="44">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n200" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15808" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15826">"Only throw away another, good-for-nothing that thou art!" said the mother grinning at him. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="45">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n201" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15827" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15839">"I do not throw them away, they fall of themselves. What am I to do?" he replied. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="46">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n202" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15840" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15888">"Ah! it's well for thee that I have my hands full," replied the woman, agitating her fists as though she were giving the poor boy a good shaking; and by this movement, making more flour fly away than would have been enough to make the two cakes which the little boy had let fall. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="47">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n203" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15889" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15900">"Come, come," said the man, "let us turn back and pick them up, or some one else will get them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n204" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15901" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15915">"We have been in want long enough. Now that we have a little abundance, let us enjoy it in holy peace." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="48">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n205" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15916" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15938">In the meantime other people arrived from the gate, and one of them going up to the woman, asked, "where are they now going to seize bread?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="49">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n206" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15939" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15970">"On, on!" she replied; and then, after they had proceeded some ten paces, she added, grumbling, "these villanous peasants will come and pillage all the bakehouses and shops, and then nothing will remain for us." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="50">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n207" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15971" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15982">"A little for each one, torment that thou art," said the husband. "Abundance! abundance!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="51">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n208" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_15983" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16027">From this, and many other things of the same kind, which he both heard and saw, Renzo concluded that he had arrived in a city which was in a state of insurrection, and that this was a day of victory,—that is to say, a day when each one pillaged in proportion to his will and his strength, giving blows as payment. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n209" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16028" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16055">Much as we desire our poor mountaineer to make a good figure; the sincerity of an historian obliges us to say that his first sentiment was that of pleasure. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n210" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16056" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16077">He found so little to praise in the ordinary course of things, that he felt inclined to approve of anything which should alter this course. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n211" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16078" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16136">And besides, not being a man superior to the age in which he lived, he also cherished the opinion, or rather the general prejudice, that this scarcity of bread was occasioned by the dealers and bakers; and he was disposed to find any means just, which should snatch out of their hands the food which they, according to this opinion, cruelly denied to the hunger of a whole people. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n212" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16137" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16161">However, he resolved to keep out of the tumult; rejoiced in being directed to a Capuchin who would find him an asylum, and be a father to him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n213" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16162" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16186">Thinking thus, and regarding attentively at the same time fresh conquerors who came along loaded with booty, he soon arrived at the monastery. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="52">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n214" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16187" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16221">In the place where now rises the beautiful palace with its high gallery was then situated, and even not many years ago might still be seen, a small square, and at the farthermost side stood the church and Capuchin monastery, with four large elms growing in front. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n215" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16222" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16256">We congratulate, not without envy, all those of our readers who have not seen things in the state we describe, since they must be very young, and have not yet had time to commit many follies. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n216" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16257" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16284">Renzo went straight to the door, put into his stomach the piece of bread which yet remained uneaten, drew out and held prepared in his hand the letter, and then pulled the bell. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n217" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16285" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16303">A very small door, with a grate in it, opened, and there appeared the face of the doorkeeper who demanded who he was. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="53">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n218" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16304" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16317">"One from the country, who brings an urgent letter for the Father Buonaventura, from the Father Cristoforo." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="54">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n219" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16318" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16327">"Give it here," said the doorkeeper, putting his hand to the grate. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="55">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n220" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16328" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16337">"No, no," said Renzo, "I must deliver it into his own hands." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="56">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n221" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16338" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16341">"He is not in the monastery." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="57">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n222" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16342" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16346">"Let me enter, and wait for him." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="58">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n223" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16347" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16372">"Follow my advice," replied the Friar; "go and wait for him in the church, so that in the meantime you may be doing some good; you cannot for the present enter the monastery." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n224" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16373" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16378">Having said this, he again closed the little door. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n225" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16379" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16387">Renzo remained outside with the letter in his hand. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n226" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16388" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16411">He made ten steps towards the door of the church, intending to follow the doorkeeper's counsel; but then he bethought him, he would first give another glance at the tumult. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n227" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16412" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16445">He crossed the square, folded his arms, and looked towards the interior of the city, where the stir was more busy and noisy. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n228" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16446" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16471">The whirlpool drew in the spectator. "Let us go and see," said he to himself; he again drew out another morsel of bread, and devouring it, moved on towards this direction. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap11-n229" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16472" targetEnd="quarantana/cap11.xml#c11_16489">Whilst he is thus walking along, we will relate, as briefly as possible, the causes and the beginning of these discontents. </note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>