<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CHAPTER XVI.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>1845</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed Lovers: a Milanese Story of the Seventeenth Century. With The Column of Infamy by Alessandro Manzoni. In Three Volumes</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
          <date>1845</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Henry Francis C. Logan</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="English_1845_cap16">
        <p n="1">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10022">"Escape, escape, honest man; here is a convent, there is a church! on this side, on that side!" was shouted to Renzo on all hands. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10023" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10032">This advice was not necessary, as far as escape was concerned. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n3" type="comm" status="insertion">From the first moment that the hope of freeing himself from these wretches' clutches had arisen in his mind, he had begun to form his plans, and determined, if successful, to fly, when once at liberty, not only the city, but the duchy. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10033" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10174">"Because," thought he, "they have my name written down in their cursed books, let them have come by it in what manner they may; and with my name and surname, they can come and seize me whenever they like." And as to an asylum, he would not have taken refuge there, unless he had had the constables on his heels. "Because," thought he to himself, "if I can be a bird of the forest, I will not be a bird of the cage." Therefore he had chosen, as his place of refuge, that part of the territory of Bergamo where his cousin Bortolo was established, who, if you remember, had already invited him so often to go there. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10175" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10182">But how to find the way, that was the difficult point. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10183" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10215">Left in an unknown quarter of a city, with which he might be said to be entirely unacquainted, Renzo did not even know by what gate to depart, in order to proceed to Bergamo; and even had he known this, he would not have known how to get to this gate. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10216" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10310">For one moment he thought of inquiring his road from one of his liberators; yet, in the short time left him to meditate upon his affairs, certain ideas had passed through his mind regarding this very obliging sword-cutler—the father of four children—and with very good reason he did not wish to make known his designs to so large a company, among which there might happen to be another friend of the same stamp; and therefore he immediately resolved to depart with all speed, and to inquire his road in some place where no one would know him, or know wherefore he made this inquiry. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10311" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10348">He said to his liberators, "many thanks, my good fellows—blessings on you!" and passed on through the opening which was immediately made for him, took to his heels, and away—down an alley, now through a little street, rushing on for some time without knowing where. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10349" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10385">When it seemed to him he was sufficiently removed, he slackened his pace, so as not to excite suspicion, and began looking here and there to choose some one from whom to procure the information he required, some countenance which should inspire him with confidence. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10386" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10390">But even here there was a difficulty. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10391" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10448">The question in itself was suspicious, time pressed; the constables recovered from this little misadventure would doubtless again be on the track of their fugitive; the report of his flight might already have arrived here; and in this multitude, Renzo might perhaps pass ten judgments founded on physiognomy, before finding the countenance that suited him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10449" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10521">This great fat man who stood upon the threshold of his shop, with his legs apart, his hands behind him, with his large corporation in front, with his chin in the air, from which hung a large double-chin, and who, having nothing else to do, alternately raised his large trembling mass upon the points of his toes, and let it fall again upon his heels, had the countenance of a curious talkative fellow, who, instead of giving replies, would have asked questions. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10522" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10550">The other, who came forward with his eyes fixed and his lips open, far from being able to direct a stranger well and quickly, seemed scarcely to know his own road. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10551" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10587">The little lad who, to speak the truth, looked marvellously wide awake, looked still more malicious, and probably would have had a foolish delight in sending a poor countryman in the very opposite direction to the one he desired. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10588" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10599">So true is it that to an embarrassed man every thing is a fresh embarrassment. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10600" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10648">He at length saw one who came along in haste, and thinking that this person, having probably some pressing affair on hand, would answer him quickly and without more ado, and hearing him talk to himself he imagined he must be a sincere openhearted man, he accosted him, saying, "pray sir, which direction must one take to reach Bergamo?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="2">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10649" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10655">"To reach Bergamo? through the Eastern-gate." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="3">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10656" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10663">"Many thanks; and to arrive at the Eastern-gate?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="4">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10664" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10675">"Take the street to the left, you will find yourself in the Cathedral-square, then—" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="5">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10676" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10681">"Enough, sir; I know the rest. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10682" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10685">God reward you!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="6">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10686" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10695">And he hastened on in the direction which had been indicated to him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10696" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10880">The other looked after him a moment,—and combining in his mind this manner of departure with the question, he said to himself, "Either he has done an evil deed, or some one will do evil to him." Renzo reached the Cathedral-square; he crossed it, passed by a heap of cinders and extinguished coals, and recognised the remains of the bonfire which he had witnessed the day before; he passed along the flight of steps of the cathedral, saw again the bake-house of "the Crutches," half demolished and guarded by soldiers, and hurried on right through the street up which he had come with the mob; arrived at the Capuchin's convent, he cast a glance at the little square and at the door of the church, and said to himself, "that Friar, however, gave me yesterday a very good piece of advice; telling me to stay and wait in the church, and thus do a little good." Here, having stopped a moment to observe attentively the gate by which he should issue forth, and seeing there, thus from afar, many people guarding it, and having his imagination somewhat heated (one must pardon him—he had reasons), he felt a certain repugnance to encounter this gateway. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="7">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10881" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10900">Finding thus at hand an asylum, where, with his letter, he would be so well received, he was strongly tempted to enter. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10901" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10913">But suddenly recovering courage, he thought, "Bird of the forest, as long as is possible. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10914" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10916">Who knows me? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10917" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10956">The constables will not have cut themselves into pieces to go and watch for me at all the gates." He turned round to see whether any one was coming from that side; but he saw no one who appeared to occupy himself about him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10957" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10979">He went forward, making those good legs, which would always be running when they should only be walking, move slower, and very quietly, whistling in a low voice, he arrived at the gate. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="8">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10980" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11065">There happened to be, precisely in the gateway, a number of custom-house officers, and, as a reinforcement, a company of Spanish soldiers; but they were all occupied in guarding the farthermost side of the gate, so as to prevent the entrance of those who, hearing of a commotion, should hasten to the city, like ravens to the field of battle; thus Renzo, with an indifferent air, with his eyes cast down, and with a gait between that of a traveller and of one who merely takes a walk, stepped forth without any one accosting him; but inwardly his heart beat violently. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11066" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11087">Seeing to the right a narrow path, he entered it, so as to avoid the principal road; and proceeded some way before he even turned round. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="9">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11088" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11113">He travelled on and on; he came upon hamlets and upon villages, he passed by them without asking their names; and certain of removing himself from Milan, he hoped to approach Bergamo; this sufficed for the time being. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11114" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11144">Sometimes he turned round; sometimes he looked at and rubbed, now one wrist, now the other, for they were still somewhat benumbed, and round them might be seen a red line, the mark of the little cord. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11145" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11194">His thoughts were, as every one can imagine, a mixture of penitence, of disquiet, of rage, of tenderness; his was a fatiguing study, the endeavouring to comprehend the things said and done the evening before, to discover the secret cause of his miserable fate, and above all, to imagine how they had been able to know his name. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11195" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11208">His suspicion fell naturally upon the sword-cutler, with whom he remembered to have spoken rather freely. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11209" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11242">And recollecting in what manner the man had secretly pumped him, his whole behaviour, all his offers, which ended ever in a desire to learn something, his suspicion became almost a certainty. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11243" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11289">He had also a confused remembrance of having continued to chat, after the departure of the sword-cutler; but with whom? guess, if thou canst, grasshopper, about what? His memory, much as he might question her, could not inform him; she could only say, that at that time she was not at home. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11290" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11335">The poor fellow lost himself in this vain search; he was like a man who, having given many a carte-blanche to a man whom he considered the very flower of honour, discovers that he is a cheat, and desires to know the state of his affairs; to know what? That all is a chaos. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11336" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11359">Another painful study of his was to form some design for the future which should please him; those which were not formed of air were all melancholy. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="10">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11360" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11372">But soon the most difficult thing was to find the road. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11373" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11390">After travelling on some time, one might say, as chance directed, he saw that by himself he could not again find the right track. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11391" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11419">He felt however a certain reluctance to pronounce the name of Bergamo, as though this name had something suspicious and strange about it; but nothing else was to be done. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11420" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11441">He resolved therefore to address himself to the first traveller he met whose physiognomy pleased him; and this he did. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="11">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11442" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11469">"You are out of the track," replied the traveller; and then thinking a short time, partly by words, partly by signs, he indicated to him the course which he must pursue in order to reach the high road. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11470" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11523">Renzo thanking him, did as though he would follow his advice, and really took this direction, intending to approach the road, not to lose sight of it, and travel on by its side as long as was possible, without however setting foot in it; but this design was easier to conceive than to put into execution. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11524" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11603">The end was that, proceeding thus from right to left, in a zig-zag manner, following in part the indications which he had received on the way, in part correcting them according to his own ideas and adapting them to his own purpose, and also allowing himself to be guided by the road upon which he found himself, our fugitive had walked perhaps twelve miles when he was not distant more than six from Milan; and as to Bergamo, it was well if he had not moved farther away from it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11604" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11623">He began to comprehend that going on after this manner he should never succeed, and resolved to find out some other expedient. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11624" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11681">The one which occurred to him was to discover through his sagacity the name of some neighbouring village, on the frontiers, at which he might arrive by cross-roads, and inquiring after this place he would thus have the road directed without sowing here and there this terrible name of Bergamo, which seemed to him to speak of flight, expulsion, and of some criminal deed. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="12">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11682" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11704">Whilst he sought the means by which to gain all this information without causing suspicion, he saw a bough hanging before the door of a small house which stood solitary in the outskirts of a village. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11705" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11732">For some time he had felt the necessity of recruiting his strength increase; he thought this would be the place in which to serve himself in both ways, and entered. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11733" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11747">Here was only an old woman, with her distaff at her side and spindle in her hand. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11748" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11794">He asked for something to eat; a little *stracchino* and some good wine were offered him; he accepted the *stracchino*, but refused the wine (wine had become hateful to him on account of the joke it had played him the night before); seated himself, and besought the woman to be as quick as she could. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11795" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11830">She had prepared the table in a moment, and immediately began to storm her guest with questions about himself, and the great events which had taken place at Milan, for the report had reached thus far. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11831" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11860">Renzo not only knew how to elude these demands with the greatest dexterity, but, profiting by this difficulty, he turned to his own advantage the old woman's curiosity, when she asked him where he was going to. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="13">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11861" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11908">"I have to go to many places," he replied; "and if I find a moment, I should like to stop a short time in that rather considerable village on the road to Bergamo, near the frontier, in the Milanese territory; however—how is it called?"—There will certainly be some such one, thought he to himself. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="14">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11909" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11914">"Gorgonzola, you would say," replied the old woman. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="15">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11915" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11925">"Gorgonzola," repeated Renzo, so as to fix the name better in his memory. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11926" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11932">"Is it far from here?" he continued. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="16">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11933" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11941">"I do not precisely know; perhaps ten, perhaps twelve miles. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11942" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11952">If one of my sons were here he could tell you." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="17">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11953" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11974">"And do you think one could go there by these pleasant little by-paths, without taking the high-road? There is such dust, such terrible dust! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11975" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11979">It is such a long time that we have had no rain!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="18">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11980" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11995">"It seems to me you could; you will be able to ask in the first village you come to on the right." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11996" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11998">And she named this village to him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11999" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12041">"That is good," said Renzo, rising and taking a piece of bread which had remained over from this meagre repast, a piece of bread very different from the one he had found the day before lying at the foot of the cross of San Dionigi; he paid his bill, went out, directing his course to the right. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12042" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12066">And not to lengthen our recital more than is necessary, with this name of Gorgonzola on his lips, he travelled on from village to village, and at length arrived about an hour after sunset. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="19">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12067" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12084">Whilst travelling on he had formed the design of making at Gorgonzola a little halt, and a somewhat more substantial repast. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12085" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12106">His body would have approved of a bed, but sooner than gratify it in this desire, Renzo would have let it fall dead upon the road. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12107" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12135">His intention was to inform himself at the hostel of the distance of the Adda, to extract cleverly the knowledge by what by-road he could most easily reach it, and to take this route as soon as he should have refreshed himself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12136" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12194">Born and brought up at the second source, so to say, of this river, he had heard it said more than once, that at a certain point and for a certain distance its current marked the confines of the Milanese and Venetian states; of this point and of this distance he had no precise idea, but for the present the most important affair was to cross it wherever it might happen to be. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12195" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12232">If he should not succeed this day, he was resolved to journey on, as long as the light and his strength would permit him, and then to await the dawn in a field, in a wilderness, or wherever it should please God to place him, provided there were no hostel. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="20">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12233" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12270">Having taken a few steps in Gorgonzola, he saw a sign, he entered the hostel, and of the host who came towards him he demanded a mouthful of something to eat and a measure of wine; a few more miles and time had caused this extreme and fanatical hatred of wine to pass away. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12271" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12284">"I pray you to make haste," he added, "for I am obliged to continue my journey immediately." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12285" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12322">And this he said not so much because it was the truth, as from fear that the host, imagining he wished to sleep there, should come and demand his name and his surname, from whence he came, and upon what business. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="21">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12323" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12347">The host replied that he should be served immediately, and our hero seated himself at the lower end of the table, near to the door; the place of the humble-minded. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="22">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12348" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12421">There were seated in this room some idlers of the village, who, after discussing and commenting upon the great news from Milan of the day before, tormented themselves in endeavouring to know how things had gone on this day, all the more industriously as the first news had been more likely to excite than to satisfy their curiosity; a sedition neither subdued nor victorious, suspended rather than terminated by the night, a thing imperfect, the end of an act, rather than of the drama. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12422" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12438">One of these detached himself from the company, approached the new-comer, and asked whether he came from Milan. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="23">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12439" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12447">"I?" said Renzo, surprised, thus taking time to reply. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="24">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12448" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12453">"You, if the question be lawful." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="25">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12454" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12489">Renzo, shaking his head, pressing his lips together, and making an inarticulate sound proceed from them, said, "Milan, from what I have heard say — must not be a place to go to at the present time, at least unless pressed by some great necessity." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="26">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12490" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12501">"Does the uproar then continue to-day?" demanded this curious fellow still more earnestly. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="27">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12502" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12508">"One must be there, to know that," said Renzo. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="28">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12509" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12514">"But do not you come from Milan?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="29">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12515" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12528">"I come from Liscate," replied the young man quickly, who in the meantime had considered his reply. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12529" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12569">In fact, in one sense, he did come from Liscate, as he had passed through it, and he had learned the name from a traveller who had pointed this village out to him as the first he must pass, in order to reach Gorgonzola. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="30">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12570" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12584">"Oh!" said this friend, as though he would say — you had done better to have come from Milan, — but patience. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12585" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12594">"And at Liscate, do they know nothing of Milan?" he added. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="31">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12595" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12612">"It is very possible that some one there may know something," replied the mountaineer; "but I have heard nothing." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="32">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12613" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12628">And these words he pronounced in that peculiar manner, which says, "I have ended." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12629" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12644">The man returned to his post, and a moment after came the host to lay the cloth. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="33">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12645" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12667">"How far is it from here to the Adda?" said Renzo, half between his teeth, with a drowsy air, which we have before seen him assume. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="34">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12668" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12672">"To the Adda—to cross over?" said the host. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="35">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12673" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12675">"That is—yes—to the Adda." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="36">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12676" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12686">"Do you wish to pass over the bridge of Cassano, or to cross in the boat at Canonica?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="37">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12687" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12693">"Wherever it be—I only ask from curiosity." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="38">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12694" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12713">"O! I tell you of these places, for they are where "honest people cross, people who can give an account of themselves." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="39">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12714" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12718">"Good; and where are they?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="40">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12719" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12735">"One may reckon, that to one and to the other, more or less, it is six miles." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="41">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12736" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12742">"Six miles! I did not think it was so much," said Renzo. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12743" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12768">"But if," he continued, with an air of indifference, which was even carried to affectation, "but if it were necessary to take a shorter cut, there are other places where one could cross?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="42">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12769" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12782">"Certainly," replied the host, fixing upon him two eyes full of malicious curiosity. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12783" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12796">This was sufficient to make the other questions the youth had prepared expire on his lips. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12797" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12819">He drew his plate before him, and regarding the measure of wine which the host had placed upon the table, he said, "The wine is pure?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="43">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12820" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12841">"As gold," said the host; "only ask all the inhabitants of the village and of the neighbourhood, who understand these things, and then you will hear." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12842" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12940">And saying this, he turned towards the company. "Cursed be all hosts!" exclaimed Renzo to himself; "the more I know of them, the worse I find them." Notwithstanding, he commenced eating with a good appetite, at the same time listening attentively, without, however, appearing to do so, in order to reconnoitre the land, to learn what was thought in this place of the great event in which he had played no small part, and especially to observe whether among these speakers there were one honest man from whom a poor lad might dare to inquire his road, without the fear of being seized upon, and forced to gossip about his own affairs. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="44">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12941" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12954">"But!" said one, "it seems this time that the Milanese have wished to do some good. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12955" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12962">To-morrow, at farthest, something will be known." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="45">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12963" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12974">"I repent not going to Milan this morning," said another. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="46">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12975" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12988">"If thou wilt go to-morrow, I will go also," said a third, and then a fourth, and then a fifth. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="47">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12989" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13018">"What I should like to know," said another, "is, whether these gentlemen of Milan will think of the poor people in the country, or whether they will only have the laws made good for themselves. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13019" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13022">You know what they are. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13023" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13034">Proud citizens, they only think of themselves; they treat the country people as though they were not Christians." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="48">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13035" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13076">"We also have mouths, whether for eating or for letting them know our rights," said another, in a voice as modest as the proposal was daring; "and when the thing is in a fair way——" but he believed it best not to finish his speech. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="49">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13077" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13098">"It is not alone at Milan that there is concealed grain," commenced another, with a cunning and malicious air, when a horse was suddenly heard to approach. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13099" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13109">They all ran to the door, and recognising the one who arrived, they went towards him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13110" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13144">He was a merchant from Milan, who, going often to Bergamo on matters of trade, was accustomed to pass the night in this hostel; and thus almost always finding there the same company, he became acquainted with them all. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13145" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13155">They crowded round him; one seized the bridle, another the stirrup. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13156" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13159">"Welcome! welcome!" they cried. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="50">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13160" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13161">"Happy to meet you." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="51">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13162" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13165">"Have you had a good journey?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="52">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13166" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13171">"Very good; and you, how have you been?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13172" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13173">"Well, very well. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13174" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13179">What news do you bring us from Milan?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="53">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13180" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13197">"Ah, here is news!" said the merchant dismounting, and leaving his horse with a boy. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13198" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13214">"But then," he continued, entering the house with the rest of the company, "by this time you will perhaps know it better than I." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="54">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13215" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13226">"Really, we know nothing," said more than one, laying his hand upon his breast. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="55">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13227" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13238">"Is it possible?" said the merchant; "then you shall hear good, or rather bad, news. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13239" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13247">Eh, host! is my customary bed at liberty?—Good. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13248" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13276">A glass of wine, and my customary mouthful, quick; for I want to go early to bed, so as to depart early to-morrow, and arrive at Bergamo for dinner-time. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13277" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13304">'And you,' he continued, seating himself at the place opposite to where Renzo sat, silent and attentive, 'and you know nothing of all the devilish business of yesterday?' </note>
        </p>
        <p n="56">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13305" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13307">"O—yesterday—yes!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="57">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13308" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13317">"You see then," replied the merchant, "you know the news. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13318" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13331">I said that being here always on the watch, to seize upon those who pass——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="58">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13332" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13336">"But to-day, how has it gone on to-day?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="59">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13337" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13338">"Ah, to-day! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13339" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13342">Do you nothing of to-day?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="60">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13343" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13348">"Entirely nothing; no one has passed." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="61">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13349" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13360">"Then let me moisten my lips, and I will tell you about to-day." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13361" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13403">He filled his glass, took it in one hand, then with two fingers of the other raised his moustache, then smoothed his beard, drank, and continued; "to-day, my dear friends, little has been wanting to make this as stormy a day as yesterday, and even worse. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13404" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13434">And it scarcely appears to me real that I am here gossiping with you; because I had given up all thoughts of travelling, and intended to remain at home to watch over my poor shop. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="62">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13435" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13441">"What was then the matter?" said one of the listeners. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="63">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13442" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13462">"A great matter, you shall hear;" and cutting the meat which had been placed before him, and then eating, he continued his relation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13463" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13502">The guests, standing on the right and left of the table, listened open-mouthed; Renzo at his post, slowly chewing his last mouthful, without its seeming to be his affair, was more attentive, perhaps, than all the rest. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="64">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13503" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13563">"This morning, when the rogues who had made all the horrible uproar yesterday, were at the various posts agreed upon, for there was a general understanding—every thing was prepared; they united and recommenced this fine running from street to street, shouting, so as to draw together other people—you know that with these people, it is as when you sweep a house (speaking with all due respect), the heap of dirt increases the farther you advance. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13564" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13598">When it appeared to them that there were people sufficient, they proceeded towards the Superintendent's house; as though they had not yesterday committed acts of oppression enough. And towards a Signor such as he too! O what villains! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13599" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13606">And the injurious things they said against him! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13607" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13632">All inventions! He is an excellent Signor, and very punctual; and I can say this, I who know all his affairs, and I serve him with cloth for his servants' livery. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13633" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13663">They proceeded then towards this house; you should have seen this mob—these faces! Imagine only, they have passed before my shop; faces that—— the Jews of the *Via Crucis* are nothing to them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13664" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13686">And the things that issued from their lips! One must have stopped one's ears, had one not been forced carefully to avoid observation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13687" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13717">They went with the full intention of plundering; but —" And here, raising and stretching forth his left hand, he placed the end of his finger to the point of his nose. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="65">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13718" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13723">"But?" said almost all the listeners. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="66">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13724" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13754">"But," continued the merchant, "they found the street closed up with beams and carts, and behind this barricade a beautiful file of musketeers, with their arquebuses, prepared to receive them as they deserved. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13755" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13763">When they saw this beautiful preparation — What would you have done?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="67">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13764" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13765">"Turned back." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="68">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13766" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13769">"Certainly, and this is what they did. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13770" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13781">But only see whether it was not the devil who conducted them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13782" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13864">They are in the Cordusio — they see there the bake-house which they desired to plunder yesterday; and what is done in this shop? Bread is distributed to the customers; and nobles, the very flower of the nobility, are there to see that all goes on properly; but these wretches — they had the devil behind them I tell you, and he set them on — these wretches enter like madmen: 'if thou wilt seize on the bread, I will seize on it also;' in the twinkling of an eye, nobles, bakers, purchasers, bread, counter, benches, troughs, boxes, sacks, bolters, bran, flour, dough, all were topsy-turvy." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="69">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13865" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13867">"And the musketeers?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="70">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13868" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13884">"The musketeers had to guard the Superintendent's house; one cannot sing and bear the cross. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13885" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13902">This happened in the twinkling of an eye, I tell you; pillage, pillage; all that was good for anything was taken. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13903" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13923">And then was again proposed the beautiful invention of yesterday, the carrying the remainder to the square and making a bonfire of it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13924" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13947">And already the wretches had begun dragging away all the goods, when one, a greater wretch than the other, proposed — only guess what he proposed?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="71">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13948" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13950">"What?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="72">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13951" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13968">"To make a pile of every thing in the shop, and to set fire to the pile and the house at once. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13969" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13970">No sooner was the thing said than done—" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="73">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13971" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13974">"They have set fire to it?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="74">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13975" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13975">"Wait a little. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13976" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13983">An honest man of the neighbourhood was inspired by heaven. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13984" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14018">He flies up stairs, he seeks a crucifix, he finds one, he fastens it to the arch of a window; takes from a bed's-head two holy tapers, lights them, and places them one on each side of the crucifix. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14019" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14023">The people look up. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14024" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14076">One must say that in a Milanese there is yet left some fear of God; all retired; the greater part I would say, for there were some devils among them who, to rob, would have set fire to Paradise itself; but, seeing that the mob was not of their opinion, they were obliged to restrain themselves and remain quiet. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14077" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14152">Guess now, what arrived quite unexpectedly?—all the Monsignori of the cathedral in procession, the cross carried on high, dressed in sacerdotal robes; and Monsignor Mazenta, the arch-priest, began to preach on this side, and Monsignor Setalla, the Penitenziere, on the other side; and then others, here and there, addressed the mob after this fashion: "But, good people, what would you do? Is this an example to set your children? Return home. Do you not know that bread is cheap—cheaper than before? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n172" type="comm" status="insertion">But go and see, there is the notice pasted up on the corners." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14153" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14154">"Was this true?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="75">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14155" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14155">"The devil! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14156" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14169">Would you have Monsignori of the cathedral come in their grand robes to tell lies?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="76">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14170" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14174">"And what did the people do?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="77">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14175" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14192">"By little and little the mob dispersed; they ran to the corners of the street, and there, for those who could read, stood the list of prices. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14193" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14201">Only guess! a loaf of eight ounces for a penny!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="78">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14202" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14203">"What luck!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="79">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14204" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14211">"The vine is beautiful, provided that its fruitfulness continues. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14212" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14222">Do you know how much flour has been wasted yesterday and this morning? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14223" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14229">Enough to support the duchy for two months." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="80">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14230" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14240">"And has no good law been made for those who live out of Milan?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="81">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14241" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14252">"What has been done at Milan regards only the city itself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14253" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14265">I do not know what to say to you; for you, there will be what God gives you. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14266" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14272">The uproar has entirely ceased now. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14273" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14280">I have not told you all; now comes the good." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="82">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14281" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14283">"Is there yet something more?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="83">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n189" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14284" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14305">"It is this, that yesterday evening or this morning several of the ringleaders have been taken, and it was quickly known that the principal ones will be hanged. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n190" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14306" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14325">Hardly had this report begun to spread, than every one hastened home the nearest road, so as not to run the risk of being among the number. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n191" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14326" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14335">Milan, when I set out, resembled a convent of friars." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="84">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n192" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14336" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14338">"But will they really be hanged?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="85">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n193" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14339" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14344">"Certainly, and that quickly," replied the merchant. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="86">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n194" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14345" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14357">"And what will the people do?" demanded again he who had asked the former question. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n195" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14358" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14365">"The people! they will go and see them hanged," returned the merchant. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n196" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14366" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14386">"They are so fond of seeing a Christian die in the open air, that they wanted—the scoundrels—to kill the Superintendent! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n197" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14387" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14412">Instead of that they will now have four miserable creatures served up with all formality, accompanied by Capuchins and the brothers of the Good Death; and these are people who have deserved such a fate. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n198" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14413" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14420">This is a providential thing; you see it was a necessary thing. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n199" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14421" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14454">They had already begun to enter shops and help themselves; if this had been allowed to continue, after the bread would have come the turn of the wine, and so on. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n200" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14455" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14467">You can think, whether of their own accord they would have given up so convenient an usage. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n201" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14468" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14485">And I can tell you that for a worthy man who keeps open shop, this was no very agreeable thought." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="87">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n202" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14486" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14490">"Truly not," said one of his auditors. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n203" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14491" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14497">"Truly not," repeated the others with one voice. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="88">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n204" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14498" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14515">"And," continued the merchant, wiping his beard upon the cloth, "this had been prepared for a long time; there was a league, you know?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="89">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n205" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14516" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14518">"There was a league?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="90">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n206" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14519" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14521">"There was a league. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n207" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14522" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14558">This was all a cabal formed by the Navarrini, by this Cardinal of France you know, who has a half-Turkish name, and who every day forms some new plot to spite the Spanish crown. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n208" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14559" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14580">But he aims most especially at Milan, for he sees, the rogue, that there lies the king's greatest strength." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="91">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n209" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14581" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14581">"Really!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="92">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n210" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14582" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14585">"Should you like a proof? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n211" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14586" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14605">Those who have made the greatest disturbance were foreigners; there were countenances in the street, which had never been seen before in Milan. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n212" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14606" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14617">I have forgotten to tell you something which has been told me as a fact. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n213" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14618" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14624">The officers of justice had seized one in a public-house—— </note>
        </p>
        <p n="93">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n214" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14625" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14653">Renzo, who had not lost a syllable of this discourse, when this chord was touched, felt himself grow cold, and gave a shiver before he was able to think of restraining himself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n215" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14654" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14726">No one, however, noticed it; and the narrator, without breaking the thread of his relation, added: "It is not yet known from whence he came, by whom he was sent, neither what sort of a man he was; but certainly he was one of the chief ringleaders. Yesterday, in the midst of the uproar, he had played the devil; and then, not satisfied with this, he had set himself to propose a fine thing, that they should murder all the nobles. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n216" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14727" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14727">The rascal! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n217" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14728" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14738">How would the poor live, if the nobles were murdered? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n218" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14739" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14778">The officers of justice, who had watched him, laid hands upon him; they found on him a packet of letters, and they conducted him to prison; but what happened? His companions, who watched round the hostel, came in great numbers, and liberated him, the villain!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="94">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n219" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14779" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14782">"And what has become of him?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="95">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n220" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14783" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14836">"It is not known; he will have escaped or concealed himself in Milan! there are people who have neither house nor home, and who yet find everywhere lodging and concealment, so long as the devil can and will aid them; they fall, however, into the snare, when they least expect it; for when the pear is ripe, it must fall. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n221" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14837" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14867">It is known for certain that the letters have remained in the officers' hands, and that in them the whole of the cabal is described, and it is said that many persons will be compromised. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n222" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14868" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14882">The worse for them; they have wished to turn Milan topsy-turvy, and even worse. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n223" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14883" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14898">People say that the bakers are rogues, I know that myself, but they must be hanged according to justice. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n224" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14899" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14902">There is grain concealed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n225" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14903" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14906">Who does not know it? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n226" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14907" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14931">But it is for those who command to keep good spies, and go and disinter it, and send the dealers to dangle their heels in the air in company with the bakers. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n227" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14932" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14978">And if those who are in command do nothing, it is for the city to remonstrate; and if at first no attention is paid, remonstrate again; so that by much remonstrance they may obtain what they want, and not have recourse to such a rascally usage as that of entering shops and warehouses to plunder." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="96">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n228" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14979" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14988">The little that Renzo had eaten was turned to poison. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n229" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14989" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_15012">It seemed to him a thousand years before he should be out of the room, and at some distance from this inn and the village; and already more than ten times he had said to himself, "go, go." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n230" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_15013" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_15035">But the fear of causing suspicion now much increased, and become the tyrant of his thoughts, had held him fast on the bench. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n231" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_15036" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_15061">In this perplexity, he thought that this everlasting talker must certainly sometime finish speaking of him, and he determined to move off as soon as he should hear some other subject introduced. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="97">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n232" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_15062" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_15098">"And it is on this account," said one of the company, "that I, knowing the way these things go on, and that honest folk are not well off in these tumults, have not allowed myself to be conquered by my curiosity, and have remained at home." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="98">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n233" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_15099" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_15106">"And I? Have I stirred?" said another. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="99">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n234" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_15107" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_15130">"I," added a third, "had I by chance found myself at Milan, I should have left unfinished my affairs, and have returned immediately to my home. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n235" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_15131" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_15144">I have a wife and children, and to speak the truth, these uproars do not please me." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="100">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n236" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_15145" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_15166">At this point the host, who had placed himself to listen, went towards the other end of the table to see what the stranger was about. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap16-n237" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_15167" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_15213">Renzo seized the opportunity, he called the host to him by a sign, asked for his bill, paid it without cheapening, although his money was very low, and without farther discourse walked straight to the door, passed over the threshold, and under the guidance of Providence moved off in the opposite direction to that by which he had come. </note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>