<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CHAPTER XVIII.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>1845</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed Lovers: a Milanese Story of the Seventeenth Century. With The Column of Infamy by Alessandro Manzoni. In Three Volumes</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
          <date>1845</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Henry Francis C. Logan</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="English_1845_cap18">
        <p n="1">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10191">This same day, the 13th of November, there arrived a courier extraordinary at the house of the Signor Podestà of Lecco, who presented him with a despatch from the Signor Captain of the Police, containing orders to make every possible and necessary inquiry, whether a certain young man, named Lorenzo Tramaglino, a silk-weaver, who had escaped from the hands, *predicti egregii domini capitanei*, were returned, *palam vel clam*, to his village ignotum precisely which, *verum in territorio Leuci.* *Quod si compertum fuerit sic esse*, the Signor Podestà shall exert all his efforts, *quanta maxima diligentia fieri poterit*, to lay hold of him, and after having well bound him, *videlicet*, with good hand-cuffs, he shall have him conducted to prison, and there keep him under good and sure custody until he shall be consigned into the hands of those sent to fetch him, *accedatis ad domum predicti Laurentii Tramalini; et facta debita diligentia, quidquid ad rem repertum fuerit auferatis; et informationes de illius prava qualitate, vita, et complicibus sumatis;* and of all that shall have been done and said, found and not found, taken and left, *diligenter referatis.* </note>
        </p>
        <p n="3">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10192" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10229">The Signor Podestà, after having been assured by all human means that the subject of the despatch was not returned to his home, sends for the consul of the village, and is conducted by him, accompanied by a numerous train of notaries and constables, to the fugitive's house. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10230" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10244">The house is locked up, and the one who has the key is either not there, or does not let himself be found. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10245" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10264">The door is broken in, the usual careful search is made, that is to say the house is treated as though it were besieged. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10265" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10330">The report of this expedition immediately spreads itself throughout the neighbourhood, and soon reaches the ears of Father Cristoforo, who, astonished no less than afflicted, questions this person and that, in order to learn something of the cause of an event thus unexpected; but he only gathers wild conjectures, and immediately writes to Father Bonaventura, from whom he hopes to receive some more precise intelligence. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10331" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10365">Meanwhile the friends and relatives of Renzo are cited to depose all they know regarding his *prava qualitate*; to bear the name of Tramaglino is a misfortune, is a disgrace, a crime; the whole village is in a commotion. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10366" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10409">By degrees it begins to be known that Renzo has escaped from the officers of justice in the very heart of Milan, and then has disappeared; there are rumours that he has done something terrible, but people are not able to say what the thing is, or they relate it in a hundred ways. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10410" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10456">The less terrible it is, the less it is believed in the village where Renzo is known as a worthy young man. The greater number think and whisper into their neighbours' ear that this is only a machination of the oppressor Don Rodrigo to ruin his poor rival. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10457" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10479">So true it is, that judging by induction, and without the necessary knowledge of facts, one is sometimes liable to do even villains injustice. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="4">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10480" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10522">But we, who have the facts under our hand as one may say, can affirm that if this man had had no part in Renzo's misfortune, he took as much pleasure in it as though it had been one of his own works, and triumphed in it with his confidants, particularly with the Count Attilio. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10523" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10568">The latter, according to his first design, should already have found himself in Milan; but at the earliest news of the tumult, which reigned there, and of the mob which roamed through the streets, and which had assumed no very submissive attitude, he had thought it best to amuse himself in the country until all again should be quiet. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10569" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10605">More particularly, as having offended many individuals, he had reason to fear that among so many who, through impotence, had kept silence, some one might now take courage from the present circumstances, and judge the moment opportune for avenging the wrongs of all. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10606" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10643">This suspense, however, was not of long duration; the arrival of the order from Milan for the pursuit of Renzo indicated that already things had returned to their ordinary course; and almost at the same time more positive certainty was obtained. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="5">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10644" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10683">The Count Attilio departed immediately, encouraging his cousin to persist in the enterprise, and overcome every obstacle; promising him at the same time, that on his own account he would speedily lend a hand to free him of the friar; in which project the fortunate accident of the rival being so despicable would make it an admirable joke. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10684" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10778">Attilio had scarcely departed when Griso arrived safe and sound from Monza, and reported to his master all he had been able to collect there; that Lucia had been received into a certain convent under the protection of a certain Signora, that she always remained concealed there as though she herself were a nun, never setting a foot beyond the door, and that she assisted at the ceremonies of the church behind a little grated window; a circumstance which displeased many people, who having heard speak of her adventures, and of the beauty of her countenance, would like to have seen a little how this same countenance was formed. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="6">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10779" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10801">These relations put the devil into Don Rodrigo, or more correctly speaking, rendered still worse the one which was already at home within him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10802" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10830">Many circumstances favourable to his design inflamed still more his passion, that is, the mixture of pique, rage, and infamous desire of which his passion was composed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10831" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10916">Renzo was absent, outlawed, banished; every thing might be permitted towards him, and even his betrothed might be considered as the property of a rebel; the only man in the world who could and would interest himself in his behalf, and make noise enough to be heard far off and by people in power, this mad Friar, would probably soon be no longer in a condition to injure any one; and behold, a new impediment arises, which not only counterbalances all these advantages, but renders them, so to say, useless. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10917" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10965">A convent at Monza, even had no Princess resided in it, was too hard a bone for Don Rodrigo's teeth; and however much he might rove round this asylum in imagination, he could devise neither way nor means of violating it, either by strength or artifice. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10966" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11010">He was almost inclined to abandon his enterprise; he had resolved to go to Milan, making a detour in order to avoid passing through Monza, and in Milan, in the midst of his friends, deliver himself up to amuse ment, and thus endeavour to drive away, by gaiety, this thought, which was ever becoming a greater torment. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11011" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11021">But—these friends! He must go gently to work with these friends. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11022" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11047">Instead of a distraction from sad thoughts, he might expect fresh vexations in their society; for already, doubtless, Attilio would have blown his trumpet, and all would be full of expectation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11048" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11059">On all sides he would be questioned regarding this mountain maiden; he should be obliged to reply. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11060" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11066">He wished, and he attempted, what had he obtained? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11067" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11100">He had made a resolve, a somewhat ignoble resolve, it is true; but no one can always regulate his desires; the point is to satisfy them; and how should he extricate himself from his embarrassments? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11101" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11109">Surrender to a villain, to a friar? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11110" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11147">Uh! and this too precisely when an unexpected good fortune has delivered him, without the slightest exertion on his part, from one difficulty, and a clever friend from another, the fool does not know how to avail himself of the favourable circumstances, and withdraws pusillanimously from the enterprise. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11148" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11170">Here is occasion for him never again to raise his head among gentlemen, and always to carry his sword in his hand. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11171" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11234">And then how could he return, or how remain in this castle, in this place, which, setting aside the incessant and bitter memories of passion, would always remind him of an unsuccessful undertaking? Where the public hatred against him would have increased, and his reputation for power would have decreased? Where in the countenance of every clown, even in the midst of his bows, might be read a bitter irony? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11235" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11270">The way of iniquity, remarks the manuscript in this place, is wide; but this does not mean that it is an easy way; it has its serious obstacles, its rough places; it has its share of fatigue and vexation, even although it descends. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="7">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11271" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11337">An idea certainly occurred to Don Rodrigo, who would neither renounce this enterprise, draw back, nor remain where he was, and who yet could not proceed by himself, an idea by which he could assist himself; and this was to solicit the aid of one whose power was unknown, a man or a devil, for whom the very difficulty of the undertaking was often a stimulus. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11338" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11384">But this course had also its risks and inconveniences, and these were all the graver, because their consequences could be the less calculated; no one would be able to foresee how far affairs might go when once they had embarked themselves with this man, a powerful auxiliary certainly, but a not less arbitrary and dangerous commander. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="8">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11385" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11404">Such thoughts as these kept Don Rodrigo for some days in a terrible uncertainty between a no and a yes, both one and the other more than annoying. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11405" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11419">In the meantime a letter arrived from his cousin, which said that the plot was well laid. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11420" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11445">Shortly after the lightning was heard the thunder; suffice it to say, that one fine morning it was known that Father Cristoforo had left the convent of Pescarerico. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11446" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11496">This speedy success, Attilio's letter which inspired him with courage, and threatened him with much pleasantry, induced Don Rodrigo more than ever to incline towards the bold course; what, however, determined him at last, was the unexpected intelligence of Agnese having returned home; here was another impediment less in the way. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11497" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11504">Let us render account of these two events, commencing with the last. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="9">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11505" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11550">The two poor women were scarcely settled in their retreat, than the news of the great disturbance at Milan spread itself through Monza, and consequently through the convent; and following this great piece of news an infinite number of particulars, which increased and varied every moment. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11551" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11578">The housekeeper, who from her house was able to keep one ear towards the convent and the other towards the road, gathered news here and news there, and imparted it to her guests. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="10">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11579" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11608">"They have imprisoned two, six, eight, four, seven; they were seized in part before the bakehouse delle Gruoce, in part in the street near the house of the Vicar of Provisions. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11609" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11623">Eh, eh! listen to this! Only one has escaped, and he was from Lecco, or that part of the world. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11624" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11641">I do not know his name; but I shall see some one who will be able to tell me; we shall see whether you know him." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="11">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11642" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11697">This announcement, together with the circumstance of Renzo's having arrived in Milan precisely on this fatal day, caused the women some uneasiness, particularly Lucia; you can then imagine what they must have felt when the housekeeper came and said to them, "He is really from your village; this fellow who has run away to escape hanging, he is a silk-weaver, and calls himself Tramaglino; do you know him?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="12">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11698" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11732">Lucia, who sate hemming something, let her work fall from her hands; she became pale, and changed colour so suddenly, that most certainly the housekeeper would have perceived it had she been nearer. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11733" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11786">But she stood at the threshold with Agnese, who also troubled, but not so much as her daughter, was able to stand firm; and, in order to return some reply, said, that in a small village every one knew every one, and that therefore she was acquainted with this man; but that she could not imagine how he had done such a thing, because he was a very quiet young fellow. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11787" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11795">She then asked whether he had certainly escaped, and whither. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="13">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11796" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11824">"Every one says he has escaped, but where to no one knows. It may be that they will take him again; it may be that he is already in safety;—but if they get him again into their clutches, your quiet young fellow——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="14">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11825" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11843">Here, fortunately, the housekeeper was called away, and went; imagine to yourself the state of mind in which the mother and daughter were left. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11844" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11885">More than one day were the poor mother and the desolate child obliged to remain in this uncertainty, turning over in their minds the how and the wherefore, the various consequences of this sad event, and commenting with themselves, or when this was possible, to each other in a low voice, upon these terrible words. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="15">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11886" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11896">One Thursday, there at length arrived a man at the convent who sought Agnese. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11897" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11988">This was a fisherman from Pescarenico, who going to Milan, according to his custom, to sell his merchandise, in passing through Monzo had visited the convent at the request of the good friar Cristoforo, to greet the women from him, to relate to them as much as he knew concerning Renzo's sad situation, to recommend them to preserve patience, and place confidence in God; to assure them that he, poor friar as he was, would certainly not forget them, but would watch for the opportunity to aid them; and that in the meantime he would not fail to send them every week all the intelligence he knew, either by this means or through some other messenger. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11989" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12035">Regarding Renzo, the messenger was unable to tell them anything either new or certain, except respecting the visit made to his house, and the search which had been instituted after him; but they learned at the same time that all this had been in vain, and that it was held for certain that he had placed himself in safety in the territory of Bergamo. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12036" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12081">There is no necessity to say that such a certainty was a great balm for poor Lucia; from this day forth her tears flowed more freely and more gently; she experienced a greater comfort in the secret consolations of her mother, and a thanksgiving mingled itself with all her prayers. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="16">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12082" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12111">Gertrude often sent for her into her private parlour; she would sometimes converse for a long time together with Lucia, as it gave her pleasure to observe the candour and sweetness of the poor girl, and to hear herself every moment thanked and blessed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12112" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12145">She related also, in confidence, a portion—the innocent portion—of her own history; she related how much she had had to endure in order to suffer yet more in the convent, and Lucia's first feeling of astonishment, not unmingled with suspicion, changed itself gradually into compassion. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12146" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12178">She discovered in this history more than sufficed to explain all that was somewhat singular in her benefactress's manner—an explanation which was much more satisfactory than Agnese's doctrine regarding the brains of the Signori. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12179" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12230">Much as she felt inclined to return the confidence Gertrude had reposed in her, she never once thought of mentioning to her these new causes of disquiet, her new misfortune, of telling the Signora who this silk-weaver was who had made his escape, she feared spreading a report thus full of sorrow and scandal. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12231" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12254">She avoided as much as she could replying to the curious questions put to her by Gertrude regarding her history before the betrothal; but this was not through prudential motives. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12255" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12282">And it appeared to the poor innocent creature that her history was more thorny, more difficult to be related than anything she had heard or could hear from the Signora. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12283" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12335">In Gertrude's history there was tyranny, deceit, suffering; things hideous and sorrowful, but nevertheless things which could be named; but in hers there was mingled a sentiment, a word, which speaking of herself it appeared impossible to pronounce; a word for which she had never been able to find a substitute which did not seem wanting in modesty—love! </note>
        </p>
        <p n="17">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12336" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12359">Sometimes Gertrude grew almost angry with her for thus always standing on the defensive; but then throughout she exhibited so much affection, respect, gratitude, and so much confidence also! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12360" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12417">Sometimes again, this very delicate modesty would displease her in another way; but all anger was lost in a sweet thought which constantly returned to her whilst gazing at Lucia,—"I do good to the poor girl." And this was true; for, besides the asylum she offered her, these conversations, these familiar caresses, were no little consolation to Lucia. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12418" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12479">She found another consolation in constant employment, and always prayed that she might have something given her to do; she even carried into the parlour some work with which she might keep her hands busied; but, alas! how sad thoughts will thrust themselves in everywhere! Sewing on and on unceasingly, a new occupation for her, her reel would recur every now and then to her mind, and with this reel how many other things! </note>
        </p>
        <p n="18">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12480" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12503">The second Thursday this fisherman, or another messenger, again appeared with greetings from Father Cristoforo, and with the confirmation of Renzo's happy flight. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12504" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12570">More positive intelligence regarding his misfortunes he did not bring; for, as we have already told the reader, the Capuchin had hoped to receive such from his friend in Milan, to whom he had recommended Renzo; but this friend replied that he had neither seen the person, nor the letter; that certainly some one from the country had come to the monastery in search of him; but that, not having found him there, he had gone away, and not again presented himself. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="19">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12571" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12612">The third Thursday no one was seen; and for the poor women this was not only the loss of a desired and hoped for consolation, but, as it happens with people in affliction and embarrassment that every little thing is a cause of disquiet, this little circumstance filled them with a hundred alarms. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12613" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12634">Before this occurrence, Agnese had thought of making a little journey home, and now the singularity of their ambassador's not arriving decided her. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12635" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12669">For Lucia it was a serious affair, this separation from her mother; but the desire of knowing something, and the security which she enjoyed in this guarded and sacred asylum, conquered her repugnance. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12670" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12709">And it was decided between them that the following day Agnese should go and watch on the road for the fisherman, who must pass that way, returning from Milan, and request a seat in his cart as far as her mountains. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12710" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12747">She met him, and asked whether the Father Cristoforo had not intrusted him with some commission for her; the fisherman, it seemed, had been busied fishing the whole day before his departure, and had heard nothing of the Father. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12748" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12783">Agnese had no need to pray long, in order to obtain the boon she desired; she took leave of the Signora and of her daughter, not without tears, promising soon to send news of herself, and to return quickly, and then departed. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="20">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12784" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12790">Nothing particular occurred during the journey. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12791" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12808">They reposed part of one night at an inn, as was customary, set off the next morning before dawn, and arrived early at Pescarenico. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12809" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12841">Agnese ascended to the little square before the monastery, and took leave of her conductor with many thanks, and being there, wished to see the Friar, her benefactor, before going to her home. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12842" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12854">She rang the bell; and he who came to open the gate was Fra Galdino, the friar of the walnuts. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="21">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12855" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12862">"O! my good woman, what wind has brought you here?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="22">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12863" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12868">"I come to seek Father Cristoforo." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="23">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12869" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12871">"Father Cristoforo? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12872" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12873">He is not here." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="24">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12874" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12878">"O! will it be long before he returns?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="25">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12879" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12891">"But ——?" said the Friar, raising his shoulders, and burying his shaven head in his hood. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="26">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12892" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12893">"Where is he gone to?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="27">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12894" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12895">"To Rimini." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="28">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12896" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12896">"To ——?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="29">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12897" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12898">"To Rimini." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="30">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12899" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12901">"Where is that place?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="31">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12902" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12918">"Eh, eh, eh!" replied the Friar, cutting the air vertically with his outstretched hand, as if to indicate a great distance. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12919" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12921">"O poor creature that I am! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12922" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12928">But why has he set off thus suddenly?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="32">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12929" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12935">"Because the Father Provincial has wished it." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="33">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12936" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12944">"And why has he sent him away? He who does so much good here? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12945" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12946">O good heavens!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="34">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12947" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12962">"If the Superiors were obliged to render an account of all the orders they give, where would be our obedience, my good woman?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="35">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12963" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12969">"Yes, but this is my ruin." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="36">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12970" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12972">"Do you know how this will have happened? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12973" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13029">They will have had occasion for a good preacher at Rimini (we have good preachers everywhere, but sometimes they want a man made expressly for the occasion). The Father Provincial of Rimini will have written to the Father Provincial of this place, to know whether there were a brother such as he required here; and the Father Provincial will have returned for answer, that it is only Father Cristoforo who can answer his purpose." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="37">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13030" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13032">"O unfortunate people that we are! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13033" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13034">When did he depart?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="38">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13035" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13035">"The day before yesterday." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="39">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13036" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13048">"Ah, only see! if I had but paid attention to the desire I felt to leave some days ago! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13049" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13060">And it is not known when he will return? Not even within a few days?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="40">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13061" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13074">"Ah, my dear woman! If any one knows, it is the Father Provincial. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13075" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13094">When one of our preaching fathers has taken his flight, it is impossible to foresee on what bough he will settle. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13095" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13112">He is sent for here, he is sent for there; for we have convents in the four quarters of the globe. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13113" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13156">You may be certain that, at Rimini, Father Cristoforo will make a great sensation by his sermons preached in Lent; for he does not always preach extempore as he does here to the fishers and peasants; for the pulpits of the city, he has his beautiful written sermons; that is the important point. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13157" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13176">The fame of this great preacher will spread on all sides; they may even send for him from — from where do I know? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13177" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13197">And then he must go, because as we live on every one's charity, it is but right that we should serve every one. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="41">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13198" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13211">"O Lord, Lord!" exclaimed Agnese again, almost in tears; "what must I do without this kind man? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13212" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13218">He was a father to us. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13219" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13223">This will be our ruin." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="42">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13224" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13255">"Listen, good woman, Father Cristoforo was certainly a good man, but we have other brothers do you know? full of charity and of talent, who know how to behave, both towards the rich and the poor. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13256" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13267">Will you see Father Atanasio? Father Girolamo? Father Zaccaria? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13268" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13316">He is a worthy man do you see, this Father Zaccaria, and don't be astonished, as many ignorant people are, that he is so thin, has such a cracked voice, and such a miserable little beard; I don't say anything of his preaching, for every one has his peculiar gifts, but for giving advice he is a man, I can tell you." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="43">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13317" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13378">"O heavens!" exclaimed Agnese, with that mixture of gratitude and impatience, called forth by an offer, in which there is more goodwill than usefulness. "What does it matter to me what this man or the other is, if the poor man, no longer here, is the one who knew our affairs, and had prepared all to assist us?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="44">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13379" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13382">"Then you must have patience." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="45">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13383" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13389">"That I know," replied Agnese; "pardon the trouble I have given." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="46">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13390" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13399">"For what shall I pardon you? I am sorry for you. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13400" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13417">If you should decide upon seeking advice from one of our Fathers, the convent is here, and will not stir. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13418" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13427">Ah! I shall soon shew myself for the collection of oil." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="47">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13428" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13450">"Good-bye," said Agnese, and walked towards her little village, feeling desolate, confounded, disconcerted, like some poor blind man who has lost his staff. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="48">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13451" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13465">Being somewhat better informed than Fra Galdino, we can say how the affair really happened. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13466" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13487">Attilio, as soon as he arrived at Milan, went as he had promised Don Rodrigo, to visit their mutual uncle of the secret council. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13488" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13519">This was a council composed of thirteen members, men of the robe and the sword, from whom the governor received advice; and he dying, or being removed, this council assumed the temporary government. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13520" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13550">This uncle the Count, decorated with his robes, and one of the oldest members, enjoyed a certain power in the assembly; but in exercising this authority, and in making it felt by others, he had not his equal. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13551" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13591">An ambiguous manner of speaking, a significant silence, a stopping short in the middle of his sentence, a contraction of the eyes, which expressed, "I cannot speak," a manner of flattering without absolutely promising, were all artifices directed to this one end; and all, more or less, were exercised in its behalf. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13592" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13661">And this was carried so far that his saying, "I can do nothing in this affair," often the pure truth, but spoken in a manner which made the words not believed, would often serve to increase the reputation, and therefore the reality of his power; just as you may sometimes still see in apothecaries' shops, boxes upon which are written certain Arabic words, boxes which, though empty, serve to maintain the credit of the shop. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13662" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13712">This uncle, the Count, who for a long time had been progressing by slow degrees, lately had all at once taken a giant's stride. On an occasion of importance, he had made a journey to Madrid, charged with an embassy at Court, and you should only have heard him relate how he was received there! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13713" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13776">The Count-Duke had treated him with a marked attention, not to say with something more, and he had taken him so far into his confidence, as once to ask him in the presence, one might say of half the court, whether Madrid pleased him; and to have said to him another time in a tête-à-tête, when standing in the recess of a window, that the cathedral in Milan was the grandest temple in the king's dominions. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="49">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13777" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13833">Having paid his compliments to the Count his uncle, and presented those of his cousin, Attilio, with a serious mien, which he well knew how to assume at the proper time, said, "I believe I am performing my duty, without betraying the confidence of Rodrigo, in informing my Signor uncle of an affair which, unless he take it in hand, may become serious, and lead to consequences which—" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="50">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13834" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13837">"Some one of his follies, I imagine." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="51">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13838" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13851">"For the love of justice I must say that the fault is not on my cousin's side. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13852" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13865">But he is warm; and as I say there is no one but my Signor uncle who could—" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="52">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13866" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13867">"We see, we see." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="53">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13868" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13903">"There is living near him a Capuchin friar, who is angry with Rodrigo, and things have arrived at such a point—" "How often have I told you both, that you must let the friars cook their broth." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13904" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13918">It is enough that they give to those to whom they are obliged to give — to those whom it concerns —" and here he drew a deep breath. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13919" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13924">"But you who can avoid—" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="54">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13925" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13940">"Signor uncle, in the present case it is my duty to inform you that Rodrigo would have avoided it, had this been possible. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13941" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13956">It is the Friar who has a grudge against him, who has endeavoured to provoke him in every possible manner —" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="55">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13957" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13964">"What the devil has this friar to do with my nephew?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="56">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13965" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13982">"In the first place, he is a hot-headed fellow, and known as such, who makes it his profession to quarrel with cavaliers. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13983" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14011">This fellow protects, directs, a little peasant girl of that part of the world; and has for her a love, a love—I do not say an unselfish love, but a very jealous, suspicious, touchy love." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="57">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14012" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14048">"I understand," said the Count; and over a surface of stupidity implanted on his countenance by nature, overlaid again and again by layers of craftiness, there played a ray of malice very beautiful to observe. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="58">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14049" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14069">"Now, for some time," continued Attilio, "this friar has got it into his head, that Rodrigo has designs upon this —" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="59">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14070" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14096">"He has got it into his head, he has got it into his head,—I also know Don Rodrigo,—and some other advocate than your lordship would be necessary to justify him in these affairs." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="60">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14097" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14157">"Signor uncle, that Rodrigo may have joked with this creature, meeting her in the road, I should not be far from believing; he is young, and then he is no Capuchin; but these are frivolous things, not proper subjects of conversation with the Signor, my uncle; the serious part of the affair is, that the friar has actually spoken of Rodrigo as though he were a villain, and endeavours to excite the whole country against him ——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="61">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14158" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14161">"And the other friars?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="62">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14162" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14198">"They do not meddle in the affair, for they know him to be a hot-headed fellow, and entertain much respect for Rodrigo; but then on the other hand, this friar stands high with the peasants, for he also passes himself off as a saint, and ——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="63">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14199" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14207">"I imagine that this friar does not know that Rodrigo is my nephew." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="64">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14208" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14210">"Yes, he knows it! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14211" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14221">And it is this that makes him all the more violent." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="65">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14222" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14223">"How? How!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="66">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14224" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14275">"For this reason, and he says this himself, he finds all the more pleasure in opposing Rodrigo, because he has a natural protector of so much authority as your lordship, and that he laughs at grandees and politicians, knowing that the cord of San Francesco holds bound even the sword, and that ——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="67">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14276" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14278">"O the audacious Friar! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14279" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14282">What is his name?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="68">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14283" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14310">"Fra Cristoforo da ——," said Attilio; and the noble uncle took out of a little chest, which stood upon his table, a memorandum-book, and wrote in it, still loudly breathing, this poor name. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14311" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14324">Meanwhile Attilio continued, "This fellow has always been of the same disposition; his life is well known. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14325" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14359">He was a plebeian, who finding himself possessed of a few pence, wished to compete with the cavaliers of his neighbourhood; and through rage, at not being able to vanquish them all, he killed one of them; and then to escape the gallows he turned friar. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="69">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14360" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14363">"But bravo! that's excellent! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14364" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14374">We will see, we will see," said the Count, continuing to puff forth mighty blasts. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="70">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14375" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14406">"Now," continued Attilio, "he is more enraged than ever, because a project which he had much at heart has failed, and from this, my Signor uncle will be the better able to understand what kind of man he is. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14407" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14469">He wished to marry this creature of his,—it was to remove her from the perils of this world — you understand me; or for some other motive, he wished absolutely to get her married; he had found the man; another of his creatures, a fellow whom perhaps, or even without any perhaps at all, my Signor uncle will know by name; I hold it for certain that the Secret Council will have been forced to occupy itself with this worthy individual." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="71">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14470" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14472">"Who is the fellow?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="72">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14473" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14480">"A silk-weaver, Lorenzo Tramaglino, the one who—" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="73">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14481" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14491">"Lorenzo Tramaglino!" exclaimed the noble uncle; "but well done, bravo, Father! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14492" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14506">Certainly — in fact, — he had a letter for a — A crime that — But it matters not — It is good. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14507" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14538">And wherefore has the Signor Don Rodrigo told me nothing of all this? Why has he allowed things to go on so far, and not had recourse to those who could and would direct and support him?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="74">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14539" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14546">"I will speak the truth in this instance also," continued Attilio. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14547" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14587">"On one hand, knowing how many affairs, how much business my Signor Uncle has in his head—" here the uncle, breathing loud, placed his hand upon his head, as though to indicate the great difficulty he felt in keeping all this world of business contained within it—"Rodrigo felt a scruple in troubling him with any other affair. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14588" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14638">And then I will tell you all; from what I have been able to hear, he is so much enraged, so out of himself, so wearied with the insults put upon him by this friar, that he has sooner wished to do himself justice in some summary manner, than to obtain it in a regular way, by prudence, and the arm of the signor, his uncle. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14639" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14675">I have endeavoured to extinguish this passion, but seeing that things were taking a bad course, I believed it my duty to inform my Signor uncle of all, who is the head and pillar of the house—" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="75">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14676" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14683">"You would have done better to speak a little earlier." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="76">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14684" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14727">"That is true; but I went on hoping that the affair would pass away of itself, or that the friar would return to his senses, or that he would leave his convent, as often happens with these friars, who now are here and now are there, and that thus all would be at an end. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14728" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14728">But—" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="77">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14729" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14734">"Now it will be my affair to settle this dispute." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="78">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14735" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14771">"This is what I also think, I have said to myself; our uncle, with his foresight, with his authority, will know how to prevent any scandal, and at the same time preserve Rodrigo's honour, which is also his own. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14772" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14799">This friar, as I have before said, is always boasting of the cord of San Francesco; but is it necessary, in order to make a good use of this cord, to wear it round your body? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14800" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14845">The Signor uncle has a hundred means of which I know nothing; I know, however, that the Father Provincial entertains, as is but right, a high deference for him; and if the Signor, my uncle, should think that the best remedy in this case would be to give the friar a change of air, he, with two words— </note>
        </p>
        <p n="79">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14846" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14859">"Leave thinking to those whom it concerns, young sir," said the noble uncle, somewhat roughly. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="80">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14860" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14878">"Ah, that is true!" exclaimed Attilio with a shake of the head, and a smile of compassion for himself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14879" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14887">"I, indeed, a proper man to give advice to my Signor uncle. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14888" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14901">But it is my jealousy for the reputation of the house which makes me speak. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14902" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14927">And then I fear to have committed another folly," he added, with a sorrowful air. "I fear I have injured Rodrigo in the opinion of my uncle. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14928" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14953">I should be unable to find peace had I caused him to think that Rodrigo had not the confidence in him and all the submission which he really has. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14954" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14962">Believe, Signor uncle, that in this case it is right—" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="81">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14963" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14981">"Come, come, what injury, what injury between you two? who will be friends until one of you becomes wise. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14982" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_15021">Libertines, libertines, who always are committing some folly; and then it is for me to set things to rights again; who—you will make me say some nonsense or other, who give me more to think of than—and here imagine the mighty puff he gave—than all these blessed affairs of state." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="82">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap18-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_15022" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_15054">Attilio again makes some apologies, some promises, some compliments, and then took leave, accompanied by a "be prudent," which was the noble uncle's form of leavetaking with his nephews. </note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>