<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CHAPTER XXI.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>1845</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed Lovers: a Milanese Story of the Seventeenth Century. With The Column of Infamy by Alessandro Manzoni. In Three Volumes</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
          <date>1845</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Henry Francis C. Logan</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="English_1845_cap21">
        <p n="1">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10041">The old woman had hastened to obey and command with the authority of this name, which, by whatever mouth it might be pronounced in this place, put every one in movement; for no one ever imagined that any person would be daring enough to make use of it upon false pretences. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10042" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10083">In short, she arrived at the Malanotte a short time before the carriage; and seeing it approach, she descended from the litter, signed to the coachman to stop, neared the coach window, and signified in a low voice to Nibbio, who put out his head, her master's orders. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="2">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10084" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10097">Lucia, when the carriage stopped, started, and recovered from a species of lethargy. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10098" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10112">She felt the blood again begin to circulate, opened her mouth and eyes, and looked around her. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10113" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10146">Nibbio had drawn himself back, and the old woman, her chin resting upon the carriage-door, gazing at Lucia, said, "Come, my good girl; come poor thing; come with me, with me, who have orders to treat you well and encourage you!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="3">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10147" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10168">At the sound of a woman's voice, the poor girl experienced a consolation, a momentary courage, but she immediately fell into a still greater terror. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10169" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10182">"Who are you?" she demanded with a trembling voice, fixing her astonished gaze on the countenance of the old woman. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="4">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10183" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10188">"Come, come, poor girl," the old woman continued, to repeat. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10189" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10273">Nibbio and his companions, divining by the words and the extraordinary softness of the old woman's voice what were the intentions of their master, sought by gentle words to persuade the unfortunate girl to obey; but Lucia continued to gaze out of the carriage, and although the place, wild and unknown to her, and the guardians' air of security did not allow her to form one hope of succour, she nevertheless opened her mouth to scream; but, seeing Nibbio exhibit the handkerchief, she restrained her cry, trembled, became silent, and was taken and placed in the litter. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10274" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10298">After her entered the old woman; Nibbio ordered the two other bravoes to follow behind, whilst he ascended quickly to wait upon the commands of his master. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="5">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10299" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10318">"Who are you?" demanded Lucia, with anxiety, of this unknown and deformed visage; "why am I with you? Where am I? Where are you conducting me to?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="6">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10319" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10344">"To one who will be kind to you," replied the old woman; "to a great— fortunate are those to whom he wishes well; it is lucky for you, it is a lucky for you. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10345" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10355">Do not be afraid, be gay, for he has commanded me to encourage you. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10356" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10362">You will tell him that I have encouraged you, will you not?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="7">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10363" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10369">Who is he? Why? What does he want of me? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10370" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10373">I do not belong to him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10374" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10391">Tell me where I am, let me go! Tell these men to let me go,—to carry me to some church. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10392" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10402">Oh! you who are a woman, in the name of the Virgin Mary— </note>
        </p>
        <p n="8">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10403" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10453">This holy and gentle name, formerly repeated with veneration in her early years,—this name, which she herself had neither invoked for a long time, nor yet heard pronounced, excited in the mind of the unfortunate being who now again heard it, a strange, confused, and vague sentiment; like the remembrance of light in an old man who has been blind from his infancy. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="9">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10454" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10509">Meanwhile, the Unknown, standing in the portal of the castle, gazed below. He saw the litter ascend slowly, as before the carriage had done, and at a distance which decreased every moment, Nibbio ascending with hasty steps; when he had reached the summit, the Signor signed to him to follow, and went with him into an apartment of the castle. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="10">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10510" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10513">"Well?" he said, stopping short. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="11">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10514" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10544">"Every thing to a moment," replied Nibbio; "the information in time—the woman in time—no one at the place—a single cry—no one appeared—the coachman ready—the horses excellent—not a person on the road;—but——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="12">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10545" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10546">"But what?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="13">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10547" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10572">"But—I say the truth, I should have been better pleased had the order been to have given her a musket shot in the back, without hearing her speak, and without looking into her face." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="14">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10573" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10578">"How? how? what wouldst thou say?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="15">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10579" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10591">"I would say, that all this time, all this time—— She has excited my compassion too much." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="16">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10592" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10597">"Compassion! what dost thou know about compassion? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10598" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10600">What kind of a thing is compassion?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="17">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10601" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10629">"I have never understood it so well as this time; it is a thing something like fear, this compassion; if one allows it to take possession of oneself, one is no longer a man." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="18">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10630" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10640">"Let us hear what the girl has done, thus to move thee to compassion." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="19">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10641" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10688">"Oh, most illustrious Signor! Such a long time — weeping, praying, and casting such looks, and becoming as white, as white as death, and then sobbing, and then praying anew, and certain words —" "I do not wish her in my house, this girl," thought the Unknown, "I have been a fool to have engaged myself; but I have promised, but I have promised. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="20">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10689" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10741">When she is far off—" Then raising his head in a commanding attitude, he addressed Nibbio, saying, "Now, put aside compassion; mount on horseback, take a companion, two, if thou wilt, and speed to the house of this Don Rodrigo, whom thou knowest; tell him to send — but quickly, quickly, otherwise—" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="21">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10742" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10754">But here another internal no, more imperious than the first, prohibited him from finishing his sentence. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10755" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10843">"No," he said, with a resolute voice, as though to express to himself the command of this secret voice; "no, go and repose thyself; and to-morrow do what I shall command thee." "This girl must have some demon in her," he then thought, and remained standing alone, his arms crossed upon his breast, his gaze fixed upon a part of the pavement where the rays of the moon, entering by a high window, formed a square of pale light, divided into smaller squares by the thick iron-bars, and again intersected more minutely by the compartments of the panes. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="22">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10844" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10899">"Some demon, or — some angel protects her.—Nibbio, feel compassion!—To-morrow, to-morrow early, this girl shall leave this place; she shall follow her destiny, and — and nothing more shall be said about her. And —" he continued, with that air with which one commands a disobedient boy, knowing all the time that he will not obey, "and nothing more will be thought about her. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10900" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10936">This animal, Don Rodrigo, must not come and weary one with his thanks; for—I will not again hear this girl spoken of; I have served him, because—because I have promised; and I have promised, because—it was my destiny. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10937" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10946">But I wish him to recompense me well for this service. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10947" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10993">Let us see——" And he sought to imagine some very difficult enterprise which he might impose on him as a compensation or even as punishment; but again these words crossed his mind, "Nibbio feel compassion!—What can this girl have done?" he continued, tormenting himself with this thought; "I will see her. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10994" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10995">Ah! no,—yes, I will see her." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="23">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_10996" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11022">And passing from one apartment into another, he found a small staircase, mounted it, groping along, went to the old woman's chamber, and assailed the door with a kick. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="24">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11023" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11024">"Who is there?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11025" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11025">"Open the door." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="25">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11026" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11046">At the sound of this voice, the old woman took three springs, and immediately the bolt was heard drawn back, and the door opened. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11047" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11074">The Unknown, standing on the threshold, cast a glance into the room, and by the light of a lamp which burned upon a small table he saw Lucia crouched down on the earth in the farthest corner of the chamber. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="26">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11075" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11095">"Who has told thee to fling her there, like a bundle of rags, miserable woman?" said he to the old hag, with an angry frown. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="27">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11096" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11121">"She has placed herself where it pleased her," she humbly replied; "I have done every thing I could to encourage her; she can tell you that herself; but she has not listened to me." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="28">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11122" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11128">"Rise!" said the Unknown to Lucia, and approached her. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11129" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11170">But Lucia, in whose alarmed mind, this knocking, this opening of the door, the arrival of this man, and his words, had created a new terror, remained all the more shrunk together in the corner, with her face concealed in her hands, and only trembled all over. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="29">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11171" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11185">"Rise; I do not wish to do you evil—and I can do you good," repeated the Signor. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11186" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11196">"Rise!" again thundered this voice, angered by having twice commanded in vain. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="30">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11197" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11228">As though invigorated by her terror, the unfortunate rose suddenly upon her knees; and joining her hands, as she would have done before the image of some saint, raised her eyes to the countenance of the Unknown, and immediately lowering them again, said, "I am here, kill me." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="31">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11229" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11249">"I have told you that I do not wish to hurt you," replied the Unknown, with a gentler voice, gazing upon this countenance, disturbed by anguish and terror. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="32">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11250" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11265">"Courage, courage," said the old woman; "if he tells you himself, that he will not hurt you——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="33">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11266" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11293">"And wherefore," replied Lucia, with a voice in which, spite of the trembling of fear, might be heard a certain confidence caused by her indignation and desperation, "wherefore have you made me suffer the pangs of hell? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11294" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11298">What have I done——?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="34">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11299" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11301">"They have perhaps ill-treated you? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11302" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11302">Speak!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="35">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11303" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11304">"Oh, ill-treated me! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11305" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11319">They have seized upon me by treachery, by force. Why? why have they taken me? why am I here? where am I? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11320" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11327">I am a poor young creature—what have I done? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11328" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11331">In the name of God—— </note>
        </p>
        <p n="36">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11332" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11361">"God, God," interrupted the Unknown; "it is always God; those who cannot defend themselves, who have no strength, have always this God to bring into the field, as though they had spoken with him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11362" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11367">What do you intend to do with this word of yours? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11368" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11375">To make me——?" he left the sentence unended. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="37">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11376" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11378">"O sir, intend! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11379" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11390">What can I intend, I, poor girl, unless you are merciful towards me? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11391" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11398">God pardons many things, for one deed of mercy! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11399" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11406">Let me go; for charity, let me go! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11407" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11423">It is not well for one who must some day die, to torment a poor creature thus. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11424" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11433">Oh, you who can command, tell them to let me go! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11434" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11438">They have brought me here by force. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11439" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11448">Send me with this woman to—to my mother. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11449" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11459">Oh, most holy Virgin! my mother, my mother! for charity, my mother! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11460" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11470">Perhaps she is not far from here,—I have seen my mountains. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11471" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11475">Why do you make me suffer? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11476" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11481">Let me be conducted into a church. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11482" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11488">I will pray for you all my life. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11489" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11494">It would only cost you a single word. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11495" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11507">Oh, I see you are moved with compassion; say one word, one word! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11508" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11572">God pardons so many things for one work of mercy." "Oh, why is she not a daughter of one of those who have banished me," thought the Unknown; "of one of those villains who wished to see me dead! How I should now rejoice in her screams; but instead—" "Do not reject a good inspiration!" pursued Lucia fervently, animated by the sight of a certain hesitation in the countenance and bearing of her tyrant. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="39">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11573" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11594">"But if you will not do me this charity, the Lord will do it for me; he will cause me to die, and then all will be ended for me; but you ----! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11595" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11613">Perhaps one day you also ---- But no, no; I will always pray the Lord to deliver you from every ill. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11614" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11619">What does it cost you to speak one word? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11620" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11626">If ever you should have to suffer these torments ----" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="40">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11627" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11639">"Come, take courage," interrupted the Unknown, with a gentleness which quite amazed the old woman. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11640" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11643">"Have I done you any evil? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11644" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11645">Have I threatened you?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="41">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11646" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11647">"Oh, no! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11648" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11661">I see that you have a good heart, and that you feel pity for me, poor creature. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11662" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11684">If you wished it, you could cause me more fear than all the others; you could make me die; but instead you have—somewhat consoled me. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11685" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11688">God will reward you for this. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11689" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11696">Complete your work of mercy—liberate me, liberate me!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="42">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11697" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11697">"To-morrow ----" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="43">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11698" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11702">"Oh, liberate me now, immediately ----" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="44">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11703" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11707">"To-morrow we will see each other again, I tell you. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11708" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11711">Come, in the meantime take courage. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11712" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11712">Rest yourself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11713" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11721">You must require food; they will now bring you some refreshment," </note>
        </p>
        <p n="45">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11722" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11731">"No, no. I shall die if any one enters; I shall die. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11732" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11741">Conduct me to a church. God will remember your actions." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="46">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11742" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11779">"A woman will come and bring your food," said the Unknown; and having said this, he was himself astonished that such an expedient should have occurred to him, and that he should have ever felt the necessity of finding one, in order to reassure a woman. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11780" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11813">"And thou," he added suddenly, turning towards the old woman, "encourage her that she may eat; put her to sleep in this bed if she like it, in company with thyself, otherwise thou canst very well sleep one night on the floor. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11814" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11819">Encourage her, I say; keep her cheerful. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11820" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11827">And do not let her have to complain of thee!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="47">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11828" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11834">Having said this, he walked rapidly towards the door. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11835" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11848">Lucia rose, and ran to detain him and renew her prayer, but he was already departed. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="48">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11849" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11851">"Oh, unfortunate that I am! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11852" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11870">Close the door, close it quickly!" and when she had heard the door closed and the bolt drawn, she returned to crouch again in her corner. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11871" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11880">"Oh, miserable girl that I am!" she again exclaimed, sobbing; "what shall I now pray for? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11881" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11882">Where am I? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11883" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11895">Tell me, tell me for charity, who is this Signor — this man who has spoken to me?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="49">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11896" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11900">"Who he is? who he is? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11901" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11905">You wish that I should tell you? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11906" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11910">You can wait till I tell you. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11911" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11928">Because he protects you, you are grown proud; you wish to be satisfied, and make me the victim. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11929" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11931">Demand this of himself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_11932" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12011">If I should content you in this, such good words as you have from him would not be addressed to me. I am an old woman, an old woman," she continued, muttering between her teeth; "cursed be young girls, who look well both weeping and laughing, and have always reason —" But hearing Lucia sob, and the command of her master recurring to her mind, she bent over the poor girl, who lay huddled together in her corner, and continued in a softer voice, "Come, I have said nothing bad to you, be gay. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12012" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12029">Do not ask after things which I cannot tell you, and for the rest, be of good courage. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12030" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12044">Ah, if you did but know how many people would be happy to hear themselves spoken to as he has spoken to you. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12045" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12066">Be cheerful, for directly something to eat will come, and I know, from the manner in which he has spoken to you, that there will be something good. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12067" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12087">And — you will leave a little corner for me also, I hope," she added, in an angry voice, in spite of herself. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="50">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12088" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12093">"I will not eat; I will not sleep. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12094" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12101">Let me be, do not approach me, do not go away!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="51">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12102" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12145">"No, no," said the old woman, retiring and seating herself upon an old chair, from whence she cast towards the poor girl certain glances at once of terror and envy. She then looked at her bed, tormented herself thinking that she should perhaps be excluded from it all the night, and grumbled about the cold. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12146" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12163">But she rejoiced herself with the idea of the supper, and with the hope that there would be also some for her. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12164" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12194">Lucia did not perceive the cold, neither did she feel hunger; and wholly overpowered by her misfortune, retained only a confused sentiment of her sorrows and terrors, similar to the delirious dreams of a sick person. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="52">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12195" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12209">She returned to herself when she heard a knock; and raising her affrighted countenance, she cried, "Who is there? who is there? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12210" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12212">Let no one come!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="53">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12213" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12225">"It is nothing, it is nothing. Good news!" said the old woman, "it is Marta, who brings us something to eat." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="54">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12226" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12229">"Shut the door, shut the door!" cried Lucia. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="55">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12230" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12261">"Ah, yes, immediately, immediately," replied the old woman, and took a basket out of the hand of this same Marta, sent her away, reclosed the door, and then came and placed the basket upon a small table in the middle of the room. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12262" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12274">She then invited Lucia many times to come and enjoy these good things. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12275" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12312">She made use of, in her opinion, the most efficacious words to produce appetite in the poor girl, and broke forth into exclamations over the exquisiteness of the food—"When people such as we happen to taste such food, they remember it for some time. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12313" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12330">Here is wine too, such as the master drinks with his friends—when any such come to visit him—and when they wish to be merry together! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12331" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12331">Eh!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12332" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12355">But seeing that all these temptations were useless, "it is you who will not," she said; "and do not say to-morrow that I have not encouraged you. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12356" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12372">I will eat, and there will remain more than enough for you when you shall have returned to your senses and will obey." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12373" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12379">And thus saying, she commenced eating with great avidity. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12380" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12401">When she had satisfied herself, she rose, went towards the corner, and bending over Lucia, again invited her to eat, and then go to bed. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="56">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12402" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12414">"No, no, I will have nothing," she replied with a weak and almost drowsy voice. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12415" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12425">And then, with more resolution, she asked, "is the door fastened? is it well fastened?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12426" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12447">After gazing round the room, she rose, and with her hands stretched forward, with an unsteady step she went towards the door. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="57">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12448" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12471">The old woman hastened there before her, placed her hand upon the bolt, shot it, and said, "Do you hear? do you see? Is it well fastened? Are you satisfied now?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="58">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12472" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12484">"Oh, satisfied! satisfied being here?" said Lucia, placing herself again in her corner. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12485" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12492">"But the Lord knows that I am here!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12493" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12503">"Come to bed; what will you do there, lying on the ground like a dog? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12504" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12513">Did one ever before see people refuse comforts where they might have them?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="59">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12514" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12517">"No, no; let me be." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="60">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12518" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12522">"It is you who wish it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12523" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12537">See, I leave you the good place, I have laid myself upon the edge; I will incommode myself for you. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12538" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12547">If you wish to come to bed, you know what you have to do. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12548" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12553">Recollect that I have begged you many times." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12554" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12562">And saying this, she drew herself under the coverlet, and all was silent. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="61">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12563" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12588">Lucia remained immoveable in her corner, her knees raised, her hands supported upon her knees, and her face concealed in her hands. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12589" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12608">The state into which she had fallen was neither that of sleep, nor yet of perfect consciousness; but there passed through her mind a rapid succession of painful thoughts, imaginations, and terrors. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12609" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12659">And now conscious, and recalling more distinctly to herself the horrible things she had seen and suffered this day, she applied herself sorrowfully to consider the obscure and formidable reality in which she found herself an actor; and now again, her mind, transported into a region still more obscure, struggled with phantoms, born of uncertainty and terror. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12660" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12692">She remained some time in this anguish. At length, however, more wearied and worn out than ever, stretching her benumbed limbs, she laid herself upon the floor, or sank down upon it, and remained some time in a state more resembling true sleep. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12693" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12722">But all at once she awoke to consciousness, as though at the summons of an inward voice, and felt the desire of arousing herself entirely, of recalling her thoughts, of knowing where she was, and how, and wherefore she came there. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12723" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12801">She listened with all her attention to a sound; it was the slow and hoarse breathing of the old woman; she opened wide her eyes, and saw a fiery brightness appear and disappear by turns; it was the wick of the lamp which, upon the point of expiring, shot forth a tremulous light, and then immediately, so to say, drew it back again, like the ebb and flow of a wave upon the shore; and this light, flying the objects before they had received relief and a distinct colour from it, only presented to the view a succession of confused images. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12802" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12819">But soon, recent impressions resuming their place in her mind, assisted her to distinguish what had been confused to her senses. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12820" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12871">The unfortunate girl, having awoke, recognised her prison; and all the memories of the horrible past day, all the terrors of the future, assailed her at once; this very quiet even, after so much agitation,—this species of repose,—this solitude in which she was left,—caused her a new terror, and she was overcome by such sorrow that she desired to die. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12872" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12893">But in this moment she remembered that she could at least pray, and together with this thought there arose in her heart a sudden hope. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12894" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12925">She again took her chaplet, and recommenced saying her rosary, and gradually, as the prayer issued from her trembling lips, her heart felt increase within it an unlimited confidence. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12926" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12956">Suddenly another thought crossed her mind, which was that her prayers would be more acceptable and more certainly granted, did she in her desolation present some offering. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_12957" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13003">She recalled that which she held as most precious, or that which had ever been dearest to her; in this moment, her soul could experience no other sentiment than terror, nor conceive any other desire than liberation; she remembered this most precious thing, and resolved immediately to sacrifice it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13004" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13048">She arose, knelt down, and holding clasped upon her breast her hands, from which hung the chaplet, she raised her countenance and eyes towards heaven, and said, "Oh most holy Virgin, thou to whom I have commended myself so often, and who hast so often consoled me! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13049" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13105">Thou, who hast endured so much sorrow, and now art so glorified, and hast performed so many miracles for us poor suffering ones, aid thou me! Cause me to escape out of this danger; cause me to return safe to my mother; and I vow unto thee to remain a virgin. I will renounce for ever this poor youth, and thus never belong to any other being than thee!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="62">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13106" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13140">Having spoken these words, she bowed her head, and placed the chaplet round her neck, at once as a sign of consecration and as a safeguard, as an armour of the new militia in which she had engaged. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13141" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13155">Having reseated herself on the ground, she felt a certain tranquillity, a deeper confidence enter into her soul. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13156" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13177">This to-morrow, repeated by the powerful Unknown, recurred to her mind; and she seemed to hear in this word a promise of salvation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13178" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13214">Her senses, fatigued by all this warfare, were lulled by degrees into calm; and at length, when the dawn was already near, with the name of her protectress upon her lips, Lucia fell into a deep and continuous sleep. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="63">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13215" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13231">But there was also another person in the same castle, who would have desired to sleep, but who could not. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13232" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13301">After having left, or rather after having escaped from Lucia, after having ordered her supper, after having paid his customary visit to certain posts in the castle, this image still vividly present to his mind, and with these words resounding in his ears, the Signor had retired to his chamber, and there, having hastily shut himself in, as though he had to defend himself from a legion of enemies, undressing himself in all haste, he had gone to bed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13302" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13330">But this image, more than ever present to his thoughts, seemed to say to him in this moment, "thou shalt not sleep." "What foolish womanish curiosity possessed me to see her?" thought he. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13331" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13354">"This stupid Nibbio was right, one is no longer a man; it is true, one is no longer a man!—I—!—I no longer a man?—I! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13355" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13365">What has happened? What devil has taken possession of me? What is there so new in this? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13366" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13375">Did I not know before now that women scream? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13376" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13386">Men also weep sometimes, when they cannot defend themselves. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13387" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13429">What the devil! have I never before heard women cry?" And here, without fatiguing himself much in taxing his memory, his memory itself presented him with more than one instance in which neither prayers nor lamentations had been able to deter him from carrying out his resolutions. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="64">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13430" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13521">But the remembrance of these undertakings was far from giving him that firmness which he required in order to complete this enterprise, was far from extinguishing in his soul this vexatious compassion; there awoke within him a species of terror, an indescribable mad penitence: so that it seemed a relief to turn to the image of Lucia, from which he had sought to free his soul. "She still lives," thought he; "she is here. I am in time; I can say to her, 'go, rejoice;' I can see this countenance change, can also say to her, 'pardon me—pardon me!' </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13522" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13529">I demand pardon!—from a woman?—I? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13530" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13555">Ah! and yet if one word, a word such as this, could do me good, could free me somewhat from this devilish business, I would say it: ah! I feel that I would say it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13556" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13560">Ah! to what am I reduced! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13561" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13598">I am no longer a man, I am no longer a man!—"Come!" he then said, turning himself madly upon this bed become so very hard, under the coverlet which was become so very heavy; "come, this is only nonsense, which has already at former times passed through my mind, and it will pass away this time also." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="65">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13599" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13628">And in order to drive this nonsense away, he sought for something of importance to think of, one of those affairs which generally occupied him so entirely, and to which he would now apply himself wholly; but he could not find a single thought of this description. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13629" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13666">Every thing appeared to him changed; that which formerly had most strongly stimulated his desires was now no longer desirable; passion, like a horse become all at once restive, through fear of a shadow would not advance. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13667" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13701">When thinking of the undertakings already in hand, but not yet completed, instead of animating himself with the idea of their accomplishments, instead of irritating himself at the obstacles in his path—and anger even at this moment would have appeared agreeable to him—he only experienced a sadness, almost a terror, at the deeds he had already done. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13702" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13732">Time spread itself out before him void of every interest, of every occupation, of every wish; alone filled with intolerable memories, all hours appeared similar to the present, which passed thus slowly, thus heavily over his head. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n189" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13733" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13770">In his imagination he made all his ruffians pass before him in review, and he did not find a single command to give them which was important to him; thus, the idea of seeing them again, of finding himself among them, was a fresh burthen — an annoying and disagreeable idea. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n190" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13771" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13805">And if he desired to discover any occupation for the morrow, any feasible work, he was obliged to think that on the morrow he should be able to set this poor young girl at liberty. "I will liberate her; yes, as soon as day shall have dawned, I will hasten to her and say, Go, go. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="66">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n191" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13806" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13816">I will have her escorted —— And the promise? — and the engagement? — and Don Rodrigo? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n192" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13817" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13864">Who is Don Rodrigo?" And like a man who is surprised by an unexpected and embarrassing question from a superior, the Unknown immediately thought how he should reply to the question he had demanded of himself,—or rather this new man which had so suddenly grown within him arose as in judgment upon the ancient one. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="67">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n193" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13865" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13923">He busied himself therefore in seeking reasons why he had resolved to take upon himself an engagement, almost before he had been besought to do so, by which he must cause this poor unfortunate unknown girl to suffer so much, without any hatred or fear on his part, but merely to serve this Don Rodrigo; but no, he did not succeed in finding any reasons which at this moment appeared to him of sufficient importance to excuse the deed; nay, he could scarcely explain to himself how he had been induced to form such an engagement. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n194" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13924" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13968">This desire, rather than this deliberation, had been an instantaneous movement of the soul, obedient to ancient and habitual sentiments; it was a consequence of a thousand deeds which had preceded it, and the tormenting self-examiner, in order to account to himself for a single action, found himself engaged in an examination of his whole life. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n195" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_13969" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14013">On looking back from year to year, from engagement to engagement, from murder to murder, from villany to villany, each action appeared to his new and now conscious soul separated from the sentiments which at the time had caused him to desire and perform it; each action appeared in its true monstrous shape, a shape which these sentiments had not then allowed him to perceive. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n196" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14014" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14034">All these deeds were his own; they formed the whole of his life. The horror of this thought, suggested by each of these images and connected with all, at length became despair. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n197" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14035" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14089">He started up furiously in his bed, and grasped wildly at the neighbouring wall, seized a pistol, and—at the very moment of ending a life which was become insupportable, his thoughts, surprised by a terror, by a disquiet, carried him into the time which would continue to flow on after his death. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n198" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14090" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14124">He imagined to himself, with horror, his disfigured lifeless corpse in the power of the most vile of human beings; he pictured the surprise, the confusion, which would reign in the castle the day following, how every thing would be in an uproar; he, without strength, without voice, thrown Heaven knows where! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n199" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14125" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14140">He imagined the conversations which would take place there, in the neighbourhood, afar off, and the joy of his enemies! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n200" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14141" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14179">The very gloom and silence made death seem more sad, more fearful; it seemed to him he should not have hesitated had it been day, had he been in the open air, among people, to have thrown himself into a river and expired. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n201" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14180" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14252">Absorbed in these tormenting contemplations, he continued, with a convulsive strength of his thumb, to raise and lower the cock of his pistol, when suddenly another thought presented itself to his mind. "If this other life of which they have told me when a boy, of which they always speak as though it were a certain thing; if after all there should be no such life? if it should be an invention of the priests? what then am I doing? Why should I die? what then matters what I have done? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n202" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14253" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14285">It is a foolish thing, my—— But if there should really be another life?" But, together with this doubt, he was seized with a blacker and more terrible despair, from which he could not escape even by death. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="68">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n203" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14286" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14299">He let fall his weapon, and remained, his hands grasped in his hair, trembling, and his teeth chattering. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n204" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14300" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14352">Suddenly, there flashed across his mind those words which he had heard repeated again and again, but a short time before—"God pardons so much for one deed of mercy!" And these words did not return to his remembrance with that accent of humble prayer in which they were spoken, but with a sound full of authority, which suggested a far-off hope. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n205" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14353" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14402">This was a moment of relief: he removed his hands from his temples, and, resting in a more composed attitude, saw in his mind's eye the one who had spoken these words; he saw her not as his prisoner, not as a supplicant, but in the attitude of one who dispenses pardon and consolation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n206" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14403" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14449">He awaited anxiously the day, that he might hasten and liberate her, that he might hear from her mouth other words of consolation and life; he imagined himself conducting her to her mother. "And then? what shall I do to-morrow, the rest of the day? What shall I do the day after to-morrow, and the day after that? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n207" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14450" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14459">And then the night! The night, which will return in twelve hours. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n208" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14460" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14487">Oh, the night! No, no; no night — — —! And then, sunk in the painful void of the future, he sought in vain an employment for his time — a way to pass his days and his nights. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n209" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14488" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14562">Now he thought of abandoning his castle and going to some far-off country where no one would know him, not even by name; but he felt that he should be always with himself: now there arose within him an indistinct hope that he should recover his old courage, his old will, and that this was merely like a delirium which would pass away; now he dreaded the day, which should exhibit him to his household thus miserably changed; now he sighed for it, as though it would bring light to his clouded mind. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="69">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n210" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14563" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14598">And, behold! precisely at the dawn of day, a few moments after Lucia had fallen asleep, whilst he was seated thus immoveable in his bed, there reached his ear a confused sound, but yet, at the same time, a sound full of an indescribable joy! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n211" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14599" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14628">He listened attentively, and recognised the joyous pealing of bells from some distant festival; and then, after a few moments, the echo of the mountain, which repeated faintly the harmony, and mingled itself with it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n212" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14629" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14673">Soon he heard another peal more near, now another. "What merriment is this? What have these people to rejoice about?" He sprang from this couch of thorns, half dressed, ran to open a window, and looked forth. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="70">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n213" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14674" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14780">The mountains were half veiled in mist, the heaven was rather one ash-coloured cloud than a clouded heaven, but by the dawn, which was breaking, people were to be distinguished on the road in the bottom of the valley, some hastening on, some issuing forth from their houses, all bending their steps to the same point, towards the mouth of the valley, to the right of the castle, all arrayed in their holiday garb, and all moving forward with an extraordinary alacrity. "What the devil are these people about? What is there joyous in this cursed country? Whither is all this mob going?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="71">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n214" type="comm" status="insertion">And he called to a confidential bravo who slept in an adjoining chamber, and inquired the cause of all this movement. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n215" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14781" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14792">He, however, knew no more than his master, but replied that he would go and procure information. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n216" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14793" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14803">The Signor remained, leaning out of the window, intently watching the moving spectacle. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n217" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14804" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14840">There were men, women, children, in companies or alone; here one joining himself to another who was gone on before, they would travel on in company; or another issuing forth from his house would unite himself to the first who came up, and they also would proceed together like friends who met by appointment. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n218" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14841" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14884">Their action plainly indicated a common haste and joy, and the sound of these bells more or less distant, not always in unison, yet always agreeable, seemed almost like the voice of these actions, and the spirit of their words, which could not mount thus high. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap21-n219" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14885" targetEnd="quarantana/cap21.xml#c21_14908">He gazed, and gazed, and there arose within his heart something more than curiosity, to know what thing it might be which could communicate an equal transport to so many different people. </note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>