<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CHAPTER XXII.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>1845</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed Lovers: a Milanese Story of the Seventeenth Century. With The Column of Infamy by Alessandro Manzoni. In Three Volumes</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
          <date>1845</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Henry Francis C. Logan</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="English_1845_cap22">
        <p n="1">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10058">SHORTLY afterwards the bravo came, and related that the day before, Cardinal Federigo Borromeo, archbishop of Milan, had arrived at —, and was to stay there the whole of this day; that the news of this, spreading throughout the neighbourhood on the evening of his arrival, had excited the people to go and see this celebrated man; and that the bells were now being rung as much for joy as to give notice of this event to the inhabitants. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10059" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10074">The Signor, left alone, continued to gaze into the valley still more thoughtfully. "All this for a man!" thought he. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10075" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10094">"All eager, all happy, to see a man! and yet every one of these beings has his demon which torments him! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10095" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10110">But not one, not one of them, has such a demon as mine! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10111" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10117">What is there about this man to make so many people happy? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10118" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10131">Some money which he will distribute, by chance — But they do not all go to receive alms. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10132" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10153">Well, some signs made in the air, some words — Oh, if he had only for me the words which could console! if — Why should I not go? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10154" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10155">Why not? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10156" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10166">I will go, I will go; and I will speak to him, alone I will speak with him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10167" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10174">What shall I say to him? that which, that which — I will hear what he can say, this man!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="2">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10175" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10269">Having thus hurriedly formed his resolution, he finished dressing himself in all haste, arraying himself in one of his coats which had something of a military cut; he took the pistol which remained lying on his bed, and attached it to his girdle on one side; on the other he thrust a second pistol, which he took from a nail in the wall; placed in the same girdle his dagger, and then having removed from the wall a carabine, almost as famous as himself, he slung it crosswise over his shoulder; then took his hat, and issued forth from his chamber. He proceeded first of all to the room where he had left Lucia. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10270" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10286">Having placed his carabine in an angle near the door, he knocked, letting his voice be heard at the same time. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10287" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10298">The old woman descended from her bed in one spring, and ran to open the door. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10299" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10315">The Signor having entered, glared round the room, and saw Lucia, where she lay quietly in her corner. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="3">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10316" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10329">"Does she sleep?" he demanded in an under-tone of the old woman; "does she sleep there? Were these the orders I gave, wretched woman!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="4">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10330" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10347">"I have done every thing possible," returned the old creature, "but she would not eat, she would not come—" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="5">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10348" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10377">"Let her sleep in peace; take care not to disturb her; and when she wakes— Marta shall be in the neighbouring room, and thou must send her for every thing this poor girl may demand. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10378" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10401">When she wakes, tell her that I— that the master has gone out for a short time, that he will return, and that — he will do all that she desires." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="6">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10402" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10458">The old woman remained quite stupified, thinking to herself, "this must be some princess!" The Signor went forth, took his carabine again, sent Marta to wait in the antechamber, sent the first bravo he met, to keep guard; so that no one but this woman should set foot within the chamber; and then issuing out of the castle, with a hasty step he commenced the descent. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="8">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10459" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10489">The MS. does not say how far it was from the castle to the village where was the Cardinal; but judging from the facts which we have to relate, it could not be farther than a long walk. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10490" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10528">This, however, could not be inferred alone from the great concourse of villagers, and even of people living at a greater distance, which hastened to this hamlet; for we find in the histories of those times that people came in crowds the distance of twenty miles, and even farther, to see Federigo. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="9">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10529" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10575">The braves, who met the Unknown upon the ascent, stopped respectfully as their lord passed, waiting to receive any orders he might choose to give them, or to see whether he would take them with him upon any expedition, and they knew not what to think of his air, and the glance with which he returned their salutations. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="10">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10576" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10591">When he arrived on the public way, what astonished the passers by was to see him without attendants. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10592" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10611">Every one made way for him, a way which would have sufficed for the attendants also, and all respectfully raised their hats. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10612" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10632">When he arrived at the village, he encountered a great crowd; but his name quickly passed from mouth to mouth, and the crowd opened for him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10633" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10652">He accosted a man, and demanded where the Cardinal was: "In the Curate's house," he replied, bowed, and pointed out where the house stood. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10653" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10673">The Signor followed the direction, and entered a small court-yard, where were many priests, who all gazed at him with an astonished and suspicious attention. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10674" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10689">He saw opposite to him an open door, which led into a small parlour where many other priests were congregated. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10690" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10714">He removed his carabine, and placed it in a corner; then he entered the parlour; but here again were glances, whisperings, a name repeated, and silence. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10715" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10730">He then, turning to one of the company, asked where was the Cardinal, and said he desired to speak with him. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="11">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10731" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10769">"I am a stranger," replied the one whom he had accosted, and casting a glance around, he called the cross-bearer, who was at this moment standing in a corner of the room, saying in a low voice to one of his companions; "this man? this famous man here? What has this man to do here? Make way!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10770" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10841">However at this summons, which resounded through the general silence, he was obliged to come forward; he bowed himself before the Unknown, stood to hear his will, raised his eyes with a restless curiosity to this awful countenance, suddenly lowered them again, remained silent a moment, and then said, or rather stammered, "I do not know whether my illustrious Signor— at this moment — is — may — can — But I will go and see—" and he went much against his will to carry this embassy into the neighboring apartment where the Cardinal was. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="12">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10842" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10892">At this place in our history we cannot do less than pause a short time, like a traveller who, wearied and exhausted by a long journey through an arid and savage country, refreshes himself, and loses a little time under the shadow of a fine tree, reposing himself upon the grass, near to a spring of living water. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10893" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10942">We have here encountered a personage whose name and memory, let them be presented to the mind at whatever time they may, refresh it with a calm emotion of reverence, and with an agreeable sentiment of sympathy; and now, how much the more is this the case after so many images of pain, after the contemplation of so much vexatious ill-nature! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10943" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10972">It is absolutely necessary that we expend a few words upon this personage; let those who do not care to hear them, or who are desirous to proceed with our history, pass over to the following chapter. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="13">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10973" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11010">Federigo Borromeo, born in 1564, was one of those men so rare in all times, who have employed a high genius, all the resources of a large fortune, all the advantages of a privileged condition and a constant application, in the search after good, and in the exercise of it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11011" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11040">His life is like a rivulet, which issuing limpid from the rock, without ever pausing or troubling itself during its long course through many territories, pours itself still limpid into the river. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11041" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11092">In the midst of pleasures and of pomp, he fixed attention from his earliest childhood to those words of self-denial and humility, to those maxims regarding the vanity of pleasure and the injustice of pride, regarding true dignity and true good, maxims which, whether understood or not by the heart, are transmitted from generation to generation in the most elementary instruction of religion. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11093" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11154">He paid attention, I say, to these words; he regarded them as serious, tried them, and found them true; he saw therefore that the other words and maxims which were opposed, and which were also transmitted from generation to generation with the same certainty, and often by the same lips, could not be true; and he proposed to choose as the rule of his actions and thoughts, those which were true. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11155" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11196">Persuaded that life is not destined to be a burthen for the many and a holiday for the few, but that it is an employment for all, of which every one must render an account, he began as a child to consider how he might render his useful and holy. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="14">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11197" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11228">In the year 1580, he declared his resolution of dedicating himself to the ministry, and received the habit from his cousin Carlo, whom the voice of fame had already universally proclaimed a saint. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11229" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11284">Shortly after this he entered the college founded by this same cousin in Pavia, and which still bears the name of their family; and there applying himself assiduously to the occupations which he found prescribed, he imposed upon himself two others by his own free will, and these were, teaching the Christian religion to the poorest and most ignorant of the people, and visiting, serving, consoling, and succouring the infirm. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11285" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11335">He took advantage of the authority which he enjoyed in this place, to induce his companions to second him in works like these; he possessed in every thing which was honest and profitable a pre-eminence which his personal endowments would have been sufficient to give him had he been weak by position. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11336" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11358">The advantages of another kind, which this position would have been able to procure him, he not only left unsought for, but even studiously avoided. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11359" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11384">He kept a table which might be sooner called poor than frugal, and clothed himself in a mean rather than simple garment; and, in fact, the whole tenor of his life and behaviour was equally unassuming. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11385" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11405">But he never once thought of changing his mode of life, however much some of his relatives might exclaim and lament that he thus degraded the dignity of the house. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11406" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11504">He had to sustain another warfare, and this, with his instructors, who by stealth sought to confer upon him marks of distinction, something, in short, which should distinguish him from others and cause him to figure as the prince of the place; whether it was that they believed that in the long run they should please him by this means, whether they were induced by that servile love which rejoices and aggrandizes itself in the splendour of others, or whether they belonged to that prudential class who, starting back in horror at virtue as well as vice, always preach that perfection is found between the two extremes, and fix the middle at the precise point where they themselves have arrived and are comfortably stationed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11505" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11525">Federigo did not allow himself to be conquered by these temptations, he even blamed those who had tempted him, and all this in his earliest youth. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="15">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11526" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11629">That Federigo, during the lifetime of the Cardinal Carlo, his elder by six-and-twenty years, in so grave and solemn a presence, thus breathing holiness and recalling so many holy works, to which, had this been needed, the constant and fervent obsequiousness of the by-standers would have added authority; that Federigo, I say, as child and youth, should endeavour to conform himself to the behaviour and opinions of such a superior, is certainly not to be wondered at; but it is certainly a remarkable thing, that, after the death of this pious man, no one could ever perceive that Federigo, then twenty years of age, ever stood in need of a guide or a censor. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11630" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11691">The increasing fame of his genius, of his doctrine and piety, his parentage, and the interest of more than one powerful Cardinal, his very name to which Carlo had annexed in every mind an idea of holiness and pre-eminence, all that which ought, and all that which can, conduct men to ecclesiastical dignities, concurred in prognosticating such for him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11692" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11762">But he, persuaded in his heart of what no one who professes Christianity can deny with his mouth, that a man can have no just superiority over other men, except by devoting himself to their service, dreaded all ecclesiastical dignities, and sought to avoid them; this was most certainly not in order to fly the obligation of serving others, for few lives were so constantly employed in such duties as his, but because he did not esteem himself sufficiently worthy or capable of filling these high and dangerous offices. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11763" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11780">It was on this account, therefore, that, when Clement VIII. proposed to him in the year 1595 the Archbishoprick of Milan, he appeared greatly disturbed, and refused it without hesitation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11781" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11787">He afterwards, however, yielded, at the express command of the Pope. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="16">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11788" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11823">Such demonstrations, as every one knows, are neither difficult nor rare. And hypocrisy requires no greater exertion of talent to make them, than raillery to deride them upon every occasion. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11824" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11836">But do they on this account cease to be the natural expressions of a virtuous and wise sentiment? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11837" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11880">Life is the touchstone of the words; and words which express such a sentiment, even should they pass over the lips of all the impostors and jesters in the world, will always be beautiful, are they preceded and followed by a life of disinterestedness and sacrifice. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="17">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11881" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11913">Federigo, when archbishop, made it his peculiar study never to employ for himself, riches, time, his office, anything connected with himself, in short, unless it were strictly necessary. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11914" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11936">He said, as all say indeed, that the ecclesiastical revenues are the patrimony of the poor; how he put this maxim into practice, we shall see. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11937" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12004">He desired that his own expenses and those of his domestics should be calculated; and, being informed that they amounted to six hundred scudi (the name scudo was then given to that gold coin which, retaining the same weight, was afterwards called Zecchino), he commanded that such a sum should be every year reckoned out of his private funds, and placed with the Archbishop's revenue, not considering it was lawful for so rich a man as himself to live upon this patrimony. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12005" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12053">Of his own, he was such a penurious and careful economist for himself, that he was careful never to cast off a garment until it was entirely worn out; he joined to this spirit of simplicity, as is noticed by contemporary writers, an exquisite cleanliness; two habits very worthy of notice in that filthy and ostentatious age. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12054" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12091">In the same spirit, in order that nothing should be lost of his frugal table, he bestowed the remains upon a hospital of the poor; and one of these wretched beings, by his order, entered every day the dining-hall to collect all that remained. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12092" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12190">These petty cases might perhaps lead us to imagine his was a niggardly, wretched, anxious sort of virtue, his a mind in love with minutiae, incapable of elevated design, were it not for this Biblioteca Ambrosiana, which still exists, the idea of which Federigo conceived with such extreme magnificence, and erected at such expense. To furnish this library with books and manuscripts, beside the present he made of those which he had himself collected with great care and expense; he sent eight men, the most learned and clever he could meet with, to purchase books in Italy, France, Spain, Germany, Flanders, in Greece, Lebanon, and Jerusalem. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12191" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12201">He succeeded in collecting about thirty thousand printed works, and forty thousand manuscripts. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n64" type="comm" status="insertion">He united to this library a college of doctors. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12202" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12317">There were nine of them who received pensions from him as long as he should live; afterwards, the ordinary revenues, not sufficing for this expense, the number was reduced to two. Their office was to cultivate various branches of learning, theology, history, polite literature, ecclesiastical antiquities, and the Oriental languages, each one being obliged to publish some work upon the materials assigned him,—to this also he united a college, called by him the Trilingue, for the study of the Greek, Latin, and Italian languages. This was a college where pupils were instructed in these sciences and languages, in order some day to teach in their turn. To this college was added also a printing establishment for the Oriental languages,—that is, of the Hebrew, Chaldee, the Arabian, the Persian, and the Armenian; a gallery of paintings, another of statuary, and a school for the three principal arts of design. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12318" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12369">For the latter, he could easily find professors already educated; we have seen how much trouble the search after books and manuscripts had given him; and most difficult, certainly, must it have been to discover the types for these languages, then much less cultivated in Europe than at the present day; and perhaps to find men who understood them would be the most difficult of all. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12370" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12424">Suffice it to say that, of these nine doctors, eight had been chosen from among the young pupils of the seminary; and from this circumstance, one can easily infer what judgment was passed upon the completed studies and achieved reputations of that time; a judgment which appears to have been similar to the one posterity seems to have pronounced upon them, by casting them both into forgetfulness. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12425" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12465">Among the rules which he established for the use and government of the library is to be observed a desire for perpetual usefulness, not alone beautiful in itself, but in many instances wise and noble, and far beyond the ideas and general customs of the time. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12466" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12533">He ordered the librarian to maintain a correspondence with the most learned men of Europe, so as to receive information from them regarding the state of the sciences, to gain intelligence of the best books which appeared in every branch, and to procure them; he ordered also that all citizens or foreigners shall have sufficient time and opportunity given them to make use of the books. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12534" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12554">An intention such as this will appear to every one now only natural and consonant with the foundation of a library; in those days, however, it was not. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12555" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12680">And in a history of the Ambrosian Library, written (with the construction and usual elegance of the century) by a Pierpaolo Bosca, who was librarian after the death of Federigo, it is expressly noticed as a singular thing that in this library, founded by a private individual, and almost entirely at his own expense, the books were exposed to the public view, brought to whoever asked for them, that even seats to sit upon were offered to the public, with paper, pens, and ink, to take notes; whilst in all the other great Italian libraries, not only were the books invisible, but were locked up in cupboards, whence they never were removed, unless through especial favour of the librarians, who would perhaps allow these to be seen for a moment; but as for giving the public an opportunity of studying, there was not yet even an idea of it! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12681" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12706">To enrich libraries after this manner was only to remove books from common use; one of those kinds of cultivation, of which there were at that time, and of which there always are so many, a cultivation which renders the field only more sterile. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="18">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12707" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12764">Do not demand what have been the effects of this foundation of Borromeo upon public instruction. It would be easy to demonstrate in two phrases, after the manner people demonstrate, that the effects were miraculous, or that they had no effect. To search and explain to a certain point what really the effects have been, would be a very fatiguing thing, of but little use, and out of place. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12765" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12849">But think what a generous, what a wise, what a benevolent, what a persevering lover of human amendment, must have been the one who desired such a thing, desired it after this manner, and executed it in the midst of murmurs of: "What does it matter?—Are there no other things to think about?—What a fine invention!" and similar exclamations, which would certainly be more numerous than the scudi spent by him upon the undertaking; and these were five hundred thousand. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="19">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12850" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12906">To pronounce such a man extremely beneficent and liberal, it would not be necessary that he should spend a deal of money in immediate succour of the poor; but yet there are many people who think that expenses of this kind, and I will say expenses of all kinds, are the best and most useful alms. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12907" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12927">Federigo, however, considered alms, properly bestowed, a principal duty; and here, as in every thing else, his deeds were consistent with his opinions. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12928" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12975">His life was a constant almsgiving to the poor; and with reference to this famine, of which our history has already spoken, we shall have occasion to relate some instances of this, which will shew what wisdom and gentleness he knew how to employ in his liberality. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12976" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12994">We will only relate a single example of generosity from the numerous ones his biographers have recorded. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12995" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13053">Having learned that a noble was employing artifice and force to persuade one of his daughters to turn nun, who desired rather to marry, he sent for the father; and having drawn from his mouth the confession that the real motive for this torture was that he had not four thousand scudi, which according to him, he must have to marry his daughter respectably, he endowed her with the four thousand scudi. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13054" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13082">Perhaps to some of my readers this may appear an excessive liberality, a liberality not well considered, too condescending towards the silly caprices of a proud father; and that four thousand scudi might have been better employed in a hundred ways. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13083" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13137">To this we have nothing to reply, except that it would be desirable to see often excesses of a virtue, thus free from the ruling opinions of the age (every age has its own), thus independent of the general tendency, as, in this instance, was that which induced a man to give four thousand scudi, because a girl would not turn nun. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="20">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13138" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13153">The inexhaustible charity of this man shone forth, not alone in his deeds, but also in the whole of his behaviour. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13154" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13184">Easy of access, he believed it especially his duty to shew a pleasant countenance, an affectionate courtesy to those who are called the lower class; all the more so, as they meet with but little courtesy in this world. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13185" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13212">And here even he had to combat with gentlemen of the *ne quid nimis*, who would have had him keep within bounds, that is within their bounds. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13213" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13286">One day, during one of his visits in a wild and mountainous region, Federigo was instructing some poor children, and in the midst of his questions and instruction, he lovingly caressed them, when one of these gentlemen advised him to take better heed how he caressed these children, as they were too filthy and loathsome; now, we must suppose that either this good man, this Federigo, had not sense sufficient to make such a discovery, or not penetration enough to discover by himself this clever reason. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13287" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13328">Such is, at certain times, the misfortune of men full of goodness, that whilst there are found very few persons who inform them of their failings, courageous people are not wanting to reprimand them for their good deeds. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13329" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13356">But the good Bishop replied, not however without a certain resentment, "These are souls intrusted to me; they will, perhaps, never again see my countenance, and you wish me not to embrace them!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="21">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13357" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13396">But resentment was, however, very rare in him, who was admired for the gentleness of his temper, for an imperturbable calm, which one would have attributed to an extraordinarily happy temperament; but this was only the effect of constant discipline upon a warm resentful nature. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13397" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13427">If sometimes he shewed himself severe, even harsh, it was with the inferior clergy whom he discovered guilty of avarice, of neglect, or of other vices diametrically opposed to the spirit of their noble ministry. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13428" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13469">But in every thing regarding his own interest, or his own temporal glory, he never exhibited the slightest sign of joy or regret, of ardour or agitation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13470" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13540">Not alone did he carry away with him, from many conclaves which he had attended, the reputation of never having aspired to that post so much desired by ambition, and so terrible to piety; but once, when one of his colleagues who had considerable influence came to offer him his vote and the votes of his faction—it is an ugly word, but it was then in use—Federigo refused such a proposition in such a manner that the other changed his mind, and turned his steps elsewhere. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13541" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13553">This same modesty, this aversion to pre-eminence, shewed themselves equally in the more common events of his life. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13554" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13599">Attentive and indefatigable in persuading and governing, where he felt that it was his duty so to do, he always carefully avoided busying himself in the affairs of others: thus he excused himself with all his might when his intervention was sought; a discretion and modesty not common, as every one knows, in men zealous for good; and such a one was Federigo. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="22">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13600" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13630">If we allowed ourselves the pleasure of collecting all the notable traits in his character, there would most certainly result a singular complication of merits, apparently opposed to each other, and certainly rarely to be found existing together. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13631" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13678">However, we must not omit to notice one other singularity in this beautiful life. Filled as this life was with activity, important cares, his religious duties, instruction, audiences, visits to his diocese, journeys, controversies; not alone did study form a portion, but a portion which would have been sufficient for any literary man by profession. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13679" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13697">And, in fact, besides so many other different titles of praise. Federigo even enjoyed among his contemporaries the title of a learned man. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="23">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13698" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13738">We must not however dissimulate that he held with a firm persuasion, and maintained in practice, with great constancy, opinions, which at the present day would sooner appear to every one strange, than ill-founded; I will say, even to those who might have a great desire to find them good. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13739" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13795">Whoever should desire to defend him in this respect, would have the very current and accepted excuse,—that these were the errors of the time rather than his own; an excuse, which for certain things, and when it is drawn from a particular examination of facts, may have some value; but which applied nakedly and foolishly, as is commonly done, signifies properly nothing. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13796" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13844">And, therefore, not wishing to solve with simple words this complicated question, neither desiring too much to lengthen this episode, we will desist from exposing them; contenting ourselves with having thus hastily hinted, that in a man so admirable a compound of good qualities, every thing, however, was not equally perfect; so that it may not appear that we have wished to write his funeral oration. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="24">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13845" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13872">It is not certainly doing our readers injustice to suppose that some one among them asks, whether, with all this genius and all this study, the Cardinal has not left some monument behind him? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13873" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13875">Whether he has left any! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13876" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13938">About a hundred are the works of his which remain—large and small, Latin and Italian, printed and in manuscript, all preserved in the library which he founded; moral treatises, orations, dissertations on history and on antiquity, both sacred and profane, on literature, on the fine arts, and on other subjects. And how happens it, the reader will exclaim, that so many works are thus forgotten, or at least so little known, so little inquired after? </note>
        </p>
        <p n="25">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13939" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_14015">How happens it, with so much genius, so much study, so much practical knowledge of men and things, with so much meditation, with such a passion for the good and beautiful, with so much candour of soul, with so many other qualities which make great authors, that this man has not, among a hundred volumes, left behind him one of those which are considered superior even by people who do not entirely approve them, and the titles of which are known by those who do not read the works themselves? </note>
        </p>
        <p n="26">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_14016" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_14089">The question is reasonable, doubtless, and the subject a very interesting one; but the causes of this phenomenon will be discovered in the observation of many general facts; and when they are discovered, will lead to the explanation of other similar phenomena; but these explanations would be many and prolix, and then, if they should not please you, if they should make you turn up your nose? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap22-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_14090" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_14121">Therefore it will be better that we resume the thread of our history, and instead of longer gossiping about this man, that we, with the guidance of our author, hasten to see him act. </note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>