<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CHAPTER XXVII.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>1845</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed Lovers: a Milanese Story of the Seventeenth Century. With The Column of Infamy by Alessandro Manzoni. In Three Volumes</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
          <date>1845</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Henry Francis C. Logan</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="English_1845_cap27">
        <p n="1">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10048">More than once we have had occasion to mention the war which then raged, regarding the succession to the estates of the Duke Vincenzo Gonzaga, the second of that name; but this has always been in great haste, so that we have never been able to give more than a slight intimation of it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10049" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10062">Now, however, for the proper understanding of our narrative, it is necessary that we should enter more into detail. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10063" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10108">These are events which all those who are acquainted with history will be acquainted with; but nevertheless, from a just appreciation of our own merit, we can only suppose that this work will fall into the hands of the ignorant, therefore it will not be amiss if we should here give a smattering of this knowledge to those who may stand in need of it. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="2">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10109" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10162">We have already said, that at the death of this Duke, the nearest heir, Carlo Gonzaga, head of a younger branch transplanted into France, where he possessed the duchies of Nivers and Rhetel, had taken possession of Mantua, and we may now add of Monferrat; our precipitation caused us to omit this latter circumstance. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10163" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10231">The Spanish court desired, at any price, to exclude the new prince from these two fiefs, and being obliged to discover some reason in order to exclude him (for wars commenced without any reason at all would be too unjust), had sided with those who desired another Gonzaga, Ferrante, Prince of Guastalla, to rule in Mantua; and Carlo Emanuele I, Duke of Savoy, and Margherita Gonzaga, dowager Duchess of Lorraine, to reign in Monferrat. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10232" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10325">Don Gonzalo, who was of the same family as the great captain whose name he bore, who had already made war in Flanders, and who, being desirous beyond measure to direct a war in Italy, was perhaps the one who most fomented the discord. By interpreting the intentions and exceeding the orders of the minister, he had concluded a treaty of invasion and division of Monferrat; and having easily obtained its ratification by the Count-Duke, persuading him that the acquisition of Casale, which was the best defended point in the portion granted to the King of Spain, was extremely easy; had, nevertheless, protested in the name of his sovereign, that he would occupy this country only as a trust, until the Emperor's decision should be made known. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10326" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10390">The Emperor, however, partly by the intervention of others, partly influenced by his own private reasons, had meanwhile refused the investiture to the new Duke, and intimated to him that he should leave in sequestration the estates which caused this controversy; and promised that then, having heard both sides of the question, he would bestow them upon the one who had the strongest right. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10391" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10399">These were conditions to which the Duke of Nevers would not agree. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="3">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10400" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10420">The Duke had powerful friends; these were the Cardinal Richelieu, the Venetian Senators, and the Pope, who was, as we have already said, Urban VIII. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10421" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10458">But the Cardinal, entirely absorbed in the siege of Rochelle and in a war with England, and thwarted by the Queen-mother Maria de Medici, who from certain reasons of her own was opposed to the house of Nivers, could only hold out hope to him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10459" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10506">The Venetians would not move, nor even declare themselves, until a French army should have arrived in Italy; and aiding the Duke secretly as well as they could, they merely, with the court of Madrid and the governor of Milan, employed protests, proposals, and exhortations, either pacific or menacing, according as circumstances directed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10507" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10533">The Pope recommended the Duke de Nivers to the kindness of his friends,—he interceded for him with his adversaries, and formed projects of accommodation; but he would hear nothing of bringing troops into the field. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="4">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10534" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10546">Thus the two powers allied for offensive operations, could all the more securely commence their concerted enterprise. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10547" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10585">The Duke of Savoy had entered that part of Monferrat which had been assigned him; Don Gonzalo had with great good-will laid siege to Casale; but he had not found in it all the satisfaction which he had imagined: let no one believe that in war all is delight. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10586" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10622">The Court of Spain had not assisted him according to his desires; nay, it even allowed him to stand in need of the most necessary supplies; his ally rendered him only too much assistance; that is, having possessed himself of his own portion, he set about seizing what belonged to the King of Spain. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10623" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10669">Don Gonzalo was more enraged at this than we can give any idea of; but fearing that if he made the slightest noise, this Carlo Emanuele, as active in intrigue and fickle in his machinations as he was valiant, would join France, he was forced to close an eye, swallow his displeasure, and remain silent. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10670" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10754">The siege also went on but badly, was protracted to a great length, and often took a very unfortunate course, either through the resolute, vigilant, and bold conduct of the besiegers, through the smallness of their numbers, or according to some historians, owing to many blunders which Don Gonzalo himself committed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10755" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10769">In the midst of these misfortunes, he received the news of the sedition at Milan, and hastened there in person. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="5">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10770" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10813">There, in the report which was made him, Renzo's flight did not fail to be mentioned; that rebellious flight which had made so much stir, and together with this, the real and supposed circumstances which had caused his arrest; he was also informed that this young man had taken refuge in the territory of Bergamo. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10814" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10820">This circumstance had fixed the attention of Don Gonzalo. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10821" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10884">He had been everywhere informed how much interest the insurrection at Milan had excited in Venice; he had heard how in the beginning they had believed he would be obliged to raise the siege of Casales, and how they still thought he was in great trouble and vexation about it; more especially as, immediately after this event, there arrived intelligence of the raising of the siege of Rochelle, intelligence so much desired by the Senators, and so much dreaded by him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10885" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10930">And very much nettled, both in his character as man and politician, that these Signors should have such an opinion of him, he watched every occasion by which he could, by means of induction, persuade them that he had lost none of his old confidence; for merely to say, "I am not afraid," is as good as saying nothing at all. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10931" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11016">A good means to appear dauntless, is to act displeasure, to complain, and expostulate. And the Venetian ambassador having presented himself before Don Gonzalo to pay his compliments, and at the same time to read in the great man's countenance and mien what was passing within, Don Gonzalo, after having spoken of the tumult very slightly, and like a man who has already repaired every thing, — availed himself of poor Renzo's reception in the Bergamascan territory, to gratify his own private ends, as we have already seen. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11017" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11106">After this time he no longer occupied himself about an affair so very unimportant, and which, as far as himself was concerned, he considered already terminated: and when a short time afterwards the reply reached him in the camp before Casale, whither he had returned, and where his mind was occupied with quite other thoughts, he raised and shook his head from side to side, like a silkworm which seeks a mulberry leaf; he paused a moment to recall the circumstance, of which there only remained a shadowy remembrance; recalled the affair, had a fugitive and confused idea of the personage, passed on to some other circumstance, and thought no more of the young man. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="6">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11107" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11143">But Renzo, who was far from suspecting all this, had for a long time no other thought, or rather we should say, no other study, than to live concealed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11144" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11163">We leave you to imagine whether he did not ardently desire to send intelligence of himself to the two women, and to receive news of them — but there were two great difficulties in the way. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11164" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11234">One was, that he should have been obliged to take a secretary into his confidence, for the poor fellow did not know how to write, nor even to read in the proper sense of the word. When asked whether he could read, as you may perhaps recollect was once the case when with the Doctor Azzecca-Garbughli, he had replied "yes," but this was no boast; the fact was, he could read what was printed, when he took his time; to read what was written, was something quite different. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11235" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11286">He would have been, therefore, obliged to take a third person into his confidence, and intrust him with the knowledge of a secret thus important; and in those times it was not so easy to find a man who could use the pen, and who could yet be confided in; and more especially was this the case in a place where he had no old friends. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11287" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11324">The other difficulty was to find a messenger; a man who should be going precisely to that part of the country, who would take charge of the letter, and who would undertake to deliver it; these were all things very difficult to find united in one man. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="7">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11325" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11333">At length, having inquired again and again, he found a man who could write for him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11334" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11360">But not knowing whether the women were still at Monza, or where they were, he thought it best to inclose the intended letter for Agnese in one directed to Father Cristoforo. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11361" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11414">The writer of the letter engaged also to despatch it, and, in fact, consigned it into the hands of a man who was to pass not far from Pescarenico; the man left it with many instructions in an hostel on the road, at the nearest point to Pescarenico; the packet, being directed to a convent, arrived there; but it has never been known what became of it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11415" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11444">Renzo, seeing that no reply arrived, had another letter written pretty much like the first, and inclosed it in another addressed to a friend and relation of his at Lecco. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11445" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11460">Another courier was sought for and found; this time the letter reached the one to whom it was directed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11461" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11508">Agnese hastened to Maggianico, and there had it read and explained by this cousin of hers, Alessio; concerted with him a reply, which he put upon paper; and discovered the means by which to send it to Antonio Rivolta at his place of abode: but all this did not take place as speedily as we relate it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11509" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11515">Renzo received the reply, and had another letter written. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11516" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11536">In short, they established between them a correspondence, neither regular nor rapid, but which was nevertheless continued at intervals. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="8">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11537" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11568">But in order to have an idea of this correspondence it is necessary to know how things went on then, or even how things go on at the present time; for in this particular, I imagine, there will be little or no change. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="9">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11569" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11627">The peasant who does not know how to write, and who yet stands in need of having something written, applies to some one who understands the art, selecting this one from among those of his own condition, because he is either afraid of, or places little confidence in those above him. He informs his amanuensis, with more or less order and perspicuity, of what has already happened; and explains in the same manner that which he desires to have written. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11628" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11708">The man of letters understands part, guesses part, gives some advice, proposes some change, and says, "Leave it to me." He takes his pen, translates as well as he can the thoughts of the other into written language, corrects them, improves them, overcharges them, nay, even sometimes omits them, as may appear to him the best; for—and there is no remedy for this—a man who knows more than other people, will not be a mere tool in their hands; and therefore, when he occupies himself with other people's affairs, he desires that they shall be managed a little after his own manner. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11709" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11741">But spite of this, the writer does not always succeed in saying all that he would like to say; sometimes he happens to say quite the contrary: but this even occurs to us who write for the press. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11742" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11774">When the letter, thus composed, reaches the hand of the correspondent, who also is but little accustomed to read writing, he carries it to another learned man of the same calibre, who reads and explains it to him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11775" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11811">Questions arise regarding the manner of understanding it: for the interested party, founding conjectures upon events that have gone before, maintains that certain words mean one thing; and the learned man, insisting upon the practice which he has in style, maintains that they signify another. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11812" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11844">At length the one who knows nothing, must place himself in the hands of the one who knows something, and intrusts him with the reply; which, composed in the same manner, will be most likely subjected to a similar interpretation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11845" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11934">And should it happen that the subject of the correspondence be somewhat important, does it concern secret affairs, which ought not to be confided to a third person, and therefore through fear of the letter's falling into improper hands be somewhat dubiously expressed, the two parties end by mutually agreeing as well as the scholars who in former times had disputed during four hours, regarding some point of ethics. We do not choose a simile from existing things, for fear we should come in for a heavy chastisement. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="10">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11935" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11947">Now the situation of our two correspondents was precisely such as we have described. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11948" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11958">The first letter written in Renzo's name contained a deal of matter. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11959" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12030">After an account of his flight, much more concise doubtless, but also much worse arranged than the one you have read, there followed a narration of the present state of his circumstances, of which Agnese and her interrogator were far from gaining a clear or perfect idea. He spoke of secret intelligence, of changing his name. He was in safety; but he was obliged to keep himself concealed; things in themselves not over and above familiar to their minds, and which were related in the letter somewhat enigmatically. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12031" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12055">There were also affectionate and impassioned inquiries regarding Lucia's situation, together with obscure and sorrowful words concerning the reports of her adventures, which had reached even Renzo. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12056" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12085">Finally, there were distant and uncertain hopes, designs for the future and for the present, promises and prayers to preserve their given faith, not to lose either patience or courage, and to await better times. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="11">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12086" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12110">Shortly after this, Agnese found a safe opportunity by which to send Renzo a reply, together with the fifty scudi which Lucia had assigned him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12111" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12154">At the sight of so much gold, Renzo did not know what to think; and with his soul agitated by astonishment and suspense, which were far from being agreeable, he ran in haste to seek his secretary, to beg him to interpret the letter, and give him the key to this strange mystery. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="12">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12155" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12223">In the letter, Agnese's secretary, after some complaints about the want of clearness in his former communication, went on to relate, with about equal clearness, the terrible history of this person—so he designates the Unknown—and here he explains the meaning of the fifty scudi; he then commenced speaking of the vow, and by means of circumlocution counsels Renzo to calm his mind, and not think anything more about Lucia. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="13">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12224" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12250">Renzo was very near quarrelling with his interpreter; he trembled, he became alarmed; he grew enraged both with what he had understood and with what he had not been able to understand. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12251" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12274">Two or three times he had this terrible epistle read over to him; now he seemed to understand it better, now that became confused which before had appeared clear to him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12275" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12291">And in this delirium of passion, he desired the secretary immediately to take the pen in hand and reply. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12292" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12438">After the strongest expressions which you can imagine of his terror and compassion for Lucia's misfortunes, "Write," he said, "that I do not wish to calm my heart, and that I never will; that this is not advice to be given to a youth such as I; that I will not touch the money; I will keep it, in trust, as a dowry for the young girl; and say that she ought already to be mine; that I will know nothing of this promise, and that I have always heard say the Madonna interests herself in our affairs in order to assist the unhappy, and to plead for them, not to do them evil, and to cause them to break their word; this I have never heard; and say also that this thing cannot be, but that with this money we have enough to commence housekeeping; and that if now our affairs are somewhat perplexed, it is a storm which will pass away." And many other similar things did he say. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="14">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12439" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12455">Agnese received this letter after some time; she had a reply written, and the correspondence continued in the manner which we have described. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="15">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12456" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12507">Lucia, when her mother had, I do not know by what means, sent her the intelligence that Renzo was alive, in safety, and informed of what had happened, experienced a great relief, and desired nothing else, except that he should forget her, or rather that he should endeavour to forget her. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12508" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12530">On her side, a hundred times a day she formed the same resolution with regard to him, and adopted every means by which to accomplish her end. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12531" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12556">She applied herself very assiduously to her work, and strove entirely to occupy herself with it; when the image of Renzo presented itself to her mind, she sought to banish it by prayer. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12557" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12594">But this image, as though through sheer malice, did not generally introduce itself openly, but secretly, concealed by other thoughts, so that the mind did not perceive the image until it had already been sometime there. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12595" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12626">Lucia's thoughts were often with her mother; how could it be otherwise? and the ideal Renzo softly presented himself as third person, as the real one had so many a time done. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12627" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12646">Thus, with all the persons who had figured in the history of her life, in all places, all memories of the past, this ideal personage introduced himself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12647" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12676">And if the poor girl sometimes allowed herself to imagine her future, even there this friend arrived to say, "I, at all events, shall not be there." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12677" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12716">However, if to think no more of him were a desperate undertaking, she succeeded to a certain degree, and this was to think less about him, and less intensely, than her heart would have dictated: she would have succeeded better, however, had she been left alone to her work. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12717" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12740">But there was Donna Pressede, who, on her side, determining to remove him from her soul, found no better expedient than to speak of him very often. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="16">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12741" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12749">"Well," she would say to Lucia, "do you not still think of him?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="17">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12750" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12756">"I do not think of any one," Lucia would reply. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="18">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12757" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12799">Donna Pressede did not content herself with a reply of this kind; she desired deeds and not words, she said; she spoke much upon the usual behaviour of young girls, "who," she said, "when they have once placed in their heart the image of a libertine (and they have all of them this inclination) will never remove it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12800" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12824">But if an honest, reasonable connexion with a worthy man is by any accident broken off, they are speedily resigned; but love for a libertine is an incurable wound." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12825" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12859">And then she began the panegyric of poor Renzo, of this rascal who came to Milan to riot and kill; and she wished to make Lucia confess all the deeds of violence he had committed in his native country. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="19">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12860" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12918">Lucia, in a voice trembling with shame, grief, and with as much anger as her gentle spirit and humble fortune would permit, assured Donna Pressede, and protested, that in his own country this poor youth had never caused himself to be spoken of except in terms of commendation; she only wished, she said, that some one out of that part of the country were there to bear his testimony to what she said. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12919" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12979">Even with regard to his adventures in Milan, of which she had no very clear idea, she defended him, by the knowledge which she had of him and his conduct from his very childhood; she defended him, or at least she proposed to defend him from the pure duty of charity, from love of the truth, or to make use of the exact expression by which she expressed her sentiment, because she was his neighbour. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12980" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13001">But from this very apology did Donna Pressede deduce fresh arguments to prove to Lucia that her heart was still devoted to this worthless man. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13002" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13015">And in truth, in these moments it would not be easy to say how affairs stood. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13016" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13112">The unworthy picture which the old lady drew of the poor youth awoke, as in opposition, more livingly and distinctly in the young girl's mind the image which had so long found a place there; the memories banished by force returned in crowds; Donna Pressede's aversion and scorn recalled so many old reasons for her to esteem and admire him; this blind and violent hatred excited in Lucia's heart a stronger compassion; and who knows how strong in her heart another sentiment might or might not be, a sentiment which, concealed by other feelings, so easily introduces itself into the soul. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13113" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13137">However this might be, on Lucia's side the conversation could never be much prolonged, without the words speedily ending in tears. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="20">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13138" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13192">If Donna Pressede had been actuated to this treatment by inveterate hatred towards Lucia, perhaps these tears might have touched and silenced the good lady; but her words being directed towards a good object, she pursued her discourse without allowing herself to be moved; groans and cries of supplication may avert the sword of an enemy, but not the steel of the surgeon. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13193" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13231">After having well performed her duty for this time, from reproaches she passed on to exhortations and advice, mingling them with some praise, so as to temper the sour with something sweet, and thus better obtain her end, by operating on the soul in all possible ways. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13232" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13277">Assuredly these disputes (which had always pretty nearly the same commencement and termination), left in our good Lucia's heart no feeling of bitterness towards her severe lecturer, who in other things treated her with great gentleness; and even in these sermons, a good intention might be perceived. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13278" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13305">There remained, however, such an awakening of disquiet thoughts and love, that it required much time and much exertion to recall that calmness which she had before enjoyed. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="21">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13306" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13330">It was fortunate for her that she was not the only one whom Donna Pressede desired to benefit. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13331" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13395">Beside the other domestics, who were all of them, according to her, souls which required more or less to be corrected and guided; besides all the other occasions she had of fulfilling the same duty from pure goodwill towards many people who had not the slightest claim upon her, occasions which she went in search of, did they not present themselves; she had five daughters, not one of whom was in her house, but who, nevertheless, on this very account, gave her more to think of than if they had been. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13396" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13450">Three were nuns, two were married; and thus Donna Pressede naturally found she had three convents and two houses to superintend: a vast and difficult undertaking, all the more laborious, as two husbands supported by fathers, mothers, and brothers, and three lady-abbesses, encouraged by many dignitaries and nuns, would not accept of her superintendence. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13451" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13503">It was a war, or rather five wars, disguised, polite, to a certain point, but active, and without any cessation of arms: there was in all these places, a constant attention to avoid her eagerness, to close every ear to her advice, to elude her inquiries, and an endeavour as much as possible to transact all affairs in secret. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13504" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13532">I will not speak of the opposition, of the difficulties she met with in the management of other affairs, which concerned her even less than those we have spoken of; it is well known that generally men must be benefited against their own will. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13533" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13568">It was in her own house that her zeal could most freely exercise itself: there every one was subject to her authority, with the exception of Don Ferrante, and with him things went on in a peculiar manner. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="22">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13569" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13579">Being a studious man, he did not like either to command or to obey. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13580" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13651">In all household matters, his lady wife might be mistress, certainly; but make him her slave,—no, that was another matter. And if, when besought, he, upon a certain occasion officiated as her secretary, it was because in such employments he considered his genius lay,—nay, he even could refuse her such a favour, if he were not persuaded of the propriety of what she desired him to write: "try yourself," he would say to her, "do it yourself then, if the thing seems so clear to you." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13652" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13701">Donna Pressede, having endeavoured in vain to lead him to do as she desired, was not unfrequently reduced to grumble against him, and call him an original, a man obstinately attached to his own ideas, a learned man; a title, which, together with some anger, she never pronounced without a certain degree of pleasure. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="23">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13702" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13741">Don Ferrante passed a deal of time in his study, where he had a considerable collection of books; a collection consisting of little less than three hundred volumes; these were all selected works, works of the highest reputation in various branches, in every one of which he was more or less versed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13742" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13810">In astrology, he considered himself, and with reason, as more than a mere *dilettante*; for he was not only possessed of the general notions, and of the common vocabulary of influences, aspects, and conjunctions, but he knew how to speak upon proper occasions, like any professor, of the twelve houses of the heavens, of the great circles, of the lucid and obscure degrees, of exaltations and dejections, of passages and revolutions, of those principles, in short, the most certain and recondite of the science. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13811" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13869">And during perhaps twenty years he had, in frequent and long disputes, maintained the pre-eminence of Cardan, against another learned man, who was warmly attached to the system of Alcabizio, and this out of pure obstinacy, as Don Ferrante said. He willingly recognised the superiority of the ancients, but could not, however, endure that prejudice which will not grant to the moderns, even that merit which they evidently deserve. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13870" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13917">He had more than an ordinary knowledge of the history of the science; he was able, if need were, to cite the most celebrated predictions which had been verified, and to reason subtilely and learnedly on other celebrated predictions which had failed of verification; and could demonstrate that the fault did not lie in the science itself, but in those who had not known how to apply it. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="24">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13918" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13938">He had acquired as much knowledge of ancient philosophy as would have sufficed for an ordinary learned man, but he continued to increase it by the reading of Diogenes Laertius. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13939" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13981">Yet, however beautiful various systems may be, it is impossible to adopt them all; and wishing to be a philosopher, it is necessary to select some one or other in particular; therefore Don Ferrante had selected Aristotle, who, as he was accustomed to say, was neither ancient nor modern. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13982" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14020">He possessed also divers works written by the most wise and subtile followers of Aristotle among the moderns; those of his opponents he never would read; in order not to throw away his time, as he said; nor buy them either, lest he should throw away his money. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14021" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14109">He alone, and by way of exception, assigned a place in his library to the celebrated two-and-twenty volumes—*De subtilitate*, and to a few other anti-peripatetic works by Cardan, in consideration of his worth as an astrologer; saying that whoever could have written the treatise *De restitutione temporum et motuum coelestium*, and the work *Duodecim Geniturarum*, deserved a hearing, even although he should be mistaken; and that the great fault of this man, was his having had too much genius; and that no one could imagine what eminence he might not have attained, even in philosophy, had he always kept in the straight path. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14110" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14161">Although, in the opinion of the learned, Don Ferrante passed for an accomplished peripatetic, however, in his own eyes, he did not appear to consider himself so; and more than once, he said with great modesty, that the essence, the universals, the soul of the world, and the nature of things, were not so clear as might be believed. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="25">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14162" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14344">Natural philosophy he had made more a pastime than a study; even the works of Aristotle upon this subject, and of Pliny himself, he might be sooner said to have read than studied; nevertheless, with this reading, with the information gathered incidentally from treatises upon general philosophy, and from Hastily glancing over the *Magia Naturale* of Porta, the three histories, *Lapidum, Animalium, Plantarum* of Cardan, and the treatise upon herbs, plants, and animals of Albertus Magnus, with several other works of less account, he was able upon occasion to entertain an assembly of well-instructed people by reasoning upon the most admirable virtues, and curious singularities of many plants; describing exactly the forms and habits of the Sirens, and of the unique Phoenix; explaining how the Salamander could exist in the fire without being consumed; how the Remora, that little fish, should have the strength and power in the open sea suddenly to retard the progress of the largest vessel; how the dewdrops become pearls in the shells; how the chameleon feeds upon air; how ice, slowly hardened by the lapse of ages, becomes crystal; and, in short, could explain a thousand other marvellous secrets of nature. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="26">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14345" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14386">He had applied himself still more to the study of magic and sorcery, for, says our Anonymous, this was a science much more in vogue, and much more necessary; the facts of which were of a much greater importance, and much more easily verified. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14387" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14419">It is not needful to say that in such a study he had never had any other desire than that of instructing himself, and of gaining an accurate knowledge of the worst arts of sorcery, in order by this means to preserve and defend himself from them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14420" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14473">And, guided by the great Martino Delrio, a scientific man, he was able to discourse ex professo upon the witchcraft of love, upon the witchcraft of sleep, upon the witchcraft of hatred, and upon the innumerable species of these three principal kinds of witchcraft, of which, alas! remarks the Anonymous, one only sees too much at the present day. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14474" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14511">Equally vast and profound was his knowledge of history, particularly of universal history. His authors were, Tarcagnota, Dolce, Bugatti, Campana, Guazzo, the most famous, in short. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="27">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14512" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14523">"But," Don Ferrante would often say, "what is history without politics? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14524" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14555">It is a guide who goes on and on without any one following him, without any to whom he can direct the way, and who consequently throws away his time; and politics without history resemble a man who travels on without a guide." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14556" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14586">Therefore was a small space in his shelves assigned to statistics; where among works of secondary fame shone forth Bodino, Cavalcanti, Sansovino, Paruta, and Boccalini. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14587" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14664">There were, however, two books which Don Ferrante preferred to all others on this subject, two books which for a long time he considered as the first of their kind, without ever being able to decide to which of the two alone belonged the rank of pre-eminence; the Il Principe and the Discorsi of the celebrated secretary of Florence; "A rascal it is true," said Don Ferrante, "but a profound thinker." The other work was La Ragion di Stato, by the no less celebrated Giovanni Botero; "an honest man," he would say, but "a cunning one." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="28">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14665" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14883">However, a short time before the period to which our history is circumscribed, there appeared a book which had terminated the question of priority, taking its stand far above the works of the two great men we have just named, a book in which were to be found comprised and condensed all vices, in order that men might learn to avoid them; and all virtues, that they might practise them; a very small work, but all of gold; in one word, *Lo Statista Regnante* of Don Valeriano Castiglione, whom the most learned men of his time emulated each other in distinguishing, and for whose notice the greatest personages disputed; whom the Pope Urban VIII. honoured by magnificent praises; whom the Cardinal Borghese and the Viceroy of Naples, Don Pietro di Toledo, solicited to write—the first, the deeds of Pope Paul V., the latter an account of the wars of her Catholic Majesty in Italy, but both one and the other in vain; this man, whom Louis XIII., at the suggestion of Cardinal Richelieu named his historiographer; upon whom the Duke Carlo Emanuele of Savoy conferred the same office; and in praise of whom the Duchess Christina, daughter of the very Christian King, Henry IV., added in a diploma, after many other titles, "the certitude of that renown which he had obtained in Italy as the first writer of the age." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="29">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14884" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14910">But if in all the above-named sciences, Don Ferrante might be considered well informed, there was one in which he merited and enjoyed the title of professor; this was the science of chivalry. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14911" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14928">He not only spoke about it with the air of a master, but was often requested to interfere in some affair of honour, and always gave his decision. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14929" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_15012">He had in his library, and one might say in his head, the works of all the most celebrated authors who had written upon this subject: Paride dal Pozzo, Fausto da Longiano, Urrea, Muzio, Romei, Albergato, and all Torquato Tasso, whom he had always ready; and out of whose *Jerusalem Delivered,* as well as his *Jerusalem Conquered,* he could repeat from memory, when needed, all those passages which related to matters of chivalry. HowTHE BETROTHED. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="30">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_15013" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_15055">ever, in his opinion, the greatest authors among them all was the celebrated Francesco Birago, in connexion with whom he had found himself more than once engaged in passing judgment upon some affair of honour; and who also, on his side, spoke of Don Ferrante in terms of peculiar esteem. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_15056" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_15106">And even before the Discorsi Cavallereschi of this renowned author had appeared, Don Ferrante had prophesied, without hesitation, that this work would ruin the authority of Olevano, and would remain, together with its noble sisters, a code for posterity of the very highest authority; a prophecy which has verified itself, as every one may see, remarks our Anonymous. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="31">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_15107" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_15254">Our author does not content himself with these hasty particulars, but is remarkably communicative regarding this learned man; for ourselves, however, we are too much in haste to resume the thread of our story to permit ourselves longer to dwell upon this topic. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="32">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_15255" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_15294">Until the autumn of the following year, 1629, the principal personages of our history remained pretty nearly as we left them, without anything worthy of relation occurring to either one or other of them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_15295" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_15343">This autumn, in which Agnese and Lucia had agreed to meet, at length arrived; but a great public calamity destroyed their project; and this certainly was one of its very least effects: other events followed, which, however, wrought no remarkable change in the fate of our *dramatis personae*. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_15344" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_15423">At length fresh calamities, more general, more serious, more extreme, reached even them; even those who in the scale of the world were even lower than they. These calamities came upon them like a violent tempestuous whirlwind, which tearing up trees, overthrowing walls and houses, scattering their remains over the earth, carries away even the straws concealed in the grass, and collects from out of corners the dry and light leaves which a more gentle wind had driven there, carrying them on with the rest of its mighty prey. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="33">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap27-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_15424" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_15451">In order, however, that the private events which yet remain for us to relate should be clear, it is absolutely necessary that we relate, as well as we can, something regarding these public events, commencing at a somewhat earlier period. </note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>