<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CHAPTER XXV.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>1845</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed Lovers: a Milanese Story of the Seventeenth Century. With The Column of Infamy by Alessandro Manzoni. In Three Volumes</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
          <date>1845</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Henry Francis C. Logan</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="English_1845_cap25">
        <p n="1">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10051">The day following, in Lucia's native village, and in all the territory of Lecco, nothing was spoken of but her, the Unknown, the Archbishop, and another person, who, however much it pleased him to be spoken of in the world, would in the present instance have desired less notoriety—we would say Don Rodrigo. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="2">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10052" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10128">Do not imagine, however, that his deeds had not been spoken of before; they had been—but only in interrupted and secret conversations; it was necessary that two people knew each other very well, before they opened their hearts upon such a subject, and even then they were far from entering into it with all the warmth of sentiment which they would have been able to do,—for men, generally speaking, when they cannot without serious danger express their indignation, not only exhibit less, and keep concealed within them that which they feel, but also really feel less. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10129" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10200">But now, who could prevent themselves inquiring about and reasoning upon an event which had made so much noise, an event in which the hand of Providence was visible, and in which two such distinguished personages played such distinguished parts? In one of whom such a courageous love of justice united itself with so much authority; in the other, in which it seemed that oppression personified, had humbled itself, and that so to say the whole bravo-system had laid down arms and besought repose. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10201" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10211">Through such comparisons Don Rodrigo became somewhat petty. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10212" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10236">People now understood what it really was to torment innocence, in order to dishonour it, to persecute it with such impudent obstinacy, with such atrocious violence, with such abominable deceit. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10237" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10263">There passed before them in review upon this occasion all the other deeds of prowess performed by this Signor; and they now spoke just as they felt, every one encouraged by finding that all were agreed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10264" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10282">There was a murmuring, a general tumult, at a considerable distance from Don Rodrigo's palace, however, for reason of the bravoes which this man had around him. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="3">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10283" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10295">A considerable share of this public odium fell also upon his friends and courtiers. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10296" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10326">The Signor Podestà was well called over the coals; he who was always deaf, blind, and dumb towards the acts of this tyrant; but this took place far from the presence of the Signor Podestà; for if he had no bravoes, he had at least constables. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10327" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10371">With the Doctor Azzecca-Garbugli, who possessed only useless words and cabalistical knowledge, and with other small courtiers, his equals, they were not so ceremonious; they were pointed after, and such glances cast at them, that for some time they considered it best not to shew themselves in the streets. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="4">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10372" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10411">Don Rodrigo was struck, as by a thunder-bolt, at this unexpected news, so different from the intelligence he had daily awaited, nay, almost every moment expected to receive; he kept himself shut up in his castle alone with his bravoes, for two days, to devour his rage; the third, he set out for Milan. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10412" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10465">Had there been only the dull murmur of the people, although affairs had gone on so unfortunately, he would have remained in the country on purpose to oppose it, as well as to seek an occasion of making one of the most insolent an example for all the rest; but what drove him away was the certain intelligence that the Cardinal was also coming to visit this part of the territory. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10466" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10515">His uncle, the Count, who only knew as much of this history as Attilio had told him, would certainly have expected that, upon an occasion such as the present, Don Rodrigo should have played a distinguished part, and have received in public the most marked reception from the Cardinal; but one sees how much disposed he was to such a mode of conduct. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10516" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10543">He would have expected it, and would have had the whole minutely related to him; for this was an important occasion, which would shew in what esteem their family was held by a powerful authority. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10544" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10625">To remove himself, however, from such an annoying embarrassment, Don Rodrigo arose one morning before the sun—placed himself in a carriage with Griso, and with other bravoes outside, both before and behind; and leaving word that the rest of the domestics should follow, he departed like a fugitive (if we may be permitted to elevate our characters by an illustrious comparison), like Catiline leaving Rome, raging with anger, and swearing to return quickly and accomplish his vengeance. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="5">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10626" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10640">Meanwhile the Cardinal continued his progress, each day visiting one of the parishes situated in the territory of Lecco. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10641" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10662">The day on which he should arrive at Lucia's village, a great portion of the inhabitants had gone forth along the road to meet him. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="6">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10663" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10749">At the entrance of the village, exactly at one side of the cottage belonging to our two women, there was erected a triumphant arch constructed of wood, covered with straw and moss, ornamented by green boughs of the holm and holly, distinguished by their scarlet berries. The front of the church was decorated with tapestry; from the windows were hung coverlets, sheets, and children's swaddling clothes, disposed after the fashion of pennons; all the few necessaries, in short, which could be made to appear superfluities. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10750" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10836">Towards evening, the time when the Cardinal was expected, those who had remained at home, old people, women and children for the most part, also set out to meet him, preceded by Don Abbondio, who was gloomy in the midst of all this festivity, partly owing to the uproar which confounded him, to the stir of people around and behind him, which he kept repeating made his head turn round, and also occasioned by the secret fear that the women might have told certain things to the Cardinal, and that he should have to relate to him the affair of the marriage. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10837" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10892">At length was seen the Cardinal, or rather the crowd, in the midst of which was he in his litter, surrounded by his suite; for of all this there was only to be perceived an indication in the air above this crowd of heads, a piece of the cross borne by the Chaplain, who rode along on a mule. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10893" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10943">The people who were with Don Abbondio hastened to join the others, and he, having said three or four times, "slowly, proceed in a line; what are you doing?" angrily turned back, and grumbling, "it is a Babel, it is a real Babel!" entered the church, which was empty, and prepared to await the Cardinal there. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="7">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10944" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10972">The Cardinal came along, bestowing benedictions with his hand, and receiving them from the mouths of the crowd, which the attendants could scarcely, spite of all their efforts, keep a little back. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10973" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11005">This being Lucia's village, the inhabitants desired to do the Cardinal peculiar honour; but this was not easy, as it was the custom wherever he arrived for all the people to do the very most they could. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11006" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11161">Even at the very commencement of his Archbishop's career, at his first solemn entrance into the cathedral, the crowd and the impetuosity of the people behind him was such, that his life was feared for; and some gentlemen who were near him had drawn their swords to terrify and repulse the crowd. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11162" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11267">Such was the disorder and violence of those times, that even in the general desire to do honour to their bishop in the church, and again, in the desire to moderate the people's enthusiasm, blood was nearly shed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11268" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11356">And even this defence would have been insufficient, had not the Master and Deputy-master of the ceremonies, Clerici and Picozzi, two young priests, strong both in body and mind, raised him in their arms and carried him with care from the door to the high altar. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11357" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11502">This first entrance into the church may be, without joking, counted among his pastoral fatigues, and among the dangers which he had passed through, even after he had made many episcopal visits. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="8">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11503" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11586">He entered this church also with difficulty; proceeded to the altar, where, having some time stood in prayer, he addressed, as was his custom, a short discourse to the people, regarding his love for them, his desire for their salvation, and in what manner they should dispose themselves for the divine service of those of her mother, or rather she had none; she had entirely abandoned herself to the will of Providence. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11641" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11783">She sought, therefore, to let these discourses drop, or said in general terms, that she had no longer any hope or desire regarding things in this world, except the desire of being soon able to join her mother; mostly a flood of tears opportunely cut short her words. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="9">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11784" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11805">"Dost thou know why this seems so to thee?" said Agnese; "it is because thou hast suffered so much, and it does not seem to thee that all can again be well. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11806" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11834">But leave all to the Lord; and if — And only let a gleam appear, scarcely a gleam of hope, and then thou wilt be able to tell me whether thou art still of the same mind." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11835" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11840">Lucia kissed her mother and wept. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="10">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11841" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11871">For the rest, between them and their hosts there had arisen a great friendship; and where should it arise, if not between the benefited and their benefactors, when both one and the other are excellent people? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11872" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11880">Agnese especially had great gossips with the mistress of the house. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11881" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11916">The tailor also gave them some amusement with his histories and moral discourses; and at dinner, more particularly, he had always something interesting to relate of Boro d'Antona, or of the Desert Fathers. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="11">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11917" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11938">At a short distance from this village there resided a married pair of importance — Don Ferrante and Donna Pressede; their surname of course has remained in the pen of our Anonymous. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11939" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11970">Donna Pressede was an old gentlewoman, much inclined to doing good; a profession certainly the most worthy which a woman can exercise; but which, carried too far, may do mischief, like all other things. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11971" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12007">In order to do good, it is necessary to know what is good; and as in every thing else, we can only know this through our passions, by means of our judgments and our ideas, which very often may chance to be erroneous. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12008" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12050">Donna Pressede stood in the same relationship to her ideas which one ought to do with one's friends; she had few, but to these she was very much attached; unfortunately, however, among these few, there were some which were distorted, and these were not less dear to her. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12051" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12159">Therefore it sometimes happened that she proposed for good, that which was really not so, or that she chose means which would bring about an opposite effect, or that she believed other means lawful which in effect were unlawful, and this from a confused supposition that he who does more than his duty, may direct his conduct as he pleases. It not unfrequently occurred that in an affair she would often not see what was real, and again would see what there really was not; many other similar things happened to her, which may, and do often, happen to all people, not even excepting the very best; but to Donna Pressede these things happened very often, and not unfrequently all at the same time. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="12">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12160" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12197">Hearing Lucia's singular history, and all that upon the occasion was said about the young girl, she was seized with a curiosity to see her, and sent a coach, attended by an old usher, to fetch the mother and daughter. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12198" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12217">The latter felt no inclination to comply, and requested the tailor who had borne this embassy to them, to discover some means of excusing her. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12218" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12253">As long as it had merely been insignificant people who desired to see the girl of the miracle, the tailor had willingly performed this service; but in the present instance the refusal appeared to him a species of rebellion. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12254" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12320">He made many excuses, many exclamations, said many things, "that this could not be done, that this was a great family, and that one could not say no to gentlefolks; that this might be a piece of good fortune to them; and that the Signora Pressede was a holy woman," and in short, said so many things, that Lucia was obliged to surrender, all the sooner too, as Agnese confirmed these reasons by repeating as often "certainly, certainly." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="13">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12321" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12384">When they arrived before the great lady, she gave them a very grand reception, and made them many congratulations; she questioned, she counselled them; and all this, with a certain superiority almost innate, but softened by many humble expressions, tempered by a deal of zeal, embellished by a deal of godliness, so that Agnese, almost immediately, and Lucia after a short time, began to feel relieved from the oppressive respect which at first this lordly presence had inspired them with; nay, they even felt a certain attraction in it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12385" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12441">But to be brief, Donna Pressede, hearing that the Cardinal had engaged to find an asylum for Lucia, and excited by the desire of at once seconding and forestalling this good intention, offered to take the young girl into her house, where, without being devoted to any particular service, she could, according to her own pleasure, assist the other women in their work. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12442" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12451">She added that she would inform his lordship. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="14">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12452" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12491">Besides the clear and immediate good which there was in a deed such as this, Donna Pressede saw and proposed to herself another, one much more considerable according to her; and this was to minister to a mind diseased, to place in the right path a young girl who stood very much in need of such guidance. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12492" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12535">For, from the first time she had heard speak of Lucia, she had immediately persuaded herself that a girl who could have engaged herself to a good-for-nothing fellow, a man guilty of sedition, to a rascal, in short, must have some defect, some hidden fault. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12536" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12543">"Tell me who thou keepest company with, and I will tell thee who thou art." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12544" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12551">The sight of Lucia had confirmed this persuasion. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12552" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12569">Not that, at the bottom, as she said, she did not appear to her a good young girl; but there were many things to be said. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12570" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12610">This little cast-down head, with this chin buried in her throat, this manner of not replying, or of replying only in a few words, as though unwillingly, might indicate modesty; but it could equally denote obstinacy; it was not difficult to divine that this little head had its own ideas. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12611" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12629">And then this blushing every moment, and these sighs — and these two large eyes, which did not please Donna Prassede at all! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12630" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12682">She felt certain, as though she knew it from very good authority, that all Lucia's misfortunes were a punishment from heaven for her friendship with this good-for-nothing — and a warning to her to release herself; and, such being the case, she proposed to co-operate in such a work. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12683" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12717">Since, as she often said to others and to herself, all her study was to second the will of heaven; but she often made a gross blunder in mistaking her own brain for heaven. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12718" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12732">However, regarding her second intention, she carefully preserved herself from giving the slightest hint. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12733" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12763">For one of her maxims was this, that to succeed in doing good to people, the first thing, in most cases, is not to make them a party in the design. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="15">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12764" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12772">The mother and daughter looked at each other. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12773" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12811">Considering the sad necessity there was that they should part, this offer appeared to both of them acceptable, were it for no other reason than that this villa was so near their village; where, even at the very worst, they could meet and be together, whilst the family was in the country. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12812" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12830">They read in each other's eyes this consent, and both turned towards Donna Pressede with those thanks which they accepted. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12831" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12848">She renewed her politeness and promises, and said that she would immediately send a letter to be presented to the Cardinal. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="16">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12849" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12876">The women having taken their departure, she caused the letter to be written by Don Ferrante, who, being a literary man, as we shall afterwards relate more particularly, she employed as her secretary upon important occasions. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12877" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12920">And such a one being now required, Don Ferrante exercised all his learning, and giving the draft to his wife to copy, warmly recommended her to be careful of the orthography, which was one of the many things which he had studied. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12921" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12932">Donna Pressede copied it very carefully, and despatched it to the tailor's house. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12933" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12952">This occurred two or three days before the Cardinal sent the litter to carry the women back to their village. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="17">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12953" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12962">Having arrived there, they descended at the parsonage, where the Cardinal was staying. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12963" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13013">He ordered them immediately to be introduced; the Chaplain, who was the first to see them, hastened to obey the command, detaining them only so long as was necessary to give them, in all haste, a few instructions regarding the etiquette to be used towards his lordship, and regarding the titles to be addressed to him, a thing which the Chaplain was accustomed to do whenever he could do it unknown to the Cardinal. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13014" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13051">It was for this poor man a constant torment, the seeing how little order reigned around Federigo in this particular. "All," said he to the household, "through the too great goodness of this blessed man, through his great familiarity." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13052" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13099">And he related how he had heard even more than once, with his own ears, people reply, "Yes, sir; no, sir." In this moment the Cardinal was discoursing with Don Abbondio regarding the affairs of his parish, so that he was not able to give, as he would have desired, his instructions to the women. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="18">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13100" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13129">He could only in passing them on his way out, when they were coming forward, give them a glance, which showed that he was satisfied with them, and that they should continue, like good souls, to say nothing. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="19">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13130" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13178">After the first reception on one side, and the first curtsies on the other side were over, Agnese drew the letter from her bosom, and presented it to the Cardinal, saying, "This is from the Signora Donna Pressede, who says she knows your lordship very well, my lord; for it is natural that all great people should know each other. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13179" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13181">When you have read it you will see." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="20">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13182" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13198">"Good," said Federigo, when he had read it, and extracted the sense from all the flowers of Don Ferrante's style. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13199" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13225">"I know this house sufficiently to feel certain that Lucia has been invited from a good intention, and that there she will be safe from the snares and violence of her persecutor." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13226" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13237">What conception he had formed of Donna Pressede's head, we are not told. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13238" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13274">Probably she was not the person he would have selected for such a purpose; but, as we have said, or given it to be understood elsewhere, it was not his custom to disarrange affairs which did not concern him, in order to arrange them better. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="21">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13275" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13327">"Accept quietly this separation, and the uncertainty in which you are placed; but," continued he, "have confidence that this trial may soon end, and that the Lord will conduct all to the termination He has ordained; but consider as certain that whatever He wills will be the best for you." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13328" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13348">He bestowed on Lucia in particular some other friendly remembrance, and spoke words of comfort to them both, blessed them, and allowed them to depart. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13349" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13375">Scarcely were they outside the door, than they found themselves in a perfect swarm of their friends; all the community, one might say, who were expecting them, and who conducted them to their house as in triumph. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13376" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13401">There was among all these women quite a rivalry of congratulations, of condolence, of questions, and all exclaimed with displeasure upon hearing that Lucia should depart the following day. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13402" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13417">The men emulated each other in offering their services; every one desired to keep guard before the cottage that night. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13418" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13439">Regarding which circumstance our Anonymous thought well to make a proverb — "Do you desire many to assist you? endeavour to have no need of assistance." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="22">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13440" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13451">So many warm receptions confounded and confused Lucia; Agnese, however, did not get confused about such a little matter. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13452" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13486">But, in reality, this did even Lucia good, distracting her somewhat from the thoughts and remembrances which, even in the midst of this uproar, awoke within her, standing, as she did, upon the threshold, in this little room, among so many familiar objects. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="23">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13487" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13512">At the tolling of the bell which announced that Divine service was at hand, all moved towards the church, and this was for our women another triumphal progress. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="24">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13513" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13535">Service being over, Don Abbondio, who had run to see whether Perpetua had arranged every thing well for the meal, was summoned by the Cardinal. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13536" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13651">He immediately hastened to his grand guest, who allowed him to approach quite near, when, "Signor Curato," he commenced,—and these words were spoken in a manner to make one understand that they were the commencement of a long and serious discourse,—"Signor Curato, why have you not united in matrimony this poor Lucia with her affianced husband?" "They have let the cat out of the bag this morning," thought Don Abbondio, and muttering replied, "His illustrious lordship will have heard speak of the disturbances which have arisen in this affair; there was such a confusion, that no one even at the present day can fathom them, as your illustrious lordship can infer from the young woman's only arriving here after so many accidents, as though by a miracle, and from the young man's being, after so many accidents, one does not know where." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="26">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13652" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13679">"I ask," resumed the Cardinal, "whether it is true that, before all these events occurred, you refused to celebrate the marriage when this was requested of you on the appointed day; and I also demand the wherefore?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="27">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13680" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13714">"Truly——if your illustrious lordship knew—— what intimations — what terrible commands I have had given me not to speak —" And he paused, without concluding his sentence, with a certain manner which was intended respectfully to give the Cardinal to understand that it would be indiscreet to desire to know more. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="28">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13715" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13758">"But," said the Cardinal, with a voice and mien much graver than usual, "it is your bishop who, through his duty and for your justification, desires to know from yourself wherefore you have not performed that which in the regular way it was your bounden duty to perform." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="29">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13759" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13786">"My lord," said Don Abbondio, making himself very, very small, "I have not yet wished to say — But it has appeared to me that these being such entangled affairs, so old, and without remedy, it was useless to meddle with them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13787" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13800">However, however, I say — I know that your illustrious lordship will not betray a poor clergyman. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13801" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13825">For my lord sees well that his lordship cannot be everywhere at the same time; and I remain here exposed — However, if you command me, I will tell, I will tell all." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="30">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13826" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13834">"Speak! I desire nothing but to find you without blame." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="31">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13835" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13869">Upon this Don Abbondio began to relate the sad history, but he was silent regarding the principal name, and substituted in its stead "a great Signor;" thus being as prudent as he could in such a fearful strait. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="32">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13870" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13883">"And you have had no other motive?" demanded the Cardinal, when Don Abbondio had ended. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="33">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13884" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13903">"But perhaps I have not explained myself suffi"ciently," replied the latter; "under pain of death they have intimated to me that I should not perform this marriage." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="34">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13904" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13916">"And this has appeared to you reason sufficient for leaving an important duty unfulfilled?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="35">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13917" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13936">"I have always sought to perform my duty, even much to my own inconvenience, but where life is concerned——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="36">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13937" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13960">"And when you presented yourself to the church," said Federigo, with a still graver accent, "to assume this ministry, did the church give you security for your life? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13961" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13977">Did she tell you that the duties annexed to the ministry were free from every obstacle, exempt from every danger? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13978" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13990">Or did she, perhaps, tell you that where danger commenced the duty ceased? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13991" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13997">Or did she not expressly say the contrary? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13998" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14009">Has she not informed you that she sent you forth like a lamb among wolves? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14010" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14026">Did you not know that there were violent men, to whom what you were commanded to do might be displeasing? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14027" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14059">He from whom we have our doctrine and example, and in imitation of whom we allow ourselves to be called, and call ourselves, pastors, coming upon earth to exercise this office, made it perhaps a condition that his life should be saved? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14060" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14089">And to save it, to preserve it, I say, these few days longer on the earth, at the expense of charity and duty, was there need of the holy unction, of the imposition of hands, of the grace of the priesthood? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14090" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14100">The world suffices to give this virtue, to teach this doctrine. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14101" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14151">What do I say? Oh, shame! the world itself refuses it; the world also makes its own laws, laws which prescribe evil as well as good; it has its gospel also—a gospel of pride and hatred; and will not even permit it to be said love of life is a reason for transgressing its commands. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14152" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14157">It does not permit this, and it is obeyed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14158" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14180">And we!—we sons and messengers of the promise!—what would the church be, if this your language were the language of all your brethren? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14181" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14190">Where would she now be, had she appeared in the world with such doctrines?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="37">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14191" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14226">Don Abbondio stood with a bowed head; his soul attacked by these arguments was like a chicken in the talons of a falcon, which holds it suspended in an unknown region—in an air which it has never breathed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14227" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14241">Seeing how necessary it was to reply something, he said with a certain forced submission, "My illustrious Signor, I was wrong. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14242" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14253">If life is not to be counted as something, I know nothing else to say. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14254" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14286">But when one has to do with certain people, with people who have power in their hands, and who will not hear reason, I do not know what there is to gain, even in putting on a brave face. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14287" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14299">This is a Signor whom one can neither vanquish, nor escape from with impunity." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="38">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14300" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14313">"And do you not know that to suffer for the sake of justice is our conquest? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14314" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14334">And if you do not know this, what do you preach? Of what are you the teacher? What is this good news you announce to the poor? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14335" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14345">Who expects you to overcome strength by strength? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14346" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14372">Certainly it will not be demanded of you at the day of judgment whether you have been able to make the mighty obey you, for neither was this your mission, nor were the means given you. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14373" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14469">But it will certainly be demanded of you, whether you have employed the means which were in your hands to do that which was prescribed you, even when the "powerful should have the temerity to prohibit you from doing it." "These saints are really curious," thought Don Abbondio meanwhile to himself. "The substance of all this is, that the loves of two young people lie nearer his heart than the life of a poor priest" — And as far as himself was concerned, he would have been very well pleased that the discourse should end here; but he saw the Cardinal, at every pause, remain as though he awaited a reply — a confession, an apology, or something, in short. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="40">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14470" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14487">"I return to what I said, my lord," he at length replied, "that I was wrong —— Courage one cannot give oneself." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="41">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14488" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14510">"And wherefore then, I might say to you, did you engage in a ministry which obliges you to stand in warfare against the passions of the age? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14511" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14546">But how, I will rather say, is it you do not think that there is a God, who will infallibly bestow courage upon you, if in this ministry, in which you have entered yourself, courage is necessary for the fulfilment of your obligations? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14547" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14588">Do you believe that all the millions of martyrs had naturally courage — that they naturally thought nothing of their lives? So many tender youths who just began to taste the joys of existence, so many old people accustomed to lament that it was so near its close, so many maidens, so many wives, so many mothers? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14589" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14600">All have received courage, for courage was necessary, and they had faith. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14601" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14627">Knowing your weaknesses and your duties, have you thought how to prepare yourself for those difficult circumstances in which you might happen to find yourself, and in which you have in reality found yourself? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14628" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14666">Ah! if for so many years of a pastor's life you have loved your flock—and how should you not have loved it?—if you have reposed in it your heart, your cares, your delights, courage ought not to fail you, for love is intrepid. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14667" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14713">Well, if you love them, those who are confided to your spiritual care, those whom you call children, when you see two of them menaced, together with you—ah! certainly as the weakness of the flesh will have made you tremble for yourself, so will love have made you tremble for them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14714" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14785">You will have been humbled by this first fear, because it was an effect of your misfortune; you will have implored strength to vanquish it, to drive it forth, because it was a temptation; but holy fear for others is noble, this fear for your children, you will have listened to it; this you will not have silenced—this will have excited, constrained you to think of doing all that was possible to defend them from the danger which menaced them—What idea has this fear, this love inspired you with? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14786" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14790">What have you done for them? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14791" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14793">What have you thought of? </note>
        </p>
        <p n="42">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap25-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14794" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14800">And he was silent, like one who awaits a reply. </note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>