<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CHAPTER XXVIII.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>1845</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed Lovers: a Milanese Story of the Seventeenth Century. With The Column of Infamy by Alessandro Manzoni. In Three Volumes</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
          <date>1845</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Henry Francis C. Logan</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="English_1845_cap28">
        <p n="1">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10021">After the famous sedition of San Martino and the following days, it really seemed as though by a miracle, abundance had returned to Milan. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10022" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10037">There was bread in great quantities in all the shops; the price was the same as in the most fruitful years; there was grain in the same proportion. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10038" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10078">Those, who during these two terrible days had yelled in the streets, and even done worse, had now—excepting those few who had been arrested—something to congratulate themselves upon. But do not suppose that, the first alarm of seizure being over, they remained quiet. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10079" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10104">In the public squares, at the corners of the streets, in the taverns, there was a shew of dancing, a congratulating each other, and a boasting, in undertones, that they had at last discovered the way of reducing the price of bread. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10105" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10129">In the midst, however, of all this festivity and merriment, there was—and how should it have been otherwise?—a certain uneasiness, a certain presentiment that this abundance could not last. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10130" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10175">The people besieged the bakers' shops just as they had done before in the artificial and short-lived abundance produced by Antonio Ferrer's first tariff—the flour and bread were consumed without the slightest economy; whoever had a few pence laid by now, invested them in bread and flour; boxes, small casks, nay, even cauldrons, were turned into magazines. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10176" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10207">Thus striving against each other to enjoy the present abundance, they rendered—I do not say its long duration impossible, for impossible it already was, but caused its temporary continuation to be still more difficult. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="2">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10208" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10367">Therefore, on the 15th of November, Antonio Ferrer, by order of his Excellency, published a decree, by which it was forbidden to any one who should have any quantity of grain or flour in his house to purchase any more; and to any one to buy bread more than sufficient for two days, under penalty of both pecuniary and corporal punishment, according to the will of his Excellency. This decree intimated to the officers of justice, and in fact to every one, that they should denounce the transgressors; ordered the judges to institute search in all those houses which should be indicated to them; and at the same time commanded that the shops should be well provided with bread, under pain of five years in the galleys, and even greater punishment, according to the will of his Excellency. Whoever imagines a proclamation such as the present put into execution, must have a very powerful imagination; and certainly had all these orders been executed, the duchy of Milan would have had as many men on the sea as Great Britain has at the present day. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="3">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10368" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10391">But, commanding the bakers to make so much bread, care should have been taken that the materials out of which to make it, should not have failed them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10392" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10430">In times of famine, people study how to make bread out of productions which ordinarily are consumed under other forms. It was therefore now imagined that rice might enter into the composition of the bread called *di mistura* (mixture). </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10431" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10493">On the 23d of November was issued a decree, which placed at the disposal of the Vicar, and twelve members of provision, the half of the raw rice which each one possessed; any one disposing of this without the permission of these gentlemen, to be liable to lose the whole of his rice, and be fined three scudi the bushel: this was, as every one perceives, the most reasonable of all the orders. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="4">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10494" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10507">But it was necessary to pay for this rice, and that at a price very disproportionate to that of bread. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10508" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10545">The charge of supplying this enormous difference had been imposed upon the city; but the Council of Ten deliberated that same day, the 23d of November, upon representing to the Governor, the utter impossibility of their longer sustaining such a burden. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10546" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10608">And the Governor, by the proclamation of the 7th of December, fixed the price of rice of this kind at twelve lire the bushel: whoever shall demand a higher sum than the fixed price, or refuse to sell, is threatened with the loss of the whole of his rice, and with a fine equal to its value, and still greater punishment, both pecuniary and corporal, even the galleys, according to the will of his Excellency, as the degree of the offence, and as the person shall admit. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="5">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10609" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10654">The price of superior rice had already been fixed, even before the first of these popular commotions; probably the tariff, or to make use of a word of much celebrity in modern annals, the maximum of corn and the other ordinary kinds of grain had been settled in other decrees, which we have not happened to meet with. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="6">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10655" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10679">Now, therefore, corn and flour being by these means kept at a low price at Milan, there rushed thither crowds of famished people from the country. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10680" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10763">Don Gonzalo, in order to remedy this inconvenience, as he calls it, prohibited by another edict of the 15th of December any one carrying out of the city bread to above the amount of twenty soldi (pence), under pain of losing this same bread and twenty-five scudi, and, in case of inability, of undergoing a public flogging; and even still greater punishment, according, etc., etc. The 22d of the same month (and one does not see well wherefore this should not have been attended to sooner) he published a similar order regarding flour and grain. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="7">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10764" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10786">The multitude had desired to cause abundance by pillage and conflagration; the Governor now desired to maintain it by the galleys and the cord. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10787" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10813">The means were tolerably well matched; the reader may judge whether they would attain their end; what end they did attain, he shall see directly. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10814" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10869">It is easy, and not useless, to observe how between these strange means there exists an intimate and necessary connexion; each was the inevitable consequence of the preceding; and all, in fact, flowed from the first, which had fixed upon bread a price so disproportionate to that which ought to have resulted from the real state of things. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10870" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10912">An expedient such as this has always appeared to the multitude, not only just, but very simple, and very easy to put in execution: it is then very natural that, enduring the miseries of famine, they should desire, implore, and even impose it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10913" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10950">But gradually, as the consequences make themselves felt, it behoves those whose business it is, to repair them, by a law which shall prohibit men from doing that which they had been instigated to do by former proclamations. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10951" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10960">May we be permitted here hastily to observe a singular combination of circumstances. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10961" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11065">In a country, and in an epoch, not very distant from us, in the most renowned and important epoch of modern history, they had recourse in similar circumstances to similar measures; they were almost the same in substance, only a little different in their proportion, and the events followed pretty nearly in the same order. They adopted these measures, in spite of the great changes that had come over society, of the general increase of knowledge in Europe, and more especially in this very country; and this principally, because the great mass of the people who had not yet become enlightened, was able in the long run to make its judgments prevail, and to control the hand of those who formed the laws. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="8">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11066" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11114">But let us return to our narrative. Hear what had been the fruits of all this strife:—they had spoiled and utterly lost a quantity of food in the tumult itself; they had consumed, as long as the tariff was in operation, largely and without measure, even at the expense of the small quantity of grain which was to last them until the approaching harvest. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11115" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11144">To these general effects must be reckoned four unfortunate men who were hanged as ringleaders of the mob: two before the bakehouse of the Crutches, two at the end of the street where stood the house of the Superintendent of provisions. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="9">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11145" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11174">The historical relations of these times are written so carelessly that we are not able to discover when and how this violent tariff ceased. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11175" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11207">If, however, in the absence of positive proof, it be permitted us to advance a conjecture, it was, we are inclined to think, suppressed a little earlier or a little later than the 24th of December, which was the day of this execution. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11208" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11264">As to the edicts, after the one of the 22d of the same month, which we have quoted, we find no other relating to food; but whether they have perished, or have escaped our research, or whether the Governor, at length discouraged by the inefficacy of his remedies, and overwhelmed by the torrent of public calamity, abandoned things to their own course, we know not. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11265" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11399">But we find in the relations of more than one historian (inclined as they all are, sooner to describe great events than to note their causes and progress), a description of the country, and particularly of the city, during the advanced winter and in the spring. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11400" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11425">All the shops were closed, the manufactories were for the most part deserted; the streets presented an indescribable spectacle, there was one constant stream of miserable objects through them; they were the perpetual abode of sufferers. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11426" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11455">The mendicants by profession, now the smallest portion, were confounded and lost among a new multitude of unfortunates, and these poor wretches were seen disputing for alms with those very beggars who had formerly received assistance from them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11456" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11586">Clerks and journeymen who, dismissed by the merchants and shopkeepers, were deprived of their daily earnings, and who could scarcely exist upon their scanty savings; masters themselves, who through the cessation of trade, had become utterly ruined; and workmen, and possessors of every manufacture and every art, from the humblest to the most refined, from the most necessary to those of the highest luxury, now wandered from door to door, from street to street, leaned against the corners of the streets, laid themselves down upon the stones, upon the steps of houses and churches, piteously beseeching alms, or hesitating between necessity and shame, not yet overcome; thin and feeble, they had scarcely strength to support themselves, exhausted as they were by a long fast, and by the cold which penetrated their worn garments, in which might yet be perceived traces of a better state. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11587" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11658">Mingled in this miserable troop, and forming no small portion of it, were domestics, dismissed by their masters, who however wealthy, found themselves unable in such a season to maintain their usual number of attendants; and to all these various miserable objects associated themselves a number of others, accustomed in part to live upon their gains—children, women, old people, grouped around their ancient supporters, or dispersed in various places, beseeching alms. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="10">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11659" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11721">There was also, and these might be distinguished by their tangled locks, their ragged finery, and by a certain indescribable air in their bearing and gestures, and by the traces of their habits stamped upon their countenances, many of the Bravo class, who through the general misery had lost their wickedly gained bread, and were forced to crave it now as charity. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11722" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11785">Tamed by hunger, now only disputing with others in prayers and petitions, they dragged themselves along the very streets which they had so often traversed with haughty steps, with a proud and ferocious air, clothed in rich and gay liveries, with waving plumes, decorated with rich arms, elegant, perfumed; but now they humbly held forth that hand which they had so often raised insolently to threaten, or treacherously to kill. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="11">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11786" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11824">But perhaps the most disgusting, and yet at the same time the most piteous spectacle, were the country people, alone, or in companies of whole families together; husbands, and wives with their children in their arms, or fastened upon their backs, with elder children by the hand, with old people beside them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11825" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11885">Some whose houses had been invaded and pillaged by the soldiery when quartered with them, or on their march, had fled in despair; and among these were those who, to excite more compassion and to distinguish their misery among so much, exhibited the bruises and wounds which they had received whilst defending the few last remains of their provisions, or when escaping from a blind and foolish licentiousness. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11886" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11943">Others, whom this particular scourge had not yet reached, but driven by two other scourges from which no part of the land had been exempt, sterility and the high price of food, had come, and were still hastening to the city as the last asylum of abundance and pious munificence. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11944" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11994">It was easier to distinguish the newly arrived by their air of astonishment and rage at discovering such a superabundance of misery where they had alone expected to be objects of compassion, than even by their uncertain and strange manner. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11995" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12042">In the features of the others, who for a longer space of time had traversed and inhabited the city streets, prolonging their miserable existence by the succour which they so sparingly received, was deposited a deeper consternation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12043" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12127">Different were the costumes of those who might still be said to be clothed, and different also were their countenances. There were seen the pale visages of the dwellers in the marshes, the bronzed faces of the inhabitants of the higher lands and of the hills, and the ruddy complexion of the mountaineers; but all were alike sharp and distorted; all had the same hollow eye, the same fixed stare, half ferocious, half idiotic; all tangled hair, long and rough beards; bodies inured to labour, but now bowed by pain and poverty; and through their tattered garments might be seen how the wrinkled skin hung upon their dry arms, legs, and thin chests. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12128" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12158">Different to the spectacle of this reduced vigour and masculine power, but not less painful, was the languor and utter debility of those who were of a weaker sex and age. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="12">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12159" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12179">Here and there in the streets, and along the walls, were to be seen heaps of straw and stubble mingled with filthy rags. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12180" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12206">These, disgusting as they might appear, were however charitable donations; they were couches prepared for these poor wretches, where at night they could repose their weary limbs. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12207" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12256">Often, during the day, were these couches occupied by those who, exhausted by suffering and fasting, could no longer drag themselves along. Sometimes a corpse would lie extended upon one of these miserable beds. Sometimes a body would be seen suddenly to fall flat upon the pavement, and there remain a corpse. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="13">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12257" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12275">Bending over these dead or dying, might sometimes be seen a passer-by, or a neighbour, attracted thither by an impulse of compassion. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12276" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12306">Again, there would arrive succour, administered by a hand, rich in means, and accustomed to confer princely benefits—the hand of the good Federigo. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12307" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12358">He had chosen six priests, endowed with lively charity, perseverance, and robust constitutions; these he had divided into pairs, and to each pair had assigned a third of the city as their charge; these priests were followed by attendants, who brought with them food, the most efficacious restoratives, and clothing. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12359" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12386">Every morning, these three pairs set forth on their mission by various routes, approached those they saw lying abandoned on the earth, and bestowed their attention wherever it was required. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12387" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12406">One, who already in his last agony was no longer in a condition to receive food, received from them the last consolation of religion. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12407" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12435">To the hungry they distributed broth, bread, and wine; and to the others, exhausted by a longer fast, they administered jellies, soup, and more generous wine; restoring them at first, when needful, with spirits. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12436" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12445">At the same time they distributed articles of clothing. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="14">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12446" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12519">Neither did their assistance end here. The good pastor desired, wherever this were possible, that the poor sufferers should receive permanent, and not mere momentary relief; therefore, the good priests gave a little money to those whose strength had been sufficiently restored for them to pursue their way, fearing least want and hunger should again speedily reduce them to their former misery; for the others he sought an asylum in some neighbouring house. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12520" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12565">In the houses of the wealthy, they were for the most part charitably received as protégés of the Cardinal: in those where the means were wanting to the good will, the priests requested that the poor creatures should be taken in as boarders, arranged the price, and paid a certain sum in advance. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12566" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12583">They gave information of this to the different curates, in order that they might visit them, and returned themselves at a certain time. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="15">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12584" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12605">Federigo had not waited until the misery had attained its height, in order to have his compassion. excited, and then exercise his benevolence. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12606" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12717">By uniting all his means, by rendering his system of economy still more strict, by drawing upon sums destined for other liberalities, which now had become of secondary importance; he had endeavoured in every possible way to amass money to be employed in succouring this famished people. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12718" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12889">He had made great purchases of grain, a considerable portion of which he sent to those places of the diocese where corn was the most scarce. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12890" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13082">And as this supply was very inferior to the demand, he sent also a quantity of salt, "with which," says Ripamonti, relating the circumstance, "the grass of the field, and the bark of trees was turned into food." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13083" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13253">He had distributed grain and money among the various curates of the city; he himself visited the various quarters, and bestowed alms; he succoured in secret many poor families; and in the episcopal palace, we are informed by a contemporary writer (the physician Alessandro Tadino, in one of his reports, which we shall have frequent occasion to quote), were dealt out to the people two thousand measures of boiled rice every morning. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="16">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13254" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13294">The void which mortality created each day in this deplorable multitude, was each day more than replenished; there was a perpetual concourse, at first from the neighbouring villages, then from more distant parts of the country, from the various Milanese towns, and at length, even from other states. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13295" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13352">From Milan itself departed many of the old inhabitants: some to remove themselves from the sight of so much misery; others, seeing their place usurped by foreign intruders, went forth with a last desperate attempt to find succour elsewhere, in some place where at least, either the crowd should be less dense, or the clamour of demands less great. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13353" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13382">These two bodies of pilgrims met on the same road — a spectacle of terror to each other, a fearful warning, a dark omen of the fate towards which both were hastening! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13383" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13414">But each pilgrimage pursued its way, if not with the hope of improving its condition, at least to avoid returning again to those places where famine and despair had first seized them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13415" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13447">Sometimes a miserable fugitive, entirely deprived of all strength, would fall down on the road, and remain there a corpse; an ominous spectacle to his companions in misery, an object of horror, perhaps of reproach to the other passers-by. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13448" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13463">"I saw," writes Ripamonti, "lying on the road which encircles the walls, the body of a woman. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13464" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13481">From her mouth issued the remains of half-chewed grass, and her lips were still curved with an expression of frenzy. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13482" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13522">She had in her lap a small bundle of sticks, and bound in its swaddling clothes, on her bosom, lay a little infant, which was wailing bitterly." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="17">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13523" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13543">The striking contrast of magnificent dresses and of rags, of luxury and misery, which is an ordinary spectacle in ordinary times, had then entirely ceased. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13544" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13564">Rags and misery had intruded almost everywhere, and the only sign of distinction was scarcely an appearance of humble mediocrity. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13565" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13623">Even the nobles were seen in the streets in simple, almost mean garments: some either because the public calamity had thus affected their fortunes, or reduced their patrimonies, already embarrassed; others, because they either feared to provoke by their pomp the public despair, or dreaded to insult the public misery. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13624" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13653">Those oppressors who were accustomed to parade the streets with a train of bravoes, now pursued their way almost unattended, with bowed heads, and countenances which seemed to offer and beseech peace. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13654" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13696">Others, who in prosperity had been filled with more humane thoughts, and appeared with a more modest bearing, seemed also confounded and overwhelmed at the continued sight of a misery which exceeded all possibility of relief. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13697" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13718">But whoever was possessed with the desire to bestow an alms had a difficult and melancholy task in selecting the object for his charity. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13719" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13783">Scarcely was a beneficent hand seen to approach the hand of one of these sufferers, than there arose a terrible contention among the surrounding miserable beings: those who still retained vigour sufficient, pressed forward more urgently to beseech attention; the exhausted old people and children raised their thin hands; mothers held up their crying infants who were ill, inclosed in their miserable ragged swaddling clothes, and who from very languor, bent forward in their mothers' hands. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="18">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13784" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13831">Thus passed the winter and the spring: and already for a long time had the Tribunal of Health represented to the Tribunal of Provisions the danger in which the city ran of contagion, through so much misery being dispersed in every quarter; and had proposed that the mendicants should be shut up in various hospitals. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13832" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13869">Whilst they discussed this project, whilst they approved it, whilst they considered the means of putting it into execution, the number of dead bodies continued every day to increase in the streets, and in proportion, the amount of misery also. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13870" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13935">The Tribunal of Provisions then proposed another simpler and much more expeditious method: and this was to inclose all the mendicants, healthy and sick, in one place, in the Lazaretto, and there support them at the public expense. This was resolved upon in spite of the Tribunal of Health, which objected that in such a great assemblage of people, the very danger which they desired to avoid would be only augmented. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="19">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13936" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13994">The Lazaretto of Milan is a four-sided, almost square enclosure, without the city, on the left hand of the eastern gate, and separated from the city walls by the moat, a circumvallation and a ditch, which surrounds the inclosure itself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13995" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14043">The two principal sides are about five hundred feet long, the two others about fifty feet shorter. The exterior has been divided into a series of small rooms one story in height; within, above three stories of similar chambers runs a piazza, supported by slender columns. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14044" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14107">Formerly there were two hundred and eighty-eight of these chambers, and even more; at the present day, a large entrance opened in the middle, and a smaller one in a corner of the wall which faces the high road, have destroyed a considerable number. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14108" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14120">In the centre of the inner space there was, and still exists, a small octangular church. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="20">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14121" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14208">This building, commenced in the year 1489, at the expense of a private individual, and afterwards carried on by public subscription, and by other donations and bequests, was, as its name announces, destined for the reception of people seized with the plague. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14209" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14225">At the moment of which we speak, the lazaretto only served as a place of deposit for merchandise, which had to be subjected to the laws of quarantine. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14226" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14258">Speedily to clear this building, the various prescribed regulations of the sanatory law were hastily attended to, and the merchandise at once released. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14259" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14291">Straw was spread in all the chambers, and provisions were laid in of such quality, and in such quantity, as could be procured; and by a public edict all mendicants were invited to betake themselves there. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="21">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14292" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14326">Many hastened there voluntarily; all those who lay sick in the streets were carried thither; and within a few days there were assembled in all, upwards of three thousand. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14327" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14334">But there were many who still remained without the walls of the lazaretto. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14335" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14443">Whether it was that each one waited, hoping to see the others move off, and thus leave him to enjoy the charity of the city all to himself; whether it was the natural repugnance of man to being imprisoned within stone walls, or that mistrust felt by the poor towards every regulation proposed by the rich and powerful; whether it was a knowledge of what was in reality the benefit offered, or whether it was all these reasons together, or something else that influenced them, the fact remains, that the greater portion of the populace paying no attention to this invitation, continued to drag themselves painfully along the streets. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14444" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14453">Perceiving this, the law-makers thought well to adopt force. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14454" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14501">They despatched constables who should drive the beggars to the lazaretto, and carry them thither bound, did they make any resistance; a premium of ten soldi was assigned to the constables for each mendicant thus carried away; and worthy is it of remark, that even in the greatest times of distress, enough money belonging to the public is always found to be employed in some folly or other. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14502" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14550">And although a certain number of these wretched people banished themselves from their native city, as though at the express desire of the Tribunal of Provisions, in order at least to live or die in freedom; yet so successful was the chase, that in a short time the number within the lazaretto, both of guests and prisoners, amounted to about twelve thousand. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="22">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14551" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14574">It is to be supposed, although the memoirs of the time make no mention of the fact, that the women and children were placed in a separate quarter. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14575" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14665">Rules and regulations for good order would certainly not be wanting; but let any one imagine what order could be maintained, more especially in those times and in these circumstances, in such a vast assemblage, where, together with voluntary guests, were prisoners carried thither by force and stratagem; people, for whom begging was a grief, a shame, brought in contact with others with whom it was a trade; where men, grown up in the honest activity of camps and offices, mingled with those educated in the streets, in taverns, in the palaces of oppressors, where they had learned to idle, to cheat, to mock, and commit violence. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="23">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14666" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14686">It would not be difficult to form a melancholy conjecture regarding the mingling of these uncongenial elements, even did we possess no positive intelligence — but this we do possess. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14687" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14740">They slept heaped up twenty or thirty in each of these small cells, or else lay stretched under the piazza upon a little putrid straw, or on the earth: certainly, orders had been issued that the straw should be fresh, that there should be sufficient of it, and that it should be often changed; but in truth, there was but a miserable supply, what there was, was bad, and it was never changed! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14741" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14789">It had been likewise ordered that the bread should be fresh; for what administrator ever said that bad articles should be distributed? But how was it possible that bread, which could not have been obtained under ordinary circumstances, even in a much less supply, could now be procured for such an immense multitude? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14790" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14823">It was said, we find by the memoirs of the times, that the lazaretto bread was adulterated with heavy, but not nutritious substances; and it is only too probable that this was the fact. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14824" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14866">Pure water was very scarce, I would say running and wholesome water; the only well was the ditch which surrounded the enclosure, where the water was muddy and stagnant, and rendered vile by the constant use and neighbourhood of such an immense and wretched multitude. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="24">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14867" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14905">To these causes of mortality, all the more active because operating upon bodies already exhausted or enfeebled, was added the unfavourableness of the season; obstinate rains were followed by a more obstinate drought, and by unreasonable and violent heat. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14906" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14973">These physical evils were increased by mental suffering, the weariness and despair of captivity—the remembrance of former habits of life—grief for the beloved dead—the disquieting memory of the absent beloved ones—and a number of other tormenting and exhausting passions; and then the very apprehension and constant spectacle of death occasioned by so many causes, became in itself a powerful cause of disease. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14974" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15128">Therefore it is not to be wondered at that the mortality should have increased in this building to such a degree as to assume the appearance, and be considered by many, as the plague. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15129" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15202">Whether this was simply an epidemic sickness, augmented by all their sufferings, or whether there really was a species of contagion afloat, which easily seized upon bodies already rendered liable to its attacks by poverty, suffering and filth; or whether the plague first broke out in the lazaretto itself, as appears from an obscure and imperfect relation of the time, to have been the opinion of the physicians of the Tribunal of Health, we cannot now decide. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15203" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15222">At all events the number of deaths in the lazaretto soon exceeded a hundred a day. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="25">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15223" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15241">Whilst in this fearful prison there reigned languor, agony, terror, lamentation; in the Tribunal of Provision, shame, astonishment, and uncertainty, had seized upon all minds. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15242" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15269">They consulted, they listened to the advice of the Tribunal of Health, and now nothing was to be done but destroy all that work which had been prepared with such ceremony, with such expectation, and with so much vexation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15270" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15290">The lazaretto was opened; all the mendicants who still remained in health were dismissed, and rushed forth with a mad joy. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15291" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15323">The city again resounded with lamentations, but more weak and interrupted. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15324" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15340">Those who fell sick were transported to Santa Maria della Stella, which was then the hospital for the poor, and there the greater number perished. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="26">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15341" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15348">In the meantime, however, the fields began to grow golden with the ripening crops. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15349" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15364">The peasants departed from the city, each one returning his own way towards this long sighed after harvest. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15365" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15396">The good Federigo in dismissing them, bestowed upon them another proof of his love; to every peasant who presented himself at the episcopal palace, he ordered to be given a guilio and a sickle. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15397" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15418">With the harvest the famine ceased to be felt; but the mortality, increasing day by day, continued until the middle of autumn. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15419" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15425">It was, however, on the point of ceasing, when a new scourge desolated the country. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="27">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15426" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15444">Many events of high historical interest had occurred within this interval. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15445" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15499">The Cardinal Richelieu having taken Rochelle, as we have already informed our readers, had formed a treaty of peace with England; had proposed and obtained, by his powerful influence in the council of the King of France, efficacious succour for the Duke di Nevers; and at the same time had induced the king to conduct this expedition. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15500" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15531">Whilst these preparations were proceeding, the Count of Nassau, the imperial commissary, intimated in Mantua, to the new duke, that he should place the states in the hands of Ferdinand; otherwise, in case of refusal, the emperor would dispatch an army to occupy them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15532" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15585">The duke, who in the most desperate circumstances had rejected such a hard condition, and, now encouraged by the approaching succour from France, defended himself still more boldly. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15586" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15596">The commissary departed, protesting that force should decide the affair. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15597" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15670">In March, the Cardinal Richelieu, together with the king at the head of an army, demanded a free passage from the Duke of Savoy; they entered into treaties, but nothing was concluded. After a rencounter, in which the French obtained the advantage, they again formed a treaty, in which, among other things, it was stipulated that Don Gonzalo de Cordova should raise the siege of Casale; engaging himself, should the French be the conquerors, to join them for the invasion of the Duchy of Milan. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15671" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15693">Don Gonzalo raised the siege of Casale, and a body of French troops entered it to reinforce the garrison. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="28">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15694" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15728">It was upon this occasion that Achillini addressed King Louis in his famous sonnet. *Sudate o fochi a preparar metalli;* and another, in which he exhorts him to go and deliver the Holy Land. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="29">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15729" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15759">But it is a species of fate that the advice of poets is never listened to; and if in history you discover some few deeds performed according to their suggestions, you may depend upon it, that these deeds have been resolved upon long before. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15760" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15779">The Cardinal de Richelieu had, on the contrary, resolved to return to France, on account of certain affairs which appeared to him more urgent. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15780" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15831">It was in vain that Girolamo Soranzo, the Venetian envoy, employed the most powerful arguments to combat this resolution; the King and the Cardinal paid as little attention to his prose as they had done to the verses of Achillini; he returned with the greater part of the army, only leaving six thousand men behind in Suza, to occupy the pass and maintain the treaty. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="30">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15832" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15858">Whilst this army moved off on one side, that of the Emperor advanced from the other; he had invaded the country of the Grisons and the Valtellina; and now he was preparing to descend into the Milanese. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15859" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15910">Besides all the distress and annoyance which might be expected from such a march, express intelligence had been received by the Tribunal of Health, that the plague lurked in this army. There were always some sprinklings of it among the German troops, remarks Varchi, when speaking of the plague brought by the Germans to Florence a century before. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15911" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15971">Alessandro Tadino, one of the guardians of the public (there were six of them besides the president; magistrates and two physicians), was commissioned by the Tribunal, as he himself relates in the report already cited,* to represent to the government the frightful danger which threatened the country, did this army pass through the Milanese on its way to besiege Mantua, as was the universal report. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="31">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15972" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16067">All the actions of Don Gonzalo shew that he was possessed by a great desire to occupy an important place in history, and certainly history could not pass him over in silence; but, as often happens, she has failed to register one of his actions, the most worthy of memory, his reply to the request of Tadino, which was, "that he did not know what to do; that the motives of interest and honour which occasioned the march of this army were of greater weight than the danger represented; that he should endeavour to arrange all for the best, and trust in Providence." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="32">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16068" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16192">In order, therefore, to arrange all for the best, the two physicians of the Tribunal, the above-named Tadino, and the Senator Settala, son of the celebrated Lodovico, proposed that all people should be prohibited under the severest penalties from buying any manner of article from the soldiers as they passed through; but it was not possible to make the necessity of such an order evident to the President, "a man of great kindness," says Tadino, "who could not believe that from intercourse with these soldiers, and the sale of their property, the deaths of so many millions should result." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="33">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16193" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16217">As for Don Gonzalo, he quitted Milan shortly after his reply to Tadino, and this departure was as grievous </note>
        </p>
        <p n="34">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16218" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16276">* for him as its cause. He was removed owing to the ill success of the war, the captain and promoter of which he had ever been. The populace accused him of having caused the famine; they had suffered under his government. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16277" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16328">Therefore, setting forth from his palace in a travelling carriage, surrounded by a guard of halberdiers, with two trumpeters on horseback before him, and followed by the carriages of various nobles who formed his escort, he was received by the hisses of a number of people assembled in the Cathedral Square, and who followed after in his train. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16329" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16380">The procession having entered the street which led to that gate through which he must go forth, he began to find himself in the midst of a crowd which partly was awaiting him there, partly was attracted by the sounds of the trumpets; for the trumpeters, men of great formality, had never ceased blowing their trumpets from the time they left the palace until they arrived at the city gate. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16381" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16429">And in the trial which was occasioned by this tumult, one of these trumpeters, reprimanded for having by his trumpeting increased the uproar, replied, "My lord, this is our profession; and if his Excellency did not like us to sound our trumpets, he should have commanded us to be silent." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16430" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16464">But Don Gonzalo, either fearing to appear actuated by terror, or dreading to render the multitude still more confident, or perhaps somewhat confounded, gave no command. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16465" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16494">The mob, which the guards had attempted in vain to repulse, preceded, surrounded, and followed the carriage, crying, "there go high prices out of the city!—there goes the blood of the poor!—" and even worse things than these. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16495" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16532">When they drew near the gate, the people began to fling stones, bricks, cabbage-stalks, in short, all the missile weapons usually employed in such expeditions; some hastened upon the walls, and thence made a last discharge upon the carriages which passed out through the gate. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16533" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16536">Immediately upon this they disbanded. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="35">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16537" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16564">Don Gonzalo was succeeded by Ambrogio Spinola, whose name had already acquired in the wars in Flanders that military celebrity which it still enjoys. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16605" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16646">Armies were in those times mostly composed of adventurers, enlisted by *condottieri* by profession, who received their commission from some prince, and who sometimes plied their occupation on their own account, in order then to sell both their followers and themselves. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16647" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16668">These men were attracted to this profession not so much by the pay, as by the hope of plunder, and the other allurements of utter license. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16669" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16689">There was no fixed and general discipline; this would not readily have accorded with the independent authority of the various captains. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16690" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16748">These captains themselves were not very particular regarding matters of discipline, and even had they desired a certain order, it is not very easy to see how they could have succeeded in establishing and maintaining it. Soldiers of this description would have revolted against any innovator who should have taken it into his head to abolish pillage; or at best they would have left him alone to guard his standard. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16749" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16816">And beside this, the princes who hired these troops thought more about procuring a quantity of men who would insure the success of their enterprises, than of proportioning their numbers to the means which they had of paying them, means generally very inadequate; and thus the spoils of the countries they overran became as it were a booty tacitly accorded them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16817" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16842">But little less celebrated than the name of Wallenstein is this maxim of his—that it is easier to maintain an army of a hundred thousand men, than one of twelve thousand. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16843" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16893">The army of which we speak was in great part composed of men who under his command had ravaged Germany in his war so celebrated among all other wars, both for itself and its effects, and which afterwards received its name from the thirty years of its duration. It was now eleven years since the war had commenced. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16894" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16937">In this army was even Wallenstein's own regiment, conducted by one of his lieutenants; most of the other captains had served under him; and among these were some who, four years later, assisted him to meet with that tragical end which is known to every one. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="36">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16938" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16996">There were twenty-eight thousand infantry and seven thousand horse. Descending from the Valtellina towards Milan, they had to follow the Adda to where it empties itself into the Po, and then must coast along this river for a considerable distance—in all, eight days' march in the duchy of Milan. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="37">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16997" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_17052">A great part of the inhabitants fled to the mountains, carrying with them their most valuable property and their cattle; some remained, in order not to abandon sick relatives, to preserve their houses from being burnt, or to keep watch over concealed or buried treasure; others, because they had nothing to lose; and a few because they hoped to gain something. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_17053" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_17108">When the first squadron arrived at the village where it should halt, the news quickly spread through the whole of that village and the neighbouring ones, and the soldiers immediately commenced plundering; whatever could be eaten or carried off directly disappeared, the rest they destroyed or at least ruined; furniture became firewood; houses, stables; we say nothing of the wounds and blows and violence that was committed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_17109" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_17127">All schemes and stratagems by which to conceal property were at best useless, often only productive of terrible consequences. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_17128" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_17206">The soldiers, people much better practised in these arts than the poor peasants, groped in every hole and corner of the houses, dismantling and pulling down walls; they easily discovered in the gardens the freshly turned up earth; they even ascended to the mountains to steal the cattle; guided by treacherous peasants, they descended into the caves in search of some wealthy inhabitant who might have concealed himself there; they would drag him to his house, and torturing him with threats and blows, constrain him to disclose to them his hidden treasure. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="38">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_17207" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_17246">At length they depart; they are gone,—in the distance the sounds of their drums and trumpets die away, and some hours of a terrible calm succeed. But again is heard the fearful roll of the drum, which announces another squadron. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_17247" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_17306">These, ferocious at finding no longer anything to plunder, destroy all that remains; burn the furniture, the doors, the beams, the casks, the very houses even; and exercise the most terrible cruelties towards the inhabitants. Things grew worse and worse for twenty days, for into so many detachments was the army divided. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="39">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap28-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_17307" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_17337">Colico was the first village in the duchy which these demons invaded; they then threw themselves upon Bellano; and next entered and spread themselves through the Valsassena, from whence they marched into the territory of Lecco. </note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>