<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CHAPTER XXIX.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>1845</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed Lovers: a Milanese Story of the Seventeenth Century. With The Column of Infamy by Alessandro Manzoni. In Three Volumes</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
          <date>1845</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Henry Francis C. Logan</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="English_1845_cap29">
        <p n="1">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10010">Here among the poor terrified inhabitants we find persons of our acquaintance. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="2">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10011" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10045">Who did not happen to see Don Abbondio that day, when suddenly the rumours of the descent of this army, of its approach and of its excesses, spread itself through the country, can form no just idea of embarrassment and terror. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10046" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10116">"They are coming! there are thirty—forty—fifty thousand! They are devils, Arians, antichrists! They have sacked Cortenova; have set fire to Primaluna; they are ravaging Introbbio, Pasturo, Barsio; they have arrived at Balabbo; to-morrow they will be here!" Such were the reports which passed from mouth to mouth, and there was a rushing about and a standing still by turns, a tumultuous consultation, a hesitation of whether they should fly or remain, an assembling of women, a wailing and tearing of hair. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10117" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10146">Don Abbondio had resolved upon flight, and had resolved upon it earlier than all the rest; he discovered, however, in every path he might take, in every place where he could conceal himself, invincible obstacles and frightful dangers. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10147" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10151">"What must I do?" he exclaimed: "where shall I go?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10152" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10182">The mountains, without speaking of the difficulty of the ascent, were not secure; it was already well known that the German lancers clambered up them like cats, even where they could scarcely have had the slightest indication or hope of prey. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10183" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10236">The lake had overflowed its banks: there blew a violent wind; besides this, the greater part of the boatmen, fearing to be forced to carry over the soldiers or the baggage, had fled with their boats to the opposite shore; the few which remained were crowded with passengers; together with their heavy cargoes and the tempest, it was expected that every moment they would be lost. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10237" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10278">It was impossible to find either a carriage, or a horse, or any other means of conveyance, to carry him out of the route of the army. Don Abbondio could not proceed very far on foot, and besides he feared to be overtaken on the road. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10279" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10345">The confines of the Bergamascan territories were not so far but that his legs might have carried him there in one journey; but already the report had reached them that a detachment of cappelletti had been despatched in all haste to guard the frontiers, and keep the German lancers in subjection; and these cappelletti were no less devils incarnate than the lancers, and on their side did all the mischief they could. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10346" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10467">The poor man ran about his room like one insane, almost out of his wits with terror; he hastened to Perpetua, to concert some resolution with her; but Perpetua, occupied in collecting the most valuable articles, and concealing them under the floor in the smallest holes, passed on, busy and preoccupied, with her hands and arms full, and only replied, "immediately I shall have placed these things in safety, and then we will do like all the rest." Don Abbondio wished to detain her, and discuss with her the various plans to be resolved upon; but she, between her occupation and her haste, the terror which she herself was seized with, and the anger she felt at seeing the terror of her master, was in the present circumstances even less tractable than usual. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10468" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10473">"Others do the best they can, and so will we. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10474" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10481">Excuse me, but you only hinder me. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10482" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10493">Do you think that other people have not their lives to save? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10494" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10503">Why, are the soldiers coming to make war upon you in particular? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10504" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10522">You might at least lend a hand in such a moment as this, instead of only getting into one's way." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10523" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10557">And with these and similar replies she succeeded in ridding herself of him, having already arranged in her mind that, when all this hurried business should be at an end, she would take him like a child by the arm and drag him up the mountains. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10558" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10597">Being thus left alone, he approached a window, looked out, listened, and perceiving some one pass, he cried, in a tone between that of lamentation and reproach, "Do your poor Curate the charity to seek for him some kind of a horse, a mule, or an ass. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="3">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10598" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10603">Is it really possible that no one will assist me? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10604" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10606">O what people they are! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10607" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10627">Wait for me, at least, so that I can go with you; wait until there are fifteen or twenty of you who can go along with me altogether, so that I am not left abandoned here. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10628" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10633">Will you leave me in the hands of these dogs? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10634" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10649">Do you not know that the greater part are Lutherans, who consider murdering a priest a meritorious work? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10650" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10656">Will you leave me here to suffer martyrdom? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10657" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10662">O what people—what people!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="4">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10663" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10668">But to whom did he address these words? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10669" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10710">To men who passed along, bowed under the burden of their poor property, full of thought regarding that which they had left behind in their houses; some were driving their cattle before them; others dragging along their children, who were also heavily laden, and their wives hurried on carrying their infants in their arms. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10711" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10740">Some pursued their route without returning any reply, or even without casting a glance towards the speaker; one said, "Ah, sir! you must do as well as you can; you are fortunate in having no family to care for. Assist yourself, bestir yourself." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="5">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10741" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10751">"Oh, unfortunate that I am!" exclaimed Don Abbondio. "O what people! what hard hearts! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10752" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10764">There is no charity: every one thinks only of himself, and no one will think of me." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10765" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10770">And here he went in search of Perpetua. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="6">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10771" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10778">"Oh! here you are just at the right time," said she, "and the money?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="7">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10779" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10780">"What shall we do?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="8">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10781" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10796">"Give me it, that I may go and bury it in the garden with the plate." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="9">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10797" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10797">"But—" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="10">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10798" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10815">"But, but—give it me here; keep a few pence for our necessities, and then leave the rest to me." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="11">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10816" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10842">Don Abbondio obeyed; he went towards his chest, drew forth his little treasure, and consigned it into Perpetua's hands, who said, "I shall go and bury it in the garden at the foot of the fig-tree," and away she went. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="12">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10843" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10885">Shortly after she entered with one basket in which was a supply of provisions, and with another which was empty, and into this, with the greatest haste, she began laying a change of linen for her master and herself, saying meanwhile—"you yourself will at least carry the Breviary." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="13">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10886" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10888">"But where are we going?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="14">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10889" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10893">"Where is every one going? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10894" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10908">First of all we shall go into the road; and there we shall hear and see what we must do." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="15">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10909" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10929">At this moment, Agnese entered with a large basket on her shoulders, and with the air of one who is about to make an important proposition. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="16">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10930" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10962">Agnese, being also resolved not to await such dangerous guests, alone as she was, in her cottage, with the remains of the Unknown's gold, had for some time been uncertain as to where she should retire. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10963" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11017">The remainder of these scudi, which during the famine had been of such signal service to her, was the principal cause of her alarm and irresolution; for she had heard say, how in the villages already invaded those who were possessed of money had been reduced to a greater extremity than the others, exposed at once as they were to the violence of the foreigners and the snares of their fellow-countrymen. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11018" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11061">It is true she had never confided to any one the secret of this wealth, which as it were had fallen from heaven, except to Don Abbondio, to whose house she went time after time to get a scudi changed, always, however, leaving with him something for the poor. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11062" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11083">But concealed money, particularly to those who are not accustomed to such a possession, is a cause of constant alarm and distrust of others. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11084" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11164">Now, whilst she was busied in hiding here and there as well as she could those things which she could not carry away with her, and thinking also of the scudi which she had concealed in her petticoat, she remembered that, together with these, the Unknown had made her the most friendly offer of his service; she remembered the things she had heard related of his castle, situated in such a very secure place, and which, without permission of the master, none but the birds of the air could approach; and there she resolved to go and seek an asylum. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11165" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11235">She thought in what way it would be possible to make herself known to this Signor, and immediately Don Abbondio recurred to her mind, who, since the conversation with the Archbishop, had been particularly gracious towards her, and had exhibited a kindness which was all the warmer, there being no longer any danger of his compromising himself, for the two young people were far enough away, and there was no probability of a request which would have tested his benevolence. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11236" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11269">She imagined that, in this general confusion, the poor man would be even more embarrassed and alarmed than herself, and that this scheme would also appear very good to him; therefore she came to propose it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11270" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11278">She found him with Perpetua, and laid the proposal before both of them. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="17">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11279" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11285">"What do you say to it, Perpetua?" demanded Don Abbondio. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="18">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11286" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11304">"I say that it is an inspiration from heaven, and that we must not lose time, but immediately set out." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="19">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11305" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11306">"And then——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="20">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11307" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11317">"And then, when we are there, we shall find ourselves very well satisfied. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11318" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11339">This Signor, it is now well known, only desires to assist his neighbour; and he will be very happy to give us an asylum. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11340" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11351">There, on the frontiers, and almost in the clouds, the soldiers certainly will never reach us. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11352" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11386">And then besides, in this castle, we shall find something to eat. And up among the mountains, when these good gifts of God were ended," saying this, she arranged the provisions in the little basket, "we should find ourselves but badly off." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="21">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11387" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11391">"He is then converted—he is really then converted?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11392" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11409">" What doubt can there be about it, after all that is known, after what you yourself have seen?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="22">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11410" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11416">" But, if we should be putting ourselves in gaol?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="23">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11417" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11418">" In gaol! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11419" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11432">With all your excuses, pardon me, we shall never come to a conclusion. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11433" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11440">Good Agnese, you have indeed had an excellent idea." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11441" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11457">Perpetua placed the large basket on the table, passed her arms through the straps, and heaved it upon her shoulders. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="24">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11458" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11477">" But could we not," said Don Abbondio, "find some men who would come with us, and form an escort for their curate? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11478" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11496">If we should encounter some ruffian, and there are only too many of the kind about, what assistance could you be to me?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="25">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11497" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11502">" Another excuse—and only to lose time!" exclaimed Perpetua. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11503" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11515">"Go then, and look out for such a man, and see whether you can find him, now every one is looking after his own affairs. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11516" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11526">Come!—go and fetch your Breviary and your hat, and let us be gone." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="26">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11527" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11561">Don Abbondio went, and immediately re-appeared with his Breviary under his arm, his hat on his head, and his staff in his hand; then, through a small door which opened into the churchyard, they passed out. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11562" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11587">Perpetua closed the door, more out of regard to custom than from any faith which she placed in this lock or in these panels, and then put the key in her pocket. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11588" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11609">Don Abbondio in passing by cast a glance at the church, and muttered between his teeth, "it is the people's business to take care of the church; it is built for their service. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11610" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11630">If they had any love for their church, they would think about that; if they have not, that's their concern." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="27">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11631" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11655">They travelled on through the fields very silently, each one thinking over his own affairs, and glancing around them, especially Don Abbondio, to see whether any suspicious figure, or anything extraordinary presented itself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11656" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11679">But they did not meet any one; the people were either in their houses waiting to guard them, busy making up their packages, or upon the roads which led to the heights. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="28">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11680" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11698">Don Abbondio, having sighed, and sighed again, having broke forth in several interjections, commenced grumbling aloud. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11699" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11761">He attacked the Duke de Nevers, who should have stayed in France, enjoyed himself there, and played the prince, instead of which he wished to be Duke of Mantua, in despite of all the world; the Emperor, who ought to have had judgment enough for the others, and who would after all have been Emperor, had Peter or Paul been Duke of Mantua. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11762" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11795">But above all did he attack the Governor, whose business it ought to have been to keep this scourge at as great a distance as possible from his country, and yet it was he himself who had brought all this misery upon them through his love of war. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="29">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11796" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11809">"These Signors ought to be here," said our poor Curate, "to experience how delightful all this is. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11810" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11815">They will have a fine account to render. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11816" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11826">But in the meantime those who are innocent suffer." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="30">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11827" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11844">"Only leave these people alone; it is not they who will come to our aid," said Perpetua. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11845" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11857">"Pardon me, but this is your usual gossip which ends in nothing. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11858" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11863">What makes me more uneasy——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="31">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11864" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11865">"Is what?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="32">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11866" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11907">Perpetua, who during their walk had thought over at leisure the hasty concealment of the property, began to torment herself that she had not brought such an article, that she had so ill secreted something else, that she had left behind a trace which might direct the thieves, that— </note>
        </p>
        <p n="33">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11908" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11930">"Well done!" exclaimed Don Abbondio, who now felt sufficiently secure of his life, to suffer anxiety regarding his property, "well done! what were you about? where was your head gone to?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="34">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11931" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11976">"How!" cried Perpetua, suddenly stopping short, and placing her arms as much a-kimbo as the basket on her back would permit, "how! you overwhelm me with reproaches, when it was you yourself who made me lose my head, instead of having assisted and encouraged me. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11977" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12019">I have perhaps thought more of the household property than of my own. I have not had a single soul to lend me a hand; if anything evil happens, I have nothing to say. I have done more than my duty." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="35">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12020" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12096">Agnese interrupted these disputes by lamenting her own woes. "She did not complain," she said, "so much of all this inconvenience and trouble, as of seeing her hope of speedy re-union with her Lucia vanish;" for, if you remember, it was precisely this autumn that they had arranged to meet; neither was it to be supposed that Donna Prassede would come for country air into this neighbourhood; and even had she come, she would speedily have departed again, like every one else. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="36">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12097" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12113">The sight of the various places they passed rendered these thoughts of Agnese still more bitter, and her vexation more evident. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12114" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12148">Having left the by-paths, they had entered the high road, the same along which the poor woman had for so short a time conducted her daughter home, after they had both lodged togeother in the tailor's house. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12149" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12154">Already she perceived the village. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="37">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12155" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12163">"We will go and salute these good people," said Agnese. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="38">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12164" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12186">"And let us rest ourselves a little, for I begin already to have had enough of this basket; and let us eat a mouthful also," said Perpetua. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="39">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12187" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12202">"Under the one condition, that we lose no time; for this is by no means a mere journey of pleasure," concluded Don Abbondio. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="40">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12203" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12216">They were received with open arms and kind looks by their good host and hostess, who were reminded of a benevolent deed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12217" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12241">"The more good you do," remarks our Anonymous, "the oftener will you meet with countenances which will inspire you with joy." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="41">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12242" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12272">Agnese, embracing the good woman, burst into a flood of tears, which greatly relieved her; and replied with many sobs to the questions which both husband and wife asked regarding Lucia. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="42">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12273" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12289">"She is better off than we," said Don Abbondio; "she is at Milan, out of all danger, far away from all this devilish business." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="43">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12290" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12300">"The Signor Curato and his companions are escaping?" asked the tailor. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="44">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12301" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12310">"Certainly," replied the master and servant in one breath. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="45">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12311" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12312">"I am truly sorry for you." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="46">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12313" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12328">"We are on our way to the castle of ———," remarked Don Abbondio. "You have decided very wisely; you will be as secure there as in a church." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="48">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12329" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12336">"And pray are you not afraid in this place?" asked Don Abbondio. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12337" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12394">"We are too far out of the road, thank heaven; and even should the worst happen—which God forbid—we should still have time to escape." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="49">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12395" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12429">The three fugitives had decided to rest there a few moments, and recover breath. It was the hour of dinner: "Will you honour my poor table?" said the tailor; "at least you will meet with a hearty welcome." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="50">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12430" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12439">Perpetua said that they had brought a small supply of provisions with them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12440" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12464">After a little ceremony on both sides, they agreed to place all on the table and dine in company. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="51">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12465" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12477">The children had arranged themselves with a deal of joy around their old friend Agnese. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12478" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12518">The tailor ordered a little girl—the same who had carried his donation to the widow Maria; who knows whether our readers may still remember the circumstance?—to go and unhus k some early chestnuts which were lying in a corner, and put them to roast. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="52">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12519" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12541">"And thou," said he to a little boy, "go into the garden and shake down some of the peaches, and bring them here,—all of them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12542" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12556">And go thou," said he to a third child, "and climb into the fig-tree, and gather a few of the ripest. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12557" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12563">You are only too well versed in the business." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12564" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12580">He himself went to broach a little barrel, and his wife went in search of some table-linen. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12581" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12607">Perpetua drew forth her provisions. The cloth was laid; there was a coarse napkin and an earthenware plate placed at the post of honour for Don Abbondio, also a cover which Perpetua had brought in her basket. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12608" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12632">The dinner was served, and they dined, if not gaily, at least with far more comfort than any one of the guests had expected to enjoy that day. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12633" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12655">"What does the Signor Curato say to a dispersion of this kind?" said the tailor. "It seems to me that I am reading the history of the Moors in France." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="53">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12656" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12658">"What I say to it? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12659" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12664">Why should such a misfortune have fallen upon me!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="54">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12665" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12680">"You have, however, chosen an excellent asylum," returned the host; "for who can reach the heights without the Signor's permission? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12681" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12698">You will find plenty of company there. I have heard that many people have already taken refuge there, and others arrive every hour." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="55">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12699" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12707">"I hope that we shall be well received," said Don Abbondio. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12708" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12726">"I am acquainted with this worthy Signor; and the other time when I had the honour of being in his company, he was so very polite!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="56">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12727" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12749">"And he sent me word by his illustrious lordship," said Agnese, "that if ever I stood in need of assistance, I had only to go to him." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="57">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12750" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12762">"A grand and beautiful conversion!" resumed Don Abbondio; "and he perseveres in it, does he not—he perseveres in it?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="58">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12763" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12787">The tailor here began at much length to expatiate upon the holy life now led by the Unknown, and how, after being for so long the scourge of the whole country, he was become its example and benefactor. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="59">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12788" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12815">"And all those people which he had with him — all that band? —" demanded Don Abbondio, who had more than once heard speak of them, but who knew nothing positive. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="60">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12816" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12832">"The greater part have left him," replied the tailor; "and those that have stayed have changed their mode of life, in such a way! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12833" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12845">In short, this castle has become like the Thebaid; but you know all this." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12846" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12855">He then began speaking to Agnese about the Cardinal's visit. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12856" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12858">"A great man!" said he, "a great man! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12859" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12877">Pity that he left here in such haste that I was unable to do him a little honour. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12878" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12890">How happy I should be to have an opportunity of speaking to him again, a little more at my leisure!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="61">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12891" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12943">Having risen from table, he made them observe a print representing the Cardinal, which he had fastened upon the door in veneration of this good man, and also that he might be able to tell every one that the portrait was not like, for he had examined the Cardinal in person, closely and at his leisure, and in this very room too. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="62">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12944" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12953">"And they mean this thing for him?" said Agnese. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12954" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12958">"The dress is like him, but—" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="63">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12959" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12986">"It is not like—is it?" interrupted the tailor; "that's what I always say; they can't cheat us with it—eh? But if there's nothing else, there's at least his name underneath; it is just a memory of him." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="64">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12987" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13015">Don Abbondio appeared in haste to depart; the tailor ran to seek a vehicle to carry the fugitives to the foot of the ascent, and shortly after returned to say that it was coming. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13016" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13049">He then turned towards Don Abbondio, and said, "Signor Curato, if you should desire to carry any book with you up to the castle for a little pastime, I could be of service to you perhaps, for I also amuse myself a little with reading. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13050" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13059">They are not such books as yours, they are books in the vulgar tongue; but yet—" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="65">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13060" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13078">"Thanks, a thousand thanks," returned Don Abbondio; "the circumstances are such, that I have scarcely brains enough left to read my Breviary." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="66">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13079" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13107">Whilst they are exchanging thanks, condolences, good wishes, invitations, and promises to pay another visit upon their return, the cart has paused before the door. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13108" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13128">The baskets are placed in it; they mount, and they begin, with a little more calmness and tranquility of mind, the second half of their journey. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="67">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13129" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13139">The tailor had related to Don Abbondio the truth regarding the Unknown. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13140" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13168">From that day on which he left him, the Signor had pursued the course of life which he had proposed to himself—repairing wrongs, reconciling himself with his enemies, succouring the unfortunate, doing, in short, all the good which lay in his power. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13169" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13190">The courage which formerly he had exhibited in offence and defence, now he exhibited in doing neither one nor the other. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13191" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13260">He was now always seen alone and unarmed; disposed to suffer the possible consequences of all the violence he had committed, and persuaded that it would only be committing a fresh crime should he employ force in the defence of himself, who was a debtor to the whole of society; persuaded that all evil done to him would be a sin against God, yet only towards him a just retribution; and that he less than any one had a right to avenge himself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13261" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13281">But he was not less inviolable than when he bore arms, and was surrounded by so many armed followers. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13282" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13321">The remembrance of his ancient ferocity, and the spectacle of his present gentleness, the former exciting a desire for vengeance, the latter rendering this vengeance so easy, conspired in exciting and maintaining an admiration of him which served principally as his safeguard. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13322" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13334">This man, whom no one could ever humble, had humbled himself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13335" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13395">The hatred which his scorn and fear had excited against him had vanished now before this new humility: those whom he had wronged, had obtained, contrary to their expectations and without danger, a satisfaction which they could never have promised themselves even by the most signal vengeance, the satisfaction of seeing a man repentant of his evil deeds, and participating, so to say, in their indignation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13396" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13449">Many whose anger during such a length of years had been all the more bitter and intense at seeing no probability of their ever becoming more powerful than he, and thus finding an opportunity by which to avenge their injuries, now meeting him alone, unarmed and unresisting, felt no other impulse than that of respect and compassion. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13450" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13489">In this voluntary abasement, his air and countenance had acquired, without himself being aware of it, something indescribably noble and elevated; for now stronger than ever might be perceived in his demeanour a carelessness towards all danger. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13490" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13513">Even his most violent and obstinate enemies felt awed and checked by the public veneration for this penitent and beneficent man. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13514" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13558">So strong was this public veneration, that he often found himself embarrassed by it, and had great difficulty in preventing his internal compunction from depicting itself too visibly in his countenance and air, and thus, by abasing himself too much, be exalted too highly in general estimation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13559" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13579">He had chosen for himself the lowest seat in the church; there was no fear lest it should be occupied by any one else—that would have been like usurping a place of honour. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13580" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13619">To have offended this man, or even to have treated him with irreverence, would have appeared not only a crime and an infamous thing, but even sacrilege. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="68">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13620" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13648">These and yet other causes averted from him the vengeance of the public authorities, and procured him even from them a security which he had never anticipated. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13649" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13688">His rank and high connexions, which always had served him as a certain defence, were now of double value, seeing that this illustrious and dreaded name had become glorified through his exemplary conduct and striking conversion. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13689" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13714">The magistrates and the nobility had publicly rejoiced with the people over this change; and it would indeed have appeared very strange to denounce a man who had been the object of so much joy. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13715" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13766">Besides, a power occupied in perpetual warfare, and always unfortunate in violent and ever-recurring rebellions, might consider itself happy in being liberated from one of its most dangerous and untameable enemies. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13767" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13811">To torment a saint did not appear a good method by which to cancel the shame of not having known how to subdue a villain; and this example of their clemency would only have deterred similar characters from becoming inoffensive. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13812" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13839">Probably also the part taken by the Cardinal Federigo in his conversion, and his name being associated with that of the converted, served also as a sacred buckler. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="69">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13840" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14056">Thus this very man, who, had he fallen by misfortune and evil destiny, would have been trampled under foot by high and low, now that he voluntarily prostrated himself upon the earth, was pardoned by all, revered by many. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="70">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14057" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14154">By degrees the greater number of his myrmidons, unable to accustom themselves to this new discipline, and seeing that there was no probability of change, had taken their departure. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14155" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14215">Some had sought other masters, often among the former friends of their former lord; others had enlisted in some terzo, as it was then called, of Spain, or Mantua, or perhaps with some other belligerent party; some had taken up their abode on the highway, there to wage petty war upon their own account. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14216" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14231">The same thing happened with those who previous to his orders had been stationed in various other places. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14232" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14305">Those who had accustomed themselves to this new mode of life, or who had voluntarily embraced it, the greater part of whom were natives of the valley, had returned to labour in the fields, or to ply those trades which they had learned in their youth, and which they had abandoned for the bravo's profession; the few who were foreigners remained in the castle, occupying the place of domestics; all, as though at the same time with their master inspired by the grace of God, passed like him their lives, neither offering nor receiving offence, unarmed and respected. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="71">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14306" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14408">But when, upon the arrival of these German troops, a few fugitives from menaced or invaded villages arrived at the castle seeking an asylum, the Unknown, quite happy that these his awe-inspiring walls should now be sought as a place of refuge, received the wanderers with expressions rather of gratitude than of mere courtesy. He announced that his dwelling should be opened to whosoever desired to take refuge there; and thought immediately of putting not only his castle, but also the whole valley, in a state of defence, should either German lancers, or cappelletti, ever dare to molest him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14409" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14493">He assembled his few remaining servants, and addressed a few words to them regarding the good opportunity which God thus offered them and himself of exercising themselves for once in aid of the weak, whom they had so often oppressed and terrified; and with that natural tone of command which announced his certainty of their ready obedience, he informed them in general terms of what he desired should be done, and, above all, prescribed how they should conduct themselves towards the fugitives, and consider them as friends and defenders. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14494" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14600">He had the arms and ammunition brought down from a room in the roof where he had consigned them, and caused them to be distributed among his household. He sent word to his peasants and tenants in the valley, that any one who desired should come armed to the castle; he gave arms to those who were without, selected some as officers, and placed the others under their command; he assigned their posts, at the entrance, and in different parts of the valley, upon the ascent, and before the castle-gates; he fixed in what manner and at what hours they should change guard, as in a camp, or also as had been customary in this very castle during the wicked portion of his life. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="72">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14601" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14633">Apart by themselves in a corner of this same garret were placed the arms which he himself had worn — his famous carabine, his muskets, his swords, his daggers, lying on the ground or reared up against the wall. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14634" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14650">Not one of the servitors dared to remove them, but they concerted among themselves that they would ask their master which they should bring him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14651" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14667">"Not one of them," he replied; and whether from principle, or having made a vow, he remained always unarmed at the head of his garrison. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="73">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14668" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14708">At the same time, he set in motion a number of other men, and women also, who were in his service and among his dependents, to prepare the castle for the reception of as many people as possible; they had to erect beds, and dispose sacks and mattresses, in all the apartments, and even in the halls, which were turned into dormitories for the occasion. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14709" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14735">He ordered that an abundant supply of provisions should be laid in for the use of the guests whom God should send him, and who, in fact, arrived in greater numbers day by day. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14736" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14785">He, meanwhile, was never idle; he was either in or out of the castle, on the heights, or in the valley, visiting the various posts, examining every thing, shewing himself everywhere, placing and maintaining every thing in order, by his word, his glance, and his presence. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap29-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14786" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14840">In his castle, upon the road, he received cordially all the fugitives who arrived; and all, whether they had seen him before, or whether they now saw him for the first time, gazed upon him with astonishment, forgetting for a moment their misfortunes and their terror which had conducted them thither; and would again turn round to look after him as he pursued his way. </note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>