<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CHAPTER XX.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>1845</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed Lovers: a Milanese Story of the Seventeenth Century. With The Column of Infamy by Alessandro Manzoni. In Three Volumes</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
          <date>1845</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Henry Francis C. Logan</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="English_1845_cap20">
        <p n="1">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10062">The castle of the Unknown was situated above a narrow and gloomy valley, upon the summit of a cliff which jutted forth from a rugged chain of hills, and it would have been difficult to say whether it were united to, or separated from this chain by a chaos of rocks and precipices, and a labyrinth of caves and abysses which stretched themselves on either hand. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10063" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10093">The only accessible side of the cliff is that which faces the valley; you behold a rather steep, but regular and continuous descent; above are pastures, below are fields scattered over here and there with habitations. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10094" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10116">Along the bottom of the valley extends a bed of pebbles, where flows, according to the season, either a small stream or a mighty torrent, which then serves as a boundary to the two states. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10117" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10155">The opposite chain, which forms as it were the other wall of the valley, has also a small tract of cultivation; the rest presents only rocks and stones, rapid descents, pathless and utterly bare, except where here and there a few bushes start out of the crevices of the rock. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="2">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10156" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10191">From his gloomy castle, like the eagle from his bloody nest, this savage Signor reigned supreme over every inch of earth on which a human foot could tread, and never saw a living soul above him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10192" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10208">Casting a glance below he could overlook all this inclosure, the mountain sides, the depth, and the various paths which had been made there. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10209" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10253">The pathway, which full of turns and windings ascended to this terrible habitation, stretched itself out before the eyes of him who regarded it from below like a curling ribbon; and from the windows of this murderous dwelling, the Signor could at leisure count the steps of those who approached, and level his weapon a hundred times. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10254" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10285">And even had a considerable body of his enemies shewn itself, with the garrison of bravoes which he kept in his castle he would have been able to stretch them lifeless on the way, or have sent them all rolling to the bottom of the valley before a single one should have reached the summit. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10286" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10312">In short, no one dared set foot in the valley, not even to pass through it, unless he were regarded by this Signor with friendly eyes. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10313" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10334">An officer of justice then, who should have shewn himself there, would have been treated as a spy seized in an enemy's camp. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10335" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10369">Tragical stories were related of the last who had wished to attempt the undertaking; but these were already old histories, and not one of the younger men remembered ever to have seen a creature of this race in the valley either alive or dead. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="3">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10370" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10413">Such is the description the Anonymous gives of the place, of its name he says nothing; and even, lest he should put us in the way to discover it, he says nothing either of Don Rodrigo's journey. He brings him straight into the middle of the valley, at the foot of the cliff, at the opening of the steep and winding pathway. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10414" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10427">Here was a tavern, which might also be called a corps-de-garde. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10428" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10473">Upon an old sign-board, which hung over the entrance, was painted on both sides a rising sun; but the public, who sometimes repeat the names which they are taught, and sometimes alter them after their own fancy, only called this tavern the *Malanotte*. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="4">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10474" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10509">At the sound of an approaching cavalcade, a lad, armed like a very Saracen, appeared upon the threshold, he cast a hasty glance at the party, and entered the tavern, to give information to three hectoring fellows, who were seated, playing with a filthy crumpled pack of cards. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10510" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10527">He who seemed the chief rose, looked out at the door, and recognising a friend of his master, saluted him respectfully. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10528" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10565">Don Rodrigo returned his salutation with great politeness, asking whether the Signor were at his castle, and, upon this man's replying that he believed he was, dismounted, and threw the bridle to Tiradritto, one of his followers. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10566" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10600">He then laid aside his musket, consigning it to Montanarolo, as if to disencumber himself of a useless weight, and thus ascend more easily; but in reality he did this, knowing very well that no one was permitted to shew himself on this cliff carrying a musket. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10601" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10628">He then drew from his pocket a few berlinghe, and gave them to Tanabuso, saying, "You wait here for me; and in the meantime amuse yourselves with these good fellows." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="6">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10629" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10667">He drew forth some gold coins, which he placed in the chief's hand, half for himself, half to be divided between his men; and, at length, with Griso, who had also laid aside his musket, he commenced the ascent on foot. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10668" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10711">Meanwhile, the three bravoes we have already mentioned, and Squinternotto, who was the fourth, (O only observe what beautiful names these are to be preserved with such care!) remained with the three belonging to the Unknown, and with the lad educated for the gallows, to play, to drink, and to relate by turns their various feats of valour. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="7">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10712" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10756">Another of the Unknown's bravoes, who was ascending, shortly after joined Don Rodrigo. He looked at him, recognised who he was, and accompanied him on his way, thus sparing him the annoyance of having to tell his name and give account of himself to as many others as should happen to meet him and not know him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10757" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10811">When he had arrived at the castle, and, been introduced into it, leaving Griso at the portal, he passed through a labyrinth of dark corridors, and through various halls, hung with a tapestry of muskets, sabres, and partisans; and in every one of these halls there was a bravo on guard. After having waited some time, he was admitted into the room where was the Unknown. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="8">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10812" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10848">This mysterious personage came towards Don Rodrigo, returning his salutation, at the same time that he glanced at his hands and face, as he was accustomed to do, almost involuntarily, when any one came near him, even though this should be one of his oldest and most tried friends. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10849" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10905">He was tall, of a dark complexion, and bald; the few hairs which remained were white, his countenance was wrinkled; at the first glance, you would have pronounced him more than sixty, which was his real age. But his bearing, his movements, the remarkably hard expression of his features, the dark yet quick flash of his eyes, indicated a strength of body and mind which would have been extraordinary in a youth. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="9">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10906" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10953">Don Rodrigo said that he was come to him for counsel and for aid; that finding himself engaged in a difficult undertaking, out of which his honour prevented him from withdrawing himself, he had recollected the promises of this man, who never promised too much, or in vain, and determined to explain his terrible embarrassment to him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10954" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11002">The Unknown, who already knew something of the affair, but only confusedly, listened with much attention, like one curious in such histories; for in this one was mixed up a name, at the same time, known and odious to him, the name of Fra Cristoforo, the open enemy of all tyrants. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11003" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11024">Don Rodrigo, knowing with whom he spoke, began to exaggerate the difficulties of the enterprise; the distance of the place, a monastery, the Signora </note>
        </p>
        <p n="10">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11025" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11047">At this the Unknown, as though a demon concealed in his heart had prompted him, suddenly interrupted Don Rodrigo, saying, that he would take the whole affair upon himself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11048" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11071">Took note of our poor Lucia's name, and took leave of Don Rodrigo, saying, "In a short time you shall receive from me advice what to do." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="11">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11072" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11120">If the reader remember that wretch Egidio, who dwelt near the monastery in which poor Lucia was received, let him now learn that this man was one of the Unknown's most intimate associates in wickedness; it was on this account, therefore, that the latter had so readily and resolutely given his word. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11121" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11133">But no sooner was he alone, than he, I will not say repented, but felt sorry that he had given it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11134" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11149">Already for some time he had experienced, if not remorse, a certain disgust towards his wicked deeds. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11150" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11189">Each time that he committed a fresh one, the many with which he had loaded, if not his conscience, at least his memory, were revived, and presented themselves to his mind in hideous colours; every fresh act of wickedness committed, was like increasing a weight already inconvenient. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11190" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11208">A certain repugnance which he had experienced in perpetrating his first crimes, but which he had afterwards conquered so that it had eventually disappeared, now returned to torture him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11209" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11293">But, in former times, the idea of a long undefined future, the feeling of vigorous life, filled his soul with a careless confidence; now, on the contrary, these very thoughts of the future were what rendered the past still more painful. "To grow old! to die! and then—?" Strange to say, the image of death which, when near to danger, when in the very face of his enemy, had used to redouble the ardour of this man, and inspire him with an anger full of courage—this same image appearing to him in the silence of the night, in the security of his castle, threw him into a sudden consternation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11294" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11345">This death was no longer that with which a mortal adversary would have menaced him; this it would be impossible to repulse by better weapons, by a quicker arm; this death came alone, was born within him, was perhaps still far off, but every moment approached nearer, and even whilst the mind painfully strove to remove the thought, the reality drew near. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11346" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11414">In earlier times the frequent examples, the spectacle, so to say, of perpetual violence, of vengeance, and of homicide, inspiring him with a ferocious emulation, had also served as a species of authority wherewith to overrule his conscience; now again rose every moment within his soul, the confused but terrible idea of an individual judgment, of a reason independent of example; now, the having issued forth from the common crowd of criminals, the having left them all behind him, called forth a terrible feeling of solitude. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11415" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11464">This God of whom he had heard speak, but about whom he had not troubled himself for many a long day, either to deny or to acknowledge; this having lived as though there were no such Being, now, in certain moments of depression without a cause, of terror without danger, seemed to cry within his soul, "I exist, nevertheless!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11465" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11509">In the first outbreak of his passion, the law which he had heard pronounced in the name of this God, had only appeared hateful to him; now, when this idea recurred suddenly to his mind, his mind, spite of himself, comprehended it as something which has its fulfilment. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11510" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11547">But he never opened his mind to any one regarding this his new cause of disquiet, he concealed it deep in his heart, and to dissemble his real feelings assumed a sterner ferocity, by this means seeking to hide them from himself and stifle them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11548" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11592">Regretting the time (since he could neither annihilate nor forget it) in which he had been accustomed to commit crimes without remorse, without another thought than that of success, he did all in his power to make it return, to detain, and again bring back, this ancient will—bold, proud, immoveable, so as to convince himself that he was still the same man. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="12">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11593" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11610">Thus, on the present occasion, he had immediately given his word to Don Rodrigo, so as to prevent any hesitation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11611" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11688">But scarcely had the latter departed, than he felt the firmness which he had called forth for the moment, vanish, felt by little and little thoughts come into his mind which tempted him to break his word, thoughts which would have led him to lessen himself in the eyes of a friend, of an inferior accomplice; at once to cut short this painful combat he called Nibbio, one of the most active and courageous ministers of his crimes, the one he generally employed in his correspondence with Egidio. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11689" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11714">With a resolute air he commanded him immediately to mount a horse, ride straight to Monza, inform Egidio of the engagement he had entered into, and require his aid in fulfilling it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11715" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11763">The infamous messenger returned sooner than his patron had expected, bringing Egidio's reply that the enterprise was easy and safe; that the Unknown should send him immediately a carriage with two or three bravoes well disguised; that he would take upon himself the care of all the rest, and manage the whole affair. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11764" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11794">At this announcement, the Unknown, whatever might be his internal feelings, commanded this same Nibbio, in all haste, to dispose every thing according to the desire of Egidio, and to set off upon this expedition with two others whom he named. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="13">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11795" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11824">If, in order to render the horrible service demanded of him, Egidio could only have counted upon ordinary means, he would certainly not have given thus quickly so decided a promise. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11825" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11859">But in this very asylum where it would seem every thing must be an obstacle, this wicked young man possessed a power known alone to himself; and that which for others would have been the greatest difficulty was for him an instrument. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11860" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11898">We have related how the unfortunate Signora had once listened to his words, and the reader will have comprehended that this was not the last time; it was only the first step in a path of abominations and blood. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11899" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11921">This same voice which had acquired strength, and I could almost say authority, through crime, now imposed upon her the sacrifice of that innocence of which she was the guardian. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11922" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11927">The proposition appeared to Gertrude frightful. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11928" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11962">To lose Lucia through some unforeseen accident and without sin would have seemed a misfortune, a bitter punishment; and now she was commanded to deprive herself of her through an act of wicked perfidy, and to change a means of expiation into fresh remorse. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11963" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11986">The unfortunate being tried every way by which she could free herself from this horrible command; all, except the only one which was safe, and which always remained open before her. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11987" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12006">Crime is a severe and inflexible master, against whom you never are strong, unless you entirely rebel. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12007" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12014">Gertrude would not resolve to do this, and therefore she obeyed. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="14">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12015" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12087">The appointed day had arrived; the very hour approached. Gertrude, alone with Lucia in her private parlour, lavished upon her more caresses than usual, and Lucia received and returned them with an increasing tenderness; as the sheep, trembling without fear under the shepherd's hand, which gently strokes and pats it, will turn and lick this hand, unconscious that the butcher to whom the shepherd but a moment before has sold her stands without the fold. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="15">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12088" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12097">"I stand in need of assistance, and you alone can serve me. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12098" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12109">I have many people to obey my commands, but there is no one in whom I can confide. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12110" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12153">Concerning an affair of great importance, about which I will tell you afterwards, I want to speak immediately with the Capuchin Father Superior who conducted my poor Lucia to me; but at the same time it is necessary that no one should know that I have sent for him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12154" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12161">I have no one but you to send upon this secret embassy." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="16">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12162" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12206">Lucia was terrified by such a request; and with her usual timidity, but not without a strong expression of astonishment, she, immediately to excuse herself, alleged various objections, which the Signora ought to comprehend, and must certainly have foreseen; without her mother—without any one—alone on a solitary road, in an unknown country—. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12207" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12290">But Gertrude, educated in an infernal school, also shewed equal astonishment and much displeasure at meeting with a refusal from a person whom she had loaded with benefits, and she affected to consider these very frivolous excuses. In broad daylight, but a few yards along a road which Lucia had traversed but a few days before, even had she never seen it before, a simple direction would prevent her mistaking it—in short, she said so much, that the poor girl, touched, and yet at the same time driven to consent against her own will, let "well, what must I do?" escape her lips. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="17">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12291" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12332">"Go to the convent of the Capuchins," and here she again described the road; "ask to see the Father Superior, and say to him when quite alone, that he must come immediately to me, but he must tell no one that it is I who have sent for him." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="18">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12333" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12348">"But what shall I say to the stewardess, who has never seen me leave the monastery, and who will ask me where I am going to?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="19">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12349" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12370">"Endeavour to go forth without being seen; and if you do not succeed, say that you are going to such a church, where you have promised to say certain prayers." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="20">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12371" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12418">Here was a new difficulty for the poor girl, the telling a lie. But the Signora again shewed herself so much hurt by this refusal, and made it appear to Lucia so mean, the preference of a foolish scruple to gratitude, that the poor girl, confounded rather than convinced, and, above all, moved by her words, replied, "Ah, well! I will go. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12419" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12423">God help me!" and moved away. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="21">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12424" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12454">"When Gertrude, who watched her from the grate with a fixed and troubled eye, saw her step upon the threshold, as though overpowered by an irresistible feeling, she opened her mouth, and said, "Listen, Lucia!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="22">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12455" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12462">Lucia turned back, and approached the grate. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12463" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12481">But already another thought, a thought accustomed to rule, had again obtained the victory in Gertrude's unhappy mind. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12482" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12514">She feigned to be dissatisfied with the instructions she had given, again described to Lucia the road which she should take, and then took leave of her, saying, "Do all that I have told you, and return quickly." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12515" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12516">Lucia then departed. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="23">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12517" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12570">She passed unobserved through the cloister-gate, and walked on with her eyes cast down, keeping close to the wall; she found, assisted by descriptions given her, and by her own recollection, the suburb-gate, passed underneath it, walked along the high-road full of fear and trembling, and in a few moments reached the one which led to the convent; this she recognised also. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12571" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12598">This road was, and is still at the present day, sunk like the bed of a river between two high banks, bordered with trees, which meeting above formed a kind of vault. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12599" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12646">Lucia entered this road, and seeing that it was completely deserted, felt her terror increase, and quickened her steps; but soon she took courage upon seeing a travelling carriage waiting in the road, and near it, before the open door, two travellers who looked here and there, as though uncertain of their way. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12647" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12663">Going forward, she heard one of these two say, "Here is a good young woman who will tell us the road." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12664" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12693">And when she came up to the carriage, the same traveller, with a manner more gentle than his appearance, turned to her, and said, "My good girl, can you tell us the way to Monza?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="24">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12694" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12727">"Going in this direction you are wrong," replied the poor girl; "Monza lies over here—" and she turned round to point out the direction, when the other traveller (he was Nibbio) suddenly caught her round the waist and lifted her from the ground. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12728" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12781">Lucia, terrified, turned her head and screamed; the robber threw her with violence into the carriage. Another, who was seated within, seized her, and, spite of her struggles, forced her to sit opposite him, whilst a fourth, holding a handkerchief to her mouth, stifled her cries. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12782" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12802">Meanwhile, Nibbio quickly jumped into the carriage, the door was shut, and the carriage set off at full speed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12803" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12845">The other, who had asked this treacherous question, remained in the road, and cast glances here and there, to see whether any one had hastened up on hearing Lucia's screams; but there was no one; he sprang upon one of the banks, and, seizing a branch of one of the trees, he disappeared in the thicket. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12846" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12883">This was one of Egidio's servants, who had been placed at his master's door to see when Lucia should leave the monastery, and then had hastened a shorter way to wait for her at the appointed spot. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="25">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12884" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12899">Who could describe the terror, the agony, which this poor Lucia endured? Who could express what passed in her mind? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12900" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12965">She opened her terrified eyes, in her anxiety to know her horrible situation, and closed them again suddenly in her fear of these ugly faces; she struggled, but was held fast on every side; she collected all her strength, and endeavoured to fling herself out of the window, but two nervous arms held her, as though she were fastened to the seat of the carriage, four other immense hands detained her. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12966" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12982">Every time that she opened her mouth to scream, the handkerchief was thrust into it. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="26">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12983" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13005">Meanwhile, three infernal mouths in the most humane voice which they knew how to assume, continued to repeat, "Hush! hush! Do not be afraid, we will do you no ill." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13006" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13063">After a few moments of this painful struggle, she seemed to grow calm; her arms relaxed, her head fell back, she scarcely opened her eyelids; whilst her eyes remained immoveable, the horrible faces before her seemed to mingle, and blend themselves into a monstrous confusion; the colour fled from her countenance, a cold sweat covered her, she lost all power, and fainted. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="27">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13064" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13069">"Come, come, courage!" said Nibbio. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13070" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13094">"Courage, courage," repeated the other two ruffians; but the loss of every sense prevented Lucia at this moment from hearing the encouragement spoken by these horrible voices. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="28">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13095" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13105">"Diavolo! she seems dead!" said one of the bravoes. "If she should really be dead?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="29">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13106" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13118">"Oh, dead!" said the other; "it is only one of those fainting fits which women have. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13119" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13136">I know very well, that I do, when I have wished to send some one into the other world, either man or woman, something else has been wanted." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13137" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13150">"Come," said Nibbio, "attend to your duty, and don't be looking after other things. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13151" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13171">Get the muskets out of the case, and hold them in readiness, for in this wood in which we now are, there are always lots of robbers housed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13172" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13194">Don't hold them so in your hands. Diavolo! place them behind you. Don't you see that this is a chicken-hearted girl who is ready to faint at nothing? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13195" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13202">If she were to see arms, she would die in good earnest. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13203" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13224">And when she is recovered, take good care not to frighten her; do not touch her, unless I give you a signal; I am enough to hold her. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13225" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13230">And be silent, leave me to speak." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="30">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13231" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13241">In the meantime the carriage, still travelling on at the same speed, had entered the wood. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="31">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13242" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13261">After some time poor Lucia began to revive, as from a profound yet distressing sleep, and at length opened her eyes. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13262" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13284">At first she had considerable difficulty in distinguishing the frightful objects which surrounded her, and in collecting her thoughts; but soon she again comprehended her terrible situation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13285" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13321">The first use she made of the little strength which had returned to her was to endeavour to throw herself out of the window, but she was held back, and she could only see the wild solitude through which they passed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13322" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13361">She again sent forth a scream; but Nibbio, raising his large hand with the handkerchief, said, as gently as he could, "Come, be quiet, that will be the best for you. We do not wish to hurt you, but if you do not keep silent, we must make you." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="32">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13362" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13363">"Let me go! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13364" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13366">Who are you? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13367" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13369">Where are you taking me to? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13370" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13372">Why have you seized me? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13373" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13376">Let me go, let me go!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="33">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13377" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13395">"I tell you not to be afraid; you are not a child," and ought to know that we do not wish to hurt you. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13396" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13407">Don't you see that we could have killed you a hundred times before this, if we had had the intention? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13408" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13410">Therefore remain quiet." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="34">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13411" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13422">"No, no, let me go my ways; I do not know you." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13423" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13425">"We know you." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13426" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13431">"Oh, holy Virgin! How do you know me? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13432" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13435">Let me go, for charity. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13439" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13441">Why have you taken me?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13442" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13445">"Because we have been commanded." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13446" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13453">"Who, who? who can have commanded you?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13454" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13469">"Hush!" said Nibbio, with a severe countenance; "such questions may not be asked of us." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="35">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13470" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13522">Lucia attempted once more to precipitate herself suddenly through the windows, but, seeing that this was useless, she had again recourse to prayers; and, with her head bowed, with her cheeks streaming with tears, with her voice interrupted by weeping, with her hands clasped, she said, "Oh, for the love of God and the Holy Virgin, let me go! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13523" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13528">What evil have I done you? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13529" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13537">I am a poor creature, who have never hurt any one. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13538" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13552">From my heart I pardon you, and I will pray to God for you. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13553" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13571">If you have a daughter, a wife, a mother, only think what she would suffer were she thus situated. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13572" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13586">Recollect that we must all of us die, and that one day you will desire God to shew mercy to you. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13587" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13598">Let me go, let me go; the Lord will cause me to find my way." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="36">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13599" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13600">"No, we cannot." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="37">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13601" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13602">"You cannot? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13603" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13607">O Lord! Why cannot you? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13608" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13610">Where will you take me to? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13611" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13611">Why——?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="38">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13612" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13629">"We cannot, it is useless; do not be afraid, for we do not wish to hurt you; be quiet, and no one shall touch you." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13630" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13665">Yet more alarmed, depressed, and terrified, at seeing that her words produced no effect, Lucia turned to Him who holds in his hands the hearts of men, and who can, when He wills it, soften even the hardest. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13666" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13714">She drew herself together as much as she could in the corner of the carriage, crossed her arms upon her breast, and prayed for some time in her heart; then, drawing forth her rosary, she told her beads with more faith and fervour than she had ever before done in her life. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13715" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13731">Sometimes hoping she had obtained the mercy which she implored, she would turn to beseech these ruffians, but always in vain. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13732" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13746">Now she would again lose her senses, now recover them, only to revive to fresh agony. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13747" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13784">But we have not the heart to describe her sufferings more fully; too painful a compassion makes us hasten to the termination of this journey, which lasted more than four hours, after which we shall have to describe other hours of agony. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13785" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13791">We will transport ourselves to the castle where this unfortunate was expected. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="39">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13792" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13801">She was expected by the Unknown, with a disquiet and a very unusual agitation of mind. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13802" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13862">Strange that this man, who had disposed of so many lives in cold blood, who in the many crimes he had committed had counted as nothing the torments which he caused, unless it were something to enjoy in them a savage vengeance, now, in seizing upon this unknown and poor peasant girl, experienced an abhorrence, I might almost say a terror. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13863" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13902">From a lofty window of his castle he had already for some time gazed towards an opening in the valley, and now saw the carriage appear, and now advance slowly, for the first speed had consumed the impetuosity and exhausted the strength of the horses. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13903" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13953">And although, from the point at which he watched, the carriage did not appear larger than a child's toy coach, he immediately recognised it, and felt his heart beat quicker. "Will she be there?" he suddenly thought. "What vexation this girl causes me! </note>
        </p>
        <p n="40">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13954" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13982">I must free myself of her." And he was about to call one of his myrmidons, send him to meet the carriage, and order Nibbio to turn again and conduct the girl to Don Rodrigo's palace. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="41">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13983" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13995">But an imperious no, which resounded in his mind, caused this design to vanish. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13996" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14031">Tormented, however, by a desire of giving some order, and finding intolerable this inactive waiting for the carriage, which slowly advanced step by step, like some treason, or, who knows? like some chastisement, he sent for an old woman of his household. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="42">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14032" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14052">This old woman had been born in this very castle, she was the daughter of an old seneschal, and had passed here all her life. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14053" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14104">What she had seen and heard since her infancy had impressed her mind with a mighty and terrible conception of the power of her masters; and her principal maxim, founded upon instructions and example, was, that it was necessary to obey these masters in every thing, for they were able to do either great good or great evil. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14105" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14136">The idea of duty, implanted like a seed in the hearts of all men, unfolding itself in hers, together with sentiments of respect, terror, and of a servile cupidity, had associated and adapted itself to them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14137" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14164">When the Unknown became lord of the castle, and began to make such frightful use of his power, this woman felt at first a certain fear, together with a sentiment of the most profound submission. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14165" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14199">In time she had become accustomed to the scenes she always had before her eyes, and always heard spoken of; the powerful and uncurbed will of so great a Signor seemed to her a species of fatal justice. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14200" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14228">Grown up, she had married a servant of the house, who, shortly after being absent on a perilous expedition, left his bones on the highway, and his widow in the castle. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14229" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14251">The manner in which the Signor immediately avenged his death gave her consolation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14252" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14286">From that time forth she rarely set foot beyond the castle; and gradually she retained no other ideas of human life than those which she had received in this place. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14287" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14313">She held no regular situation, but in this troop of ruffians, now one, now another, gave her something to do; and this was her torment. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14314" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14335">Now she had rags to patch, now in haste to prepare food for those who returned from some expedition, now wounds to heal. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14336" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14371">Then the commands of these men, as well as their reproofs and thanks, were embellished with jeers and reproaches. "Old woman," was her usual appellation; and the additions varied according to circumstances, and the humour of her friend. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14372" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14407">And she, disturbed in her laziness and her self-love, provoked in two of her predominating passions, returned these compliments by words in which Satan would have recognised more of his own spirit than in the words of her provocators. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="43">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14408" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14416">"Thou seest that carriage, down there!" said the Signor. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="44">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14417" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14440">"I see," said the old woman, stretching out her pointed chin, and expanding her sunken eyes as though she would try to make them touch their sockets. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="45">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14441" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14451">"Order a litter to be ready immediately, get into it, and be carried to the Malanotte. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14452" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14469">Quick, quick, that thou mayst arrive there before the carriage; there it comes on with the pace of death. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14470" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14477">In this carriage there is — there ought to be — a young girl. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14478" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14497">If there should be, tell Nibbio, in my name, to place her in the litter, and to come immediately to me. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14498" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14513">Thou wilt remain in the litter with this — girl; and when you have arrived here, conduct her to thy chamber. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14514" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14527">If she should ask whither thou art taking her, to whom the castle belongs, be careful not to —" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="46">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14528" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14531">"Oh!" said the old woman. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14532" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14536">"But," continued the Unknown, "encourage her." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14537" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14540">"What must I say to her?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14541" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14544">"What thou must say to her? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14545" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14548">Encourage her, I tell thee. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14549" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14566">Hast thou reached thy age without knowing how to encourage a person when necessary? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14567" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14573">Hast thou never felt sickness of heart? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14574" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14578">Hast thou never felt fear? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14579" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14588">Dost thou not know what words console in such moments? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14589" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14595">Speak such words to her; find them in the memory of thy misfortunes. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14596" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14596">Go." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="47">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14597" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14652">When she was gone, he stood some time at the window, his eyes fixed upon the carriage, which already appeared much larger; then he raised them towards the sun, which at this moment concealed itself behind the mountain; now gazed at the clouds, which suddenly changed from brown to the hue of fire. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap20-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14653" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14674">He drew back, closed the window, and commenced pacing to and fro in the chamber with the step of a man in haste. </note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>