<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CHAPTER II.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>1845</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed Lovers: a Milanese Story of the Seventeenth Century. With The Column of Infamy by Alessandro Manzoni. In Three Volumes</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
          <date>1845</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Henry Francis C. Logan</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="English_1845_cap2">
        <p n="1">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10039">It is related, that the Prince of Condé slept profoundly the night before the battle of Rocroi; but in the first place he was much fatigued, and in the second he had given all the necessary directions, and decreed every thing that should take place the next morning. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10040" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10066">Don Abbondio, instead, only knew as yet that the morrow should be the day of battle; therefore a great part of the night was spent in consultations full of anguish. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10067" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10088">Not to pay any attention to this wicked intimation, neither to the menace, and to solemnize the marriage, was a line of conduct which he would not even put into deliberation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10089" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10100">To confide to Renzo this occurrence, and seek with him some other means—God help us! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10101" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10139">"Let not a word escape—otherwise—hem!" had said one of the bravoes; and hearing this hem echo in his mind, Don Abbondio, who could not think of transgressing such a law, repented of having gossiped with Perpetua. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10140" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10140">Should he fly? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10141" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10141">But where? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10142" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10149">And then how many difficulties, how many reasons to be given! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10150" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10160">At every line of conduct which he rejected, the poor man turned himself round in his bed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10161" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10182">The one which appeared to him the best, or the least evil one, was to gain time by delaying Renzo. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10183" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10295">He remembered, fortunately, that it wanted but a few days of the time when marriages are prohibited; "and if I could only keep this youth at bay for these few days," thought he, "I should then have two months of repose, and two months may give birth to great things. He thought over excuses to propose; and although they might appear to him rather frivolous, still he reassured himself with the thought that his authority would make them appear weighty enough, and that his great experience would give him a decided advantage over an ignorant youth. "We shall see," said he to himself; "he thinks of his mistress, I think of my life; I am the one most interested, let alone that I am the most prudent. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10296" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10333">My dear son, if thou shouldst feel the fire on thy back, I should not know what to say, but I do not intend to be the victim." Having thus, at length, somewhat quieted his mind with this deliberation, he could close his eyes—but what sleep, what dreams! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10334" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10343">Bravoes, Don Rodrigo, Renzo, pathways, rocks, escapes, pursuits, cries, musket-shots!! </note>
        </p>
        <p n="2">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10344" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10393">The first awakening after a misfortune and in an embarrassment is a very bitter moment; the mind, scarcely aroused to consciousness, returns to the habitual ideas of the tranquil preceding life, but the thoughts of the present state of affairs soon, however, present themselves most unceremoniously; and the pain thus occasioned is still more lively in this instantaneous comparison. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="3">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10394" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10426">Don Abbondio, having most bitterly experienced this moment, ran over in his mind his designs of the night, strengthened himself in them, arranged them better, rose and waited expecting Lorenzo, now with fear, now with impatience. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="4">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10427" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10437">Lorenzo, or as every one called him Renzo, did not cause himself long to be waited for. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10438" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10466">Scarcely had the hour arrived, when without indiscretion he could present himself before the curate, than he flew to him with all the gay impetuosity of a man of twenty, who on that day is to espouse the one he loves. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10467" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10514">He had lost his parents in his earliest youth, and exercised the profession of a silk-weaver, hereditary, so to say, in his family. It was a profession which in former years had been very lucrative, but now was in decay, not, however, so much so, but that an able workman could still earn enough wherewith to live honestly. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="5">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10515" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10552">The business decreased daily, but the constant emigration of workmen enticed into the neighbouring states by promises, by privileges, and higher wages, occasioned this still to be sufficient for those who remained in the country. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10553" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10581">Besides this, Renzo possessed a little farm, which he had farmed for him, and which he also farmed himself when the silk-loom stood still, so that for his station he might be said to be at his ease. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10582" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10628">And although this year there was a still greater scarcity than in the preceding ones, and a real dearth began to be felt, our youth, who, since he had cast his eyes upon Lucia, had become a steward, found himself sufficiently provided for, and had not to struggle with hunger. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="6">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10629" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10671">He appeared before Don Abbondio in holiday costume, with feathers of various colours in his hat, with his dagger with its handsome handle in the pocket of his breeches, and a certain holiday, yet, at the same time, swaggering air, which in those times was common to the most quiet men. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10672" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10720">The uncertain and mysterious reception of Don Abbondio formed a singular contrast to the joyous and resolute manner of the youth. He has something in his head—thought Renzo to himself, and then said, "I am come, Signor Curato, to know at what hour it will be agreeable to you, that we should be in the church." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="8">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10721" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10725">"Of what day is it you would speak?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="9">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10726" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10737">"How! do you not know what has been fixed for to-day?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="10">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10738" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10758">"To-day?" replied Don Abbondio, as though he heard this spoken of for the first time, "To-day, to-day—Have patience——to-day I cannot." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="11">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10759" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10761">"You cannot to-day! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10762" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10763">What has happened?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="12">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10764" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10771">"First of all, I do not feel myself quite well you see." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="13">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10772" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10790">"I am sorry, but what has to be done is a matter of so little time, and so little fatigue——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="14">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10791" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10796">"And then, and then, and then——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="15">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10797" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10800">"And then what?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="16">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10801" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10805">"And then the difficulties." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="17">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10806" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10811">"What difficulties can there be?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="18">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10812" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10829">"It would be necessary for you to be in our shoes, in order to know how many obstacles rise up in these affairs, how many accounts there are to be rendered. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10830" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10868">I have too tender a heart. I only think of aiding the removal of these obstacles, of facilitating every thing, of doing every thing according to the pleasure of others, and I neglect my duty, and then I am overwhelmed with reproaches and worse." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="19">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10869" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10887">"But in the name of heaven, don't keep me thus upon the rack! tell me clearly and distinctly what all this is." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="20">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10888" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10901">"Do you know how many formalities are necessary to make a marriage legal?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="21">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10902" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10925">"I ought to know something of it," said Renzo, beginning to get angry, "since you have already sufficiently crazed me about it, for these many days past. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10926" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10941">But now, is not every thing despatched? Is not every thing done which had to be done?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="22">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10942" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10964">"All, all appears so to you—because—have patience —I am the ass, who neglects his duty through fear of causing pain to others. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10965" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10971">But now — enough, I know what I say. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10972" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10995">We poor curates are between the anvil and the hammer. You grow impatient —— I pity you, poor youth, and the Superiors——enough, I cannot tell thee all. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_10996" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11004">We are the go-betweens." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="23">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11005" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11022">"But explain to me once for all, what is this other formality which has yet to be performed, as you say, and this shall be done immediately." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="24">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11023" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11028">"Do you know how many absolute impediments there are?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="25">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11029" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11033">"But what do you wish that I should know about impediments?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="26">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11034" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11055">"Error, conditio, votum, cognatio, crimen, Cultus disparitas, vis, ordo, ligamen, honestas, Si sis affinis ——," began Don Abbondio, counting them upon the point of his fingers. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="27">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11056" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11063">"You are playing a joke with me," interrupted the youth. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11064" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11071">"What should I know of your latinorum?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="28">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11072" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11085">"Well, then, if you don't understand these things, have patience, and leave them to those who do." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="29">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11086" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11086">"Well——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="30">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11087" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11113">"Go away, dear Renzo; do not get angry, which you are very ready to do —— every thing which depends upon me — I — I should like to see you contented; I wish you well. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11114" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11123">Ah! when I think how well you were off; what is it that you are in want of? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11124" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11144">And now this whim of marrying has sprung up ——" "What manner of discourse is this, Signor mio?" interrupted Renzo, with a look between astonishment and anger. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="31">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11145" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11155">"I talk for the sake of talking—I should like to see you contented." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="32">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11156" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11157">"In short——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="33">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11158" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11195">"In short, my son, I am not to blame, I have not made the laws; and before performing a marriage, we ourselves are obliged to make many, many inquiries, to assure ourselves that there are no impediments." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="34">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11196" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11205">"But come, tell me once for all, what impediment has arisen?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="35">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11206" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11217">"Have patience; these are not things to be deciphered thus immediately. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11218" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11232">This will be nothing, as I hope; but, notwithstanding, these inquiries must be made. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11233" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11241">The text is clear and plain—antequam matrimonium denunci-et—" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="36">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11242" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11248">"I have already said I do not wish for Latin." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="37">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11249" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11254">"But it is necessary, in order that I explain to you——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="38">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11255" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11262">"But have you not already made all these inquiries?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="39">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11263" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11272">"No, I have not made them all, as I should have done, I tell you." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="40">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11273" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11287">"Why have you not made them in time? Why tell me all was ended? Why expect?——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="41">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11288" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11294">"See! you blame my too great goodness. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11295" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11311">I have facilitated every thing in order to serve you more quickly; but—but now are arrived—enough, I know." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="42">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11312" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11316">"And what do you desire that I should do?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="43">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11317" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11322">"Have patience for some days. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11323" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11332">My dear son, a few days is not an eternity. Have patience." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="44">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11333" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11360">"For how long?" "We are in a good harbour," thought Don Abbondio to himself; and with a manner more polite than ever, "Come," said he, "in fourteen days I will endeavour—I will take care——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="46">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11361" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11367">"In fourteen days! O, indeed, this is news! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11368" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11393">All has been done as you desired; the day is fixed, the day arrives,—and now you tell me to wait fourteen days! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11394" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11442">Fourteen days!!" repeated he then with a louder and more angry voice, raising his arm, and striking the air with his clenched fist. And who knows what devilish business might not have been attached to this member, had not Don Abbondio interrupted him by taking his other hand with a timid and yet eager affability? "Come, come, do not make yourself angry, for the love of heaven! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11443" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11448">I will see, I will try if in a week——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="47">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11449" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11454">"And what must I say to Lucia?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="48">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11455" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11459">"That it has been a mistake of mine." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="49">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11460" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11464">"And to the remarks of the world?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="50">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11465" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11486">"Say only to every one that I have made a mistake through too much zeal, through too much goodness of heart; throw all the blame upon my back. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11487" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11493">Can any one say anything better? Go away for a week." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="51">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11494" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11501">"And then there will be no longer any impediment?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="52">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11502" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11504">"When I say——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="53">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11505" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11521">"Well, I will have patience for a week; but remember well, that this week passed, you will not satisfy me longer with idle talk. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11522" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11524">In the mean time, I take my leave." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11525" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11546">And saying this he left the room, making Don Abbondio an inclination less profound than usual, and casting a glance at him more expressive than reverential. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11547" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11580">Having left the house, and for the first time approaching unwillingly the abode of his betrothed, he in the midst of his wrath turned over in his mind this conversation, and each time found it more strange. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11581" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11670">The cold and embarrassed reception of Don Abbondio; his manner of speaking, at once constrained and impatient; those two grey eyes which while he spoke were trying to escape here and there, as though they were afraid of encountering the words which issued from his lips; his novel conduct regarding this marriage, so expressly agreed upon; and above all, his hinting always at some great thing, but never speaking clearly;—all these circumstances together made Renzo imagine that perhaps there was some mystery different to that which Don Abbondio had wished to make him believe. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11671" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11710">The youth hesitated a moment whether he should not turn back and force him to speak more clearly; but raising his eyes, he saw Perpetua, who was coming towards him, and who entered a little kitchen-garden a few paces distant from the house. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11711" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11744">Whilst she was opening the gate he called to her; hastening his step, he joined her at the entrance, and then, with the design of discovering something more positive, paused to begin a conversation. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="54">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11745" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11756">"Good-day, Perpetua; I hoped to-day that we should all have been merry together." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="55">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11757" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11765">"As God wills it, my poor Renzo." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="56">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11766" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11794">"Do me a kindness: this good man, the Signor Curato, has been assigning certain reasons, which I have not been able to understand; explain to me better why he has not been able to marry us to-day." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="57">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11795" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11834">"O! it seems to you then that I know my master's secrets?" "I said there was a mystery underneath all this," thought Renzo; and in order to bring it to light, he continued—"Come, Perpetua, we are friends; tell me what you know; assist a poor fellow." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="59">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11835" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11842">"It is an evil thing to be born poor, my dear Renzo." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="60">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11843" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11870">"This is true," replied the other, still more confirmed in his suspicions; and endeavouring to approach nearer the question, "this is true," he added, "but does it become priests to behave ill towards the poor!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="61">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11871" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11908">"Listen, Renzo! I cannot tell anything—because I don't know anything; but this I can assure you, that my master does not wish to do wrong either by you or by any one; it is not he who is in fault!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="62">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11909" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11929">"Who then is?" demanded Renzo, with an indifferent air, but a heart all suspense and an ear all attention. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="63">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11930" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11959">"When I tell you that I know nothing—— In defence of my master, however, I can speak, since it pains me to hear you give him the character of wishing to hurt any one. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11960" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11966">Poor man, if he sins, it is through too much goodness. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11967" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11993">But there are enough rogues, oppressors, and men without the fear of God, in this world." "Oppressors! rogues!" thought Renzo; "these are not then the Superiors?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="64">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_11994" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12005">"Come," said he, concealing with difficulty his increasing agitation, "come, tell me who this is?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="65">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12006" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12030">"Ah, you wish to make me speak, and I cannot speak, since I do not know anything; when one does not know anything, it is as though one had sworn to keep silence. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12031" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12041">You might torture me, but you would not get anything out of my mouth. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12042" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12057">Adieu!—this is lost time to both of us;" and saying this, she entered in haste the little garden, and closed the gate. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12058" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12119">Renzo answered by a bow, and turned back very softly, in order not to inform her of the road which he took; but when he was out of the range of the good lady's hearing, he lengthened his strides, and in a moment was at Don Abbondio's door; entered, went to the little parlour where he had left him, found him there, and hastened towards him with a daring manner and flashing eyes. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="66">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12120" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12128">"Eh, eh! what is all this?" said Don Abbondio. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="67">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12129" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12155">"Who is this oppressor?" demanded Renzo, in the voice of one who is determined to obtain a precise answer; "who is this oppressor who wills that I shall not marry Lucia?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="68">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12156" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12215">"Who?—who?—who?" stammered the poor curate, quite surprised, with a countenance become in an instant white and flabby, like a rag just taken out of the wash, and still muttering, sprang out of his great chair, in order to escape by the door; but Renzo, who must have expected this movement, was all alert, flew there before him, seized the key, and put it into his pocket. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="69">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12216" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12221">"Ah, ah! will you speak now, Signor Curato? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12222" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12234">Every one knows my affairs but myself; and by Bacchus, I also will know them! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12235" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12238">What is the name of this man?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="70">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12239" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12250">"Renzo, Renzo! for charity, mind what you do! think of your soul!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="71">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12251" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12276">"I think that I will know this immediately—this very moment!" and thus saying, he placed—perhaps without being aware of it himself—his hand upon the handle of his knife, which protruded from his pocket. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="72">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12277" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12283">"Mercy!" exclaimed Don Abbondio, with a hoarse voice. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="73">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12284" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12286">"I will know it!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="74">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12287" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12289">"Who has told you ——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="75">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12290" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12298">"No, no; no more lies: speak clearly and quickly." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="76">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12299" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12301">"Will you murder me?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="77">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12302" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12309">"You know that which I have a right to know." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="78">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12310" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12314">"But if I speak I am dead. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12315" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12321">Ought not my life to be of consequence to me?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="79">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12322" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12323">"Then speak!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="80">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12324" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12349">This then was pronounced with such energy, and Renzo's look became so menacing, that Don Abbondio could no longer suppose the possibility of disobeying. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="81">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12350" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12363">"You promise me, you swear," said he, "not to speak of it to any one; never to say ——?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="82">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12364" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12380">"I promise you to commit a folly, if you do not immediately tell me the name of this man." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="83">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12381" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12403">At this new entreaty, Don Abbondio, with the look and countenance of one who has the instrument of the dentist in his mouth, uttered, "Don"— </note>
        </p>
        <p n="84">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12404" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12435">"Don?" repeated Renzo, as though to assist the patient in bringing forth the rest; and he stood bent forward, his ear over the mouth of Don Abbondio, his arms stretched out, and his hands clenched. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="85">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12436" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12490">"Don Rodrigo!" pronounced in haste the poor priest, hurrying over these few syllables, and sliding the consonants into each other, partly through perturbation, partly since he had employed the little attention which remained free to him in making an agreement between his two causes of terror, and appeared desirous of taking away and decreasing in nine the words, in the very moment when he was constrained to give them forth. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="86">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12491" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12503">"Ah, dog!" shouted Renzo, "and what did you do, what did you say to — ?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="87">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12504" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12527">"How, then? how?" answered Don Abbondio, with a somewhat angry voice, who, after this great sacrifice, felt himself in a certain way become the creditor. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12528" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12529">"How? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12530" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12556">I wish this had happened to you as it has to me, who have nothing to do with the affair; then certainly there would not have remained so many whims in your head." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12557" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12617">And here he painted in terrible colours the ugly rencounter, and gradually in his discourse might be perceived a mighty anger within him, which until then had lain concealed and enveloped in fear; and seeing, at the same time, that Renzo, between rage and confusion, stood immovable with his head bowed, he continued more boldly: "You've done a fine action! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12618" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12622">You've rendered me a fine service! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12623" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12639">An action of this sort to a gentleman, to your curate!—in his own house!—in a sacred place! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12640" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12644">You've shewn fine prowess! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12645" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12663">To draw out of my mouth, my own misfortune and yours! That which I had concealed from you through prudence, and for your own good! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12664" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12673">And now that you know it, I should like to see what you would have done to me? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12674" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12677">For the love of heaven! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12678" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12692">It is no joking matter; it does not treat of right and wrong,—it treats of strength. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12693" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12705">And when this morning I gave you a good piece of advice, eh! Suddenly what a rage you flew into! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12706" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12723">I have judgment enough for both you and myself; but what is done?—Open the door at least, give me my key." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="88">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12724" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12761">"I may have done wrong," returned Renzo, with a voice softened towards Don Abbondio, but in which was heard his anger against his discovered enemy. "I may have done wrong, but lay your hand upon your heart and think if in my situation——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="89">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12762" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12773">Thus saying, he took out of his pocket the key, and went to unlock the door. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12774" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12817">Don Abbondio followed after him; and whilst he placed the key in the key-hole, approached him with a serious and anxious face, and raising the three first fingers of the right hand as though he would assist him in his turn, "swear, at least,——" he said. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="90">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12818" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12830">"I may have done wrong; but pardon me," answered Renzo, opening the door, and preparing to go out. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="91">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12831" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12841">"Swear!" replied Don Abbondio, holding his arm fast with his trembling hand. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="92">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12842" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12886">"I may have done wrong," replied Renzo, setting off in great haste, and thus cutting short the question which like many another, either of literature or philosophy, or in fact regarding anything else, might have lasted centuries, since neither party did anything but repeat his own argument. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="93">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12887" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12887">"Perpetua! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12888" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12897">Perpetua!" cried Don Abbondio, after having in vain called after the fugitive. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12898" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12910">Perpetua did not answer, Don Abbondio no longer knew in what world he was. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="94">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12911" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12948">It has happened, more than once, to personages of much more consideration than Don Abbondio, to find themselves in such vexatious situations, in such uncertainty of resolve, that the very best remedy has seemed to them to be to fall ill of a fever. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12949" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12963">He, however, was not obliged to go and seek for this remedy, since it presented itself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12964" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12983">The fright of the preceding day, the night passed in agonising watching, the terror he had this moment experienced, and anxiety for the future, produced this effect. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_12984" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13014">Troubled and stupified, he rested himself in his great chair; beginning to feel piercing cold in his bones, he gazed on his finger-nails, sighed, and called "Perpetua!" from time to time, with a tremulous and angry voice. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="95">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13015" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13034">At length she arrived with a large cabbage under her arm, and a very innocent face, as though there were nothing the matter. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13035" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13064">We will spare the reader the laments, the condolences, the accusations, the defences, the "only you could have spoken," and the "I have not spoken," in short, all this tedious colloquy. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13065" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13101">Suffice it to say, that Don Abbondio ordered Perpetua to bolt the door, and not to open it again on any consideration, and if any one knocked to answer from the window, that the Curate was gone to bed ill of a fever. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13102" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13121">Then he slowly ascended the stairs, saying at every three steps, "I am served," and in truth put himself to bed, where we will leave him for the present. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="96">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13122" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13149">Renzo, in the meantime with hasty steps made his way home, without having determined what he ought to do, but with a madness upon him to do something strange and terrible. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13150" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13181">Provocators, oppressors, all those who, in whatsoever manner do injury to others, are guilty, not alone of the evil they themselves commit, but also of the violent deeds occasioned by the anger of the injured party. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13182" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13220">Renzo was a peaceful youth, averse to bloodshed, of an open disposition, and an enemy to deceit; but in this moment his heart only beat for homicide, his mind was only occupied with imagining a deed of treachery. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13221" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13290">He would have wished to rush to the house of Don Rodrigo, seize him by the throat, and —; but it came into his mind that this house was like a fortress, garnished with bravoes within and guarded without; that alone the best known friends and servants entered freely without being searched from head to foot; that an unknown artisan could not enter without an examination, and that he, above all others — that he, perhaps, would be only too well known there. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13291" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13392">He imagined then to himself the taking his musket, planting himself behind a hedge, waiting if ever this enemy should pass by alone; and he, busying himself with ferocious pleasure in this imagination, pictured to himself that he heard a footstep, recognised the villain, leveled his musket, took aim, shot — that he saw him fall, and breathe his last! and that he then, hurling a curse after him, flew along the road which led to the frontiers, there to place himself in safety. And Lucia? scarcely had this name crossed these wicked imaginings, than all the better thoughts of Renzo's mind crowded upon him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13393" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13457">He recalled the last admonitions of his parents, he remembered God, the Madonna, and the Saints; the thoughts of the happiness he had so often experienced in feeling himself free from crime, of the horror he had so often felt at the relation of homicide; and turned away from this dream of blood, with horror, with remorse, and yet at the same time with a species of joy in alone having imagined this. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13458" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13466">But the thought of Lucia, how many others did it not bring along with it! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13467" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13483">So many hopes, so many promises, a future so attractive and held so secure, and this day so often sighed for! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13484" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13492">And then with what words to announce to her such news? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13493" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13497">And then what course to pursue? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13498" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13507">How to make her his, in despite of the power of this wicked noble? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13508" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13524">And together with all this, not a shaped suspicion, but a tormenting shadow passed through his mind. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13525" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13540">This oppression of Don Rodrigo's could not have been excited but by a brutal passion for Lucia. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13541" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13542">And Lucia? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13543" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13568">That she could have given him the slightest occasion, the slightest encouragement, however, was not a thought to fix itself for one moment in the mind of Renzo. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13569" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13571">But was she informed of it? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13572" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13582">Could he have conceived this infamous passion without her being aware of it? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13583" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13595">Would he have pushed things so far without having tempted her in some manner? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13596" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13609">And Lucia had never said a word of this to him, to her betrothed! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13610" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13637">Governed by these thoughts, he passed his house, which stood in the middle of the village, and traversing the street, reached Lucia's cottage, which was situated at the opposite end. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13638" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13655">This cottage had a small court-yard before it, which separated it from the road, and was surrounded by a stone wall. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13656" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13673">Renzo entered the court, and heard a mingled and continuous hum, which proceeded from an upper chamber. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13674" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13701">He thought that these would be friends and gossips of the neighbourhood, come to attend upon Lucia, and he did not wish to shew himself to this assemblage, with such news in his mien and countenance. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13702" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13716">A little girl who was in the court-yard ran towards him, crying, "the bridegroom, the bridegroom!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="97">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13717" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13721">"Hush, Bettina, hush!" said Renzo. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13722" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13756">"Come here; go up to Lucia, draw her aside, and whisper in her ear, but so that no one either hears or suspects anything, dost thou see?---- say that I have something to tell her, that I wait for her in the room on the ground-floor, and that she must come quickly." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="98">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13757" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13772">The little maiden ascended the stairs in haste, happy and proud to have a secret commission to execute. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n189" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13773" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13783">At this moment Lucia gaily attired, issued forth from the hands of her mother. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n190" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13784" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13832">The friends seized upon the bride, and compelled her to let herself be seen; and she defending herself with the rather warlike modesty of the peasant girl, bending her face over her bosom, shielded it with her elbow, contracted her long black eyebrows, whilst her lips opened with a smile. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n191" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13833" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13879">Her black and youthful hair, parted above the forehead with a white and direct line, was confined at the back of the head in a multitude of braids, through which, according to the usage of the peasant girls of Milan, were passed long silver needles arranged upright round the head, like to the rays of a glory. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n192" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13880" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13932">Round her neck she had a necklace of garnets, alternating with beads of filigree-gold; she wore a bodice of flowered brocade, the sleeves separated from the bodice and adorned with beautiful ribbons, a short skirt, with many minute thick plaits, vermilion-coloured stockings, and little shoes also, of embroidered silk. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n193" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13933" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13992">Beside these, which were the ornaments peculiar to the wedding-day, she was adorned with the every-day ornaments of a modest loveliness, now relieved and increased by the various emotions which painted themselves on her countenance; a joy, tempered by a slight disquiet—that placid anguish which from time to time shews itself in the face of the bride, and which, without destroying her beauty, gives it a peculiar character. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n194" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_13993" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14018">The little Bettina ran into the company, and approaching Lucia, and giving her to understand that she had something to communicate, whispered the message in her ear. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="99">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n195" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14019" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14031">"I go for a moment, but I return," said Lucia to the women, and descended in haste. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n196" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14032" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14051">Seeing the mute countenance and unquiet manner of Renzo, "What is this?" she demanded, not without a presentiment of terror. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="100">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n197" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14052" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14069">"Lucia!" answered Renzo; "for to-day all is at an end, and God only knows when we shall be man and wife." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="101">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n198" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14070" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14074">"How!" said Lucia, very much distressed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n199" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14075" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14104">Renzo related briefly to her the history of the morning: she listened with agony, and when she heard the name of Don Rodrigo— "Ah!" exclaimed she, blushing and trembling; "how is it come thus far?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="103">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n200" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14105" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14109">"Then you knew?" said Renzo. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="104">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n201" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14110" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14117">"Only too much!" replied Lucia; "but thus far!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="105">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n202" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14118" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14120">"What do you know?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="106">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n203" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14121" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14129">"Do not make me speak of it now, do not make me weep. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n204" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14130" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14143">I will run and call my mother, and dismiss the women; we must be alone." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n205" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14144" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14153">Whilst she was going out of the room, Renzo muttered, "But you have never said anything of this to me." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="107">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n206" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14154" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14162">"Ah, Renzo," Lucia replied, turning round, but without pausing. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n207" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14163" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14193">Renzo understood very well that his name pronounced in this moment, and in this tone by Lucia, meant to say, can you doubt I have kept silence except from pure and just motives? </note>
        </p>
        <p n="108">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n208" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14194" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14226">In the meanwhile, the good Agnese (this was the name of Lucia's mother), whose suspicion and curiosity had been excited by the whisper and disappearance of her daughter, had descended to see what had happened. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n209" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14227" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14257">The daughter left her alone with Renzo, and, composing the best she could her voice and manner, said, "The Signor Curato has fallen ill, and nothing will take place to-day." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n210" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14258" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14268">This said, she saluted all in haste and again descended. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="109">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n211" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14269" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14277">The women separated and disappeared to talk over what had happened. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n212" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14278" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14291">Two or three even went to the Curato's door, to see if he were really fallen sick. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap2-n213" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14292" targetEnd="quarantana/cap2.xml#c2_14323">"A fever," replied Perpetua from the window; and these sad words, reported to the others, cut short the conjectures which had already begun to stir in their brains, and to announce themselves short and mysteriously in their discourses. </note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>