<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CHAPTER XXIII.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>1845</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed Lovers: a Milanese Story of the Seventeenth Century. With The Column of Infamy by Alessandro Manzoni. In Three Volumes</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
          <date>1845</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Henry Francis C. Logan</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="English_1845_cap23">
        <p n="1">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10036">CARDINAL FEDERIGO, whilst waiting for the hour when he should proceed to church, there to celebrate divine service, was studying, as was his custom to do in all his leisure moments, when the Chaplain cross-bearer entered with a disturbed countenance. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="2">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10037" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10043">"A strange visit, strange in truth, my illustrious Signor!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="3">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10044" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10048">"Who is it?" demanded the Cardinal. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="4">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10049" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10075">"No one less than the Signor ——," returned the Chaplain; and distinctly pronouncing the syllables with great signification, he spoke that name which we have not been able to write for our readers. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10076" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10091">And then he added, "And he is here himself in person, and asks nothing less than to be introduced to your illustrious lordship." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="5">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10092" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10109">"He!" said the Cardinal, with an animated countenance, closing his book and rising from his seat; "let him come, let him come immediately." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="6">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10110" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10126">"But ——," replied the Chaplain, without moving, "your illustrious lordship ought to know who this is, this outlaw, this famous ——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="7">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10127" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10147">"And is it not a good fortune for a bishop, that the desire to visit him has arisen in the mind of such a man?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="8">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10148" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10199">"But ——" insisted the Chaplain; "we never dare speak of certain things, for my lord says, that all this is foolish gossip; however, when the thing arrives, it seems to me it is a duty — Zeal makes many enemies, my lord; and we know positively that more than one villain has dared to boast, that one day or other — </note>
        </p>
        <p n="9">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10200" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10206">"And what have they done?" interrupted the Cardinal. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="10">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10207" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10228">"I say that this man is an instigator of crime, a desperate character, who stands in correspondence with maddened desperadoes, and that he may be sent —" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="11">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10229" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10246">"Oh, what discipline is this," interrupted Federigo, again smiling, "that the soldiers exhort the general to have fear?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10247" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10272">Then, becoming serious and thoughtful, he continued: "San Carlo would never have found himself debating whether he ought to receive such a man, he would have gone in search of him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10273" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10279">Let him enter immediately; he has waited already too long." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="12">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10280" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10327">The Chaplain moved away, saying to himself — "There is no remedy; all these holy men are so obstinate." Having opened the door, and presented himself in the apartment where were the Signor and the company, he saw the priests had retired into one corner, and were whispering and glancing at the Unknown, who was left alone in another corner. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="13">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10328" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10365">He went towards him, and examining him as well as he could, without looking him full in the face, thought what weapons he might have concealed under his cloak, and that, really, before introducing him, he ought at least to propose — but he could not resolve to do so. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10366" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10378">He accosted him, and said, "My lord expects "your lordship, be pleased to follow me." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10379" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10412">And preceding him through the little crowd, which immediately opened a way for them both, he cast glances to the right and left, which signified, "What would you have? Do you not all of you know, as well as myself, that this holy man always has his own way?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="14">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10413" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10446">Scarcely was the Unknown introduced than Federigo hastened towards him with a serene and joyous air, with open arms, as though to receive a much desired person, and immediately signed to the Chaplain to retire, which sign he obeyed. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="15">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10447" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10456">The two remained some time without speaking, and both were undecided, although both were influenced by different reasons. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10457" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10534">The Unknown, who had been, as it were, driven there by force, by an inexplicable madness, rather than by any determined design, remained there, as it were, by force, torn by two conflicting passions — the desire and confused hope of finding a refuge from his inward tormentor, and a kind of anger and shame at having come there like a penitent, like a miserable man full of submission, come to confess himself guilty, and to implore pardon; he could not find words — he scarcely sought for them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10535" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10575">However, raising his eyes to the countenance of the holy Archbishop, he felt himself even more penetrated with a sentiment of veneration, at once all-powerful and gentle, which, whilst it increased his confidence, lessened his spite, and without affronting his pride abated it, or, we might almost say, imposed silence upon it. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="16">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10576" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10591">The person of Federigo was, indeed, one of those which announce a superiority, and make, at the same time, this superiority beloved. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10592" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10692">His carriage was naturally modest, and almost involuntarily majestic, neither was he bowed, nor had become less active by the weight of years; he had grave, yet lively, eyes, and a serene and thoughtful brow; spite of the whiteness of his locks, of his paleness, still among the signs of abstinence, meditation, and fatigue, might be traced a species of youthful bloom. All his features indicated that in an earlier period of life he would have been endowed with that which is most properly termed beauty; the habit of solemn and benevolent thought, the inward peace of a long life, love of the human race, the constant joy of an ineffable hope, had now substituted, in the place of youthful beauty, the beauty of old age — a beauty which shone forth yet more splendidly in the magnificent simplicity of the purple. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="17">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10693" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10769">He riveted his penetrating glance for some moments on the countenance of the Unknown, a glance long exercised in reading the thoughts of men in their exterior; and under this gloomy and cloudy air, it appeared to him he discovered gradually something similar to the hope he had conceived at the first announcement of such a visitor, and all animated, he said, "Oh! what a precious visit this is! And how much ought I to be grateful to you for so good a resolution, although it is for me a little reproach." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="18">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10770" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10797">"Reproach!" exclaimed the Signor, much astonished, but yet softened by these words and behaviour, and at the same time satisfied that the Cardinal should have broken the ice, and commenced any kind of a discourse. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="19">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10798" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10822">"Certainly, a reproach," replied the other, "that I should have allowed you to be the first to come;" when so long ago, when many a time before now, I ought to have gone to you!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="20">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10823" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10825">"To me, you! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10826" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10828">Do you know who I am? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10829" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10834">Have they told you my name?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="21">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10835" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10859">"And does it seem to you that I should experience the pleasure which I feel, and which manifests itself in my appearance, at the announcement of an unknown visitor? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10860" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10910">It is you who make me experience it; you, I say, whom I ought to have sought out; you, whom I have at least loved and wept over, and for whom I have prayed; you, the one of my children (and I love them all from my heart) whom I should have most desired to see and embrace, if I had believed I might hope such a thing. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10911" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10928">But God alone knows how to work miracles; he makes up for the weakness, for the slowness, of his poor servants." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="22">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10929" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10963">The Unknown stood filled with astonishment, hearing this warm address, these words, which responded so entirely to that which he had not yet said, and which he had not yet determined to say, and moved, yet confounded, he stood in silence. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="23">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10964" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10983">"And how?" resumed Federigo, still more affectionately; "you have good news to communicate to me, and yet you make me wait thus long?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="24">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10984" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10987">"Good news! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10988" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10997">I?—I have hell in my heart; and I shall yet tell you good news! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10998" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11013">Tell me, if you know, what this good news is, which you expect from one like me." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="25">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11014" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11027">"That God has touched your heart, and desires to make you one of His servants," replied the Cardinal, calmly. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="26">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11028" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11030">"God, God, God! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11031" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11036">If I could see him! If I could see him! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11037" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11039">Where is this God?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11040" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11044">"You demand this from me—you? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11045" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11051">And who has felt this presence more than you? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11052" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11094">Have you not felt Him in your heart; something which oppresses you, which agitates you; something which does not leave you a moment's repose, but which at the same time attracts you; which gives you a presentiment of a calm, of a consolation; of a consolation which will be complete, immense, as soon as you shall have recognised Him, confessed Him, implored Him?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="27">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11095" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11105">"Oh, certainly; I have something here which oppresses me, which devours me! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11106" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11107">But God! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11108" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11122">If it is this God, if it is the one they speak of, what would you have Him do with me?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="28">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11123" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11150">These words were spoken with an accent of desperation; but Federigo, with a solemn tone, as though with calm inspirations, replied, "What can God do with you? what He will do? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11151" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11171">A sign of His power and goodness; He will obtain from you a glory which no one else could give Him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11172" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11223">From you, against whom the world has cried so long; through you, whose deeds are cursed by thousands and thousands of voices——" The Unknown trembled, and remained astonished at hearing such unusual language, and became yet more astonished upon finding that they not only occasioned him no anger, but rather a relief. "What glory," continued Federigo, "may not reach God. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="29">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11224" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11260">These are cries of terror, are cries of interest; cries perhaps of justice, but of a justice so easy, so natural! Amidst those who accuse you, there are some perhaps—there are only, alas! too many such—who are animated by a jealousy of the miserable power which you have exercised, of the deplorable security of mind which you have preserved until to-day. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11261" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11279">But when you yourself rise and condemn your life, and accuse yourself, then, ah! then God will be glorified. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11280" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11288">And you ask what God can do for you! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11289" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11326">Who am I, poor mortal, that I should know what profit God may henceforth draw from you? what He may do with this impetuous will, this immoveable constancy, when He shall have animated, warmed it with love, with hope, with repentance? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11327" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11355">Who are you, poor mortal, to believe that you have been able to imagine and execute greater evil than God is able to make you desire and perform good? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11356" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11361">What God can do with you? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11362" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11373">Whether he can pardon you? can save you? and whether he can accomplish in you the work of redemption? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11374" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11381">Are not these magnificent things, and worthy of Him? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11382" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11458">Oh, think! If I, a weak human being, a miserable sinner, and so full of myself; if I, such as I am, rejoice now so much over your salvation, that to obtain it I would give with joy—God is my witness—the few days which yet remain to me, oh, think! how much love must He have who has inspired me with a love thus lively, although so imperfect; how much the Being loves you, how much He desires for you, when He inspires me with a love for you which devours me?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="30">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11459" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11477">Whilst these words issued from his lips, his countenance, his glance, his every movement, breathed their meaning. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11478" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11542">The countenance of his listener, before agitated and convulsed, at first became astonished and intent; then his features exhibited an emotion more profound and less full of anguish; his eyes, which from his infancy had known no tears, were suffused; when the words had ceased, he covered his face with his hands, and burst into a flood of tears, which was his clearest reply. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="31">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11543" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11584">"Great and good God!" exclaimed Federigo, raising his hands and eyes towards heaven, "what have I done; a useless servant, a slumbering shepherd, that thou shouldst have called me to the banquet of grace; why shouldst thou have made me worthy to assist at so joyful a miracle!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11585" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11593">Saying this, he stretched forth his hand to take the hand of the Unknown. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="32">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11594" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11609">"No!" cried he, "no; far, far from me! do not defile this innocent and beneficent hand. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11610" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11620">You do not know all that has been done by the one you would grasp." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="33">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11621" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11653">"Let me," said Federigo, taking it with an affectionate violence, "let me press this same hand, which will repair so many wrongs, which will distribute so many benefits, which will console so many afflicted ones, which will extend itself unarmed, peacefully, humbly, to so many enemies." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="34">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11654" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11658">"It is too much!" said the Unknown, sobbing. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11659" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11663">"Leave me, my lord; good Federigo, leave me. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11664" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11686">A crowd of people await you; many good souls, many innocent creatures are come from far to see you, for once to hear you; — and you converse here, with whom!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="35">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11687" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11706">"Let us leave the ninety and nine sheep," replied the Cardinal; "they are in security upon the mountain; I wish now to remain with the one who went astray. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11707" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11719">Perhaps these souls are now happier than if they saw their poor bishop. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11720" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11742">Perhaps God, who has worked in you this miracle of mercy, may penetrate them with a joy of which they may not at present feel the cause. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11743" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11780">His people are perhaps unconsciously united with us; perhaps the Holy Ghost animates their hearts with a fervent ardour of love, and inspires them with a prayer for you, which He will grant; with a thanksgiving perhaps, of which you who are the object are not yet aware." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11781" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11822">And saying this, he threw his arms round the neck of the Unknown, who, after having resisted for a moment and endeavoured to free himself, yielded; and as though conquered by this impetuous love, embraced the Cardinal, and concealed upon his shoulders his agitated and altered countenance. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11823" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11854">His hot tears fell upon the uncontaminated purple of Federigo, and the pure hands of the Archbishop affectionately pressed this person, and this cloak, accustomed to bear and conceal arms of violence and treason. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="36">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11855" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11876">The Unknown, freeing himself from this embrace, again covered his eyes with one hand, and raising his face, exclaimed, "O God, truly great! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11877" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11918">God, truly good! I now know myself, I comprehend what I am; my iniquities stand before me; I have fear of myself; yet—! yet, I experience a consolation, a joy; yes, a joy which I have never before experienced in this my horrible life!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="37">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11919" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11951">"It is a sentiment," said Federigo, "which God gives you, in order to captivate you for his service, to animate you to enter resolutely this new life, in which you will have so much to undo, so much to repair, so much to weep over!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="38">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11952" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11966">"Unfortunate that I am!" exclaimed the Signor, "how many, many things there are over which I can only weep! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11967" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11990">But, at least, there are some enterprises which are scarcely commenced, and which I can, if nothing more, at once abandon in the middle; there is one which I can abandon now, undo, repair." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="39">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11991" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12044">Federigo became attentive; and the Unknown recounted briefly, but with words of execration even stronger than we have adopted, the violence offered to Lucia; the terrors, the sufferings of the poor girl; how she had implored, the frenzy which these supplications had excited within him, and how she was still in the castle. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="40">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12045" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12056">"Ah, do not let us lose time!" exclaimed Federigo, panting with pity and solicitude. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12057" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12058">"Blessed are you! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12059" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12078">This is a pledge of the pardon of God! God causes you to become an instrument of salvation to the one to whom you would have been an instrument of ruin. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12079" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12081">God blesses you! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12082" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12084">God has blessed you. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12085" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12092">Do you know from what part of the country our unfortunate is?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="41">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12093" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12099">The Unknown named Lucia's village. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="42">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12100" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12122">"It is not far from here," said the Cardinal; "praised be God; and probably ——" Saying this, he ran to a small table, and rang a bell. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12123" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12197">Immediately entered the Chaplain, cross-bearer, and, first of all, glancing at the Unknown, and seeing this altered countenance, and these eyes red with weeping, he looked at the Cardinal, and, spite of his composure, discerning in his countenance something of solemn pleasure, and yet eager impatience, he would have remained standing with his mouth wide open, had not the Cardinal suddenly roused him from his meditation by demanding whether, among the curates assembled in the next room, there was the curate of ——. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="43">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12198" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12203">"He is there, my illustrious Signor," replied the Chaplain. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="44">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12204" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12215">"Let him come here immediately," said Federigo, "and with him the clergyman of this church." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="45">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12216" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12233">The Chaplain retired, and when he entered the apartments in which all the priests were assembled, all eyes were directed towards him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12234" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12295">He, with his mouth still open, astonishment painted on his countenance, raising his hands, and moving them in the air, cried, "Ah! gentlemen, gentlemen! hæc mutatio dexteræ Excelsi;" and paused a moment; then changing his tone, he added, "his very illustrious and reverend lordship desires to see the Signor Curato of this parish, and the Signor Curato of ——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="46">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12296" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12317">The first named immediately came forward, and at the same moment there was heard to proceed from the middle of the crowd, an "I?" long drawn out, and pronounced in a tone of astonishment. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="47">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12318" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12328">"Are not you the Signor Curato of ——?" replied the Chaplain. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="48">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12329" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12331">"Yes, certainly; but ——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="49">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12332" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12338">"His very illustrious and reverend lordship desires to see you." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="50">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12339" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12353">"Me?" again said this voice, plainly signifying by this monosyllable, "what can I have to do with this?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12354" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12380">But this time, together with the voice, came forth the man, Don Abbondio, in person, who advanced with a constrained step, and with an air expressing something between astonishment and vexation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12381" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12398">The Chaplain gave him a sign with his hand, which was intended to say, "Come with us; come, is it so difficult?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12399" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12408">And preceding the two curates, he went towards the door, opened it, and introduced them. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="51">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12409" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12437">The Cardinal let go the hand of the Unknown, with whom he had in the meantime been concerting what ought to be done; he withdrew a little, and called towards him by a sign, the curate of the church. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12438" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12516">He told him briefly the affair, and asked whether he could immediately find a good woman who would go in a litter to the castle to fetch Lucia; a woman who would have head and heart enough to know how to manage an expedition thus unusual, who would assume manners the most likely to tranquillise, and employ words the best adapted to encourage the poor girl, whose liberation even, after so much anguish, so much disquiet, might cause her a fresh terror. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12517" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12530">Having reflected a moment, the curate said he knew such a person, and went out. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12531" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12555">The Cardinal, with another sign, summoned the Chaplain to him, and ordered him to have immediately prepared a litter and attendants, and to command two mules also to be saddled. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12556" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12564">The Chaplain having now departed, he turned towards Don Abbondio. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="52">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12565" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12624">Who, having placed himself near the Cardinal, so as to keep at a distance from the other gentleman, cast a glance first towards one, and then towards another, trying to imagine what all this could mean, and then, approaching nearer, made a reverence, and said, "they have signified to me, that your illustrious lordship desired to see me; but I believe they have made a mistake." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="53">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12625" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12641">"They have made no mistake," replied Federigo. "I have good intelligence to give you, and at the same time to confer upon you a consolatory and agreeable office. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12642" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12693">One of your flock, whom you will have wept over as lost—Lucia Mondella—is found, and is near here, in the house of this gentleman, my dear friend; and you will now go with him, and with a woman whom the curate of this parish is gone in search of—you will go, I say, to fetch this your young friend, and accompany her here." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="54">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12694" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12769">Don Abbondio did all in his power to conceal the annoyance, what do I say?—the torment, the martyrdom, which such a proposition, such an order, caused him; and not having time to dissemble an expression of vexation already formed on his face, he concealed it by profoundly bowing his head in sign of obedience, and only raised it again to make another profound reverence, casting a piteous look, which said, "I am in your hands, have mercy, *parcere subjectis.*" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="55">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12770" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12778">The Cardinal then inquired from him what relations Lucia had. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="56">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12779" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12794">"She has no near relative, except her mother, with whom she lives," replied Don Abbondio. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="57">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12795" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12801">"And is her mother in her native village?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="58">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12802" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12803">"Yes, my lord." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="59">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12804" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12868">"Since," replied Federigo, "this poor girl cannot immediately be restored to her home, it would be a great consolation to her, to see her mother; therefore, if the Signor Curato of this place does not arrive before I go to church, do me the favour to tell him to find a cart, or a horse, and send a prudent man in search of this woman, and let him conduct her here." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="60">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12869" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12875">"If I were to go myself?" said Don Abbondio. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="61">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12876" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12885">"No, no, not you; I have already begged you to do something else," replied the Cardinal. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="62">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12886" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12894">"I proposed myself," replied Don Abbondio, "in order that I might prepare the poor mother. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12895" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12922">She is a woman with great sensibilities; and it is necessary to have a person who knows her, and who will be able to manage her humour, so as not to do evil instead of good." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="63">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12923" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12946">"And it is on this account that I beg you to inform the Signor Curato that he must choose a suitable man; you will be more useful in another place," replied the Cardinal. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12947" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12992">He would have said, this poor young girl has much more need to see immediately a well-known face, a safe person, in this castle, after so many hours of terror, and when she is still in such uncertainty regarding the future; but these were not reasons to be thus clearly assigned before this third person. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12993" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13027">It appeared, however, strange to the Cardinal that Don Abbondio had not comprehended this from his air; and so out of place appeared to him this proposal and obstinacy, that he thought there must be something concealed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13028" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13050">He looked Don Abbondio in the face, and then easily discovered his terror at travelling with this tremendous man, at entering this house, even for a few moments. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13051" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13118">Wishing, therefore, entirely to dissipate these cowardly fears, and yet not liking to draw aside the curate and whisper secretly to him whilst his new friend was present, he thought that the best means to do this was to speak to the Unknown himself, so that Don Abbondio might learn by his answers that he was no longer a man to be feared. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13119" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13152">He approached, therefore, the Unknown, and with that air of spontaneous confidence which is to be found in a new and strong affection, as well as in an old friendship, said, "Do not think that I shall be satisfied for to-day with this visit. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13153" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13162">You will return, will you not, in company with this worthy ecclesiastic?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="64">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13163" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13178">"Whether I shall return?" replied the Unknown. "Even should you refuse to receive me, I should remain obstinately at your door, like a beggar. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13179" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13192">I have need to speak with you. I have need to hear you—to see you. I have need of you." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13193" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13209">Federigo took his hand, pressed it, and said, "Will you do me the favour then to stay and dine with me. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13210" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13210">I shall expect you. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13211" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13230">Meanwhile I will go and pray and return thanks with these people; and you will go and gather the first fruits of mercy." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="65">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13231" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13329">Don Abbondio, when he had heard these demonstrations of affection, was like a child who sees a man caressing in safety his great, rough, savage dog, with red eyes, and its notorious name for biting and causing terror, and yet hears this man tell his master that his dog is a good beast, quiet, very quiet; the child looks at the master, and neither contradicts nor approves; looks at the dog, and dares not approach him, lest the good beast should shew his teeth, although this were only in play; he does not dare to withdraw lest he should appear a coward, and says in his heart, "Oh that I were at home!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="66">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13330" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13361">The Cardinal, who was about to retire, still holding by the hand the Unknown, and conducting him along with him, cast another glance at the poor man, who remained behind, mortified, discontented, and making a long face without intending to do so. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13362" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13429">He thought perhaps that he was vexed that greater attention had not been paid him, that he had been left in a corner as it were, more especially in the presence of a criminal thus well received and caressed; therefore the Archbishop turned towards him in passing, paused a moment, and with a friendly smile said to him, "Signor Curato, you are always with me in the house of our good Father; but this one — this one, *perierat, et inventus est.*" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="67">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13430" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13446">"Oh, how much I rejoice!" exclaimed Don Abbondio, making a low reverence to both. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13447" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13482">The Archbishop went forward, pushed the door, and the two folding-doors being immediately thrown open by two servants who stood one on each side, the admirable pair were exhibited to the desiring gaze of the clergy assembled in the adjoining room. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13483" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13532">Here they beheld two countenances upon which was depicted a different emotion, but an emotion equally profound; there was in the venerable aspect of the Cardinal a tenderness of gratitude, a humble joy; in that of the Unknown, a shame tempered by consolation, a new modesty, a remorse, through which, however, always shewed itself the vigour of his wild and severe nature. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13533" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13570">It was afterwards known, that this passage from Isaiah had occurred to the mind of more than one spectator, "The wolf also shall dwell with the lamb, and the leopard shall lie down with the kid." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13571" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13578">Behind them came Don Abbondio, to whom no one paid any attention. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="68">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13579" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13624">When they had reached the middle of the room, the Cardinal's groom of the chamber approached him, to say, that he had executed the orders communicated to him by the Chaplain, that the litter and the two mules were ready, and that they now only waited for the woman whom the Curate should bring with him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13625" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13662">The Cardinal told him, that, as soon as he should arrive, he should immediately speak with Don Abbondio, and that then all should depend upon the commands of Don Abbondio and the Unknown; saying which, he again pressed the hand of the last-mentioned person in sign of leave-taking, and again said, "I shall expect you." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13663" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13676">He then turned to salute Don Abbondio, and directed his steps towards the church. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13677" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13696">The clergy followed him rather in a crowd than in a procession, and the two travelling companions remained alone behind in the room. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="69">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13697" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13753">The Unknown was absorbed in himself, thoughtful, and impatient for the moment to come, when he should deliver his Lucia from pain and imprisonment — his Lucia, now in a very different sense in which she had been his the day before; but his countenance expressed a concentrated agitation, which to the suspicious eye of Don Abbondio might easily appear something worse. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13754" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13774">He looked at him, and would have liked to commence a friendly conversation with him; but "what should he say to him?" thought he to himself; "ought I tell him how rejoiced I am? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13775" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13795">That I am rejoiced about what? that he, having been until now a demon, has resolved to become a respectable man like other people? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13796" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13797">A fine compliment that! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13798" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13814">Ah! in whatever way I might rejoice myself, my congratulation would mean nothing else. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13815" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13827">And even should it be true that he has become an honest man thus all at once! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13828" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13840">Such demonstrations as these are very common in the world, and are made for many reasons! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13841" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13856">How I do know? — sometimes — and in the meanwhile I have to go with him! to his castle! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13857" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13863">O what a thing! what a thing! what a thing! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13864" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13868">Who could have told me this, this morning! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13869" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13924">Ah, if I do but escape in safety, the Signora Perpetua shall hear from me for having thus driven me here by force out of my church, and this, too, when it was not necessary; saying, that all the curates of the neighbourhood, and even those from afar, were coming, and that one must not remain behind, and this, and that, and the other; and to embark me in an affair of this kind! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13925" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13927">O unfortunate that I am! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13928" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13997">Yet one must say something to this man!" He thought, and thought again, and had at length found something which he could say,—"I should never have expected the good fortune of finding myself in such respectable company," and was ready to open his mouth, when the groom of the chamber entered with the Curate of the village, who announced that the woman was already seated in the litter, and then turned to Don Abbondio, to receive from him the Cardinal's other commission. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13998" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14029">Don Abbondio acquitted himself of this duty as well as he was able in his present confused state of mind; and then approaching the attendant, said, "Give me, at least, a quiet beast, for, to say the truth, I am but a poor horseman." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="70">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14030" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14046">"Be easy," replied the man with a half smile; "it is the mule of the secretary, who is a learned man." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="71">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14047" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14079">"That is sufficient," replied Don Abbondio, and continued to think,—"Heaven sends me many blessings!" The Signor had prepared to depart at the first intelligence, but, having reached the door, he perceived that Don Abbondio had remained behind. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="72">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14080" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14114">He paused to wait for him, and when he arrived in great haste, and with an air which seemed to beg pardon, the Signor bowed, and with a courteous and humble demeanour made Don Abbondio pass out before him—a circumstance which somewhat restored the courage of the poor unfortunate. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14115" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14178">But scarcely had he set foot in the court-yard before he saw a novelty which entirely destroyed this small consolation; he saw the Unknown go towards a corner, take the barrel of his carabine in one hand, the strap in the other, and with a quick movement, as though he were performing a military exercise, sling the carabine over his shoulder. "Oh! oh! oh!" thought Don Abbondio; "what will he do with this instrument! </note>
        </p>
        <p n="73">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14179" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14184">Fine discipline this for a converted man! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14185" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14190">And if any whim should seize him? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14191" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14252">Oh, what an expedition! Oh, what an expedition!" If the Signor could have had the least suspicion in the world of the nature of the thoughts which were passing through his companion's mind, it would be impossible to say what he would not have done to reassure him; but he was very far from suspecting such a thing, and Don Abbondio was careful not to make a single movement which should clearly say, "I do not trust your lordship." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="74">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14253" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14273">When they reached the street-door, they found the two mules all ready prepared, and the Unknown leaped upon the one which was presented him by a stable-boy. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="75">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14274" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14295">"She has no vicious tricks?" Don Abbondio demanded of the groom of the chamber, placing again on the ground the foot he had raised towards the stirrup. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="76">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14296" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14304">"Only mount with a good heart; she is a very lamb." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14305" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14317">Don Abbondio, with the assistance of the groom, mounts up to the saddle, and up, up, up, and now he is seated. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="77">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14318" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14338">The litter, which was a few paces in advance, drawn by two mules, moved off at the voice of the driver, and the train departed. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="78">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14339" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14366">It was necessary to pass before the church, which was crowded with people, through a small square, which was also filled by the peasants of the neighbourhood, and by strangers who had not been able to enter the church. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14367" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14411">Already the important news had spread; and at the appearance of the train, at the appearance of this man who, but a few hours before an object of terror and execration, was now become an object of agreeable astonishment, there arose among the crowd a murmur almost of applause, and making way for him, they yet, at the same time, pressed forward so as to see him near. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14412" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14449">The litter passed on, the Unknown passed on; and arrived before the open door of the church, he raised his hat, and bowed this much-feared brow almost to the mane of his mule, amidst the confused hum of a hundred voices which cried, "God bless you!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14450" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14490">Don Abbondio also raised his hat, and bowed himself, recommending his soul to heaven; but hearing the solemn concert of his brethren, who sang without interruption, he experienced an envy, a tender melancholy, such an anguish, that he had great difficulty to restrain his tears. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="79">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14491" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14511">When they had left the habitations, and were in the open country, in the windings of the deserted road, a still blacker veil spread itself over his thoughts. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14512" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14544">He had no other object than the mule-driver whom he could regard with confidence, and he, belonging to the Cardinal's service, must certainly be a worthy man, and besides he had not a cowardly air. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14545" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14581">Every now and then, they encountered travellers who hastened to see the Cardinal; this was a consolation for Don Abbondio, but alas! only a fugitive one, for he was travelling towards that fearful valley, where they would only meet the subjects of the friend, and what subjects! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14582" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14610">He would now have desired more than ever to enter into discourse with the friend, as much to fathom his motives as to keep him in good humour, but seeing him absorbed in thought, this desire left him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14611" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14712">He was therefore obliged to talk with himself; and here is a portion of the poor man's conversation during the journey: were we to write down the whole, we should have enough wherewith to make a book. "Is it not a strange thing that saints as well as rogues should have quicksilver in their veins, and not content with always being in motion themselves must desire to draw into the dance, if they can, all the human race; and that the most active must always come in search of me, who never go in search of any one, and drag me by the hair into their affairs, I who never ask anything more than to be allowed to live? </note>
        </p>
        <p n="80">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14713" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14718">This mad rascal, Don Rodrigo! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14719" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14737">What does he require to make him the happiest man in the world, if he only had a little more wisdom? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14738" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14763">He is young, rich, respected, courted—a quiet life is wearisome to him; and he must needs go in search of troubles, both for himself and others. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14764" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14807">He might lead a life of ease; but no, sirs, he will follow the trade of molesting women—the most foolish, the most rascally, the most insane trade in this world; he might ride to paradise in his carriage, but he chooses to go limping to the devil's house. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14808" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14846">And this man!" and here he glanced at him, as though he suspected that the Unknown heard his thoughts; "this man, after he has turned the world topsy-turvy by his wickedness, now turns it topsy-turvy by his conversion—if it be real! </note>
        </p>
        <p n="81">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14847" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14868">Meanwhile it is for me to make the experiment," whether it is so or not!—There are people who, when they are born with this rage within them, must always be making a noise. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14869" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14880">Is so much then required to play the gentleman all one's life, as I have done? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14881" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14900">No, sirs; but they must quarter, kill, and play the devil—oh, poor me!—and then there must be a disturbance even when they do penance. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n189" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14901" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14972">Penance, when one really desires it, one can perform at home, quietly, without so much preparation, without causing one's neighbour so much inconvenience.—And his illustrious lordship immediately, with open arms, receives him, calls him "dear friend, my dearest friend;" listens to his slightest word, as though he had seen him perform miracles; straightway seizes a resolution, enters into it hand and foot—"quickly here! quickly there!" is what at home we call precipitation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n190" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14973" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14994">And without the least earnest-money, places in his hand a poor curate! This is what is called playing odd and even with a poor man! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n191" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14995" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15010">A holy bishop, such as he, should be jealous of his curates as of the apple of his eye. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n192" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15011" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15031">A little patience, a little prudence, a little charity, it seems to me, may exist together with holiness. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n193" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15032" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15036">And if this should be only outside show! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n194" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15037" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15050">Who can know all the designs of men, and, I say, of men such as this? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n195" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15051" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15062">Only to think, that it is for me to go with him to his house! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n196" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15063" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15076">There may be some plot concealed under all this; alas, for me! it is better not to think of this. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n197" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15077" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15082">What is all this affair about Lucia? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n198" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15083" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15097">If there should be an understanding with Don Rodrigo? What people there are! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n199" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15098" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15103">But how has she fallen into the clutches of this man? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n200" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15104" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15106">Who knows? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n201" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15107" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15126">It is all a secret with Monsignore; and to me, whom they make trot about in this manner, they say not a word. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n202" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15127" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15150">I do not trouble myself about other people's affairs; but when one risks one's life, one has some right to know something. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n203" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15151" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15161">If it were really to go and fetch this creature—why, patience! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n204" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15162" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15168">However, he could very well conduct her back himself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n205" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15169" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15185">And then, if he is thus converted, if he is become a holy father, what need was there for me? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n206" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15186" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15188">O what a chaos! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n207" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15189" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15203">Enough, heaven has willed it; it will here be a great inconvenience; but patience! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n208" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15204" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15230">I shall be very happy also for this poor Lucia; she also will have escaped wonderfully; heaven knows what she has suffered, I pity her, but she is born for my ruin. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n209" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15231" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15241">Ah, if I could only see really into this man's heart, and know what he thinks! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n210" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15242" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15245">Who can know that? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n211" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15246" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15257">See, now he appears St. Antonio in the desert, now Holophernes himself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n212" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15258" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15262">Oh, unfortunate that I am! unfortunate that I am! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n213" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15263" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15313">Enough; heaven is obliged to aid me, for I have not run into this affair through my own caprice. And in truth, over the countenance of the Unknown thoughts might be said to pass, like clouds in a tempestuous hour across the sun's disc—a violent light, and a cold gloom, alternating every moment. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="82">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n214" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15314" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15347">His soul, still intoxicated by Federigo's gentle words, and as it were enjoying a second youth in its new life, was elated by this idea of mercy, pardon, and love; then, again, it would be depressed by the weight of the terrible past. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n215" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15348" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15385">He hastened with anxiety to discover those deeds of wickedness which might yet be repaired, something which he might break off in the middle, those remedies which were the most expedient and most sure; how he should loosen so many knots, and what he should do with so many accomplices; —to think of all this was enough to confound him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n216" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15386" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15430">Even to the present expedition, which was the easiest of all, and which was so near its termination, he applied himself with an impatience, mingled with anguish, thinking that all this time the poor girl was suffering, God knows how much, and that he, the one who yearned to liberate her, was still the one who kept her in suffering. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n217" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15431" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15454">Wherever there happened to be two roads, the mule-driver turned round to inquire which he should take: the Unknown indicated the right one with his hand, and at the same time signed to him to make all speed. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="83">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n218" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15455" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15457">At length they entered the valley. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n219" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15458" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15464">How was it then with Don Abbondio? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n220" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15465" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15510">To be really in this famous valley, regarding which he had so often heard such horrible histories related; to see, in flesh and blood, these famous men, the flower of the Italian bravoes—these men without fear and mercy, and to meet them thus, one, two, three, at every turning of the road. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n221" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15511" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15538">They bowed most submissively certainly before the Signor; but these bronzed visages—these bushy whiskers! these great wicked eyes, which to Don Abbondio seemed to say, "Shall we kill this priest?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n222" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15539" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15602">So great a terror did they inspire him with, that in a moment of extreme consternation, he said to himself, "Had I married them nothing more could have happened to me." During all this time they proceeded by a sandy road, along the torrent; there these steep cliffs—gloomy, uninhabited; here this population, which would make any desert seem desirable. Dante was not placed in a worse situation in the middle of Malebolge. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="84">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n223" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15603" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15618">They passed the Malanotte; the bravoes standing at the entrance saluted the Signor, and stared at his companion and the litter. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n224" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15619" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15640">They did not know what to think; the departure of the Unknown alone that morning was something extraordinary; the return was not less so. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n225" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15641" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15645">Was this a captive he brought with him? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n226" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15646" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15651">But how had he been able to take a captive by himself? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n227" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15652" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15663">And what was this strange litter? and whose livery could this be! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n228" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15664" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15680">They gazed and gazed, but no one moved, for such was the command their master gave with his eye. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="85">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n229" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15681" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15686">They make the ascent, they have reached the summit. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n230" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15687" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15771">The bravoes, who are on the esplanade and at the portal, retire and leave a free passage; the Unknown again signs that no one shall move; he spurs his mule, and passes on before the litter; signs to the mule-driver and Don Abbondio that they shall follow him; enters a court, passes out of it into a second; rides towards a small door, commands by a sign a bravo to keep back, who runs forward to hold his stirrup, and says to him, "stay thou there, and allow no one to approach." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n231" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15772" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15805">He now dismounts, fastens the mule in haste to an iron bar, goes towards the litter, approaches the woman who has opened the curtains, and says, in a low voice, "console her quickly; make her quickly understand that she is free, in the hands of friends. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n232" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15806" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15810">God will recompense you." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n233" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15811" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15882">He signs to the mule-driver to open the litter; then nears Don Abbondio, and with a more serene appearance than Don Abbondio had yet observed, or ever had believed he could assume, and with joy at seeing his good work, at length nearly brought to its completion, painted upon his countenance, he says to Don Abbondio, also in an under-tone, "Signor Curato," "I do not ask your excuse for the inconvenience you have suffered on my account; you have done this for One who pays well, and for this your poor child." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n234" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15883" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15900">Having thus spoken, he with one hand seizes the bridle, with the other the stirrup, and assists Don Abbondio to descend. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="86">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n235" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15901" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15910">This countenance, these words, this action, had given him life. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n236" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15911" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15934">He heaved a sigh, which he had suppressed for the last hour; and, bowing towards the Unknown, replied in a very low voice, "Does it appear to you so? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n237" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15935" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15945">But, but, but, but——!" and he slid as well as he could from his mule. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap23-n238" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15946" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15986">The Unknown then fastened the second mule, told the driver to await them there, took from his pocket a key, unlocked the door, entered, made the curate and the women enter also, preceded them to the small staircase, and all three ascended in silence. </note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>