<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CHAPTER XXXIV.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>1845</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed Lovers: a Milanese Story of the Seventeenth Century. With The Column of Infamy by Alessandro Manzoni. In Three Volumes</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
          <date>1845</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Henry Francis C. Logan</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="English_1845_cap34">
        <p n="1">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10042">Renzo had heard something vague regarding the existence of certain severe orders intended to prevent the entrance of all strangers who were unprovided with certificates of health; nevertheless he believed that with a little address it would be very easy to evade these prohibitions. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10043" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10110">And certainly nothing could be more true. Without speaking of the causes which at that time prevented any public order being rigorously executed, and without even mentioning the especial reasons which rendered the execution of this particular order peculiarly difficult, Milan was at this moment so circumstanced that there no longer seemed any utility in preserving this strict watch. Whoever now entered the city appeared a man rather reckless of his own safety, than an object to be feared by the citizens. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="2">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10111" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10147">Acting upon this knowledge, Renzo's design was to attempt an entrance through the first gate he approached, and if he met with any opposition to wander about until he found one where access was less difficult. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10148" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10158">Heaven only knows how many gates Renzo imagined there were at Milan! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10159" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10191">Having arrived under the walls, he paused to look around him, with the air of one who, not knowing which direction to choose, seems to seek advice from the surrounding objects. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10192" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10248">But to the right and to the left he only saw a winding path; in front of him only the city walls; nowhere did he perceive the slightest trace of living beings, except that from a certain part of the ramparts there arose a column of dense black smoke, which ascending spread itself into vast masses, and hung suspended, motionless and dark, in the air. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10249" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10277">These were the garments, beds, and other infected articles, which were being delivered to the flames; and in many parts of the ramparts appeared traces of these melancholy bonfires. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="3">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10278" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10328">The day was gloomy, the air heavy, the whole heavens were veiled by one vast immoveable cloud, which appeared to deny the presence of the sun without prophesying rain; the whole surrounding country lay most part uncultivated and utterly barren, every blade of grass was burnt up, not a single drop of dew was to be seen upon the withered and fainting leaves. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10329" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10356">This solitude, this silence, thus near a mighty city, increased Renzo's uneasiness, and rendered his thoughts still more gloomy. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="4">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10357" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10386">He paused a few moments, and directed his steps towards the right, unconsciously approaching the New Gate, which he could not see, although he was quite close upon it, on account of a bulwark behind which it was concealed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10387" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10492">He hastened on, and having turned the angle of the bulwark, the first thing that met his view was a wooden hut, at the entrance of which stood a sentinel, leaning upon his musket, with a certain air of negligence or weariness. Behind this hut was a palisade, and behind the palisade stood the gate, that is to say, two walls surmounted by a small roof, intended to preserve the folding doors which now stood open, as did also the grating in the palisade. Precisely before this opening placed upon the ground was a melancholy impediment—a handbarrow, upon which two monatti were placing a poor wretch whom they were about to carry away. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="5">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10493" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10505">This was the chief of the custom-house officers, who had a short time before been seized with the plague. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10506" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10539">Renzo paused where he was, waiting until this sad spectacle should be at an end. The convoy having departed, and no one appearing to close the wicket, it struck Renzo that now was the proper moment to enter, and he hastened on with quick steps, but the sentinel shouted roughly after him, "Holla!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10540" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10559">Renzo again stopped, and, giving him a sign of intelligence, drew forth a half ducat, and shewed it him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10560" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10595">The sentinel, either having already had the plague, or fearing it less than he loved half ducats, signed to Renzo to throw him the money, and, seeing it immediately fly to his feet, murmured, "enter quickly." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10596" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10639">Renzo did not wait to hear this twice, but passed quickly on through the palisade, through the gateway, and pursued his road without any one paying attention to him, except that after he had walked about forty paces, he heard another "Holla!" which another sentinel shouted after him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10640" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10654">This time he feigned not to hear the cry, and without even turning round quickened his step. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10655" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10702">"Holla!" cried the sentinel again, in a voice which announced rather impatience than any resolution of forcing Renzo to obey his order; and, seeing his order was not attended to, he shrugged his shoulders, and returned into his sentry-box, with the air of one who considered it more important to avoid approaching the passers-by, than to inquire into their affairs. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="6">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10703" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10733">The road which Renzo had taken led straight to the canal called the Naviglio: on either hand, were hedges or garden walls, churches or convents, but few houses. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10734" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10758">At the upper end of this street, and about the middle of the one which runs along the canal, stood a column, with a cross placed upon it, called the cross of Saint Eusebio. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10759" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10770">Intently as Renzo gazed before him, he could distinguish nothing but the said cross. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10771" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10830">At length, however, he perceived a citizen approaching him. "Here, at least, comes a Christian!" exclaimed our hero to himself, and immediately turned towards this man, thinking that he would gain from him information regarding his way. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10831" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10863">The citizen had perceived the stranger as he advanced, and regarded him with suspicion, which was much increased when he observed that this stranger, instead of going about his own business, approached him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10864" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10924">Renzo, when he had arrived within a few paces of the citizen, raised his hat like a polite mountaineer as he was, and holding it in his left hand, placed the right hand in the crown, and thus drew near the gentleman, who, his eyes almost starting out of his head, hastily stepped back, and raising a knotty stick, directed its end, which was of iron, at Renzo's face, crying out at the same time, with all his might— "away! away! away!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="7">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10925" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10976">"Oh, oh!" exclaimed in his turn our poor Renzo. He placed his hat again upon his head, and not desiring a greeting after this manner, turned his back upon this extravagant man, and pursued his way—or more correctly that way in which he happened to find himself. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="8">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10977" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10991">The citizen also pursued his, trembling violently, and turning to look back every moment. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10992" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11043">Having reached home, he related how he had been met by an anointer, who had an humble and gentle manner, but whose countenance was that of an infamous impostor, and who had either his box of ointment or his phial of powder, he was not certain which it was, concealed in the crown of his hat, with which he would have certainly touched him, had he not managed to keep the wretch at a certain distance. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11044" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11061">"If he had only approached a single step nearer," added the citizen, "I would have run him straight through, the villain! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11062" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11084">The misfortune was, that we happened to be in such a solitary place; if it had been in the heart of Milan I would have called for help, and people would have fallen upon him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11085" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11094">They would most assuredly have found this infernal mixture in his hat. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11095" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11134">But alone as we were, I must consider myself fortunate in having succeeded in frightening him, without drawing upon myself a misfortune, for a little powder is easily thrown; and these people have a wonderful dexterity in such matters; besides they have the devil on their sides. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11135" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11145">He must now be wandering about Milan; who knows what mischief he may be about?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11146" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11186">And to the end of his life, which was a very long one, whenever the citizen spoke of the anointers, he repeated this history, and always added: "Don't let those who maintain that there is no truth in these things talk to me; before speaking, one ought to have seen the thing with one's own eyes." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="9">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11187" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11258">Renzo, far from suspecting the danger which he had just escaped, and moved by anger rather than fear, meditated, whilst he pursued his way, upon this singular reception, and pretty nearly divined the thoughts of the stranger; but the whole affair appeared to him so irrational, that he concluded this man must be a little out of his right mind. "The commencement is bad," he, however, thought to himself; "it seems as though I had an unlucky star to guide me in this Milan. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11259" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11276">Everything seconds my entrance; but then, as soon as I am once within the walls, I meet with nothing but misfortunes. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11277" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11316">Enough—with the aid of God—if I find—if I succeed in discovering—ah! then all this will appear as nothing!" Having arrived at the bridge, he turned round without any hesitation towards the left, and entered the street of San Marco, imagining that this street ought to conduct him to the heart of the city. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="10">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11317" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11361">As he proceeded, he looked here and there to see whether he could discover any human being; but he only saw a miserable, hideous corpse, which lay in a small ditch. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11362" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11403">Having passed this dreadful object, he heard a cry of "There goes a man!" and looking round he saw at a short distance, in the balcony of a miserable isolated house, a poor woman standing, with a group of children around her; she continued to call, and signed to him with her hand to approach. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11404" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11434">He ran towards her; and as soon as he arrived, "O kind youth!" exclaimed the woman, "for the love of your poor lost ones, have the goodness to go and inform the commissary that we are left here entirely forgotten. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11435" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11465">They have nailed up the door, as you may see; and since yesterday morning, no one has come to bring us food. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11466" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11490">All the hours that I have stood here I have not found a single Christian who would do me this charity; and these poor little innocents are dying of hunger." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="11">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11491" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11514">"Of hunger?" cried Renzo, thrusting his hands into his pockets; "here, here," said he, drawing "forth the two loaves, " let down something in which I can place them." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="12">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11515" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11538">"God will reward you; only wait a moment," said the woman; and she went in search of a basket, and a cord also, by which to let it down from the window. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11539" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11622">Meanwhile, Renzo recollected the two little loaves he had found near the cross, upon his first entrance into Milan, and he thought to himself—"Only see: here is, perhaps, even a more perfect restitution than if I had returned the loaves to their proper possessor; for truly this is a deed of mercy." "As to the commissary of whom you spoke, my good lady," he said, placing the bread in the basket, "I am afraid I shall be unable to serve you; for to speak the truth, I am a stranger, and know nothing about this place. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="13">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11623" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11639">However, if I meet with any man who is at all civil or humane, I will tell him." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="14">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11640" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11657">The woman besought him to do so, and mentioned to him the name of the street in which she lived. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="15">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11658" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11673">"You also," resumed Renzo, "can do me a favour, I fancy, a real charity, without in the least incommoding yourself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11674" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11689">Do you know how to direct me to the mansion of a great family who live here in Milan, the mansion of . . . . ?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="16">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11690" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11705">"I know very well that there is such a mansion, but unfortunately I do not know where it is situated. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11706" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11716">Going straightforward you will meet with some one who will direct you. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11717" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11723">And remember to mention us to him." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="17">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11724" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11730">"Do not fear," said Renzo, and pursued his way. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11731" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11774">At every step he heard a noise, which he had first perceived whilst conversing with the poor woman, increase and approach; it was a sound of wheels and horses' hoofs, accompanied by the ringing of little bells, and every now and then it was embellished by the cracking of whips, and by shouts. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11775" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11780">He looked about him, but could perceive nothing. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11781" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11826">Having reached the end of the winding street along which he was walking, and having arrived at the square of San Marco, the first objects which met his view were two upright posts, with a rope and pulleys; he was not long in recognising (for it was a very familiar object in those times) the abominable machine of torture. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11827" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11885">These machines had been raised in all open squares, and in all spacious streets, in order that the deputies belonging to each quarter of the city, who were empowered with the most arbitrary authority, might immediately exercise it upon any one who should chance to merit punishment, either upon people who escaped out of a condemned house, upon underlings who refused to obey, or in short, upon any one whom they chose to torture. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11886" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11907">It was one of those extreme and inefficacious measures of which in those times, and especially in such moments, the public authorities were so profuse. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="18">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11908" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11999">Whilst Renzo stood gazing at the machine, and wondering wherefore it was erected in this place, the noise continued to approach, and suddenly he saw a man who was ringing a bell, appear from behind an angle of the church. This was an *apparitore*; and behind him followed two horses, which, stretching out their necks, and every now and then stumbling forward, drew after them, with great difficulty, a cart filled with dead bodies; after the cart followed another — and then another — and another — and another. Beside the horses walked Monatti, who drove them forward with stripes, blows, and curses. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12000" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12073">The corpses were for the most part naked, some few were badly wrapt up in wretched rags, all were heaped up, lying one upon another, and resembled a nest of vipers, which slowly uncurl themselves upon the approach of spring, for at each shock, at each stumble, these horrible masses were seen to tremble and separate in a hideous manner; heads dangled to and fro; the long hair of women floated in the air; arms released themselves and hung over the wheels, exhibiting to the already horrified spectator, how such a spectacle might become even yet more horrible. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="19">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12074" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12093">Our poor youth had paused in a corner of the square, and prayed for the souls of these unknown dead. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12094" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12107">A dreadful thought rushed through his mind. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12108" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12149">"Perhaps there—there—together with these bodies, there, underneath them — O God, do not permit this to be! do not permit the very thought even!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="20">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12150" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12175">This fearful train having passed, Renzo moved away, traversed the square, and at length reached the bridge Marcellino, and at last arrives in the Borgo Nuovo. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12176" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12227">Looking before him always with the desire of seeing some one who could direct him, he saw at the very end of the street a priest in a doublet, with a long staff in his hand; he was standing close to a half-opened door, his head inclined towards the opening; in a short time Renzo saw the priest raise his hand, as if pronouncing a blessing. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12228" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12250">Conjecturing—as was the fact—that he had just ended confessing some one, Renzo said to himself, "This is the very man for me. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12251" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12300">If a priest, performing the vocation of a priest, has no spark of love, of charity, or of kindness, one must really say that there is no longer any virtue left in the world." The priest meantime walked away from the door and approached Renzo, carefully keeping in the middle of the street. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="21">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12301" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12331">Renzo, when he had drawn near, raised his hat, and signing to him that he desired to speak, stood still at the same time, so as to inform the priest that he had no wish to approach nearer. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12332" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12356">The good priest stopped also, with the air of one who is inclined to listen, planting, however, at the same time, his staff before him, as though to form a bulwark. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12357" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12417">Renzo proffered his inquiry, regarding which the priest not only returned very satisfactory information, telling him the name of the street in which the mansion was situated, but also gave the poor youth ample directions, directions of which he perceived Renzo stood in much need. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="22">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12418" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12445">"God preserve you in health now and in all times," said Renzo; and whilst the good priest was about to continue his way, "another favour I have to request," began Renzo, and told him about the poor woman who had been forgotten. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12446" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12469">The good man thanked Renzo for having afforded him this opportunity of performing a charitable deed which was thus urgently called for; and, saying that he would go and inform the proper authorities, continued his way. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="23">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12470" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12496">Renzo also pursued his walk, and kept repeating to himself the various directions which had been given him; so as to learn them by heart, and thus not be obliged to inquire his way at every corner. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12497" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12525">But it is impossible to imagine how difficult this operation was, not so much from the difficulty of the thing itself, as owing to a fresh disquiet which had arisen in his soul. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12526" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12537">The name of the street, the indication of the road, had redoubled his alarms. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12538" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12621">It was what he had desired, it was what he had requested, and was that without which he could have done nothing; no one had told him anything from which he could presage the least evil; but how was it? The idea of an end being put to his uncertainty, of the time being near when he should hear—"she is living"—or—"she is dead!" this idea, I say, so overpowered him, that in this moment he would rather have been still in uncertainty regarding every thing, nay, at the very outset of the journey which was now so near its termination. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12622" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12653">He collected his strength, and said to himself: "Ah! if I now begin to play the child, how will affairs go on?" And thus having encouraged himself, as best he could, he pursued his way, advancing into the city. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="24">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12654" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12721">Renzo found himself precisely in one of the most desolate and squalid quarters; in that labyrinth of streets which bears the name of the Carobio di porta Nuova. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12722" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12773">The fury of the contagion, and the stench from the dead bodies scattered about, had been so great, that the few survivors had been obliged to take themselves off. Thus, whilst the passer-by was rendered melancholy by this air of neglect and desertion, his senses were unpleasantly affected by the signs and traces left behind by the former inhabitants. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12774" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12826">Renzo quickened his step, encouraging himself with the thought that the object of his search was still far off, and hoping that before he reached it, the scene would in some degree have changed. In a short time he reached a spot which might be considered the city of the living; but what a city! and what living beings! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12827" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12914">Most of the doors were closed, either from suspicion or terror; some few stood wide open, either because the houses were uninhabited, or had been invaded; others were nailed or sealed up, owing to there being either dead or sick within; other houses were marked with a cross drawn in charcoal, as a sign to the Monatti that there were dead bodies there ready for them to fetch away. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12915" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12981">Everywhere were rags, and what was far more revolting than mere rags, old bandages, and infected straw or sheets flung from the windows; sometimes even corpses, either of people who had died suddenly in the streets, and who had been left lying there, until some cart should pick them up, or perhaps corpses which had been dropped from these very carts, or flung from the windows; so much had the duration and horror of the general calamity brutalized the soul, and caused men to forget every feeling of compassion, every social duty! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12982" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13033">All the noise of labour; all the rush of carriages; all the cries of vendors; all the hum of population, had ceased—it was rare that this silence of death was broken, except by the rolling of the funeral cars, by the lamentations of the poor, by the cries of the sick, by the yells of the delirious, or by the shouts of the Monatti. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13034" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13089">At dawn, at mid-day, and in the evening, a bell from the Cathedral tolled the hour for the recital of certain prayers which had been prescribed by the Archbishop; the bells from all the other churches responded; and then might be seen people appearing at the windows to pray in company—then might be heard a murmur of groans and prayers, which at once inspired a melancholy, mingled with some little hope. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="25">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13090" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13154">Two-thirds of the inhabitants were already dead; a good part of the remainder had either taken flight or were fallen sick; the concourse of foot passengers was reduced to a very small number, and in a long circuit you would not, except by some extraordinary chance, meet with a single individual in whom you would not notice something strange, something which indicated a melancholy change of circumstances. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13155" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13209">Men of the highest rank were seen without cloak or mantle, then a very essential part of their costume; the priests were without their robes, and even monks in simple doublets; in short, all people had cast off such garments, as, with their long folds were liable to touch the ground or surrounding objects, and thus favour the anointers' diabolical schemes. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13210" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13304">Besides this desire to go about dressed in the most closely fitting garments possible, every one was neglectful of his person. Those who were accustomed to wear a long beard were now seen with it of the longest dimensions; whilst others, who had been formerly in the habit of shaving, now allowed their beards to grow, their hair also was long and neglected. This was occasioned not so much by that carelessness which naturally arises out of a long and general dejection, but was owing to the barbers having become a very suspicious race, ever since one of them had been arrested and condemned as a notorious anointer—we mean Giangiacomo Mora, whose name for a considerable time preserved an infamous celebrity, but who ought to be regarded with sentiments of the deepest and most lasting compassion. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13305" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13357">The greater number of the foot passengers carried a large stick, or even a pistol, in one hand, as a threatening admonition to such as chose to approach too near; in the other hand might be seen an odoriferous pastile, or a small globe of perforated wood or metal, containing a piece of sponge soaked in prepared vinegar, which was applied to the nose every now and then, or perhaps kept constantly held to it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13358" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13391">Some carried suspended round the neck a small phial filled with quicksilver, persuaded that mercury was able to absorb all pestilential effluvia; and they were very careful to renew the quicksilver every few days. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13392" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13416">Gentlemen now not only traversed the streets without their accustomed retinue, but might be seen with a basket on their arm going to purchase the necessaries of life. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13417" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13434">Friends, when they happened to meet in the street, saluted each other at a respectful distance with silent and hasty salutations. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13435" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13506">Every one, pursuing his way, had a deal to do in avoiding the disgusting remains with which the ground was strewn, and in some places entirely covered: every one endeavoured to keep in the middle of the street, and thus escape the filth and the melancholy burdens which were flung out of the windows; the venomous powders which, according to general report, were not unfrequently thrown down upon the passers-by; and also the walls, which might be anointed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13507" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13532">Thus, ignorance, prudent and watchful in a wrong direction, now only increased the anxiety and misery, and occasioned false terrors, in compensation for the reasonable and salutary fears which she in the commencement had discarded. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="26">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13533" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13598">Considering all the images of misery we have presented to our readers, and recollecting other objects still more sorrowful which yet remain undescribed, we will only pause here to mention briefly the sick who dragged themselves feebly along, or lay about the street — beggars, children, and women. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13599" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13636">This spectacle was so fearful that the spectators found almost consolation in the thought which to posterity, or those removed from the terrible vision, appears always the most painful, in the thought, we would say, of how small a number these sufferers were reduced. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="27">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13637" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13679">Renzo had already walked a considerable way through this desolation, when he heard proceeding from a street along which he must shortly bend his course, a confused noise, in the midst of which might be distinguished the customary ringing of little bells. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="28">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13680" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13778">Having arrived at the corner of this street, which was one of the widest in the city, he saw four carts standing in the middle of the way; and the movement about these carts was such as is seen in a grain-market, where there is a coming and going of men, a loading and unloading of sacks. Here were Monatti entering houses, Monatti issuing out again, laden with burdens which they placed in the carts. Some were clothed in their red apparel, others were without any distinctive mark; a still greater number with a mark still more hideous than their uniform—feathers and ribbons of various colours, which these wretches wore in the midst of the general mourning, as a sign of mirth. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13779" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13808">Now from one window, now from another, issued the dismal cry of "Here, Monatti!" and from the fearful stir proceeded a still more dreadful cry of "Here I am! here I am!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13809" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13825">Or you heard the dwellers of the houses conjure the Monatti to make haste, and the Monatti reply with curses. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="29">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13826" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13870">Having entered the street, Renzo lengthened his strides, and determined to avoid as much as possible this disgusting spectacle. His glance, however, fell upon an object of peculiar compassion, and he paused to contemplate it, almost without intending to do so. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13871" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13927">There descended from one of these houses, and approached the melancholy train, a lady, whose appearance announced her early youth to be already past, but in her features might be traced a singular beauty, veiled and clouded, although not destroyed, by deep grief and the languor of death; in short, that soft and, at the same time, majestic beauty which belongs to the Lombard blood. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13928" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13968">She walked with difficulty, yet her step was firm; her eyes shed no tears, yet you saw that they had wept much; there was in her grief a certain tranquillity and depth which announced a soul entirely absorbed in its affliction. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="30">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13969" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13997">But it was not alone her appearance, which in the midst of so much misery made her a peculiar object of compassion, and revived this sentiment which had so long been dormant in the human heart. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13998" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14037">She bore in her arms a little girl of about nine years old, but she was dead. Her hair was parted over her cold forehead; she was arrayed in a robe of the purest white, as if adorned by her mother's hands for some festival which had long been promised, but which was now about to be celebrated. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14038" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14115">The lady held her upright on one arm; the child's bosom reposed upon hers; you would have said she still lived, had not a small hand, as white as wax, hung with an inanimate weight, and her head reposed upon the shoulder of her mother with an *abandon* stronger than that of sleep. Yes, truly, this was the mother! Even should the striking resemblance of these two countenances have failed to evince the fact, the expression depicted upon the living one would clearly have pronounced them mother and child. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="31">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14116" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14134">A horrible Monatto hastened to remove the little girl from her arm, betraying, however, an unusual respect, an involuntary hesitation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14135" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14179">But the lady, drawing herself back, without exhibiting either anger or scorn, said, "No, do not touch her; I must place her on the car myself; here, take this;" and, opening her hand, she shewed the Monatto a purse, which she then dropped into his hand. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14180" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14202">"Promise me," she resumed, "not to touch a hair of her head, nor to allow any one else to do so, and to inter her just as she is." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="32">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14203" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14243">The Monatto placed a hand upon his heart; and then, all eagerness, and almost with an obsequious manner, influenced more by the new sentiment which subdued him than by the unexpected reward, he busied himself in making room in his cart for this little corpse. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14244" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14276">The mother imprinted a kiss upon the child's forehead, placed her in the cart as though upon a bed, arranged her there, spread over her a white cloth, and addressed these last words to her: "Adieu, Cecilia! repose in peace! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14277" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14284">This evening we shall meet again, never more to be separated. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14285" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14296">Till then pray for us; for I will pray for thee and for the others." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14297" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14318">Then, turning towards the Monatto, she said, "When you pass here towards evening, you will come and fetch me—I shall not be alone." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="33">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14319" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14345">Having said this, she returned into the house, and in a moment after appeared at a window, bearing a still younger child in her arms; the child lived, but there were signs of death in its countenance. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14346" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14366">She remained contemplating the unworthy obsequies of the poor Cecilia, until she could no longer discern the cart; and then disappeared. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14367" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14410">And now what remained for her but to place her only remaining child upon the bed, and, lying down by its side, die with it; as the flower which proudly raises its head falls with the tender bud, under the sickle which levels all the grass of the field. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="34">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14411" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14429">"O Lord!" exclaimed Renzo, "save her! take her to thyself, her, and that poor little creature! They have suffered enough! they have suffered enough!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="35">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14430" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14484">Having recovered from this extraordinary emotion, and whilst he was endeavouring to recollect the directions which had been given him, he heard another and very different noise, a confused sound of imperious cries, of hoarse lamentations, a weeping of women, a screaming of children. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="36">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14485" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14495">Renzo pursued his way, his heart filled with its customary sad and obscure expectation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14496" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14514">When he arrived at the corner of the street, he perceived a confused multitude advancing, and he paused to let it pass. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14515" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14604">These were sick people who were being conducted to the lazaretto; some, forcibly driven forward, resisted in vain, and cried in vain that they wished to die upon their own beds, replying with useless imprecations to the curses or commands of the Monatti who conducted them; others pursued their way in silence, without exhibiting grief or any other sentiment, like people who had lost their senses. There were women with infants in their arms, and young children, who, more terrified by these cries, by these commands, and by this company, than even by the prospect of death, implored permission to return to their mothers, to their homes. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14605" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14648">And, alas! perhaps the very mother whom they fancied they had left sleeping soundly had only flung herself on her bed, suddenly seized with the plague, and would lie there deprived of all consciousness, until a cart should carry her away to the lazaretto or to the grave, if the cart should arrive somewhat later. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14649" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14682">Or perhaps a misfortune worthy of still more bitter tears! perhaps the mother wholly occupied with her sufferings has forgotten every thing, even her children, and has now only one thought—the desire to die in peace. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14683" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14755">However, in the midst of all this confusion, you might still see some examples of firmness and pity: there were fathers, mothers, brothers, daughters, husbands and wives, who sustained their beloved ones, and accompanied them on their way, soothing them with words of consolation; but it was not alone the adults who exhibited these virtues; little boys and girls guided the steps of their weaker brothers and sisters, and with the judgment and compassion belonging to a more advanced age counselled them to be obedient, and assured them that they were going to a place where all means would be employed for their recovery. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="37">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14756" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14778">In the midst of the melancholy excited by such objects, our traveller was seized with a more lively solicitude, and one which touched him more nearly. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14779" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14819">The mansion which he sought must be close at hand, and if among these people — But the whole train having passed, and his doubt being set at rest, he turned towards a Monatto who followed, and inquired for the street, and for the house of Don Ferrante. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="38">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14820" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14827">"Curse thee, thou fool!" was the reply which he received. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="39">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14828" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14866">He did not trouble himself to reply; but perceiving a few paces off a commissary who brought up the train, and who had a somewhat more Christian face, he asked of him the same question. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14867" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14886">The comcommissary, pointing with his staff in the direction whence he came, said, "the first street to the right, the last great house on the left." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="40">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14887" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14901">With a fresh anxiety in his heart, our youth proceeded in this direction. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14902" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14949">Now arrived in the street, he distinguished the mansion from among the other houses, which were meaner in appearance; he drew near the portal, which was closed, took hold of the knocker, and paused a moment in the greatest state of suspense. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14950" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14958">At length, however, he summoned courage and boldly knocked. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="41">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14959" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14986">After a few moments a window opened a little, and a woman shewed herself and looked down to see who this might be, with a gloomy face which seemed to say, Are these Monatti vagabonds, commissaries, anointers, devils? </note>
        </p>
        <p n="42">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14987" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15012">"Signora," said Renzo looking up, and with no very assured voice, "is there here in service a young country girl of the name of Lucia?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="43">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15013" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15024">"She is no longer here; go along with you," returned the woman, preparing to reclose the window. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="44">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15025" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15028">"Only one moment for the love of God! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15029" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15032">She is no longer here? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15033" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15033">Where is she?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="45">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15034" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15040">"In the lazaretto;" and she was again about to close the window. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="46">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15041" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15047">"Only one moment, for the love of heaven! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15048" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15050">With the plague?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="47">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15051" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15055">"Yes, is that anything new?—eh? go your ways." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="48">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15056" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15058">"Oh, unfortunate that I am! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15059" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15062">Wait, was she very sick? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15063" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15065">How long is it since——?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15066" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15072">But this time the window had been closed in reality. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="49">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15073" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15085">"Signora! Signora! one word for charity's sake! for love of your dead! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15086" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15092">I ask nothing that belongs to you; ah, me!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15093" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15098">But it was like talking to the wall. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15099" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15130">Afflicted by this intelligence, and irritated at this retreat, Renzo seized the knocker again, and thus standing close to the door, again raised it to give a violent knock, when he paused and held it suspended. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15131" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15156">In his agitation he turned round to see whether there were any neighbours from whom he might obtain more precise information, some explanation, some light upon the subject. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15157" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15243">But the only person he saw was another woman at the distance of about twenty paces. But she, with a countenance expressive of terror, hatred, impatience, and malice, with eyes which both sought to observe him and to gaze into the distance—opening her mouth as though to cry with all her might, yet restraining her breath, raising her two lean arms, and stretching forth her wrinkled talon-like hands as though to catch something, seemed desirous to call people to her without her intention being observed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15244" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15257">When Renzo's glance fell upon her, she became still more hideous, and trembled like some one surprised in an evil deed. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="50">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15258" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15293">"What the devil — ?" began Renzo, in his turn raising his arm towards the woman; but she having lost all hope that he would be seized upon unawares, let the cry which she had until then suppressed escape her: "the anointer! fall upon him! fall upon him! fall upon him! fall upon the anointer!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="51">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15294" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15313">"Who? I! ah, lying sorceress! be silent!" shouted Renzo, and sprang towards her at once to frighten and silence her. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15314" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15325">But he soon found that there was more need to think of his own safety. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15326" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15363">At the screams of this woman people rushed from all sides; certainly not in such crowds as some months before would have been seen upon a similar occasion; but more than sufficient to overpower a poor man. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15364" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15403">At the same time the window again opened, and the unpolite woman shewed herself and screamed, "Seize him! seize him! He must be one of the rogues who wander about anointing worthy people's doors." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="52">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15404" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15442">Renzo did not pause to reflect: it seemed to him much the best to escape from them, instead of waiting there to argue; therefore he glanced to the right and left to see where were the fewest people, and then scampered off. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15443" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15490">He repulsed with a blow one man who opposed his passage; with a heavy blow of his fist struck back another who ran to meet him; and thus away he rushed, with a clenched fist raised in the air, ready to assail any one who came in his way. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15491" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15514">The road before him was clear, but behind was heard the sound of feet, and still louder than the noise of footsteps, the savage cry of, "Upon him! upon him! seize the anointer!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15515" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15528">He knew not when he should be able to pause, or where he should find a place of safety. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15529" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15592">His anger became madness, his agony despair; his sight became obscured, he placed his hand upon his knife, drew it, paused, turned round, his countenance more grim and fierce than it had ever been before, and with his arms stretched out, brandishing the glittering blade, he cried, "Come on, such as have courage! Come on, ye rascals! I will anoint you truly with this." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="53">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15593" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15640">But he saw with astonishment, and with a confused sentiment of pleasure, that his persecutors had already paused at some distance, and stood there continuing to shout, and make with their hands certain mad gestures in the air, as if to attract the attention of people who were far behind him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15641" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15700">He again turned round and saw a sight which his agitation had not before allowed him to see—a cart which advanced towards him—nay, a whole train of funeral cars with their usual attendants; and behind this train, at some distance, another crowd of people who also longed to fall upon the anointer, and thus inclose him on all sides; but they were also restrained by the same impediment. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15701" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15759">Seeing himself as it were between two fires, it suddenly occurred to him that what to others was an object of terror, might be for him a means of salvation; he thought that this was no time in which to be over nice, so, replacing his knife, he ran on towards the carts, passed the first, and perceived a good space unoccupied in the second. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15760" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15780">He formed his resolve, gave a spring, and is up in the cart, standing on the right foot, the left high in the air, and his arms raised above his head. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="54">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15781" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15818">"Well done, well done!" exclaimed in one voice the Monatti, some of whom followed the convoy on foot, whilst others were seated upon the carts, or—to describe the horrible scene as it really was—even upon the corpses themselves, drinking out of a large flask which they passed round. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15819" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15821">"Well done, a good hit!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="55">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15822" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15846">"Thou art come to place thyself under the protection of the Monatti; believe thou art as safe as in a church," said one of the two Monatti who stood in the cart into which Renzo had mounted. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="56">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15847" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15867">His enemies, upon the approach of the train, had for the most part turned their backs and taken to their heels, never ceasing to cry, "Fall upon him, fall upon him, the anointer!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15868" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15897">Some withdrew more slowly, and would every now and then turn round with savage countenances and menacing gestures towards Renzo, who, from his cart, answered them by agitating his clenched fist in the air. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="57">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15898" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15939">"Only leave me to manage," said a Monatto to Renzo, and suddenly tearing from a corpse a dirty rag, he knotted it up in haste, and taking it by one corner, raised it like a sling, and appeared about to fling it among the obstinate crowd, crying all the time, "Wait, rascals!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15940" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15964">At this gesture, all fled seized with horror; and Renzo only saw the retreating backs of his enemies, and their heels, which were rapidly raised in the air. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="58">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15965" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15985">Among the Monatti there arose a howl of triumph, a long and noisy burst of laughter. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="59">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15986" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16009">"Ah, ah! see whether we know how to protect honest men!" observed a Monatto to Renzo: "one of us is worth a hundred of those poltroons." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="60">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16010" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16026">"Certainly, I can say that I owe my life to you," replied Renzo; "and I thank you with all my heart." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="61">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16027" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16042">"For what?" asked the Monatto; "thou deservest it; one can see that thou art a brave youth. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16043" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16081">Thou dost well to anoint this rabble; anoint them, extirpate them, for they are good for nothing, except when they are dead, they curse us for the life we lead, and say that, the plague once at an end, they will have us hanged. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16082" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16104">They will all be at an end before the plague, however; and the Monatti will be left to sing for victory, and make merry in Milan." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="62">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16105" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16150">"Long live the plague, and perish the mob!" exclaimed another; and proposing this beautiful toast, he applied the flask to his mouth, and holding it fast to his lips, spite of the jolting of the cart, he took a long draught, and then passed it on to Renzo, saying, "Drink our health." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="63">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16151" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16173">"I wish it you with all my heart," returned Renzo, "but I am not thirsty; I have no great desire to drink just at the present moment." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="64">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16174" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16198">"Thou hast had a good fright, it seems to me," said the Monatto; "thou hast the air of a peaceful man; thou shouldest have another air to play the anointer with." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="65">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16199" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16204">"Every one does as well as he can," remarked the other. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="66">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16205" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16249">"Give me to drink," said one of those who followed on foot beside the cart, "for I also wish to drink to the health of this good master, who finds himself in such good company — there, there, in this beautiful carriage." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="67">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16250" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16269">And, with an atrocious and horrible laugh, he pointed to the cart which preceded the one in which poor Renzo stood. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16270" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16305">Then composing his countenance to a gravity even yet more grim and felonious, he made a low reverence towards the cart, and continued, "Do you permit, my dear master, a poor wretch of a Monatto to taste of your cellar? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16306" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16322">You see very well what manner of life we lead; we are those who have placed you in your carriage to conduct you to the country. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16323" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16340">Besides, wine soon makes your lordships ill; the poor Monatti have good stomachs." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="68">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n189" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16341" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16400">And amidst the laughter of his companions, he took the flask and raised it to his lips; but before drinking he turned towards Renzo, and fixing his eyes upon him, said, with a certain insulting compassion, "The devil, with whom thou hast made thy compact, must needs be very young—for, if we had not been here to save thee, he would have assisted thee finely." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n190" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16401" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16412">And then, amidst a fresh burst of laughter, he applied the bottle to his lips. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="69">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n191" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16413" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16424">" And we—and we!" shouted more voices from the cart which preceded our hero. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n192" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16425" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16477">This scoundrel, after drinking as much as he chose, handed with both hands the large flask to his friends, who passed it from one to another, until one of them having emptied it, whirling it in the air several times, flung it upon the pavement, shouting, "Long live the plague!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n193" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16478" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16497">After these words he began singing one of their infamous songs; and immediately he was accompanied by the voices of the whole horrible chorus. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n194" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16498" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16533">This infernal chanting, mingling with the ringing of the little bells, the sound of the wheels, and the tramp of the horses, resounded in the silent void of the streets, and echoed in the houses, painfully depressing the hearts of the few remaining inhabitants. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="70">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n195" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16534" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16550">But may not sometimes even a disagreeable circumstance turn out to your advantage? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n196" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16551" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16591">The danger which Renzo had been in a moment before had rendered the company of these living and these dead more than tolerable; and now this music was almost agreeable to him, relieving him as it did from the annoyance of such a horrible conversation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n197" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16592" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16663">Still very much troubled and excited, he, in his heart, returned thanks to Providence for having escaped out of this misfortune without having suffered any injury himself, or having himself injured any one; and he prayed that Providence would now assist him in liberating himself from his liberators. He was all alert, watching the Monatti, noticing the streets, so as to choose his time and quietly descend without giving them occasion to make any noise, any scene which might excite the attention of passers-by. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="71">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n198" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16664" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16682">All at once, upon turning a corner, he seemed to recognise the place; he looked about him more attentively, and felt sure that he was right. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n199" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16683" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16684">Do you know where he was? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n200" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16685" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16706">He was near the Eastern-gate, in that very street along which twenty months before he had walked so leisurely when entering Milan, and down which he had fled so quickly when departing. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n201" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16707" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16741">It directly occurred to him that this street led to the lazaretto, and his having been conducted to this very street without any exertion of his own, he considered an especial act of Providence, and regarded it as a good omen. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n202" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16742" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16777">Just at this point a commissary came towards the train of carts, shouting with all his might to the Monatti to stop. The train paused as it was commanded, and the song changed itself into a noisy dialogue. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n203" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16778" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16806">One of the Monatti who were in the cart with Renzo jumped to the ground; and Renzo, saying to the other, "I thank you for your charity; God will reward you for it," jumped down also. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="72">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n204" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16807" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16819">"Go, go along with thee, poor wretch of an anointer," replied the Monatto; "thou art not the one who will destroy Milan." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="73">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n205" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16820" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16826">Fortunately there happened to be no one near who heard what was said. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n206" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16827" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16898">The train had halted to the left of the road. Renzo quickly bent his steps in the opposite direction, and hastily hurried on to the bridge; having crossed it, he soon recognised the Capuchin convent, approached the gate, saw an angle of the lazaretto, passed through the outer fence, and then the exterior of this miserable enclosure lay before him. This scene gave scarcely any idea of the misery contained within the walls, nevertheless it was a scene, vast, various, and almost impossible to describe. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n207" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16899" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16966">Along the two walls which from this point presented themselves to the eye of the spectator, was one continual stir; companies of sick people were being conducted to the lazaretto; others were seen seated or lying upon the banks of the deep ditch which surrounded the building: their strength had either proved insufficient to carry them within the asylum, or else issuing forth in despair, they had found themselves too weak to proceed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n208" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16967" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_17020">Other poor wretches wandered about like idiots, and not a few were raving mad; one stood all animated, relating his imaginations to another unfortunate who lay on the earth, oppressed with the disease; another was furious; another looked around with a joyous countenance, as though he were present at some merry spectacle. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n209" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_17021" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_17113">In the midst of this sad gaiety was heard a loud and continuous singing; the sound did not appear to proceed from this miserable crowd, and yet it was heard above all the other voices. It was a popular love song, gay and jocular, one of that class called by the Milanese villanelle. And had you, directed by the sound, cast your glance around, in order to discover who this could be who, in such a time and in such a place, was thus merry, you would have seen a poor wretch seated quietly in the bottom of the ditch, singing as loud as he could, and gazing into the sky. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="74">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n210" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_17114" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_17141">Renzo had scarcely taken a few steps along the southern wall of the edifice before he heard an extraordinary noise among the multitude, and voices in the distance crying, "Take care, catch him!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n211" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_17142" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_17212">Renzo stood on tip-toe, and saw a singular steed galloping away, mounted by a still more singular rider. It was one of these madmen, who having seen this beast free and without any guard, standing near a cart, had mounted him in haste, without any saddle, and hammering his neck with his fist, and making spurs of his heels, dashed madly forward; Monatti followed behind, shouting with all their might; and all was enveloped in a cloud of dust which hurried along. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="75">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n212" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_17213" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_17252">Thus, already confounded and wearied by all these sights of misery, our hero reached the gate of that building which enclosed within its walls perhaps more wretchedness assembled in one spot than he had met with throughout all the track he had traversed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap34-n213" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_17253" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_17269">He passed through the portal, and remained a moment motionless under the portico. </note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>