<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CHAPTER XXXVI.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>1845</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed Lovers: a Milanese Story of the Seventeenth Century. With The Column of Infamy by Alessandro Manzoni. In Three Volumes</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
          <date>1845</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Henry Francis C. Logan</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="English_1845_cap36">
        <p n="1">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10035">Who could have told Renzo, a few hours previously, that in the very midst of such a quest, at the commencement of the most dubious and decisive moment, his heart would have been divided between Lucia and Don Rodrigo? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10036" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10110">Yet so it was: this pale countenance mingled itself with all the dear and terrible images which hope or fear alternately presented to his mind during his short walk; the words heard at the foot of that bed were heard in the midst of the painful uncertainty which filled his soul. He was unable to terminate a prayer for the happy issue of his great enterprise without completing the one which he had commenced at the foot of Don Rodrigo's couch, and which the tolling of the bell had interrupted. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="2">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10111" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10205">The octangular chapel which arose, elevated upon a low flight of steps in the centre of the lazaretto, was, in its primitive form, open on all sides, without any other support than the pilasters and columns—an openwork fabric, if one may be allowed the expression; each side was composed of an arch between two intercolumniations. Within, surrounding what might properly be termed the church, ran another portico, composed of eight arches, which corresponded with the outer ones; above these arches rose a cupola; thus, the altar which was erected in the centre, might be seen from every window of the lazaretto, and from every part of the enclosure. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10206" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10230">This edifice being now converted to quite a different use, the openings have been walled up; but the ancient framework remaining untouched, clearly indicates its former state and destination. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="3">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10231" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10280">Renzo had scarcely arrived when he saw the Father Felice appear in the portico of the chapel, and place himself in the archway which looked towards the city, and before which the company had assembled in the plain; and by the Father's attitude, Renzo perceived that he had already begun to preach. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10281" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10294">He hastened to place himself behind the auditory, as had been suggested to him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10295" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10320">He quietly paused, and hastily ran his eye over the assembly; but from where he stood he could only see a crowd, one might almost say a pavement of heads. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10321" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10360">In the midst were seen a number of heads covered with handkerchiefs or veils, and in this direction he gazed most attentively; but not succeeding in discovering anything more, he raised his eyes towards the same object which attracted the eyes of the whole assembly. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="4">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10361" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10388">Renzo was touched and filled with awe at the venerable preacher's aspect; and he listened to this portion of his solemn address with as much attention as remained to him in such a moment of expectation. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="5">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10389" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10458">"Let us give one thought to the thousands who have gone forth through yonder gate;" and he, raising his finger, indicated over his shoulder the gate which led to the cemetery of San Gregorio, which might then be called an immense grave. "Let us cast one glance upon the thousands who still remain here, uncertain by which gate they shall issue forth: let us cast one glance upon ourselves, this small number who are saved. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10459" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10461">Bless the Lord. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10462" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10483">Bless Him for His justice! Bless Him for His mercy! Bless Him for death! Bless Him for health! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10484" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10554">Bless Him for the choice which He has made of us! Oh my children, wherefore should this have been, but to preserve for Himself a chosen people, corrected by affliction and animated with gratitude? That we, now feeling more keenly that life is His gift, should regard it with that esteem which, as a gift from Him, it deserves, and that we should employ it in such a manner as may be acceptable to Him. That the memory of our own sufferings may render us compassionate and full of love towards others who suffer. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10555" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10610">That those in company with whom we have suffered, hoped and feared; among whom we leave friends and relatives, and who in short are our brethren; that these, I say, when they see us depart from among them, whilst perhaps receiving some consolation in the thought that some few leave this place restored, may at the same time be edified by our behaviour. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10611" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10635">God does not wish that they should observe in us a noisy joy, a worldly joy, in having escaped this death, this death against which they still wrestle. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10636" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10663">Let them see that we depart, returning thanks for ourselves, and praying for them, and may be able to say, 'Even when our friends are far from us, they will remember us, and pray for us poor wretches.' </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10664" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10679">Let us commence with this short journey, with the first steps we are about to take, a life full of charity. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10680" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10713">Let those who have recovered their former vigour lend a brotherly arm to the weak; youths sustain your elders; you who remain childless, look around and behold how many children are left without parents—become parents to them! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10714" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10725">And this charity covering your sins, will also soften your griefs. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="6">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10726" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10767">Here a dull murmur of groans and sobs, which had continued to increase among the audience, was suddenly suspended, upon the preacher's placing a rope round his neck and falling upon his knees: all remained in the most profound silence, awaiting the words he should speak. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="7">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10768" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10805">"For myself," said he, "and for all my companions, who, without any merit of our own, have been chosen to the high duty of serving Christ in you; I humbly demand pardon, if we have not worthily fulfilled so high a mission. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10806" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10887">If the indolence of the flesh should have rendered us less attentive to your necessities, less ready at your call; if any unjust impatience, any culpable weariness, should have caused us to appear sometimes before you with a wearied or severe countenance; if, at any time, the miserable thought that you stood in need of us, should have led us not to treat you with becoming humility; if our frailty should have caused us to commit any action which has given you pain, pardon us! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10888" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10898">God pardon in the same manner your transgressions, and bless you!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10899" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10907">Saying this, he made the sign of the cross above the audience, and then arose. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="8">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10908" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10939">We have been able to report, if not the precise words, at least the sense of what he said; but the manner with which these words were uttered, is not a thing to be described. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10940" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10979">It was the manner of a man who pronounced it a privilege to serve the sick, because he really considered it as such; who confessed he had not worthily fulfilled his mission, because he truly believed he had not worthily fulfilled it; who besought pardon, because he was fully persuaded he stood in need of it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10980" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11034">Only imagine then with what sobs, what tears, the people replied to these words, they who had seen around them these Capuchins alone occupied in attending upon them; who had seen so many of them perish; and who had seen this man who spoke in the name of all, ever the first in exertion as well as in authority, except when at the point of death himself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11035" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11077">The excellent Friar then took a large cross, which was leaning against a pillar, raised it before them, left his sandals in the outer portico, descended the steps, and moving through the crowd, who respectfully made way for him, placed himself at the head. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="9">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11078" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11160">Renzo, in tears, neither more nor less than if he had been one of those from whom this singular pardon had been asked, also retired and placed himself at one side of a hut. There he waited, half concealed, his head thrust forward, his eyes wide open, his heart palpitating violently, yet at the same time filled with a peculiar faith, given rise to, I believe, by the tenderness which the sermon had called forth in him, and by the spectacle of the general emotion. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="10">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11161" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11236">And now arrived the Father Felice, barefoot and with this rope round his neck, with this high and heavy cross raised on high; his was a pale and thin countenance, one which at once breathed compunction and courage; he moved along with a slow, but resolute step, like one who alone thinks of sparing the weakness of others; and in every thing he had the appearance of a man upon whom fatigue and pain have conferred the strength necessary for the performance of his arduous duty. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11237" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11256">Immediately after him followed the elder children, most of them barefoot, very few of them entirely clothed; a few even in their shirts. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11257" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11306">Then came the women; almost all of them conducting by the hand a little child, and singing alternately the *Miserere*; the weak sound of their voices, the paleness and the languor of their countenances, were things which would have filled with compassion the soul of a simple spectator. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11307" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11332">But Renzo looked, examined every group, every countenance, without passing a single one over; for the procession proceeded very slowly, so as to accommodate every one. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11333" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11363">They passed and passed, and he looked and looked, but it was all in vain; he cast glances towards the line which had not yet come up; there were but very few remaining; now the very last has arrived; they are all passed! they were all unknown countenances! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11364" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11387">With his arms dangling by his sides, with his head inclining over one shoulder, he accompanied this multitude with his eyes, whilst the train of men passed before him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11388" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11415">His attention was again excited, a new hope sprang up within him, when he perceived that after the men appeared certain carts, in which were placed those who were not yet in a condition to walk. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11416" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11437">Here the women were the last; the train passed so slowly that he was enabled equally well to examine all the countenances without missing a single one. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11438" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11482">But what happened? He examined the first cart, the second, the third, and, in fact, all with the same result, until the very last arrived, behind which walked, as regulator of the convoy, another Capuchin with a severe air, and a staff in his hand. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11483" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11499">This was Father Michele, whom we have already mentioned as the companion of the Governor Father Felice. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="11">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11500" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11529">Thus then had vanished this dear hope; and in vanishing, had not alone carried away the consolation which it had brought him, but, as often happens, left him in a more deplorable case than before. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11530" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11542">Now the very best thing he could hope for was to discover Lucia sick. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11543" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11580">Nevertheless, uniting to the ardour of a present hope something of his fear, which had just been increased, he attached himself with all the powers of his soul to this melancholy and weak thread; he entered the road, and hastened in the direction from whence the procession had come. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11581" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11645">When he had arrived at the foot of the chapel, he knelt down upon the lowest step, and offered up a prayer to God, or rather a confusion of incoherent words, of interrupted phrases, of exclamations, of entreaties, of lamentations, of promises; one of those discourses which are never held with men, because men have neither sufficient penetration to understand, nor patience to hear them; neither are men sufficiently great to feel compassion for the petitioners, unmingled with contempt. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="12">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11646" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11703">He arose encouraged; he walked round the chapel, found himself in the other road, which he had not yet seen, and which led to the other gate. After taking a few steps, he saw the enclosure of stakes which the friar had mentioned to him, and which was broken here and there as his informer had told him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11704" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11753">Almost at the first step he took he saw lying upon the ground a little bell, such as the Monatti were accustomed to wear upon one foot: it occurred to Renzo that this little instrument might serve him as a passport; he took it, looked around to see whether any one observed him, and fastened it upon his foot. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11754" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11839">He now began his search, a search which would have been terribly laborious, even from the multitude of objects, had the objects been of quite another class. He contemplated fresh scenes of misery, in some respects similar to the misery he had before witnessed; in other respects different: for, afflicted by the same calamity, there was here quite a different suffering, so to say, quite another languor, another lamentation, another mode of supporting pain, and of pitying and succouring each other by turns. These scenes excited in the mind of the spectator quite another compassion—quite another horror. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="13">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11840" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11866">He had already proceeded, I do not know how far, fruitlessly, yet without meeting with any accident, when he suddenly heard behind him an "Oh!" a cry which appeared to be addressed to him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11867" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11899">He turned, and saw at a certain distance a commissary, who, raising one hand, signed to him and shouted, "There, in that chamber, they have need of help: here, they have quite finished cleaning." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="14">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11900" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11948">Renzo immediately perceived that he had been taken for a Monatto, and that the bell had caused the mistake. He called himself a fool for having only reflected upon the embarrassments which this distinctive mark would enable him to escape, and not upon those which it was likely to draw upon him; but at the same time he considered how he could immediately free himself from this man. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11949" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11980">Renzo returned a sign with his head, as if giving him to understand that he had heard and would obey; and then immediately, to escape out of sight, hastened among the huts. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="15">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11981" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12018">When it appeared to Renzo that the man was far enough away, he thought of delivering himself from the cause of his annoyance, and wishing to perform this little operation without being observed, he placed himself in a small open space between two huts, which, if we may be allowed the expression, turned their backs upon each other. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12019" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12048">He bent down to remove the bell, and bending with his head thus leaning against the straw wall of one of these huts, there reached his ear a voice — oh, heaven! is it possible? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12049" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12064">All his soul is in his ears: his breathing is suspended — Yes, yes! it is her voice! </note>
        </p>
        <p n="16">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12065" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12078">"For fear of what?" said this gentle voice: "We have passed through something far worse than a tempest. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12079" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12087">He who has watched over us until now, will watch over us henceforth." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="17">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12088" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12106">If Renzo did not send forth a cry, it was not from fear of being discovered, but because he wanted breath. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12107" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12149">His knees failed him, his sight became troubled; but this was only the first moment; a moment after, and he was standing upright, brisker, more vigorous than ever; in three springs he was at the entrance of the cabin, he saw the one who had spoken, he saw her risen and stooping over a bed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12150" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12168">She turned round at the noise; looked—believed she deceived herself, that it was a dream—look again more attentively—and cried, "Oh! blessed God!" "Lucia! </note>
        </p>
        <p n="18">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12169" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12183">I have found you! I have found you! It is really you! You are alive!" exclaimed Renzo, advancing, and trembling violently. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="19">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12184" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12200">"Oh, blessed Lord!" replied Lucia, who trembled yet more violently: "You? what is all this? in what manner? why? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12201" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12202">The plague!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12203" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12204">"I have had it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12205" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12206">And you—?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12207" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12208">"Ah!—I also have had it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12209" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12212">And my mother—?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12213" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12224">"I have not seen her because she was at Pasturo; I believe, however, that she is well. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12225" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12233">But you—How pale you are still! How weak you appear! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12234" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12237">But you are cured, are you not? you are cured?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12238" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12244">"The Lord has thought fit to leave me here below. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12245" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12250">Ah, Renzo, why are you here?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12251" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12259">"Why?" said Renzo, approaching still nearer; "you ask me why? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12260" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12263">Why should I come? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12264" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12269">Is there any need that I should tell you? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12270" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12275">Who is there for me to think about? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12276" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12281">Am I no longer called Renzo? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12282" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12286">Are you no longer Lucia?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12287" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12291">"Ah, what do you say; what do you say? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12292" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12298">Has not my mother written to you that—?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12299" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12304">"Yes; she has only written too much to me. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12305" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12326">Fine things, certainly, to have written to a poor unfortunate, overwhelmed with trouble, and a fugitive; to a young man, I say, who has never done anything to offend you." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12327" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12334">"But Renzo, Renzo; since you knew—why did you come? why did you?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12335" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12336">"Why did I come? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12337" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12342">Oh, Lucia, why did I come, you ask me? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12343" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12345">After so many promises. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12346" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12353">Are we no longer ourselves? do you no longer recollect? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12354" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12357">What is then wanting to us?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12358" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12381">"O, Lord!" exclaimed Lucia, sadly, joining her hands, and raising her eyes towards heaven; "wherefore hast thou not mercifully taken me to thyself—! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12382" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12386">O, Renzo! what have you done? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12387" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12405">Only see; I began to hope that—with time—I should have forgotten—" "A fine hope! fine things to say to one's very face!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12406" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12408">"Ah, what have you done? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12409" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12428">And in this place! In the midst of so much misery; in the midst of such spectacles! Here, where there is nothing but death, you have been able——!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="20">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12429" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12460">"Those who die must pray to God for themselves, and hope that they shall go to a better world; but it is not just on that account that those who live should live in despair——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="21">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12461" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12470">"But Renzo, Renzo, you do not think of what you are saying. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12471" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12474">A promise to the Madonna! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12475" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12476">A vow." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="22">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12477" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12487">"And I tell you that there are promises which count for nothing." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="23">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12488" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12489">"Oh, God! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12490" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12491">What is it you say? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12492" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12497">Where have you been all this time? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12498" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12501">With whom have you had intercourse? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12502" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12503">What do you mean?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="24">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12504" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12525">"I speak as a good Christian; and it is I who have a better opinion of the Madonna than you; for I do not believe that she would desire promises which would injure any human being. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12526" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12532">If the Madonna had spoken herself, oh, then it would have been otherwise. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12533" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12538">But how did it happen? it was merely one of your ideas. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12539" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12544">Do you know what you ought to promise the Madonna? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12545" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12585">You ought to promise that the first daughter we have shall be called Maria, for I am ready myself to promise this; these are things which do the Madonna far more honour; these are acts of devotion which are much more sensible, and injure no one." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="25">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12586" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12616">"No, no; do not speak thus: you do not know what you say. You do not know what it is to make a vow; you have not been placed in such circumstances; you have not experienced what I have. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12617" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12622">Go, go, for the love of heaven!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12623" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12632">And saying this she hastily drew back, and turned towards the bed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12633" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12650">"Lucia!" said Renzo, without moving, "tell me, at least tell me, whether if there were not this reason — you would be the same to me as ever?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="26">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12651" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12683">"Heartless man," returned Lucia, turning round, and with difficulty restraining her tears; "when you will have made me say useless words, words which will pain me, words which may perhaps be sinful, shall you then be satisfied? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12684" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12695">Leave me, oh! leave me. Forget me; it is evident that we were not destined for each other. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12696" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12708">We shall meet again above. I have not long to remain in this world. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12709" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12775">Go; seek to inform my mother that I have recovered; that even here God has succoured me; that I have found a good soul, this excellent woman, who is as a mother to me; tell her that I hope she will be preserved from this evil, and that we shall see each other again, when and how God pleases — Go, for the love of heaven, and only think of me when you pray to the Lord." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="27">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12776" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12809">And, like one who has nothing more to say, and will neither hear anything more; like one who would escape some danger, she retired still closer to the bed, in which lay the woman of whom she had spoken. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="28">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12810" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12819">"Listen, Lucia, listen!" said Renzo, without, however, approaching her. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="29">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12820" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12824">"No, no; leave me for charity." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="30">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12825" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12828">"Listen; the Father Cristoforo ——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="31">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12829" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12829">"Who?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="32">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12830" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12831">"Is here." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="33">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12832" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12833">"Here? where? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12834" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12836">How do you know this?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="34">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12837" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12863">"I have spoken with him but just now. I was a little while with him; and a religious man of his description, it seems to me ——" "He is here!—it will be to assist the sick, most certainly. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12864" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12869">But he? Has he had the plague?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="35">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12870" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12913">"Oh, Lucia! I fear, I fear only too much——" And whilst Renzo hesitated pronouncing these words which were so full of sorrow for himself, and would be so to Lucia, she had again come forward from the bed and drew near him: "I fear that he now has it!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="37">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12914" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12916">"Oh, the unfortunate, good man! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12917" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12920">But what did he say? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12921" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12928">Alas! how is he? is he in bed? is he attended?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="38">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12929" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12945">"He is up, and active, attending upon others. But if you only saw him, saw his colour—how he carries himself! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12946" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12957">One has seen so very many—only too many alas!—that one cannot deceive oneself!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="39">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12958" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12960">"Oh! unfortunate people that we are! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12961" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12964">And he is really here?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="40">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12965" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12980">"Here, and at but a short distance; not more distant than from your house to mine—if you recollect——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="41">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12981" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12983">"Oh, holy Virgin!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="42">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12984" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12986">"Well, but little farther off. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12987" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12993">And only think whether we have talked about you! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12994" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12997">He has told me things——! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12998" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13004">And if you only knew what he has shewn me! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13005" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13022">You shall hear all; but just now I must begin by telling you what he told me first of all with his own mouth. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13023" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13061">He told me that I did well in coming to seek you, and that it pleased the Lord when a youth acted after this manner, and that the Lord would assist me in finding you; as He has, in truth, done; but really, Fra Cristoforo is a saint. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13062" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13063">Thus you see——!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="43">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13064" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13095">"But if he spoke thus, it was because he did not know that——" "What would you have him know of the things which you have done in your own mind, without any reason, or the advice of any one? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13096" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13112">An excellent man, a man of judgment, such as he is, does not think about things of that sort. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13113" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13118">Ah, but what he shewed me!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13119" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13153">And here Renzo related the visit they had paid to a certain hut. Lucia, much as her senses and her soul must have become familiarized with ideas of terror since her abode in this place, was seized with horror and compassion. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="44">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13154" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13201">"And even there," continued Renzo, "he spoke like a saint; he said that perhaps the Lord was inclined to pardon this unfortunate man—(one can call him by no other name now)—that He awaited some favourable moment; but that he wished us to pray together for him — Together! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13202" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13204">Have you understood?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="45">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13205" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13221">"Yes, yes; we will pray for him; each one in the place where the Lord shall have sent us; God will know how to unite our-prayers." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="46">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13222" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13228">"But if I were to tell you his very words——!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="47">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13229" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13233">"But, Renzo, he does not know ——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="48">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13234" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13262">"But do you not know that when a saint speaks, it is the Lord who makes him speak, and that he would not have spoken thus, if it had not been right? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13263" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13267">And then the soul of this poor unfortunate! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13268" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13288">I have sincerely prayed for him, and I will pray for him; I prayed for him from my heart, as though he had been my brother. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13289" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13316">But how do you think it will be with him in the next world, if our affair is not arranged in this world, if the evil which he has done is not repaired? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13317" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13341">If you would but listen to reason, then every thing would be as it was at first; what "has been, has been; he has done his penance here—" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="49">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13342" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13356">"No, Renzo, no. The Lord does not wish us to do evil, in order to excite His mercy. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13357" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13369">Let us leave this unfortunate to Him; our duty is to pray for him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13370" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13380">If I had died that terrible night, would not God even then have been able to pardon him? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13381" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13389">And as I did not die, as I was liberated—" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="50">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13390" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13421">"And your mother, this poor Agnese, who always has wished me so well, who desired so much to see us man and wife, did she not also say that this was a foolish idea? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13422" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13440">She, who upon other occasions has made you listen to reason, for in certain things she thinks more justly than you—" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="51">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13441" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13455">"My mother! Do you wish that my mother should counsel me to break a vow? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13456" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13461">But, Renzo, you are no longer in your right mind." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="52">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13462" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13467">"But do you wish me to say it? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13468" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13476">You women cannot understand these things. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13477" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13490">Father Cristoforo told me that I should return to him, and tell him if I succeeded in finding you. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13491" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13497">I am going to him; we will hear him; what he says—" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="53">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13498" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13518">"Yes, yes; go to this holy man; tell him that I pray for him, and beg him to pray for me, for I stand in great, very great need of his prayers! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13519" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13539">But, for the love of heaven, for the love of your own soul, for the love of mine, do not come again to make me miserable—to tempt me. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13540" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13560">Father Cristoforo will know how to explain these things to you, and bring you back to your proper senses; he will set your heart at rest." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="54">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13561" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13564">"Set my heart at rest! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13565" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13569">Oh! drive all such thoughts out of your mind. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13570" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13592">You caused these words to be "written to me; and I know what they have made me suffer; and now you have the heart to tell them to me! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13593" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13610">And I, instead, tell you clearly and simply that I will never set my heart at rest! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13611" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13622">You wish to forget me, but I do not wish to forget you. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13623" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13637">And I promise you, do you see, that if you make me lose my judgment, I shall never more recover it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13638" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13662">Do you wish to condemn me to madness the whole of my life; and I shall be mad if—And then this unfortunate man! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13663" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13687">The Lord knows whether I have pardoned him from my heart; but you—will you make me think the whole of my life, that if it had not been for him—? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13688" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13696">Lucia! you have said that I should forget you; that I should forget you! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13697" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13699">What can I do? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13700" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13715">Upon whom do you suppose I have thought all this time?—And after so many things! after so many promises! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13716" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13724">And what have I done to you, then, since we were separated? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13725" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13765">Is it because I have suffered, that you treat me thus? Is it because I have endured misfortune? because the world has persecuted me? because I have passed so much time away from home, sad, and at a distance from you? because I have come to seek you the first moment that I was able?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="55">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13766" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13794">Lucia, joining her hands, and raising her tearful eyes towards heaven, exclaimed, as soon as her violent weeping permitted her to form words, "Oh, most holy Virgin, aid thou me! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13795" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13808">Thou dost know, how since that fearful night I have never passed a moment such as this! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13809" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13814">Thou didst aid me then; thou wilt aid me now!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="56">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13815" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13857">"Yes, Lucia, you do well to invoke the Madonna; but wherefore do you believe that she who is so good, who is the Mother of Mercy, can take pleasure in making us suffer — me, at least — for one word which escaped you in a moment when you knew not what you said? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13858" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13884">Will you believe that she aided you then, in order to leave us afterwards in embarrassment? — If, then, this is only an excuse — if I am become hateful to you — tell me, — speak clearly." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="57">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n189" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13885" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13900">"For charity, Renzo, for charity, for the love of your poor dead, cease this conversation, cease; do not make me die. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n190" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13901" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13905">That would be no good moment. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n191" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13906" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13920">Go to Father Cristoforo, commend me to him, and return here no more, return here no more." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="58">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n192" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13921" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13927">"I go; but do you think that I shall return here no more! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n193" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13928" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13937">I shall return, were it at the end of the world, I shall return," and saying this he disappeared. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="59">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n194" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13938" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13961">Lucia went to seat herself, or rather she let herself sink to the earth, beside the bed; and supporting her head against the bed, she continued to weep violently. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n195" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13962" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13983">The woman, her companion, who until now had remained breathless with both her eyes and ears open, now demanded the meaning of this apparition, of this strife, and this weeping. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n196" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13984" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14005">But perhaps the reader, on his side, may demand who this woman was; and we will satisfy him in a few words. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="60">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n197" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14006" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14011">She was a rich shopkeeper, of perhaps about thirty years of age. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n198" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14012" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14092">Within a few days she had seen her husband and all her children die in their home; in a short time, the plague attacked her also, and she had been transported to the lazaretto and placed in this little hut, about the time when Lucia, after having unconsciously recovered from the fury of this disease, and after having equally unconsciously changed her companions many times, began to revive and return to herself; for she had remained insensible from the commencement of her illness, when she was still in the mansion of Don Ferrante. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n199" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14093" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14126">This hut could only contain two persons; and between these two afflicted, abandoned, terrified women, alone in this vast multitude, an intimacy, a strong affection, had quickly arisen, an affection which a long acquaintance of many years could scarcely have given rise to. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n200" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14127" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14142">In a short time Lucia was in a condition to assist her companion, who was yet very ill. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n201" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14143" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14179">But now that she also was out of danger, they mutually encouraged and watched over each other by turns; they had promised each other to leave the lazaretto together; and had concerted other plans, so that they need not even afterwards be separated. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n202" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14180" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14232">The good woman, who, having left her house, her warehouse, and her money in the care of one of her brothers who was a commissary of health, now finding herself the sole and sad mistress of much more than she required to live upon at her ease, wished to keep Lucia with her as a daughter or sister. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n203" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14233" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14263">Lucia had agreed to this, you can imagine with what gratitude both towards her and towards Providence; but only until she should receive tidings of Agnese, and learn her pleasure. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n204" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14264" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14283">But being of such a reserved disposition, she had never spoken one word regarding her betrothal, or her various extraordinary adventures. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n205" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14284" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14302">Now, however, in her violent agitation she had, at least, as much need of relieving her mind by the relation of her misfortunes, as her companion had a desire to listen to them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n206" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14303" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14329">Therefore, grasping the right hand of her friend in both hers, she immediately commenced satisfying her demands, without other interruption than that occasioned by her sobs. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="61">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n207" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14330" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14338">Renzo meanwhile hastened towards the quarter where was the good Friar. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n208" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14339" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14356">With a little attention, and not without having to retrace some of his steps, he at length succeeded in arriving there. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n209" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14357" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14386">He found the cabin, but the Friar he did not find; wandering about, and seeking for him in the neighbourhood, he at last discovered him in a tent, where, bent to the earth and almost prostrate, he was comforting a dying wretch. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n210" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14387" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14392">Renzo paused and waited in silence. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n211" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14393" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14412">Shortly after he saw him close the eyes of the dead, then place himself on his knees, pray a moment, and arise. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n212" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14413" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14419">Renzo then moved and went towards him. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="62">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n213" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14420" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14426">"Oh!" said the Friar, seeing him approach; "Well?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="63">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n214" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14427" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14430">"She is here; I have found her." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="64">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n215" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14431" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14433">"In what condition?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="65">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n216" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14434" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14437">"Recovered, or at least risen from her bed." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="66">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n217" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14438" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14441">"Blessed be the Lord!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="67">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n218" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14442" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14456">"But—" said Renzo, when he was near enough to speak in a low voice, "there is another embarrassment." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="68">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n219" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14457" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14458">"What is it?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="69">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n220" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14459" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14481">"I would say that— You already know how good this poor young girl is; but sometimes she is rather obstinate in her ideas. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n221" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14482" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14520">After so many promises, after all that you know, she now says she cannot marry me, because she says that in that night of terror, in the heat of her frenzy, she has, so to say, dedicated herself to the Madonna. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n222" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14521" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14525">These are unmeaning things, are they not? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n223" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14526" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14557">Excellent things, for those who have the knowledge and means of performing them; but for us common people, who do not well know how they should be done—are they not things which are of no value?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n224" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14558" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14563">"Tell me; is she far from here?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n225" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14564" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14571">"Oh, no; a few steps beyond the church." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n226" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14572" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14583">"Wait for me a moment," said the Friar; "and then we will go there together." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n227" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14584" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14598">"You mean to say that you will make her understand—" "I know nothing, my son; it is necessary that I hear her." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="70">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n228" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14599" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14623">"I comprehend," said Renzo, and stood with his eyes fixed upon the earth, his arms crossed upon his breast, ruminating upon the uncertainty in which he still remained. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n229" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14624" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14672">The Friar again went in search of the Father Vittore, prayed him to supply his place, entered his hut, came forth again with his basket on his arm, and then turned towards Renzo, saying, "Let us go," and went on before, directing his steps towards that hut which they had both entered. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n230" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14673" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14684">This time the Friar entered alone, and re-appearing in a moment, said, "Nothing. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n231" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14685" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14691">Let us pray; let us pray;" then continued, "now, conduct me thyself." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="71">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n232" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14692" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14696">Without more words they proceeded on their way. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="72">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n233" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14697" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14712">The heavens were even yet more overcast, and announced an immediate tempest. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n234" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14713" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14754">Sudden flashes of lightning broke the increasing gloom, and illuminated with an instantaneous brightness the long roofs and arches of the porticoes, the cupola of the chapel, and the humble huts; and the repeated peals of thunder rolled from one quarter of the heavens to the other. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n235" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14755" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14803">The youth hastened on studying his route, filled with a violent impatience to arrive, yet slackening his pace so as to measure it with the strength of his companion. The old man exhausted by fatigue, oppressed by the disease and overpowered by the heat, pursued his way with difficulty, raising every now and then his thin countenance towards heaven as though to breathe more freely. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="73">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n236" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14804" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14819">Renzo, when he saw the hut, stopped, turned round, and said in a tremulous voice, "She is here." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="74">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n237" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14820" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14820">They entered. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n238" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14821" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14826">"Here he is!" cried the woman who lay in bed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n239" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14827" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14842">Lucia turned round, rose precipitately, and hastened towards the old man, exclaiming, "Oh, Father Cristoforo!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="75">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n240" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14843" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14851">"Well, Lucia; from how much anguish the Lord has delivered you. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n241" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14852" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14860">You ought to be very happy having always trusted in Him." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="76">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n242" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14861" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14862">"Oh, yes. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n243" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14863" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14865">But you, Father? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n244" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14866" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14870">Alas! how you are changed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n245" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14871" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14875">How are you? tell me, how are you?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="77">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n246" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14876" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14906">"As God wills, and as, through His grace, I wish myself to be," replied the Friar, with a serene countenance, and drawing her aside into a corner, he added, "Listen! I can only remain here a few moments. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n247" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14907" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14916">Are you disposed to confide in me, as in former times?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="78">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n248" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14917" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14924">"Oh, are not you always my father?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="79">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n249" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14925" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14933">"Well then, my daughter, what is this vow of which Renzo has told me?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="80">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n250" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14934" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14949">"It is a vow which I have made to the Madonna — oh, in great tribulation! — not to marry." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="81">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n251" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14950" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14950">"Poor girl! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n252" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14951" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14959">But did you think at that time that you were already bound by a promise?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="82">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n253" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14960" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14969">"As the Lord and the Madonna were concerned — I did not think of it." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="83">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n254" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14970" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14981">"The Lord, my daughter, accepts sacrifices, offerings, when what we offer is our own. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n255" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14982" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15003">It is the heart which He desires; it is the will; but you cannot offer Him the will of another to whom you have pledged yourself." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n256" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15004" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15006">"Have I done ill?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n257" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15007" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15033">"No, my poor girl, do not think so; I believe even that the Holy Virgin will have accepted the intentions of your afflicted heart, and will have offered them to God for you. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n258" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15034" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15045">But tell me; you have never taken counsel with any one regarding this matter?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n259" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15046" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15068">"I did not think it was evil, and that I was therefore obliged to confess it; and there was no need to relate the little good it might do." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n260" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15069" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15085">"Have you any other motive that should prevent you fulfilling the promise which you made to Renzo?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n261" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15086" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15093">"As to that —— for myself — what motive? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n262" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15094" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15124">I could not exactly say ——" replied Lucia, with hesitation, which indicated something very different from an uncertainty of thought; and her face, which was still pale from sickness, was suddenly suffused with the brightest rose. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n263" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15125" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15164">"Do you believe," replied the old man, lowering his eyes, "that God has given to his church authority to remit and retain the obligations and debts which men may have contracted towards Him, in order to produce greater good?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n264" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15165" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15168">"Yes, I believe he has." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n265" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15169" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15216">"Learn then that we, deputed to watch over the souls in this place, have for all those who have recourse to us the amplest powers of the church; and consequently, that I can, if you demand it, absolve you from any obligations which you may have contracted by this vow." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n266" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15217" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15228">"But is it not a sin to turn back—to repent of a promise made to the Madonna? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n267" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15229" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15267">I made it then from the bottom of my heart," said Lucia, violently agitated by the assault of such an unexpected hope, and by the opposition of a terror, strengthened by all the thoughts which for so long had been the principal occupants of her soul. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="84">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n268" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15268" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15298">"A sin, my daughter?" said the Father: "a sin to have recourse to the church, and to beseech her minister to exercise that authority which he has received from her, and which she received from God? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n269" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15299" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15336">I have seen how you were formed to be united; and certainly, if it ever has appeared to me that two beings ought to be united by God, you were these two: and now I do not see wherefore God has desired to separate you. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n270" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15337" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15358">And I bless him that he has given me (unworthy as I am) the power of speaking in his name, and of returning you your troth. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n271" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15359" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15382">If you ask me to declare you absolved from your vow, I shall not hesitate to do so; and I even desire that you should ask me." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="85">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n272" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15383" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15397">"Then—! then! I ask it," said Lucia, with a countenance now only troubled by a feeling of shame. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="86">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n273" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15398" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15471">The Friar called by a sign the youth, who stood in the farthest corner, gazing (since he could do nothing else) fixedly at the two speakers, whose conversation was so interesting to him. When our youth had approached, the Friar said to Lucia, in a louder voice, "By the authority which I have received from the church, I declare you freed from your vow of virginity, annulling all that may have been inconsiderate in it, and liberating you from any obligation which you may have contracted." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="87">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n274" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15472" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15482">The reader can imagine how such words sounded in Renzo's ears. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n275" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15483" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15500">He returned the most enthusiastic thanks with his eyes to the one who had proffered them, and immediately, but in vain, sought to catch Lucia's eyes. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n276" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15501" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15541">"Return with security and peace to the thoughts of a former time," pursued the Capuchin: "Again, beseech from the Lord the favour to form of you a holy wife; and be confident that he will grant you this favour still more abundantly after so many woes. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n277" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15542" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15604">And thou," said he, addressing Renzo, "recollect, my son, that if the church bestows upon thee this companion, it is not done to procure thee a temporal and mere worldly joy, which even should it be perfect and unmingled with grief, must, nevertheless, end in a great sorrow at the moment of your separation; but this is done to place you both in the path of joy which will have no end. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n278" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15605" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15623">Love each other as companions of travel, with the thought that you will have to separate, yet with the hope of being reunited for ever. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n279" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15624" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15654">Return thanks to heaven, who has conducted you to this state, not by means of noisy and transient gaiety, but through pain and misery, so as to dispose you to a perfect and tranquil joy. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n280" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15655" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15684">If God should grant you children, be careful in educating them for him—instil into their hearts love of him and of all mankind; and then you will guide them well in all the rest. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n281" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15685" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15694">Lucia! has he told you," and here the Friar indicated Renzo, "has he told you whom he has seen here?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="88">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n282" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15695" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15699">"Oh, Father, he has told me!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="89">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n283" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15700" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15703">"You will pray for him! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n284" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15704" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15707">You will not grow weary. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n285" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15708" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15712">And you will also pray for me! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n286" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15713" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15721">My children! I wish you to preserve a remembrance of the poor Friar." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="90">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n287" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15722" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15764">And saying this, he took from his basket a small box, of common wood, but turned and polished with a nicety peculiar to Capuchins of those times, and continued: "Within this is contained the remains of that bread—the first which I besought as an alms;" that bread of which you have heard speak! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n288" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15765" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15775">I leave it to you; preserve it, shew it to your children. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n289" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15776" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15808">They will come into a sorrowful world, in sorrowful times, and in the midst of proud and insolent men: tell them that they must always, always pardon! and every one, every one! and that they must also pray for the poor Friar!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="91">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n290" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15809" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15824">He presented the box to Lucia, who received it with respect, as though it had been a relic. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n291" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15825" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15861">Then, with a more tranquil voice, he continued: "Now tell me what support you have here in Milan; where do you think of finding an abode when you go forth from here? and who will conduct you to your mother, whom God preserve in health?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="92">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n292" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15862" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15882">"This good lady is a mother towards me for the present: we two shall leave this place together, and then we will think about everything." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="93">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n293" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15883" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15891">"God bless her," said the Friar, approaching the bed. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="94">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n294" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15892" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15919">"I also thank you," said the widow, "for the consolation which you have given these poor creatures, although I had counted upon always keeping this dear Lucia with me. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n295" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15920" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15942">I will care for her, I will accompany her to her village, and consign her into the hands of her mother, and," added she in an undertone, "I will give her her marriage outfit. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n296" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15943" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15958">I have a deal of property, and I have no longer left me any one of those who ought to enjoy it with me!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="95">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n297" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15959" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15975">"Thus," replied the Friar, "you can make a great sacrifice to the Lord, and to the good of your neighbour. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n298" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15976" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16017">I do not recommend this young girl to you, for I already see how much attached you are to her: we have only to praise the Lord, who shews himself a father even in his chastisements, and who in placing you together has given you such a clear sign of his love towards both one and the other. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n299" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16018" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16043">"Now," he resumed, turning towards Renzo, and taking him by the hand, "we two have no longer anything to do here; we have even remained too long. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n300" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16044" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16044">Let us go." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="96">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n301" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16045" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16051">"Oh, Father!" said Lucia, "I shall see you again? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n302" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16052" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16066">I am recovered, I who do no good in this world; and you—!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="97">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n303" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16067" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16096">"I had long," replied the old man in a serious and gentle voice, "requested a favour from the Lord, a very great favour—that of ending my days in the service of my fellow beings. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n304" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16097" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16115">If He now grant my power, all those who feel affection for me should assist me in returning thanks to Him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n305" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16116" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16125">Come; give Renzo your commission for your mother." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="98">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n306" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16126" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16156">"Relate to her what you have seen," said Lucia to her betrothed: "tell her that I have here found another mother, that I shall come with this mother to her as soon as I can, and that I hope to find her in health." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="99">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n307" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16157" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16171">"If you have need of money," said Renzo, "I have here all the gold which you sent me, and—" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="100">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n308" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16172" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16181">"No, no," interrupted the widow; "I have only too much." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="101">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n309" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16182" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16185">"Let us go," replied the Friar. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="102">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n310" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16186" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16205">"Till we meet again, Lucia—! and you also, kind Signora," said Renzo, unable to find words to express all that he felt in such a moment. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="103">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n311" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16206" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16220">"Who knows whether the Lord will mercifully permit us to see each other again!" exclaimed Lucia. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="104">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n312" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16221" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16240">"May He be always with you, and bless you," said Friar Cristoforo to the two companions, and then went forth with Renzo from the hut. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="105">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n313" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16241" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16253">Night was not far off, and the weather seemed still more threatening. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n314" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16254" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16268">The Capuchin again offered the youth shelter from this night in his tent. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n315" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16269" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16281">"I cannot bear thee company," added he; "but thou wilt be under cover." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="106">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n316" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16282" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16319">Renzo, however, felt a strong desire to be journeying onward; and did not care to remain longer in such a place, when he could not avail himself of it in order to see Lucia, and would not have been able even to pass a little time with the good friar. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n317" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16320" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16345">As to the hour and weather, we might say, that had it been night or day, sunshine or rain, a gentle breeze or a north wind, it would have been all the same to him at that moment. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n318" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16346" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16361">He thanked the Friar, therefore, saying that he desired to go in search of Agnese as soon as possible. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="107">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n319" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16362" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16409">When they were in the road, the friar pressed his hand and said: "If thou should'st find her, which God grant! salute this good Agnese also in my name; and tell her, and all who remain, to remember Fra Cristoforo, and to pray for him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n320" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16410" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16416">May God watch over thee, and bless thee always!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="108">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n321" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16417" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16423">"Oh, dear Father ———! we shall see each other again — we shall see each other again!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="109">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n322" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16424" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16467">"Above, I hope;" and with these words he moved away from Renzo, who stood gazing after him until he lost sight of the good old man, and then hastily bent his steps towards the gate, casting to the right and left his last glances of compassion upon this place of woe. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap36-n323" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16468" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16499">Here was an extraordinary movement — a running to and fro of Monatti, a carrying away of various things, an arranging of the tent awnings, a dragging along of the convalescent to the tents and the porticoes, so as to defend them from the terrible tempest. </note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>