<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CHAPTER XXXVII.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>1845</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed Lovers: a Milanese Story of the Seventeenth Century. With The Column of Infamy by Alessandro Manzoni. In Three Volumes</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
          <date>1845</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Henry Francis C. Logan</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="English_1845_cap37">
        <p n="1">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10063">Scarcely had Renzo crossed the threshold of the lazaretto, and turned towards the right in search of the small pathway by which he had that morning arrived before the walls, than large drops began to fall, one by one, upon the white and arid road, raising around them a minute dust; a moment after, and they fell thick and fast; and before he could reach the pathway, they came down in torrents. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10064" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10116">Renzo, however, instead of growing uneasy, only made merry in the rain, and rejoiced in the freshness of the air, in the murmur, in the stir among the grass and leaves, which were all trembling, drooping, reviving, glittering; he drew long and deep breaths; and in this change of outward nature, he experienced yet more intensely the change which had also taken place in his destiny. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="2">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10117" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10212">But much more intense would this sentiment have been, could Renzo have divined what was known a few days later, that this water carried away the contagion. If the lazaretto was unable to restore to the outer world all the living it still contained within its walls, at least from this day forth it would receive no others into its fearful jaws. At the end of a week, doors and shops were seen re-opened, scarcely anything more was said about quarantine, and there only remained a few traces scattered here and there; those traces which such a scourge always leaves after it for some time. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="3">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10213" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10264">Our traveller, therefore, proceeded gaily along without having formed any design of where, of how, or of when he should stop, or whether even he should stop at all this night, alone eager to proceed onward, so as to arrive quickly at his village, there to find some one with whom he could speak, to whom he could relate his good fortune; but above all was he eager to set forth immediately on his way to Pasturo in search of Agnese. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10265" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10296">He travelled on with his mind wholly absorbed by the events of the day; but in the midst of all these scenes of misery, of horror, of danger, there floated one thought,—"I have found her, she is recovered; she is mine!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10297" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10328">And then he would leap for joy, flinging the wet around him, like a spaniel just issued from the water; sometimes he would content himself with merely rubbing his hands, and then post on with more ardour than ever. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10329" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10382">Pursuing his road, he recalled the thoughts which he had felt that morning and the day previous, when coming; and this time he recalled precisely those which he had then sought to drive away—his doubts, the difficulty of the enterprise, the chance of finding her at all, of finding her living, of finding her among so many dead and dying! "And I have found her alive!" he concluded. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10383" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10437">He busied himself in thought with the most terrible occurrences of the day; he pictured himself with the knocker in his hand—"Will she, or will she not be there?"—and how little comfort there was in the reply! then to have scarcely time to deliberate upon it, before being fallen upon by those silly rascals! This lazaretto, too; that ocean of misery! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10438" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10440">He desired to find her there; he had found her! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10441" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10466">He turned to the moment when the procession of convalescents had passed by; what a moment! what heartache at not finding her! and now he troubled himself no longer on that account. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10467" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10471">And the women's quarter! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10472" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10486">And then to hear that voice, that very voice, behind that hut, when he least expected it! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10487" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10503">But how? there was still the vow, and this knot was more difficult than ever to loosen! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10504" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10506">But now it was untied. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10507" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10527">And his hatred towards Don Rodrigo, this constant rage which embittered all his woes and poisoned all his consolation, had also vanished. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10528" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10559">In fact, so great was his happiness, that he would have been unable to imagine a more perfect contentment had it not been for his uncertainty regarding Agnese, his sad presentiment concerning Father Cristoforo, and for his still being in the midst of the plague. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="4">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10560" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10570">He arrived at Sesto as night was closing in, and still it did not appear as though the rain would cease. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10571" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10592">However, feeling himself in a better walking mood than ever, spite of being wet through, he did not even think of stopping to rest. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10593" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10616">The only thing which incommoded him, was violent hunger, and hunger such as his would have easily caused him to digest stronger food than the Capuchin's weak broth. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10617" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10638">He looked around him to see whether also here there might not be a bakehouse; he saw one; he received two loaves with the tongs and the accompanying ceremonies. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10639" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10647">He placed one in his pocket and the other at his mouth, and was off again. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="5">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10648" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10666">When he passed through Monza, it was already night; however, notwithstanding this, he succeeded in finding the gate which led to the right road. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10667" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10692">The reader may imagine in what a state this road was, and how it became every moment worse. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10693" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10740">Sunk (as were then all roads; and this we must have already mentioned) between two banks, like the bed of a river, one might in such a moment have called it, if not a river, at least an aqueduct; and every now and then you came upon holes, out of which you could scarcely draw your foot, say nothing of your shoes. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10741" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10787">But Renzo extricated himself as well as he could, without giving any sign of impatience, without uttering an oath, without repenting. He thought that every step, cost what it might, carried him forward, that the rain would cease whenever it should please God; that, at proper time, day would break, and that the road, which he should traverse in the meantime, would then be traversed. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="6">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10788" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10803">And to confess the truth he only thought about the road when he was forced to do so. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10804" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10871">Such thoughts were merely a distraction; the great labour of his mind was to recall the history of the three sad past years: so many embarrassments, so many adversities, so many moments in which he was near losing even his hope, and considering all lost; and then to oppose all this to the dreams of so different a future; the arrival of Lucia, their wedding, the pleasure of mutually relating their past misfortunes, and their whole life! </note>
        </p>
        <p n="7">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10872" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10962">How then did he manage where there were two roads? Whether the little knowledge he had of the route, or whether the pale twilight assisted him in finding the right path, or whether he was directed by chance, we cannot tell; for even he himself, who was often accustomed to relate his adventures at a greater length than we—and everything leads us to believe that our Anonymous has heard him relate them more than once—even he himself, in this place, says, that he only recollects this night as though he had passed it in his bed dreaming. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10963" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10975">The fact, however, is, that in the morning he found himself on the shore of the Adda. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="8">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10976" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11024">It had not yet ceased to rain; but the rain which had at first fallen in torrents, like a deluge, had now changed into a very fine, equal, penetrating rain; the clouds, high in the heavens, formed a constant yet transparent veil, and the light of the early dawn showed Renzo the surrounding country. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11025" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11039">It was certainly his neighbourhood; and what he experienced at this spectacle could not be described. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11040" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11062">I can only say, that these mountains, this near Resegone, the territory of Lecco had become, as it were, his own property. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11063" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11127">He glanced at himself, and lo! he was in a strange plight; which, to say the truth, may easily be imagined, after all that has been related: everything sticking to his back, from his head to his waist, all wet and dripping; from his waist to his toes, all mud and mire. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11128" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11158">If he could only have seen himself in a looking-glass, with his hat-crown all soft and fallen in, and his hair all straight and sticking to his face, his appearance would have made a still greater impression upon himself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11159" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11197">As to fatigue, he might suffer from it, but he was not aware of it; and the freshness of the dawn, added to that of the night, and to the small bath he had enjoyed, only gave him greater alacrity, and a desire to travel on yet more quickly. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11198" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11225">He was now at Pescate; he coasted along the Adda, casting a melancholy glance towards Pescarenico; he passed the bridge; and then by lanes and fields he soon arrived at the house of his friendly host. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11226" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11270">The friend, who was already risen, and was at his door contemplating the weather, raised his eyes towards this soaked and bemired figure, which was at the same time so lively and nimble; and in all his days he never had seen a man in a worse condition, yet more contented. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="9">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11271" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11278">"O!" he said; "already here? and in this weather? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11279" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11280">How has all gone on?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="10">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11281" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11288">"She is there!" returned Renzo; "she is there; she is there!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="11">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11289" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11289">"In health?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="12">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11290" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11293">"Recovered, which is better. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11294" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11303">I ought to thank God and the Madonna as long as I live. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11304" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11313">But I have seen great things, terrible things; I will relate all to thee by and by." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="13">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11314" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11317">"But in what a fine trim thou art." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="14">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11318" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11320">"I am very handsome, eh?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="15">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11321" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11338">"To speak the truth, thou couldst very well wash the lower part of thy body with the upper. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11339" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11347">But wait, wait; I will make thee a good fire." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="16">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11348" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11361">"I will not say no. Dost thou know where the rain overtook me? Exactly at the gate of the lazaretto; but that was nothing. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11362" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11372">The weather had his business, and I had mine." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="17">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11373" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11404">The friend went out, and returned with two armfuls of fuel; one portion he placed on the floor, the other on the hearth, and with an ember which had remained from the night before, he quickly raised a beautiful flame. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11405" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11432">Renzo, meanwhile, had taken off his hat, and after having shaken it several times, had flung it on the ground; he had also, but not so easily, torn off his doublet. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11433" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11471">He then drew from the pocket of his breeches his large knife, the sheath of which was all wet and soft; he placed it on a bench, saying, "My knife also is in a fine condition; but it is with water, it is with water. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11472" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11478">The Lord be thanked — It was near, near committing a deed — I will tell thee all by-and-by." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11479" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11483">And he rubbed his hands. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11484" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11509">"Now do me another favour," he added; "go and fetch me that bundle that I left up-stairs, for before these clothes dry upon my back —" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="18">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11510" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11534">Returning with the bundle, the friend said, "I think thou must have a good appetite; I know that thou wilt not have stood in need of drink upon the road, but food —" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="19">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11535" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11553">"I managed to buy two loaves late last evening, but in truth they have not touched my teeth." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="20">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11554" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11585">"Leave all to me," returned the friend, who, placing water in a pot, which he then suspended to a chain, added, "I will go and milk; when I return with the milk the water will be ready, and we will make a good polenta. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11586" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11591">In the meantime make thyself comfortable." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="21">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11592" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11616">Renzo being left alone, removed, but not without difficulty, his remaining garments, for they seemed to stick to his body; he then dried and reclothed himself from head to foot. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11617" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11630">The friend returned and went to his pot. Renzo meanwhile seated himself. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="22">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11631" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11641">"Now I feel that I am fatigued," he said; "but it was a fine walk! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11642" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11653">However that is nothing, I have things to relate to thee during all the day. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11654" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11656">What a "terrible state Milan is in! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11657" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11661">The things which one is forced to see! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11662" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11666">The things which one is obliged to touch! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11667" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11674">Things which give one a disgust to oneself! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11675" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11688">I dare say nothing less than this fine washing was necessary to cleanse me! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11689" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11698">And then what those gentlemen in Milan wanted to do to me! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11699" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11699">Thou shalt hear. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11700" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11705">But if thou couldst only see the lazaretto! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11706" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11710">There is misery without end! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11711" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11743">Enough; I will relate all to thee —— And she is there, and she will come here and will be my wife; thou shalt be my witness, and pest or no pest, we will be merry at least for a few hours." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="23">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11744" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11825">In short, Renzo was faithful to his promise of relating his adventures to him all the day, more especially as the rain not ceasing, he passed all this day in the house, sometimes sitting beside his friend, sometimes occupied with his friend in preparing casks and other things for the vintage; for, as he was himself accustomed to say, he was one of those who fatigue themselves far more by doing nothing than by working. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11826" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11851">However, he could not keep himself from making a little excursion to Agnese's cottage, to look again at a certain window, and give another rub of his hands. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11852" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11863">He returned without having been seen by any one, and then immediately went to bed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11864" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11883">He arose before it was day; and perceiving that the rain had at least ceased, though as yet the weather did not appear entirely fine, he set forth on his way to Pasturo. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="24">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11884" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11905">It was still early when he arrived there, for he was not less eager than the reader to end his journey. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="25">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11906" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11920">He inquired after Agnese, learnt that she was well, and was directed to a small isolated house in which she dwelt. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11921" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11967">He hastened thither, called to her from the street; at his voice she ran to the window, and whilst she stood with her mouth open to send forth I know not what cry, Renzo forestalled her, exclaiming, "Lucia is recovered; I have seen her the day before yesterday; she salutes you; she will come here immediately. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11968" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11977">And then I have many, many things to tell you." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="26">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11978" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12018">What between surprise at his apparition, joy at this news, and her desire to know more, Agnese began now to exclaim, now to question without finishing a sentence; then forgetting the precautions she had been accustomed to observe for some time, she said, "I will come and open the door for you." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="27">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12019" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12029">"Wait," cried Renzo, "the plague? you have not had it I believe." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="28">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12030" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12033">"No, I have not, and you?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="29">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12034" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12041">"I have had it, but still you ought to be prudent. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12042" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12054">I have just come from Milan, and you will hear that I have been in the midst of the contagion, up to the very eyes. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12055" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12076">It is true that I have changed all my clothes from head to foot, but it is a sort of thing which sticks to one always, like a crime. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12077" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12117">And since the Lord has preserved you until now, I should like you to take care of yourself till this cursed influence has ceased; for you are our mother, and I want us to live a long time happily together as compensation for the great suffering we have endured." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="30">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12118" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12120">"But," commenced Agnese. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="31">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12121" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12128">"Ah!" interrupted Renzo: "there is now no bar which prevents me. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12129" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12143">I know what you would say; but you shall hear, you shall hear, for there is no longer any but! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12144" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12158">Let us go into some open space where we can speak at our ease, and without danger; and you shall hear. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="32">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12159" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12184">Agnese indicated to him an orchard, which was behind the house; and added; "Enter, and you will see two benches there, one opposite the other, benches which seem as though they had been placed on purpose for us. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12185" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12187">I will come directly." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="33">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12188" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12284">Renzo went and seated himself upon one; a moment after, Agnese found herself upon the other: and I am certain that could the reader have been there as a third person, informed as he is of all the preceding events, could he have witnessed this animated conversation; could he have heard with his own ears their various relations, their questions, their explanations, their condolences, their congratulations, all about Don Rodrigo and poor Father Cristoforo, and all the rest, and their descriptions of the future, clear and positive, as though they were descriptions of the past; I am certain, I say, that he would have taken great interest in the scene, and would have been the last to go away. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12285" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12320">But to see all this conversation merely upon paper, in silent written words, without finding a single new fact, is a thing about which he would not care a deal, but would like better to imagine it for himself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12321" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12398">The conclusion was, that they should all keep house together in that Bergamascan village in which Renzo had already settled; as to the time, nothing could now be decided, because that depended upon the plague, and upon other circumstances: as soon as the danger should be at an end, Agnese was to return home, and there await Lucia, or Lucia should go and await her there: meantime, Renzo should often take a trip over to Pasturo, to see his mother, and keep her informed of all that might happen. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="34">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12399" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12430">Before taking his departure, he offered her also money, saying, "I have them all here you see, these pieces of money: I also had made a vow, which was not to touch them until all should be brought to light. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12431" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12450">Now if you have need of any money, only bring a bowl of vinegar and water, and I will throw these fifty beautiful, glittering scudi into it." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="35">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12451" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12472">"No, no," said Agnese: "I have still more than I want for myself: preserve yours, for they will be useful to commence housekeeping with." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="36">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12473" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12490">Renzo departed with the new consolation of having found so dear a person safe and sound. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12491" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12518">He remained the rest of that day and the following night in his friend's house. The next day he was again on foot; but journeying in another direction, that is, towards his adopted country. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="37">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12519" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12546">He found Bartolo also in good health, and in less fear of losing this blessing; for within these few days things, even there, had rapidly taken a better course. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12547" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12588">Those who fell sick, were now few in number; the disease was no longer what it had been; the patients became no longer of that deadly livid hue, neither were they attacked with such violent symptoms; it was now a fever, for the most part intermittent, sometimes accompanied with small discoloured spots, which healed like ordinary biles. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12589" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12612">The very aspect of the country already appeared changed; the few inhabitants who yet remained began to go out, to relate their sufferings to each other, and to exchange mutual congratulations and condolences. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12613" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12647">People already spoke of recommencing their trades; masters thought of seeking after workmen, especially for such trades in which the number of workmen had been small even before the contagion, as was peculiarly the case with the silk trade. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="38">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12648" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12671">Renzo, without making any difficulty, promised his cousin to resume his labour as soon as he should return with his companions to settle in the country. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12672" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12723">Meanwhile he occupied himself in making more necessary preparations; he provided himself with a larger house, a thing which was now become much easier and much less expensive, and furnished it with goods and chattels; this time having recourse to his treasure, but without making a great hole in it, for now everything was cheap, there being more property than people to buy it. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="39">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12724" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12740">After I know not how many days he returned to his native village, which he found still more remarkably changed for the better. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12741" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12779">He then immediately hastened to Pasturo; he found Agnese completely reassured, and disposed to return to her house whenever this might be. He conducted her thither. We will pass over in silence their sentiments and their words, when they together again beheld these well-known places. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="40">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12780" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12812">Agnese found everything as she had left it; therefore she could not do less than say that this time, the objects being a poor widow and a poor young girl, angels had watched over them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12813" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12861">"And the other time," added she, "one might have thought that the Lord had turned his regards elsewhere, and no longer thought about us, since he permitted our small possession to be carried away; but, behold! he had done the contrary, for he sent me money out of another quarter, with which I was able to replace every thing. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12862" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12895">I say every thing, but that is not correct; for Lucia's outfit, which they had carried off with the other things, all new and excellent, was still wanting; but now, that also comes out of another direction. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12896" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12962">Who could have said to me, when I was at such pains to prepare the other, "ah, Agnese! thou dost imagine thou art working for Lucia; alas, poor woman! thou art working for those whom thou dost not know. Heaven only knows what sort of people will wear this linen and these garments! Those which Lucia will wear, and the real outfit which she will use, will be provided by a good soul, whose very existence is unknown to thee!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="41">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12963" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12996">Agnese's first thought was how to prepare in her poor little cottage the most decent lodging she could for this good soul. She next went for silk to wind, and winding, she beguiled away the time. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="42">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12997" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13024">Renzo, on his side, did not pass in idleness these days which in themselves were so long. Fortunately he possessed two trades, and he now applied himself to that of the farmer. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13025" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13060">Sometimes he assisted his host, for whom it was a great piece of good fortune to find often at his command a workman of Renzo's ability; at other times, he cultivated and put in order the small garden belonging to Agnese, which, during her absence, had remained wholly untilled. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13061" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13086">As for his own little farm, he never once troubled himself about it, saying that it was a peruke far too much entangled for him to meddle with, and that it would require more than one pair of arms to set it to rights. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13087" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13131">Neither did he set foot, either in it or the house, knowing that the sight of this desolation would pain him; and having already determined to dispose of every thing for whatever price he could get, and then employ, in his new country, what he might thus gain. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="43">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13132" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13169">If the living appeared to each other like people risen from the dead, Renzo appeared to the remaining inhabitants of his village doubly so; every one offered him the most hearty receptions and congratulations, every one desired to hear him relate his history. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13170" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13175">You will perhaps ask, "What has become of his banishment?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="44">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13176" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13201">All went on very well in that quarter: he himself thought scarcely any thing more about it, supposing that those who should execute the sentence thought no more about it themselves; and in this he did not deceive himself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13202" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13288">This carelessness was not alone occasioned by the plague, which had caused so many things to be forgotten; but in those times, as the reader may have already seen in various other passages of this history, it was no uncommon occurrence for decrees, both general and special, issued against individuals, to remain often without effect, except when they had been executed immediately, or unless some private powerful animosity kept them alive, and made them felt: they were like musket balls, which, unless they strike, remain on the earth, where they cause no one any annoyance. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13289" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13299">This was a necessary consequence of the facility with which these decrees were issued. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="45">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13300" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13318">The activity of man is limited; and if more than necessary activity is employed in laying down commands, not enough will be employed in executing them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13319" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13328">What goes for the sleeves cannot go into the gussets. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="46">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13329" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13419">Whoever is anxious to learn how Renzo and Don Abbondio went on during this interval, may be informed that they both kept away from each other. Don Abbondio, through fear of hearing something about matrimony; at the very idea of which he saw before his eyes, on one hand, Don Rodrigo with his bravos, on the other, the Cardinal with his arguments. Renzo, because he had determined not to speak of the marriage until the moment of its celebration, not wishing to run the risk of vexing him such a long time beforehand, and fearing to see him start some fresh difficulty, or embarrass affairs by useless gossip. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13420" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13426">His gossips were with Agnese. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13427" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13433">"Do you think that she will come soon?" one would ask. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13434" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13453">"I hope so," the other would reply: and very often the one who gave the reply would, a short time after, ask the same question. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13454" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13479">Thus, with similar impostures did they endeavour to beguile the time, which appeared to them to grow ever longer as it gradually passed on. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="47">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13480" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13581">For the reader's pleasure we will hasten over this time, in one moment, saying briefly that a few days after Renzo's visit to the lazaretto, Lucia left its gates with the good widow. A general quarantine having been ordered, they underwent it together, shut up in the widow's house. A portion of this time was spent in preparing Lucia's marriage outfit, at which she herself, after a little hesitation, worked; and when this quarantine was ended, the widow, leaving her shop and house in the care of her brother the commissary, made preparations for her journey. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13582" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13633">We could even relate without pausing, how they set out, how they arrived, and what then followed; but with all the desire we have to second the reader's haste, there are three things appertaining to this interval of time which we cannot pass over in silence; and regarding the relation of two of these circumstances, at least, we believe that the reader himself will confess that we have not done wrong. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="48">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13634" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13698">Here is the first. When Lucia narrated her adventures to the widow, more in detail than she had been able to do in the agitation of their first confidence, and mentioned more expressly the Signora who had afforded her an asylum in the convent at Monza, she came to hear things regarding this unhappy lady which gave her the key to many mysteries, and filled her soul with a sorrowful and painful astonishment. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13699" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13756">She learned from the widow, that the unfortunate girl, being suspected of the most atrocious crimes, had been transported by order of the Cardinal, to a convent in Milan; that there, after having for some time delivered herself up to despair and rage, she had at length ended by repenting and accusing herself; and that her present life was such a voluntary torture that no one could imagine a more fearful one, unless they were at once to have deprived her of it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13757" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13785">Any one who should desire to learn further particulars regarding this sad history, will find them in the book and at the passage which we have already quoted when speaking of this personage. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="49">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13786" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13821">The second circumstance is, that Lucia, inquiring after Father Cristoforo from all the Capuchins she could see at the lazaretto, learned with more grief than astonishment that he had died of the plague. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="50">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13822" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13849">And finally, before taking her departure she desired also to learn something concerning her former patrons, and would have liked to pay her respects, were they still alive. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13850" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13865">The widow accompanied her to the mansion, where they learned that they both had departed this life some time before. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13866" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13907">As to Donna Prassede, when one says that she was dead, all is said; but, as Don Ferrante was a learned man, our Anonymous has considered him deserving of more attention; and we at our own risk are going to transcribe pretty nearly what he has left written on the subject. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="51">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13908" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13954">He says, then, that from the very first mention of the plague, Don Ferrante was one of the most resolute in denying its existence, and that he maintained his opinion unto the very last; not, certainly, with the same cries as the people, but by arguments which no one could blame for their want of concatenation. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="52">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13955" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13994">"In *rerum natura,*" he said, "there are only two kinds of things, substances and accidents; and if I prove that the contagion is neither one nor the other, I shall have proved that it does not exist, that it is a chimera; and I can prove it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13995" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13997">And here are my arguments. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13998" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14004">Substances are either spiritual or material. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14005" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14021">That the contagion is a spiritual substance, is a proposition which no one would maintain, therefore it is useless speaking about it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14022" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14029">Material substances are either simple or compound. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14030" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14042">Now the contagion is not a simple substance; and this may be demonstrated in a few words. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14043" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14063">It is not an etherial substance, since were it such, instead of passing from one body to another, it would fly immediately to its sphere. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14064" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14073">It is not a watery substance, because it would be wet, and would be dried up by the winds. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14074" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14078">Neither is it igneous, because it would burn. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14079" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14084">Neither is it terrestrial, because then it would be visible. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14085" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14107">Nor is it a compound substance either, since as such it ought to be sensible either to the eye or to the touch; and who has seen, who has touched the contagion? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14108" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14114">It now remains for us to see whether it may be an accident. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14115" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14117">This is still more difficult to prove. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14118" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14144">These doctors say that the contagion is communicated from one body to another; this is their Achilles, their pretext for giving so many useless orders. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14145" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14213">Now supposing it an accident, it would be a transferable accident; and these are two words at variance one with the other. There is not, in all philosophy, a thing more clear, more evident than this, that an accident cannot pass from one subject to another; for if to avoid this Scylla, people are reduced to call it an accident produced, they fall into Charybdis; because if it is produced, it cannot be communicated, or propagate itself as they declare. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14214" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14226">These principles allowed, what is the use of coming to talk to us about blotches or carbuncles—? </note>
        </p>
        <p n="53">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14227" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14234">"They are all nonsense," someone happened once to let fall. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="54">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14235" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14250">"No, no," resumed Don Ferrante; "I do not say so; science is science; it is only necessary to know how to apply it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14251" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14279">Tumours, violet blotches, black carbuncles, are all respectable words, which have their good and proper signification; but I maintain that they have nothing to do with the question. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14280" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14293">Who denies that there may be such things, and even that there are? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14294" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14300">The thing is to learn from whence they come." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="55">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14301" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14308">Here commenced Don Ferrante's annoyances. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14309" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14351">As long as he only jeered at the idea of contagion, he found everywhere willing and attentive ears; for it is impossible to say how great is the authority of a learned man, when he desires to demonstrate to others things of which they are already well persuaded. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14352" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14424">But when he desired to demonstrate that the error of these doctors did not consist in affirming that there was a terrible and general evil, but in assigning its cause; then—we speak of the early times, in which no one would listen to discourses regarding the plague,—then, instead of attentive ears, he found rebellious intractable tongues; his continuous orations were at an end; and he could only expound his doctrines by bits and snatches. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="56">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14425" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14445">"The true cause is only too clearly to be proved," he said, "and even those who maintain other foolish opinions, are obliged to acknowledge it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14446" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14458">Let them deny, if they can, this fatal conjunction of Saturn and Jupiter. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14459" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14468">And whenever did we hear of influences propagating themselves—? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14469" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14475">And these signors wish to deny the influence. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14476" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14482">They will deny next that there are planets! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14483" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14501">Or do they mean to say that stars are fixed on high for no purpose, just like so many pins stuck into a pincushion? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14502" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14539">But what I cannot understand in these doctors is, that they confess we find ourselves under such a malignant influence, and yet they say to us, 'do not touch this, do not touch that, and then you will be safe!' </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14540" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14556">As though avoiding the material contact of terrestrial bodies, could prevent the virtual effects of celestial "bodies! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14557" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14563">And then all this burning of rags! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14564" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14569">Poor people! can they burn Jupiter? can they burn Saturn?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="57">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14570" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14602">*Hic fretus,* that is to say, upon these grounds he took no precaution against the plague: he was attacked by it—went to bed—to die like one of Mataseo's heroes, still complaining of the stars. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="58">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14603" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14607">And his famous library? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap37-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14608" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14615">It is even yet, perhaps, mouldering upon the walls. </note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>