<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CHAPTER XXXV.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>1845</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed Lovers: a Milanese Story of the Seventeenth Century. With The Column of Infamy by Alessandro Manzoni. In Three Volumes</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
          <date>1845</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Henry Francis C. Logan</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="English_1845_cap35">
        <p n="1">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10085">Let the reader only picture to himself the lazaretto peopled with sixteen thousand persons infected with the pest. The whole enclosure was entirely occupied, here with huts and tents, there with carts and people; the two long ranges of porticoes, to the right and to the left, were crowded with the mingled dead and dying, extended upon sacks or upon straw; and above this immense den of misery floated a dull murmur, something like the distant sound of waves. Here and there was a going and coming, a running about, a stooping down, a rising up, of the convalescents, of the sick, of attendants. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10086" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10105">Such was the spectacle which suddenly presented itself before Renzo, and riveted him to the spot, overpowered and agitated. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10106" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10159">We certainly do not here propose minutely to describe this spectacle, neither would any reader desire that we should; but, following our youth upon his painful wandering, we will pause with him, and will describe as much of what he saw as will be necessary to understand what he himself did, and what happened to him. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="2">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10160" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10224">From the gate where he had paused, as far as the little chapel which stood in the middle, the whole space seemed to be crowded with huts, and such-like impediments; at a second glance, however, Renzo noticed that there was a moving to and fro of carts; a carrying away of property, so as to make more room: he saw Capuchins and laymen directing their operations, and at the same time sending away all such persons as had nothing to do there. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10225" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10250">Fearing himself to be driven forth after the same manner, he hid himself among the huts. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="3">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10251" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10303">He went on from hut to hut, looking into each, and carefully observing all the beds which were placed in the open air, and examining every countenance, either exhausted by suffering, contracted by spasm, or motionless in death, in search of one countenance which he nevertheless dreaded to find. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10304" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10335">But having already gone a considerable way, and repeated many, many times this sad examination without having seen a single woman, he imagined the women must be lodged in a separate quarter. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10336" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10392">He encountered many of the attendants upon the sick; attendants as different in their appearance, manner, and apparel, as the principles were opposed, which had inspired them all with an equal strength, for the fulfilment of their separate vocations: in the Monatti the extinction of every sense of compassion—in the Capuchins a superhuman compassion. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10393" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10421">But he preferred making no inquiries from either class; and deliberating whether he should proceed, went on until he succeeded in finding women. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10422" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10446">Pursuing his course, he did not cease looking around him; but from time to time he was obliged to withdraw his gaze, saddened by the spectacle of so much woe. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10447" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10455">But where could he turn, where rest his eyes, but upon fresh woe! </note>
        </p>
        <p n="4">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10456" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10470">The very air and the heaven increased, if anything could, the horror of the scene. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10471" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10531">The heavy mass of cloud had gradually dispersed itself into smaller clouds, which growing ever darker announced a tempestuous evening. In the midst of this heavy and gloomy sky appeared, as though seen through a thick veil, the disc of the sun, pale and without ray, and yet, diffusing around a faint and watery light, darted down a deadly and oppressive heat. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10532" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10575">Every now and then, amidst the continuous noise of this confused multitude, was heard the grumbling of thunder, deep but interrupted; listening, you would have been unable to distinguish out of which quarter it proceeded, or would even have been inclined to imagine it merely the distant rumbling of cart-wheels, which suddenly ceased. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10576" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10626">In the surrounding country not a single leaf was seen to stir—not a bird to alight upon or quit a single tree; only the swallow might be observed suddenly above the roofs of the enclosure to dart with extended wings to the ground, as if to skim along the plain; but, terrified by the movement of the crowd, would rapidly ascend and fly away. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10627" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10704">It was that kind of weather in which, among a company of travellers, there is no one found to break the general silence: when the hunter pursues his way absorbed in thought, his gaze fixed upon the earth; when the peasant labouring in the fields unconsciously ceases his song; or, in short, that weather which is a forerunner of a tempest, when nature, motionless without, appears agitated by some internal convulsion, which oppresses every living being, adds an unspeakable weariness to every action, and makes even idleness and existence itself painful. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10705" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10766">But in this place, destined to suffering and death, human beings already seized with sickness sunk under this oppression—the unhappy victims were seen to sink by hundreds; the last struggle was more painful—the groans more suffocating; perhaps never in this abode of woe had so cruel an hour as this been passed. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="5">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10767" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10819">Already had our youth wandered a considerable way upon his fruitless search through this labyrinth of huts, when, amidst the variety of lamentations and confusion of the general hum, he began to distinguish a singular mixture of crying and bleating; at length he arrived at a wooden partition, from whence proceeded this extraordinary sound. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10820" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10899">Renzo placed an eye to a larger aperture formed between two planks, and looked into an enclosure which was scattered over with little huts; within which were seen—not the usual invalids—but infants lying upon mattresses, pillows, or sheets spread out; nurses and other women were busied about them. But what more than all the rest attracted and fixed the attention were she-goats mingling among the nurses, and acting as their assistants. This was, in short, a hospital for infants; such a one as was permitted by the place and by the times. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10900" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10955">It was, I say, a singular spectacle to see some of these animals standing quietly above the poor little creatures, and giving them to suck; whilst another goat, hearing a wail, would hasten to the spot with a maternal instinct, and pausing near the little innocent, would seek to place itself above its nursling, bleating and agitating itself, as if to call some one to the assistance of both. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="6">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10956" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10999">Here and there were seated nurses with infants at the breast; some in such an attitude of love, that the question arose in the mind of the beholder, whether they had been attracted thither by the love of gain, or by that spontaneous charity which seeks the afflicted and abandoned. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11000" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11024">One of them, wearied and exhausted, removed from her bosom a little wailing wretch, and sorrowfully went in search of a goat which would be better able to fulfil her vocation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11025" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11050">Another, gazing with looks of compassion upon the nursling which had dropped asleep, and gently kissing it, went into a hut to lay it down upon a mattress. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11051" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11104">But a third, abandoned her bosom to the little stranger, not with an air of negligence, but of preoccupation, and gazed into the heavens; and upon what did she meditate in such an attitude, with such a look? upon an infant whom she had given birth to, who perhaps but a little time before had drawn its nourishment from this same bosom; nay, who perhaps had expired upon it! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11105" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11112">Other women performed other offices. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11113" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11151">One ran towards a famished infant, and carrying it away in her arms, laid it down beside a she-goat which was feeding from a heap of fresh grass, and now by harsh words, now by caresses, sought to induce the inexpert animal to perform its duty. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11152" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11198">Another ran to remove a poor little creature whom a goat, intent upon nourishing another nursling, trampled upon with her hoof; whilst this one carried her little foster-child up and down, rocking him in her arms, seeking now to lull him to sleep with a song, now to soothe him with gentle words, calling him by a name which she herself had given him. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="7">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11199" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11245">There now arrived a Capuchin with a long and very white beard, carrying two little wailing babes, one in either arm. He had brought them from their mothers, who had just expired. A woman ran to rescue them, and hastened, looking about among the crowd for some one who would take charge of them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11246" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11280">More than once Renzo, hurried on by his one all-absorbing thought, had moved from the loophole, but again he had looked in, and remained yet another moment. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="8">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11281" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11321">At last, however, he again commenced his search, continuing to walk along the walls of this wooden enclosure until a number of small cabins, built up against the partition, obliged him to turn out of the way. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11322" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11342">Suddenly, whilst he looked before him, studying his path, an unexpected, transient, instantaneous apparition passed before him, and filled his soul with tumultuous emotion. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11343" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11381">He saw, at about a hundred paces distant, a Capuchin appear and vanish among the tents — a Capuchin who, even at this distance, and seen thus hastily, had the whole appearance, the gait, the figure of Father Cristoforo. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11382" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11463">He rushed in search of the good friar in the most violent agitation, and wandering about, seeking him up and down, here and there, he at length, with the greatest joy, again beheld the form of the same friar. He saw him at a little distance walking away from a large cauldron, with a porringer in his hand; he saw him seat himself at the entrance of a hut, make the sign of the cross over the porringer which he held before him, and, glancing around him with the air of one who is always on the alert, begin to eat. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11464" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11468">It was in truth the Father Cristoforo. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="9">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11469" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11487">His history from the point where we lost sight of him until the present time will be related in two words. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11488" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11524">He had never quitted Rimini, nor had ever thought of quitting it, until the plague breaking forth in Milan afforded him the opportunity which he had always desired, the opportunity of giving his life for his neighbour. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11525" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11535">He besought with much earnestness to be summoned thither to assist and serve those who were attacked by the plague. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11536" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11555">The uncle, the Count, had died; and in fact, at the present moment, there was a greater necessity for attendants upon the sick than for politicians; therefore his request was granted without the slightest difficulty. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11556" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11568">He immediately came to Milan, and had now been there about three months. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="10">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11569" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11594">But the joy which Renzo experienced upon meeting again with the friar was only perfect for one moment; even in the very glance which he gave to ascertain whether this were really he, Renzo saw how much the good man was altered. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11595" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11628">His person was bowed and thin; his countenance thin also and deathly: you saw an exhausted nature, a failing and broken down frame, which was only sustained by a power of the soul. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="11">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11629" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11656">He also fixing his gaze upon the youth who approached, and not daring to raise his voice, sought by gestures to make himself known. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11657" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11673">"Oh, Father Cristoforo!" exclaimed Renzo, as soon as he was near enough to be heard without raising his voice. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="12">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11674" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11687">"Thou, here!" said the friar, placing the porringer upon the ground, and rising from his seat. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="13">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11688" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11692">"How are you, Father? how are you?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="14">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11693" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11715">"Better than many unfortunates whom thou seest here," replied the friar; and his voice was feeble, exhausted, changed like all the rest. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11716" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11765">His eyes alone were as they had formerly been, nay, were even still more lively and splendid; as though Love, elevated even by the danger of her work, had replaced, by a more ardent and purer flame, the fire which Weakness was gradually extinguishing. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11766" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11778">"But thou," pursued the Father, "how art thou? why hast thou thus come to dare the plague?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="15">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11779" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11783">"I have already had it, thanks be to heaven. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11784" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11788">I come — in search of — Lucia." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="16">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11789" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11792">"Lucia! is Lucia here?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="17">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11793" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11802">"She is here: at least, I hope to God that she may still be here." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="18">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11803" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11805">"Is she thy wife?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="19">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11806" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11814">"O my dear Father! no, alas! she is not my wife. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11815" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11823">Do you know nothing of all that has occurred?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="20">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11824" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11853">"No, my son; since God removed me from you, I have heard nothing more; but now that He has sent thee to me, I can assure thee that I should very much like to know all. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11854" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11857">But — the banishment?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="21">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11858" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11865">"You know then all that they did to me?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="22">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11866" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11870">"But thou, what hast thou done?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="23">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11871" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11891">"Listen: if I were to say that I was prudent that day in Milan, I should tell a lie; but I have committed no evil deed." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="24">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11892" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11899">"I believe thee, and I even believed this before." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="25">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11900" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11905">"Now then, I can tell you all." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="26">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11906" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11919">"Wait a moment," said the friar; and he took a few steps out of the hut, calling, "Father Vittore!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11920" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11956">After a few minutes a young Capuchin appeared, whom Father Cristoforo addressed, saying, "Do me the kindness, Father Vittore, to watch for me over our poor patients, whilst I remain here a short time; but, nevertheless, if any one wants me, let me be called. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11957" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11974">Especially that man, if he give the slightest sign of returning consciousness, inform me immediately." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="27">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11975" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11989">"Do not fear," replied the young man; and then the old man turned towards Renzo, "let us enter," said he to him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11990" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12003">"But," added he suddenly, and paused, "it appears to me that thou art exhausted; thou must be hungry." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="28">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12004" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12020">"So I am," said Renzo, "now that you make me think of it; I remember that I have not yet broken my fast." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="29">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12021" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12090">"Wait," said the friar; and taking another porringer, he went to fill it out of the cauldron, returned, and presented it to Renzo with a spoon, making him sit down upon a sack that served him for a bed. He then went to a cask which stood in one corner, drew some wine from it, and placed it upon a small table before his guest. He then took his own porringer, and seated himself beside Renzo. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="30">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12091" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12102">"O Father Cristoforo!" exclaimed the youth, "is it then proper for you to do such things? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12103" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12109">But you are always the same. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12110" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12114">I thank you truly from my heart." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="31">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12115" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12133">"Do not thank me," said the friar; "this is the property of the poor; but in this moment thou also art one of the poor. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12134" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12159">But now tell me all that I do not know, tell me about our poor Lucia, and try to tell it in a few words, for there is but little time, and there is a deal to be done, as thou mayst see." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="32">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12160" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12179">Renzo commenced between one spoonful and another to relate Lucia's history; how she had been received into the monastery at Monza; how she had been carried off. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12180" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12228">At these images of her sufferings and dangers, and at the thought that he himself had conducted the poor innocent girl to this place, the good friar remained breathless; but he breathed again, hearing how she had been miraculously liberated, had returned to her mother, and been placed with the Donna Prassede. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12229" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12278">"Now I will tell you about myself," said Renzo; and he briefly related the adventures of the fatal day in Milan, and his flight; how he had lived, removed from his home; and how, everything being now in confusion, he had risked going to his native place; how he had not been able to find Agnese; and how he had learned in Milan that Lucia was at the lazaretto. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12279" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12299">"And here I am," he concluded, to seek for her, to see whether she still lives, and whether—she will have anything to say to me—for—sometimes." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="33">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12300" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12314">"But," asked the friar, "hast thou any knowledge of where she has been placed—of when she came here?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="34">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12315" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12330">"None, my dear Father; I only know that she is here, if she still lives." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="35">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12331" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12340">"Oh, my poor son! but what search hast thou made here?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="36">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12341" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12356">"I have wandered up and down, but I have seen scarcely anything but men. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12357" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12383">I have thought that the women must be in a separate quarter, but I have not been able to reach it; if it is so, you will be able to tell me." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="37">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12384" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12398">"Dost thou not know, my son, that all men are prohibited from entering, all who have no commission?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="38">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12399" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12403">"Well, and what could happen to me?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="39">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12404" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12440">"This law is just and wholesome, my dear son; and if the excessive misery prevents its being observed in its full rigour, is this a reason that an honest man should transgress it?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="40">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12441" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12478">"But, Father Cristoforo!" exclaimed Renzo—"Lucia ought to be my wife; you know how we have been separated; it is already twenty months that I have suffered; I have borne my sufferings patiently; I have risked many things in coming here, and now—" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="41">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12479" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12523">"I do not know what to say," replied the friar, replying rather to his own thoughts than to the youth's words: "Thou art come here with good intentions, and would to God that all those who have free access to this place would conduct themselves as I feel sure that thou wilt conduct thyself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12524" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12570">God, who certainly will bless thee for this thy constancy, thy perseverance, in desiring and seeking after her whom he gave thee, God, who is more rigorous than men, yet at the same time more indulgent, will not regard what there may be irregular in thy manner of seeking her. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12571" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12594">Only recollect, that we shall both of us have to render account of thy conduct in this place; to men, perhaps not, but to God without doubt. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12595" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12648">Come here," and saying this, he rose, as did Renzo also immediately, who having listened attentively to all the good friar's words, had, nevertheless, at the same time taken counsel with himself and determined, as had been his first intention, not to mention Lucia's promise. "If he were to hear this," thought he to himself, "he would certainly discover some other difficulty. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="42">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12649" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12698">Oh, if I find her, we shall have plenty of time to discuss the matter; or — and then — what use would it be?" Having led him to the entrance of the hut, the friar continued: "Listen, our Father Felice, who is the president of the lazaretto, conducted the few who have recovered to a certain quarter, where they are to observe the quarantine. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="43">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12699" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12748">Thou canst see the church there in the middle of the enclosure;" and raising his lean and trembling hand, he indicated to the left the cupola of the chapel, which towered above the miserable tents; and then continued, "there they will assemble, to issue forth in procession through the gate by which thou must have entered." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="44">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12749" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12759">"Ah! then it was for this that people were so busy clearing the way." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="45">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12760" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12772">"Yes, certainly; and thou must also have heard the tolling of a bell." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="46">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12773" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12775">"Yes, I have." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="47">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12776" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12796">"This is the second time it has tolled; the third time they will be all assembled; the Father Felice will address a short discourse to them, and then will depart with them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12797" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12830">Go there also; seek to place thyself behind the people, on one side of the road, where, without disturbing any one or being remarked, thou canst see them pass by—and see—and see whether she is there. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12831" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12871">If God has not permitted this to be; this side," and here he again raised his hand, pointing to that side of the edifice which was in front of them—"this side of the edifice and a portion of the field beyond are assigned to the use of the women. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12872" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12894">Thou wilt perceive a kind of palisade which separates the two quarters, it is interrupted and open in some places, so that thou wilt experience no difficulty in entering. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12895" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12912">When thou art once within, if thou dost give offence to no one, most probably no one will address a word to thee. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12913" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12933">If, however, thou shouldst meet with any obstacle, only say that the Father Cristoforo da—knows thee, and will render account of thy conduct. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12934" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12941">Seek for her with faith and—with resignation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12942" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12962">For remember, that it is no small thing thou art come to seek here; thou dost seek a living person in the lazaretto! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12963" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12989">Ah, if thou didst only know how many times I have seen this population renewed! how many I have seen borne away! how very few issue forth! — Go prepared to offer a sacrifice —— </note>
        </p>
        <p n="48">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12990" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13003">"Yes, I understand!" interrupted Renzo, his eyes flashing, and his whole countenance changed; "yes, I understand! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13004" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13027">I go; I will look, I will seek her in every place, again and again, throughout the whole lazaretto, up and down — and if I do not find her —" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="49">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13028" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13046">"And if thou dost not find her?" asked the friar, with a serious air, and a look full of admonition. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="50">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13047" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13076">But Renzo, whose anger had been rekindled by this doubt, was wholly blinded by his passion, and continued, "If I do not find her, I shall manage to find some one else. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13077" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13126">Either in Milan, in his own wicked palace, at the end of the world, or in the devil's house, I will meet with this scoundrel who has separated us; with this rascal, without whom Lucia would have been mine these twenty months; and then, if we had been destined to die, at least we should have died together. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13127" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13132">If this villain yet lives, I will find him —" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="51">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13133" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13145">"Renzo!" cried the friar, seizing him by the arm, and regarding him yet more severely. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="52">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13146" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13201">"And if I find him," continued Renzo, still blinded by passion, "if the plague has not already done justice — It is no longer the time when a poltroon, surrounded by his followers, may with impunity drive honest people to despair, and then laugh at them: the time has arrived when men meet face to face; and — I will do justice!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13202" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13245">"Unhappy youth!" cried Father Cristoforo, with a voice which had assumed all its former strength and depth, "unhappy youth!" and his bowed head was raised; his cheeks coloured themselves with their ancient life, and his eyes sparkled with an almost terrific fire. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13246" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13273">"Behold, unfortunate!" and whilst he held, and violently shook Renzo's arm with one of his hands, he pointed with the other towards as much of the melancholy scene as lay before them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13274" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13279">"Behold, it is He who chastises! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13280" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13286">It is He who judges, and is not judged! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13287" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13292">It is He who scourges, and yet pardons! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13293" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13301">But thou worm of the earth, thou desire to do justice! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13302" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13309">Thou—dost thou know what justice is? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13310" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13312">Go, unfortunate one, go! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13313" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13355">I will hope—I have hoped, that before I die, God would give me the consolation of hearing that my poor Lucia was alive; nay, would permit me perhaps to see her, and hear her promise that she would send a prayer towards this grave where I shall repose. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13356" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13362">Go, thou hast destroyed my hope. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13363" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13384">God has not left her on earth for thee; and surely, thou art not audacious enough to fancy thyself worthy to be consoled by God. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13385" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13401">He will think of her, for she is one of those for whom are reserved the joys of eternity. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13402" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13409">Go! I have no longer time to attend to thee." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="53">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13410" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13426">And saying this, he flung Renzo's arm away from him, and bent his steps towards a cabin of the sick. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="54">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13427" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13442">"Ah, Father!" said Renzo, following him with a supplicating air, "will you send me away in this manner?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="55">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13443" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13451">"How?" resumed the Capuchin in a no less severe voice. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13452" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13484">"Art thou daring enough to imagine that I should steal the time of these afflicted ones, who expect that I shall speak to them of the pardon of "God, merely to listen to thy mad words, to thy proposals of vengeance? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13485" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13513">I listened to thee when thou didst ask for consolation and assistance; I abandoned charity, for charity; but now that thy heart is full of vengeance, what hast thou to do with me? Go! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13514" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13548">I have seen expire here the injured who have pardoned their injurers; injurers who have groaned and lamented that they could no longer humble themselves before those they had offended; I have wept with both; but with thee what have I to do?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="56">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13549" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13561">"Ah, I pardon him! I pardon him, in truth, I pardon him for ever!" exclaimed the youth. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="57">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13562" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13580">"Renzo!" said the friar, with a calmer severity; "reflect a little, and tell me how many times thou hast pardoned him." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="58">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13581" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13605">The Capuchin, receiving no reply for some time, suddenly bowed his head, and in a still calmer voice continued, "thou knowest wherefore I wear this habit." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="59">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13606" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13607">Renzo hesitated. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="60">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13608" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13613">"Thou knowest!" resumed the old man. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="61">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13614" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13617">"I know," replied Renzo. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="62">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13618" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13642">"I also was filled with hatred; I who have reprimanded thee for a thought, for a word. The man whom I cordially hated, whom I hated for a long time, I have murdered." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="63">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13643" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13649">"Yes, but he was an oppressor, one of those——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="64">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13650" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13668">"Hush!" interrupted the friar: "if this were a good reason, dost not thou think I should have discovered it in these thirty years? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13669" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13700">Ah! if I could only infuse now into thy heart the sentiment which I have ever since and still experience for the man I hated—if I could—I—but God can. He will! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13701" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13741">Listen, Renzo: He wishes thee more happiness than thou canst wish for thyself; thou hast been able to scheme vengeance but He has sufficient power, and sufficient mercy, to prevent thee from putting it into execution. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13742" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13764">Thou knowest well, thou hast many times said that He is able to arrest the arm of the oppressor; but know also that He is able to stay the arm of the vindictive. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13765" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13788">And because thou art poor, because thou art injured, dost thou believe that He is not able to defend a man whom He has created after his image? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13789" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13798">Dost thou believe that He will permit thee to do all thou dost desire? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13799" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13805">No! But dost thou know what He can do? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13806" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13819">He can hate thee, and condemn thee! He can, owing to this sentiment which animates thee, remove from thee every blessing! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13820" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13853">For, in whatever manner thy affairs may go on, whatever fortune may be thine, recollect that all will be chastisement, until thou shalt have pardoned him so completely that thou no longer canst say—I pardon him." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="65">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13854" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13893">"Yes, yes," said Renzo, very much moved, and filled with confusion, "I feel that I have never really pardoned him; I feel that I have spoken as a brute, and not as becomes a Christian; and now, with the grace of God, I pardon him truly from my heart." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="66">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13894" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13898">"And if thou shouldst see him?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="67">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13899" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13913">"I would pray the Lord that He would give me patience, and would touch his heart." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="68">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13914" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13931">"Thou shouldst recollect that the Lord has told us not alone to pardon, but to love our enemies! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13932" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13943">Thou shouldst recollect that He has so loved his, as to die for them!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="69">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13944" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13947">"Yes, with His aid, I will endeavour to do His will." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="70">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13948" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13951">"Well, come with me. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13952" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13957">Thou hast said: I will find him, and thou shalt. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13958" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13982">Come, and behold him whom thou couldst continue to hate, him for whom thou couldst desire evil, and against whose life thou wouldst arm thyself." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13983" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13999">And taking Renzo's hand, he pressed it with all the vigour of a young man, and then moved away. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14000" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14008">Renzo, not daring to question anything, followed him. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="71">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14009" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14038">After a few steps, the friar paused near the entrance of a hut, fixed his eyes upon Renzo's countenance with a mingled gravity and tenderness, and then entered with him. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="72">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14039" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14091">The first thing which met their eyes was a sick man seated upon some straw; a sick man who was no longer in danger, nay, who even appeared almost convalescent. As soon as he saw the Father, he shook his head, as if to say, no; the Father bowed his head with an air of sadness and resignation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14092" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14171">Renzo meanwhile cast his eyes upon the surrounding objects with a restless curiosity; he observed three or four other sick people, and distinguished one in particular lying in a corner upon a mattress, wrapped in a sheet, with a gentleman's cloak flung over him by way of coverlet; Renzo regarded this figure attentively, and recognising Don Rodrigo, stepped back. But the friar, again strongly pressing his arm, drew him to the foot of the couch, and, stretching forth his arm, pointed to the man who lay there. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="73">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14172" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14210">The unfortunate lay there motionless; his eyes were wide open, but without any expression; the countenance was pale, and here and there was seen a black spot; the lips were also black and swollen; it would have appeared the countenance of a corpse, had not a violent contraction given signs of a tenacious life. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14211" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14244">The chest heaved every now and then with a painful respiration; the right hand uncovered by the cloak, was seen pressed to his heart; the fingers were all livid, and black at the ends. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="74">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14245" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14260">"Thou seest!" said the friar, in a low and solemn tone, "This may be a chastisement; this may be a mercy. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14261" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14288">The same sentiment which thou dost now feel for this man who has offended thee, God will feel towards thee at the day of reckoning. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14289" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14292">Bless him, and thou shalt be blessed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14293" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14306">Four days has he lain here in the state thou seest him, without giving any sign of consciousness. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14307" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14347">It may be the Lord is inclined to grant him an hour of repentance, but desires to be besought for it by thee; perhaps He desires that thy prayers should be mingled with those of our innocent Lucia; perhaps He will reserve this grace for thy prayers alone, for the prayers of an afflicted and resigned heart. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14348" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14368">Perhaps the salvation of this man's soul and of thy own now alone depends upon thee, upon thy sentiment of pardon, of compassion, of love." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="75">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14369" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14385">He was silent; and joining his hands, he bowed his head above them and prayed; Renzo did the same. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="76">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14386" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14396">They had remained a few moments in this attitude when the third tolling of the bell was heard. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14397" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14405">They both moved away as if in concert, and issued forth. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14406" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14416">They neither of them either demanded questions or made protestations; their countenances alone spoke. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="77">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14417" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14442">"Go," said the friar, "go prepared to praise God, let it be either in receiving a mercy or in making a sacrifice. Praise God, whatever may be the issue of thy search. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14443" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14453">And whatever it may be, come and bring me tidings; we will together praise Him." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="78">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap35-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14454" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14475">Here, without anything more being said, they separated; one returned whence he had come, the other proceeded towards the chapel, which was about a hundred paces distant. </note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>