<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CHAPTER XXXIII.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>1845</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed Lovers: a Milanese Story of the Seventeenth Century. With The Column of Infamy by Alessandro Manzoni. In Three Volumes</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
          <date>1845</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Henry Francis C. Logan</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="English_1845_cap33">
        <p n="1">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10037">One night, towards the end of the month of August, during the very height of the plague, Don Rodrigo returned to his house in Milan, accompanied by the faithful Griso, one of the very few of his attendants who had remained alive. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10038" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10065">He had just left a company of friends who were accustomed to assemble together to banish by debauchery the melancholy of the times; each time they met were seen some fresh faces, whilst some old ones were missing. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10066" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10100">This day in particular Don Rodrigo had been one of the gayest; and among other things had caused the company to laugh very much over a species of funeral oration, spoken in honour of Count Attilio, who had been carried off by the plague two days previously. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="2">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10101" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10129">During his journey, he experienced a feeling of uneasiness, a weakness, a failing of strength in his legs, a difficulty in breathing, an inward heat, which he would have chosen to attribute to the wine, to the late hours he had kept, to the influence of the season. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10130" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10155">He did not open his lips during the whole way; and his first words upon arriving at home were to order Griso to light him to his chamber. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10156" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10194">When they had arrived there, Griso remarking his master's distorted and inflamed countenance, and his bright eyes almost starting from their sockets, he kept himself at a certain distance; for in those dangerous times, every one was obliged to acquire, as was said, a medical eye. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="3">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10195" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10214">"I feel very well," said Don Rodrigo, who read in Griso's action the thoughts that were passing through his mind. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10215" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10225">"I feel very well indeed; but I have drunk, I have drunk, perhaps, a little too much. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10226" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10228">There was such excellent wine! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10229" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10237">But, with a good night's rest all will be well again. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10238" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10253">I am overpowered by sleep — Remove that light a little, it blinds me — it annoys me——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="4">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10254" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10263">"The effects of the wine," said Griso, still keeping at a certain distance from his master. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10264" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10274">"But go to bed immediately, for a good sleep will do you good." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="5">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10275" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10283">"Thou art right—if I can sleep—— Otherwise I am very well. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10284" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10308">Place that bell quite close to me, in case I should require anything in the night; and be careful to listen whether I ring. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10309" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10332">But I shall not require anything—— Carry away quickly that cursed light," he continued, whilst Griso executed his order, approaching as little as possible. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10333" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10339">"Diavolo! it troubles me more than I can say!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="6">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10340" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10360">Griso took the light; wished his master a good night, and went out in great haste, whilst his master drew himself under the coverlet. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="7">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10361" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10367">The coverlet, however, appeared to him a very mountain. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10368" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10380">He threw it off him, and composed his limbs for sleep; for, in fact, he seemed perfectly overpowered by weariness. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10381" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10408">Scarcely, however, had he closed his eyes than he suddenly awoke with a start, as though some one had given him a push; and he felt this uneasiness and the burning heat ever increase. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10409" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10471">He recurred to thoughts of the season, of the wine, of the debauch which he had just committed; in these he desired to find the cause of his illness. But there mingled itself with all his reflections one idea, which then occupied all minds, which had always formed part of the discourse held by this joyous company, for it was easier to turn it into ridicule, than to pass it over in silence — the idea of the pest. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="8">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10472" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10489">After having tossed about a long time, he at length fell asleep, and began dreaming the most horrible and tormenting dreams in the world. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10490" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10533">It appeared to him that he was in an immense church, in the midst of a vast crowd of people. He knew not how he came there, neither how this thought had entered his mind just upon such an occasion, and he grew enraged at the idea. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10534" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10566">He gazed upon those who surrounded him — nothing but pale, livid countenances, wild or dim eyes, hanging lips! The garments of these hideous beings scarcely concealed their forms, and through the rags were seen frightful blotches and plague spots. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10567" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10606">"Make way, you rascals!" he fancied he cried, gazing towards the door, which seemed far, far away from him; accompanying the cry with a menacing air, but without making the slightest movement, he only drew himself closer together, in order not to touch these loathsome creatures who were pressing upon him from every side. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10607" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10656">But none of these miserable beings gave the least sign, either of making way or even of having understood him; they pressed upon him still more; and worse than all, it seemed to him that some one among them struck him with his elbow on the left side, near his heart, where he immediately felt a sharp pang. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10657" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10676">He struggled to liberate himself, when suddenly he felt another pang shoot through the same place. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10677" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10724">Infuriated at this, he wished to draw his sword, but, behold! it appeared that the sword had glided along his side, and that the hilt was pressing in this very place. But placing his hand there, he did not find the sword; but at his touch he felt a still keener agony. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10725" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10744">Agitated and out of breath he was about to cry still louder, when all these visages appeared to direct themselves towards one particular object. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10745" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10795">He also looked; he perceived a pulpit, and in it some confused and ever-varying object; he saw arise and become distinct, first, a shaven head, then two eyes, a whole countenance, a long white beard; it was a friar standing upright in the pulpit—it was Fra Cristoforo! </note>
        </p>
        <p n="9">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10796" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10833">It appeared to Don Rodrigo, that the friar having glanced over all the assembly, fixed his eyes upon him, at the same time raising his hand precisely in the same attitude which he had once assumed in an apartment in Don Rodrigo's palace. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10834" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10870">He raised his also, in rage, he made one great effort, as though to precipitate himself forward, and avert this arm suspended over his head; a cry which had struggled in his throat escaped him, and he awoke. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10871" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10937">He let fall the arm which he had in reality raised; he had great difficulty in collecting his ideas and in opening his eyes, for the bright light of the advanced morning did not cause him less annoyance than the candle of the evening before. At length, however, he recognised his bed, his chamber; he comprehended that this was only a dream; the church, the people, the friar, all had vanished, all, except this pain in his left side. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10938" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10970">He felt a violent and distressing palpitation of his heart; there was a dull buzzing in his ears, an internal fire which consumed him, a greater heaviness in his limbs than even the night before, when he had laid himself down upon his bed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10971" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10997">He hesitated a moment before looking at the part where he felt the anguish; at length he uncovered it, cast one glance of terror at it, and saw a hideous tumour of a livid purple! </note>
        </p>
        <p n="10">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10998" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11026">Don Rodrigo saw that he was lost; the terror of death took possession of him, and together with this, the still stronger terror of falling a prey to the monatti, and of being thrown into the lazaretto. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11027" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11057">And seeking the means of avoiding this terrible fate, he felt his thoughts become confused, he felt that the moment was approaching when he would only possess consciousness enough to suffer despair. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11058" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11065">He seized the bell, and rang it violently. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11066" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11073">Griso, who stood upon the alert, immediately appeared. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11074" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11094">He paused at a certain distance from the bed, gazed attentively upon his master, and assured himself of what the evening before he had already conjectured. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="11">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11095" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11109">"Griso!" said Don Rodrigo, raising himself with difficulty in his bed, "thou hast always been my faithful attendant." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="12">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11110" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11111">"Yes, Signor." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="13">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11112" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11116">"I have always treated thee well." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="14">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11117" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11119">"Through your kindness." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="15">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11120" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11124">"I can confide in thee—!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="16">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11125" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11125">"Diavolo!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="17">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11126" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11128">"I am ill, Griso." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="18">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11129" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11131">"I have perceived that you were." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="19">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11132" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11148">"If I get better, I will shew thee still more kindness than I have ever yet done." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="20">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11149" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11162">Griso returned no reply, but waited to see whither all this preamble should lead. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="21">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11163" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11176">"I do not wish to make a confidant of any one but "thee," resumed Don Rodrigo; "do me a favour, Griso." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="22">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11177" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11186">"Command me," said the bravo, replying in his usual manner to this unusual mode of address. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="23">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11187" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11194">"Dost thou know where the house of the chirurgeon Chiodo is?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="24">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11195" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11197">"Very well." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="25">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11198" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11209">"He is a worthy man, who, if one only pays him well, preserves the secrets of the sick. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11210" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11242">Go and seek him; tell him I will give four, six scudi, for each visit—more if he ask it. Tell him to come here immediately. Manage all things prudently, so that no one shall suspect anything." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="26">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11243" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11251">"That is well thought of," remarked Griso; "I will go and return immediately." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="27">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11252" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11258">"Listen, Griso! give me first of all a little water. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11259" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11266">I am consumed with a heat which I can endure no longer." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="28">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11267" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11277">"No, Signor," replied Griso, "nothing without the advice of the physician. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11278" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11285">These are rapid diseases, there is no time to lose. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11286" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11294">Be quiet; in the twinkling of an eye I shall be here again with Chiodo." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="29">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11295" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11299">Having said this, he went out, closing the door after him. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="30">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11300" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11316">Don Rodrigo followed him in imagination to the house of Chiodo; he counted his steps, he calculated the time. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11317" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11333">Every now and then he looked at this spot, but always turned aside his head with horror. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11334" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11363">After some time he began to listen for the arrival of the surgeon; this force of attention suspended for awhile the sentiment of pain, and kept his thoughts from wandering. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11364" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11381">Suddenly he hears a distant sound of bells, which seems to approach from his rooms and not from the street. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11382" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11403">He listens again; he hears the sound grow stronger, and at the same time the tread of footsteps, and at once a horrible suspicion passes through his mind. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11404" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11478">He sits up in bed and listens still more attentively; he hears a dull sound in the neighbouring chambers, as of some burden which has been set down with precaution; he puts his legs out of bed as though about to rise; he does not move his gaze from the door; it opens, and he sees appear and advance towards him two old and dirty red garments, two cursed faces—in a word, two monatti! He partly sees also through the half-open door the countenance of Griso. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="31">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11479" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11483">"Ah, infamous traitor!—Away canaille! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11484" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11484">Biondino! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11485" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11575">Carlotto! help! I am murdered!" shouted Don Rodrigo, extending his hand under the pillow to seek a pistol; he seized one; but at his first cry the monatti had rushed towards him; the most agile is already upon him before he can make another movement; he snatches the pistol out of his hands, he flings it away, forces Don Rodrigo to lie down again, and holds him down, crying in a tone between rage and mockery, "Ah, villain! this against the monatti? against the ministers of the tribunal? against those who perform the work of mercy?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="32">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11576" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11589">"Hold him fast until we can carry him away," said the companion, going towards a strong chest. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11590" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11604">Upon this Griso entered, and began to assist him in breaking open the lock. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="33">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11605" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11637">"Scoundrel!" shouted Don Rodrigo, looking at him from underneath the one who was holding him down, and struggling violently in his nervous arms, "Only let me kill that infamous wretch," he at length said to the monatti, "and then you may do with me what you like." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="34">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11638" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11682">He then commenced calling with all the strength which yet remained to him upon his other attendants; but this was in vain, for the abominable Griso had sent them all far away, as though at the command of his master, before having proposed to the monatti that they should come with him and partake in the spoil. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="35">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11683" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11697">"Be quiet, be quiet," said the man who was then holding the unfortunate Rodrigo down upon his bed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11698" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11713">Then turning to those who were loading themselves with the booty, he cried, "Behave like honest people!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="36">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11714" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11735">"And thou—thou!" bellowed forth Don Rodrigo, when he saw Griso occupied in breaking open the chest, and bringing forth money and valuables to divide with his friends. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11736" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11740">"Thou after — — — Ah, devil of hell! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11741" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11745">I may still recover! I may still recover!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11746" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11763">Griso spoke not a word, and he even avoided as much as possible turning towards his poor master. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="37">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11764" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11772">"Hold him fast," said the other monatto; "he is out of his senses." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="38">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11773" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11776">And this was indeed true. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11777" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11810">After a last and still more violent effort to liberate himself, he fell back suddenly, exhausted and insensible; he still gazed around him like one under a spell, and every now and then either struggled feebly or moaned. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="39">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11811" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11851">The monatti took him, one by the feet, the other by the shoulders, and placed him on a handbarrow, which they had left in the neighbouring chamber. One of them returned immediately to fetch the booty; then raising their miserable burden, they bore it away. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="40">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11852" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11874">Griso remained behind to select in haste such articles as would be most to his taste; made all his spoil up into a bundle, and then departed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11875" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11920">He had been very careful neither to touch the monatti, nor to allow them to touch him; but in his thirst after gain he had removed from near the bed his master's clothes, and had, without reflecting upon the danger which he ran, shaken them to see whether they contained any money. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11921" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11951">He, however, reflected upon it the next day; for whilst carousing in a tavern, he was seized with a cold shiver, his eyes grew dim, he lost all power, and sank down. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11952" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11985">Abandoned by his companions, he himself fell into the hands of the monatti, who having robbed him of all he had about him, threw him into a cart, where he expired before reaching the lazaretto, whither his master had been carried. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="41">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11986" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12045">Leaving Don Rodrigo in this abode of woe, we must now go in search of another personage, whose history would never have been involved with that of Don Rodrigo, had not Don Rodrigo resolutely insisted upon it; nay, one might also pretty certainly affirm, that without this will of poor Don Rodrigo's there would have been no history whatsoever to relate — we mean Renzo, whom we left at his new manufactory, under the name of Antonio Rivolta. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="42">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12046" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12138">He had remained there about five or six months, when war being declared between the Republic and the King of Spain, and all fear on his account having ceased, Bartolo went in all haste to seek him, both because he was really attached to him, and because Renzo, who was a youth of talent and clever in his business, was of great use to *a factotum*, without his ever being able to aspire to such an honour himself, and all through this blessed misfortune of not knowing how to conduct a pen. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12139" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12151">As this little circumstance was among the motives which influenced Bartolo, we have felt obliged to state it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12152" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12163">Perhaps you would have liked a more ideal Bartolo. I can only say, fabricate one for yourself then. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12164" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12166">This Bartolo was such as we describe him. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="43">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12167" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12176">Renzo had then returned with his cousin, and worked with him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12177" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12220">More than once, and especially upon the receipt of Agnese's letters, he had been seized with the desire of turning soldier. And occasions for this were not wanting, for precisely at this epoch the republic stood in great need of recruits. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12221" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12265">The temptation had been all the stronger for Renzo, as just then the invasion of the Milanese States was spoken of, and naturally it appeared to him that it would be very fine indeed to return to his home as a conqueror, see Lucia, and come to an explanation with her. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12266" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12277">But Bartolo, with his many good arguments, had always known how to divert him from this resolution. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="44">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12278" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12311">"If they have to go there," he would say, "they can get there very well without thee, and thou canst follow after at thy ease; and if they return back with broken heads, will it not have been the best to remain away? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12312" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12321">People will not be found wanting. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12322" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12349">And,— before they can set foot — For myself I am very incredulous: they may boast—yes, certainly—but the Milanese is no mouthful to be so easily swallowed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12350" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12361">Spain is in the game, my good fellow; and dost thou know what manner of thing Spain is? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12362" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12372">San Marco is strong at home, but he is not strong enough. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12373" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12378">Have patience: art not thou comfortable here? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12379" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12401">I know what thou wouldst say; but if it is destined that the thing should succeed, be sure that by committing no follies it will succeed all the sooner. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12402" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12404">Some saint will aid thee. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12405" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12412">Only believe that this is no business for thee. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12413" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12423">Does it appear to thee proper to leave winding silk to go and kill people? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12424" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12431">What wilt thou do with this race of men? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12432" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12437">War requires men trained expressly to the business." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="45">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12438" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12466">At other times Renzo wished to travel there secretly, in disguise and under a false name; but Bartolo always managed to dissuade him from any such enterprise. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="46">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12467" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12541">The plague having at length spread itself through all the Milanese, and having reached the Bergamascan territory, did not delay—do not alarm yourself, good reader, lest I should relate to you the history of this plague also. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12542" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12585">All that I now say is, that Renzo caught the plague and cured himself, that is to say, he did nothing, but left all to nature. He was brought to the brink of the grave, but his good constitution conquered the strength of the disease, and in a few days he was out of danger. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12586" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12616">With his life, his anxieties, his desires, his hopes, his remembrances, and the projects of his life, returned with double force; and that is saying that his thoughts were more than ever fixed upon Lucia. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12617" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12630">What had become of her, in these miserable times when it was quite an exception to find a friend alive? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12631" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12639">And then to be within so short a distance of her, and yet know nothing of her. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12640" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12648">And to remain, God knows how long, in this uncertainty. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12649" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12703">And then even should this fear be calmed, should every danger have ceased, should he gain intelligence that Lucia yet lived, there was still this great mystery, this embarrassment of the vow! "I will go, I will go myself, and gain intelligence regarding all these points," said he to himself, long before he was in any condition to support himself. "Provided she only still lives! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12704" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12763">I will know how to find her out! I will hear from her own lips what sort of thing this promise is; I will make her comprehend that it is not binding. I will conduct her back with me here; and this poor Agnese, if she still lives! this poor Agnese, who has always wished so well by me, and who I are sure still wishes me well—but then the arrest?—those who remain alive have now other things to think about. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12764" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12780">Here even one sees certain people go about in safety, who Is there only security then for rogues! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12781" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12790">And at Milan, people say there is worse confusion. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12791" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12799">If I let such a fine opportunity slip, the pest! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12800" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12836">I shall never have such a good one again." "One must always hope, my dear Renzo." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="48">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12837" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12856">Scarcely could he drag himself along, when he went in search of Bartolo, who until the present time had succeeded in avoiding the plague, and had shut himself up in his house. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12857" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12872">He did not enter his dwelling, but, calling to him from the street, he made him approach the window. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="49">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12873" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12879">"Ah, ah!" said Bartolo, "thou hast then escaped. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12880" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12882">Thou art a fortunate fellow!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="50">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12883" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12899">"I am still rather weak in the legs, as thou mayst see; but I am quite out of all danger." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="51">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12900" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12906">"Ah! I should like to stand upon thy feet. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12907" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12921">Formerly to say, *I am well,* seemed to express every thing, now that counts but little. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12922" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12934">But when one can say, *I am better,* that is a fine thing!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="52">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12935" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12946">Renzo having prophesied a deal of good-luck for his cousin, imparted to him his design. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12947" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12981">"Go this time! and may heaven bless thee!" replied the cousin: "endeavour to avoid the officers of justice, as I seek to avoid the contagion; and if God wills that it should go well with both of us, we shall see each other again." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="53">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12982" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12990">"Oh! I shall certainly return; and O, if I should only not return alone! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12991" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12992">However, I will hope." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="54">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12993" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13010">"Return in company; for, God willing, there will be work enough for all, and we will form a pleasant little society. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13011" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13021">Heaven only grant that thou mayst find me here, and that this infernal influence may have ceased!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="55">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13022" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13028">"We shall meet again, we shall meet again; we must see each other once more." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="56">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13029" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13033">"Again I say, God grant that we may!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="57">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13034" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13061">For several days, Renzo took a deal of exercise, both to try and to increase his strength; and scarcely did he seem able to perform the journey before he set off. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13062" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13169">He placed underneath his clothes a belt containing the fifty scudi which had remained untouched, and which he had mentioned to no one, not even to Bartolo. He then took a few quattrini, which he had saved by exercising the most rigid economy; took under his arm a small bundle of clothes; put into his pocket a certificate, made out in the name of Antonio Rivolta, and given him by his second master; placed in a pocket of his breeches a large knife, the most harmless weapon an honest man might carry about with him in those unsettled times; and departed about the end of August, three days after Don Rodrigo had been carried to the lazaretto. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13170" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13207">He directed his steps towards Lecco, desiring before he went to Milan to call at his native village, where he hoped to find Agnese still alive, and could learn from her lips some of those things which he was dying to know. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="58">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13208" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13224">Those few who had recovered from the plague were looked upon by the rest of the population as a privileged class. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13225" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13271">A great portion of the survivors were either languishing or almost near death themselves; and those who until then had been respected by the disease, lived in a perpetual fear. They walked with precaution, they had an uneasy air, they hastened on with speed, yet hesitation, for every thing might turn into some deadly weapon of destruction for them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13272" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13384">Whilst those who had recovered, full of confidence, for it might sooner be said to be a miracle than a rarity to have the plague twice, advanced into the midst of the contagion with boldness and resolution; like the knights of the Middle Ages, who, clothed in steel, and mounted upon palfreys almost as strongly clothed in armour as their masters, wandered in search of adventure (from whence is derived their glorious denomination of knights errant), amidst a poor pedestrian crowd of peasants and serfs, who had only their garments to preserve them from the blows of their enemies. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="59">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13385" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13450">With such security, tempered somewhat by the solicitude which the reader already knows, and saddened by thoughts of the general calamity, Renzo approached his house, under a beautiful heaven and through a beautiful country; but he only rarely met with what might be sooner called wandering shades than living beings, or now and then perhaps a corpse carried to the grave without funeral honours, without a hymn, without attendants. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13451" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13474">Towards noon-day he rested in a little wood, to eat some bread which he had brought with him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13475" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13545">As for fruit, he had all along the road found far more than he required: figs, peaches, plums, apples, as many as he could desire; he had only to enter the fields and stretch out his hand to gather them from the trees, or pick them up from the ground, which seemed literally strewn with them, for this year was singularly abundant, especially in fruit, and there was scarcely any one left to think about caring for the crops. The grapes, one could almost say, concealed the vines, and were left to the discretion of the passer-by. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="60">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13546" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13551">Towards evening, Renzo discovered his native village. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13552" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13616">At this sight, already prepared for it as he was, his heart beat more rapidly. He was assailed suddenly by a crowd of sorrowful remembrances and sorrowful presentiment; he seemed still to hear the melancholy tolling of that bell which had accompanied, followed him when flying from his home, and yet at the same time he felt the death-like silence which reigned there. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13617" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13659">He was seized with still stronger emotion when he arrived upon the open space before the church; and he expected to be even more affected when he reached the end of his journey, for he intended to stop at the cottage which he had formerly been accustomed to call Lucia's cottage. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13660" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13684">Now it could, even under the most favourable circumstances, be no more than the cottage of Agnese; and the only boon he besought of heaven was to find this good woman there in health and in safety. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13685" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13709">He proposed to ask for lodging in this cottage, conjecturing truly that his own would now be only a fit habitation for rats and polecats. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13710" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13736">Not wishing to be seen, he struck into a by-path, the same along which he had gone in such good company the fatal night when they had surprised the Curate. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13737" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13769">About the middle of this road was situated on one hand Renzo's vineyard, on the other his little house. He was able thus as he passed by to enter for a moment and see how his affairs stood. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="61">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13770" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13830">As he walked along, he kept looking about him, anxious and yet fearful to meet with some one; after a few steps he saw a man in his shirt, seated upon the ground, his back supported against a jessamine hedge, his whole attitude was that of an idiot. By his air and then by his countenance he thought he recognised in him the poor silly Gervaso, who had gone as second witness in the unlucky expedition. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13831" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13846">But upon approaching nearer he perceived that it was the very bright Tonio who had conducted him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13847" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13879">The plague having deprived him both of his bodily and mental vigour, had developed both in his countenance and manner the faint resemblance which he had borne to his idiotic brother. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="62">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13880" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13888">"O Tonio!" cried Renzo, pausing before him; "is it thou?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="63">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13889" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13896">Tonio raised his eyes, without moving his head. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="64">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13897" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13900">"Tonio! dost thou not recognise me?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="65">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13901" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13914">"Is it my turn?" asked Tonio, remaining with his mouth open. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="66">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13915" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13924">"Poor Tonio! But dost thou not recognise me?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="67">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13925" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13937">"Is it my turn?" he again asked, with a silly smile. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="68">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13938" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13950">Renzo, seeing that he could get no other reply from poor Tonio, pursued his way still more oppressed with melancholy. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13951" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13968">All at once, at a turn of the road, he saw something black approaching, and immediately recognised this to be Don Abbondio. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13969" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14011">He was moving forward with slow steps, supporting himself upon his staff with the air of one who has great difficulty in dragging himself along. As he approached, it became evident from his pale and meagre visage, and from his every action, that he also had suffered from the tempest. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14012" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14080">Don Abbondio gazed at Renzo; he seemed to be the same, and yet not the same; there appeared to be something foreign in his apparel,—and this was precisely the foreign air which Renzo had brought with him from Bergamo. "It is certainly he!" said Don Abbondio to himself; and as he raised his hands towards heaven, with a movement of vexation and astonishment, the staff which he held in the right hand quivered in the air, and you saw his poor arms dance in the sleeves which formerly had been almost too tight for them. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="69">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14081" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14105">Renzo quickened his step and hastened towards him, making him a low bow; for, spite of the manner in which they had parted, he was still the pastor. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="70">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14106" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14111">"Are you here?" exclaimed Don Abbondio. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14112" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14116">"I am here as you perceive. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14117" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14121">Is nothing known about Lucia?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="71">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14122" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14127">"What would you have one know about her? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14128" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14142">Absolutely nothing is known about her, only she is at Milan, if she is still in this world. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14143" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14144">But you—?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="72">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14145" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14148">"And is Agnese still alive?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="73">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14149" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14159">"She may be. But what would you have me know? She is not here. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14160" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14160">But——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="74">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14161" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14161">"Where is she?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="75">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14162" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14187">"She is gone to stay in the Valsassina, with her relations at Pasturo, you know; for people say that there the plague does not make such fearful ravages as here. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14188" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14194">But you, I say——" "I am sorry for this. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14195" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14198">And then, Father Cristoforo—" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="76">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14199" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14205">"Has been gone away some time. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14206" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14206">But——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="77">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14207" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14221">"I know that; they wrote me word all about it; I only asked if in case he were returned." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="78">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14222" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14229">"Oh, certainly! Nothing more has ever been heard of him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n189" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14230" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14231">But you——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="79">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n190" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14232" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14236">"I am very sorry for that." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="80">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n191" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14237" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14250">"But for the love of heaven, tell me what you are come to do here. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n192" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14251" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14256">Do you not know all about that little affair of the arrest——?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="81">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n193" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14257" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14258">"What does that matter! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n194" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14259" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14262">People have other things to think about now. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n195" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14263" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14273">I wanted to come and look after my affairs. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n196" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14274" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14278">And it is not precisely known——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="82">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n197" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14279" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14310">"What then do you want to see? Now-a-days, there is no longer any one, there is no longer any thing; and then, as I said before, is it wise, with this little affair of the arrest hanging over you, to come here, precisely into this place, into the very den of the wolf? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n198" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14311" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14357">Listen to the advice of an old man who has more wisdom than yourself, and who speaks from the love he bears you. Escape quickly, before any one sees you; return from whence you came. If any one happens to have seen you already, return even still more quickly. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n199" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14358" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14365">Do you imagine that this air will be good for you? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n200" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14366" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14378">Are you not aware that they came to seek you here; that they have sought and sought; that they have turned every thing topsy-turvy——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="83">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n201" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14379" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14383">"I know this all only too well, the rascals!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="84">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n202" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14384" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14385">"Then wherefore——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="85">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n203" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14386" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14393">"But if I tell you that I don't think about it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n204" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14394" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14400">And that man, is he still alive? is he here?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="86">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n205" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14401" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14418">"I tell you that no one is here; I tell you no "longer to think about affairs of this place; I tell you that—" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="87">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n206" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14419" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14423">"I demand whether he is here." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="88">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n207" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14424" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14428">"Oh, holy heaven! speak in a different manner. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n208" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14429" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14439">Is it then possible that after all these misfortunes you can be so fiery?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="89">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n209" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14440" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14443">"Is he here, or is he not here?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="90">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n210" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14444" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14446">"He is not here, then. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n211" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14447" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14453">But the plague, my son, the plague! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n212" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14454" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14462">Who is he who dares to wander about in these times?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="91">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n213" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14463" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14481">"If there were nothing but the plague in the world—I speak for myself: I have had it, and am safe." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="92">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n214" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14482" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14489">"And are not such dangers warnings to you? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n215" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14490" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14506">When one has escaped a danger of this kind, it appears to me one ought to thank heaven, and—" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="93">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n216" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14507" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14509">"I sincerely thank heaven." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="94">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n217" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14510" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14516">"And not go in search of others, I say. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n218" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14517" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14520">Follow my advice—" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="95">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n219" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14521" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14529">"You have also had the plague, Signor Curato, if I do not mistake." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="96">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n220" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14530" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14532">"Whether I have had it? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n221" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14533" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14551">Yes, that I have, the most terrible, the most infamous plague; it is indeed a miracle that I am still here. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n222" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14552" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14579">I have just now great need of a little quiet to recover myself: however, I am beginning to get a little better—In the name of heaven what are you come to do here? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n223" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14580" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14580">Return—" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="97">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n224" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14581" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14586">"You always have recourse to your returns. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n225" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14587" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14593">I should have had no need to stir myself, if I must return immediately. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n226" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14594" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14598">You keep asking why are you come? why are you come? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n227" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14599" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14605">Oh, excellent! I am come home." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="98">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n228" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14606" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14607">"Come home—" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="99">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n229" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14608" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14614">"Tell me, are many people dead here?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n230" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14615" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14632">"Ah, ah!" exclaimed Don Abbondio; and commencing with poor Perpetua, he enumerated a long list of individuals, and even entire families, who had been swept away. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n231" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14633" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14661">Renzo certainly had expected something similar; but hearing all these names of acquaintance, friends, relations, he was seized with deep grief, and with a bowed head, continued to exclaim every moment: "poor fellow! poor girl! poor things!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="100">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n232" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14662" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14669">"Ah, you see!" cried Don Abbondio, "and it is not yet come to an end. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n233" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14670" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14694">If those who remain don't adopt a little wisdom, and chase all silly whims out of their heads, this will be nothing less than the end of the world." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="101">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n234" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14695" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14704">"Don't trouble yourself; I am not intending to remain here." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="102">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n235" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14705" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14713">"Ah! heaven be praised that you have still a little sense left. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n236" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14714" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14723">And now return immediately to the Bergamascan——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="103">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n237" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14724" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14729">"I am not thinking of that." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="104">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n238" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14730" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14739">"How! you are not going to commit a still greater piece of folly?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="105">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n239" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14740" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14756">"Don't you trouble yourself about it, I tell you. It concerns me; I am no longer a child; I have the use of my reason. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n240" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14757" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14767">I trust, however, that you will not mention to any one that you have seen me. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n241" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14768" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14777">You are a pastor, I am one of your flock; you will not betray me." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="106">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n242" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14778" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14786">"I understand," said Don Abbondio, sighing in an angry manner, "I understand. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n243" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14787" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14792">You wish to ruin yourself and me into the bargain. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n244" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14793" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14810">Neither all that you nor myself have suffered is then sufficient for you. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n245" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14811" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14814">I understand, I understand." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n246" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14815" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14828">And continuing to mutter these last words between his teeth, he pursued his road. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="107">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n247" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14829" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14840">Renzo remained sad and discontented, reflecting where he should find a place of repose. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n248" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14841" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14883">Among the families enumerated by Don Abbondio, there was one which had entirely perished, with the exception of one member, a youth about the age of Renzo, and his companion in childhood. The cottage stood removed a few paces out of the village. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n249" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14884" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14886">Renzo thought that he would try his fortune there. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="108">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n250" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14887" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14906">Going along, he passed by his vineyard; and from its exterior he could easily infer in what state it was. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n251" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14907" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14934">The trees which he had left no longer looked over the wall; all that was to be seen were weeds, which had sprung up in his absence. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n252" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14935" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14950">He approached a gap (there was no longer any trace of a gate), he cast a glance around,—alas, poor vineyard! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n253" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14951" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14971">During two winters in succession, the peasants had come to fetch firewood out of that poor lad's vineyard, as they expressed it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n254" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14972" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14986">Vines, mulberry trees, fruit trees of every kind, all had been lopped in the most dreadful manner, or cut up at the roots. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n255" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14987" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15096">There, however, remained the traces of former cultivation; young layers, or suckers from the mulberry, fig, peach, and plum trees, scattered sparingly among, and almost suffocated by, a new variegated and prolific generation of plants, which had sprung up without the aid of man—nettles, ferns, darnels, dog-grass, wild oats, the amaranthus, the succory, wild sorrel, and many other similar plants, which the peasants of all countries have, according to their manner, formed into one large class, calling them weeds, or something of that kind. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n256" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15097" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15151">There was indeed a medley of stems, some trying to shoot one above the other high into the air—others creeping along the ground, and stealing for themselves a place by any means; a strange confusion of leaves, flowers, and fruits, of a hundred colours, of a hundred forms, of a hundred sizes; in ears, in bunches, clusters, round, oval, white, red, yellow, blue. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n257" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15152" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15270">Some plants higher and more conspicuous, but which were not of much greater value, detached themselves from the vulgar crowd: there was the Turkish vine, higher than all the rest, with its long reddish branches, with its luxuriant dark green leaves, some already edged with purple, with its pendant bunches of fruit, the lower berries a deep violet colour, higher up lilac, then green, and the topmost sprays crowded with white blossoms: the mullein with its woolly lower leaves, with its stem directed towards heaven, and its long cone scattered, or rather starred over with bright yellow flowers; thistles with their leaves and branches full of thorns, with their prickly calixes from whence issued tufts of white or purple flowers, or whence were borne away by the winds the light and feathery seeds. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n258" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15271" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15366">Here a quantity of bindweed had attached itself to the young shoots of a mulberry, and had entirely covered them with its pendant leaves and elegant white bells; there a wild gourd, with its scarlet fruit, had twisted itself round the young shoots of a vine, which, having in vain sought a more solid support, now in its turn twisted its tendrils round the gourd, and mingling their weak stems and similar leaves, they both alternately dragged each other down, as often happens with the weak who lean for support upon each other. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n259" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15367" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15404">Ivy was everywhere — it stretched from one plant to another, climbing, descending, entangling or extending its branches, according to the opposition it encountered; and having arrived at the very limits of the vineyard, seemed as though it would dispute the entrance even with the master himself. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="109">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n260" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15405" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15429">He, however, did not care about entering such a vineyard; and very likely he did not pause to look at it as long as we have taken to describe it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n261" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15430" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15455">He hastened from this melancholy spectacle; at a short distance was his cottage; he traversed the little garden, walking up to his knees in weeds, with which it was as completely covered as the vineyard. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n262" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15456" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15498">He set foot on the threshold of one of the two rooms which were situated on the ground-floor. At the sound of his footsteps a number of enormous rats fled in affright and concealed themselves in the filth which covered the floor. The room was still as it had been left by the soldiers. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n263" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15499" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15505">Renzo glanced towards the walls, they were incrusted with the vilest filth, and blackened with smoke. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n264" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15506" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15514">He raised his eyes towards the ceiling, it was a perfect tapestry of cobwebs! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n265" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15515" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15517">There was nothing else left for him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n266" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15518" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15567">From this scene he also hastened; he turned back through the garden, treading in the same track which he had made for himself a few moments before; he pursued another small path to the left which led to the fields, and without encountering a living soul, he arrived near the house where he had thought of stopping to rest himself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n267" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15568" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15572">Night was already coming on. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n268" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15573" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15602">His friend was at the door seated upon a small wooden bench, his arms folded, his eyes directed towards the heavens, he appeared a man confounded by misfortune, grown wild through solitude. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n269" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15603" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15648">Hearing a footstep, he turned to see who there might be, and as the twilight and foliage prevented his distinguishing who was the newcomer, he cried in a loud voice, "Are there no other people than I? Have I not done enough yesterday? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n270" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15649" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15659">Leave me quiet for a little while, that will also be a work of mercy." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="110">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n271" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15660" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15671">Renzo, not comprehending what this meant, replied by calling him by name. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="111">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n272" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15672" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15678">"Renzo!—" cried the friend, at once exclaiming and interrogating. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="112">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n273" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15679" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15685">"Yes, it is he," said Renzo, and they flew towards each other. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="113">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n274" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15686" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15699">"Is it really thou!" cried the friend when they had approached each other. "O how happy I am to see thee! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n275" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15700" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15702">Who would have thought it? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n276" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15703" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15717">I took thee for Paolin of the dead, who is always coming to torment me about burying people. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n277" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15718" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15727">Dost thou know that I am left alone! alone! alone! alone, like a hermit!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="114">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n278" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15728" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15733">"I know it only too well," replied Renzo. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n279" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15734" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15748">And embracing and exchanging questions and replies they had entered the poor cottage together. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n280" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15749" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15775">As soon as they were there, without suspending the discourse, the friend commenced making in honour of Renzo such preparations as the time and season permitted. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n281" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15776" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15806">He placed water upon the fire, and began to make the polenta; then gave Renzo the roller to stir it with, and disappeared saying, "I am left alone,—ah, I am left alone!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="115">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n282" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15807" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15850">He soon returned, bringing with him a small pail of milk, a little salted meat, a little cream cheese, and a few figs and peaches. They placed all these good things and the polenta upon the table, returning mutual thanks, one for the visit, the other for the reception. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n283" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15851" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15914">And thus, after an absence of two years, they found that they were dearer friends than ever they had imagined themselves to be, even when they used to meet every day; for, observes the manuscript, they had both since that time experienced suffering, which teaches what balm benevolence is to the human soul. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="116">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n284" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15915" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15959">Certainly, however, no one could supply to Renzo the place of Agnese, or console him for her absence, not alone on account of his old and peculiar affection for her, but also because she alone could explain one among the many things which he so anxiously desired to know. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n285" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15960" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16017">He hesitated a moment whether he should continue his journey, or whether he should go in search of Agnese, since she was at so short a distance; but, considering that Agnese would be unable to give him any information regarding Lucia's health, he determined to act according to his first resolution, proceed direct to Milan, remove all doubt from his mind, hear Lucia pronounce his sentence, and then bear intelligence of her to her mother. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n286" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16018" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16075">However, he learned from his friend many things regarding which he was yet in ignorance, and many things concerning Lucia's adventures and the persecutions which she had experienced were explained to him; he also heard how Don Rodrigo had disappeared, and not again shewn his face in that part of the world. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n287" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16076" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16149">He learned also (and this was for Renzo information of no small importance) how properly to pronounce the name of Don Ferrante. Agnese, it is true, had caused her secretary to write the name, but heaven only knows how it had been written; and the Bergamascan interpreter, in reading the letter, had pronounced it so strangely that, had Renzo gone with this word in his mouth, when seeking the family in Milan, he would most probably have found no one who could have divined the object of his search. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n288" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16150" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16162">Nevertheless, this was the only clue he possessed whereby he could discover Lucia's abode. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n289" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16163" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16215">As far as the law was concerned, he was enabled to assure himself that all danger was far distant: the Signor Podestà had died of the plague—who knew when another would be nominated? Most of the constables and officers of justice had also perished, and the few who yet remained had other things to think about than such old affairs. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="117">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n290" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16216" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16236">He in his turn related his adventures to his friend, and received in exchange a hundred anecdotes, about the march of the army—the plague—the anointers—and the wonders. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n291" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16237" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16278">"These are horrible things," remarked the friend, accompanying Renzo into a chamber which the contagion had depopulated; "things which one should never have expected to see; things to destroy the happiness of one's whole life; still, however, it is a great consolation to talk about them with a friend." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="118">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n292" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16279" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16319">At the break of day the two friends were all ready in the kitchen: Renzo equipped for his journey, with his girdle concealed under his doublet, and his knife in the pocket of his breeches; he left his bundle in deposit with his host. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n293" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16320" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16379">"If all goes well," said he, "if I find her alive, if —— I return this way, I will hasten to Pasturo, and tell the good news to Agnese, and then—and then— But if, by mischance—which God forbid!—then I shall not know what to do; I shall not know where to go; however, you will certainly not see me again in these parts." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n294" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16380" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16411">And saying this, standing upon the threshold, he raised his eyes, and gazed with mingled tenderness and anguish upon the sunrise, which gilded his native mountains — a glorious vision, to which he had for so long a time been a stranger. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n295" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16412" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16439">The friend counselled him, as is customary, to hope for the best, wished him to take something to eat, then accompanied him a short way on his journey, and took leave of him with many good wishes. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="119">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n296" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16440" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16465">Renzo pursued his road at a gentle pace, for he could easily reach this day the immediate neighbourhood of Milan, and early the next morning enter the city, and directly commence his search. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n297" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16466" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16486">His journey was made without any accident or any occurrence which could distract his thoughts beyond the usual misery and suffering. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n298" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16487" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16507">He paused at noontide in a little wood, as he had done the day before, to eat a mouthful and repose himself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n299" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16508" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16531">Passing through Monza, he purchased two loaves at a small shop, where he saw bread exhibited for sale. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n300" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16532" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16578">The baker signed to him not to enter, extended a small shovel towards him, upon which stood a little porringer, which contained vinegar and water, telling Renzo to place the money in it, and this being done he with a pair of tongs presented the two little loaves, one after another, which Renzo consigned to his pockets. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="120">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n301" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16579" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16646">Towards evening he arrived at Greco, without knowing its name however; but, with the little he remembered of his former journey, and by calculating the distance he had come from Monza, he conjectured that he could not be far distant from the city. He quitted the high-road for the fields, and went in search of some hut where he might pass the night, for he would not again embarrass himself with inns. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n302" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16647" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16667">He found a better accommodation than he had gone in search of; he perceived an opening in the hedge which surrounded the yard of a dairy, he entered it boldly. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n303" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16668" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16711">There was no one about, he saw in one corner a large shed, with a deal of hay piled up under it, against which leaned a ladder; he cast a glance around, then mounted; arranged himself for the night, and, in fact, immediately fell asleep, only to wake at daybreak. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap33-n304" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16712" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16771">Then approaching the edge of this immense bed, he thrust out his head, and perceiving no one, he descended the ladder by which he had mounted, and passed out through the opening by which he had entered, and commenced his journey, taking the Cathedral for his polar-star. After a short walk, he reached the walls of Milan, between the Eastern and the New Gate. </note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>