<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CHAPTER XXXVIII.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>1845</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed Lovers: a Milanese Story of the Seventeenth Century. With The Column of Infamy by Alessandro Manzoni. In Three Volumes</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
          <date>1845</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Henry Francis C. Logan</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="English_1845_cap38">
        <p n="1">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10021">One evening Agnese heard a carriage pause before the door. "It is certainly Lucia!" cried Agnese; and in truth it was Lucia, accompanied by the good widow. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10022" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10028">The reader can imagine their meeting. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="2">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10029" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10054">The following morning Renzo arrived very early, entirely ignorant of what had happened, and came merely to console himself a little with Agnese during Lucia's long delay. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10055" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10073">His behaviour and his words when he really found that she was arrived, we will also leave to the reader's imagination. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10074" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10088">Lucia's demonstrations of joy were such as require but little description. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10089" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10099">"I salute you, how are you?" said she, with her eyes cast down, and without betraying much emotion. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10100" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10114">But do not imagine that Renzo considered this too cold a reception, or became alarmed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10115" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10151">He rightly understood her meaning; and, unlike well-educated people, who know how to believe half the compliments which are paid them, Renzo comprehended very well that these words did not express all that passed in Lucia's heart. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10152" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10174">Besides, it was very easy to perceive that Lucia had two ways of pronouncing these words; one way for Renzo, and the other for the rest of her acquaintance. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="3">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10175" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10194">"I am very well when I see you," replied the young man, in an old cut-and-dried phrase, which, however, in this instance happened to be original. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10195" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10219">"Our poor Father Cristoforo!" said Lucia, "pray for his soul; for one may be nearly sure that he is now praying for us above." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="4">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10220" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10239">"I only expected as much," said Renzo; and this was not the only sorrowful chord they touched upon in their discourse. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10240" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10252">But let the subject of their discourse be whatsoever it might, it always in the end became delightful and gay. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10253" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10318">Time with them resembled fiery horses, which prance about, raising first one foot and then the other, replacing them upon the same spot, and making a thousand gambols without advancing one step, when all at once they will start forth in their course, and away like the wind! At first, moments had appeared hours; now hours appeared moments. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="5">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10319" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10353">The widow, far from spoiling the company, added greatly to the general enjoyment; and certainly, Renzo when he first saw her lying in that miserable bed, could never have imagined her of so social and jovial a disposition. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10354" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10367">But, the lazaretto and the country, death and a wedding, are not one and the same thing; she had already formed a friendship with Agnese. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10368" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10409">It was a real pleasure to see her with Lucia, at once tender and gay, and then how she gently bantered her, yet scarcely sufficient to oblige Lucia to shew all the joy that lay concealed in her heart. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="6">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10410" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10424">Renzo at length said that he would go to Don Abbondio and concert arrangements for the marriage. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10425" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10455">He went, and with a certain air, half-jocular, half-respectful, "Signor Curato," he said, "has that bad headache left you, on account of which you told me you could not marry us? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10456" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10526">Now it is time, the bride is here, and I am come to learn when it will be "agreeable to you; but this time I pray you to make haste." Don Abbondio did not say no; but he began to assign certain excuses, to insinuate a hundred things: why place himself in the market-place and have his name cried aloud, when this arrest was hanging over him? why could not the marriage be celebrated equally well elsewhere? and this and the other thing. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="8">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10527" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10543">"I understand," said Renzo, "you have still a little of this headache remaining; but listen, listen." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10544" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10565">And he began to describe the state in which he had seen poor Don Rodrigo, and how he must certainly have already departed this life. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10566" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10574">"Let us hope," concluded Renzo, "that the Lord will have shewn him mercy." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="9">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10575" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10588">"That has nothing to do with the subject," said Don Abbondio; "did I refuse? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10589" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10599">I did not say no: I speak—I speak because I have good reasons. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10600" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10640">For the rest, you see that as long as a man breathes—Look at me, I am a cracked vessel; I was nearer dead than alive, and yet I am still here; and, if fresh misfortunes do not overpower me, I may still hope to remain here a little longer. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10641" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10654">I imagine then certain temperaments; but as I said before, that has nothing to do with the subject." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="10">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10655" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10703">After some other remarks, neither more nor less conclusive, Renzo took his leave with a very beautiful bow, returned to his friends, made his relation, and ended by saying, "I have come back, fearing I might lose my patience, and not pay him proper respect." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10704" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10734">Several times he appeared precisely the Don Abbondio of the former time; he had his same excuses, his same reasons; I am sure had the conversation lasted much longer, he would have brought his Latin again into the field. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10735" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10754">I see that this will be a long business; it would be better to do as he advises, go and be married where we mean to live." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="11">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10755" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10776">"Do you know what we will do?" said the widow. "I should like us women to go and make another trial, and see whether we shall succeed any better. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10777" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10789">Besides, I have a great desire to know this man, if he is such as you describe. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10790" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10801">I should like us to go after dinner, so as not to fall upon him immediately. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10802" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10856">Now, sir bridegroom, take us a little walk whilst Agnese is busied; I will act mother to Lucia; and really I have a great desire to see something more of these mountains, and of this lake of which I have heard so much, and the little I have already seen appears to me so beautiful." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="12">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10857" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10891">Renzo conducted them first to the house of his host, where was another scene of happiness; and they made the friend promise that he would come, not only this day, but every day if he could, and dine with them. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="13">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10892" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10899">After having walked and dined, Renzo suddenly disappeared, without saying where he was going to. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10900" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10941">The women remained a short time consulting upon the best manner to surprise Don Abbondio; and, at length, they hastened to the assault. "Here they are!" said the poor Curate to himself, when he saw them appear; but he put on a good face; offered many congratulations to Lucia, many salutations to Agnese, and many compliments to the stranger. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="14">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10942" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10998">He begged them to be seated, and then immediately began speaking about the plague. He wished to learn from Lucia how she had passed through that painful time; the lazaretto gave him an opportunity of drawing into conversation the one who had been her companion there; then, as was but natural, Don Abbondio also spoke of his own misfortune; and then he offered unbounded congratulations to Agnese upon having had the happiness to escape. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10999" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11031">The discourse was growing long; from the very commencement the two women had been upon the watch for an opportunity of introducing the important subject; at length one of them broke the ice. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11032" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11034">But what could you expect? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11035" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11040">Don Abbondio was deaf to such subjects. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11041" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11060">He did not exactly say no; but there he was again, with his doubts and his difficulties, hopping like a bird from branch to branch. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="15">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11061" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11067">"It would be necessary," said he, "to remove this sentence of arrest. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11068" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11150">You, Signora, who are from Milan, must know more or less the course of these things; you must have some powerful protector, some patron of influence; by these means all wounds may be healed. If, after all, they wish to take the shortest road, without embarking themselves in any more misfortunes; since these young people, and our Agnese, here, have the intention of leaving their country (and, I can only say, one's country is where one is well off), it appears to me that all can be done in the new country, where there is no sentence of arrest to prevent them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11151" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11165">I long to see this match concluded; but I should like it concluded well and tranquilly. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11166" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11197">I speak the truth; here with this unhappy arrest hanging over him, which every one knows, to pronounce from the altar this name of Lorenzo Tramaglino, is a thing which I could not do with an easy conscience; I should be afraid of doing him an ill service. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11198" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11202">You see yourself, my good lady, you see, my good friends." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="16">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11203" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11245">Here Agnese and the widow began combating his arguments, and Don Abbondio bringing them again into the field, but under another form. It was all the old scene over again; when Renzo suddenly entered with a decided step, and the air of one who brings news, saying, "The Lord Marquis of — has arrived." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="17">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11246" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11255">"What is the meaning of that? where has he arrived?" demanded Don Abbondio, rising. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="18">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11256" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11280">"He has arrived at his palace, formerly Don Rodrigo's; he is the heir by feoffment, as they say; so you see there is no longer any doubt about the matter. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11281" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11294">For myself I should be satisfied if I could only know that this poor man died well. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11295" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11318">Until now I have said *Paternosters*, now I will say for him *De profundis.* And this Lord Marquis is a most excellent man." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="19">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11319" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11339">"Certainly," said Don Abbondio; "I have more than once heard him called a worthy gentleman, a man of the old sort. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11340" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11344">But is it really true?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="20">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11345" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11356">"You believe the Sacristan?" "Why?" "Because he has seen him with his own eyes. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="22">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11357" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11380">I was in the neighbourhood; for, to confess the truth, I went thither because I thought something might be known there about Don Rodrigo. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11381" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11387">More than one person told me the same thing. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11388" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11405">And then I met Ambrogio, who was coming down himself, and he had seen him, as he says, acting the master. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11406" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11409">Will you listen to Ambrogio? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11410" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11415">I have made him wait outside on purpose." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11416" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11419">"Let us hear," said Don Abbondio. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11420" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11446">Renzo went and called the Sacristan, who entirely confirmed everything, added fresh details, dissipated all doubts, and then departed. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="23">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11447" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11456">"Ah! then he is really dead! he is really gone!" exclaimed Don Abbondio. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11457" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11466">"You see my children, whether Providence does not watch over all! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11467" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11487">What a great event! what a repose for this poor country! for no one could live in peace with him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11488" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11535">This plague has been a great scourge; but it has also been a good broom; it has swept away certain individuals, my children, from whom we could never have delivered ourselves; young, vigorous, strong; one might almost have said, that he who was destined to perform their obsequies was still in the seminary, learning his Latin lessons. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11536" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11546">In the twinkling of an eye they have disappeared a hundred at a time. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11547" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11582">We shall no longer see him wandering about with his Hectors behind him, with his ostentation, with his haughty airs, with his upright body gazing at the multitude as though they were only on the earth for his pleasure. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11583" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11591">Now, he is no longer here—yet we are. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11592" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11598">He will never again send such embassies to honest men. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11599" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11612">He has led us a miserable life of it, and now we dare open our mouths." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="24">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11613" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11620">"I have pardoned him with all my heart," said Renzo. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="25">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11621" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11639">"And thou hast done thy duty," replied Don Abbondio; "but thou canst also return thanks to heaven for having liberated us. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11640" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11651">To return, however, to yourselves; do what you consider best. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11652" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11670">If you desire me to marry you, here I am; if you like to do otherwise, do as you think fit. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11671" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11715">As to the arrest, I "see myself, that there being no longer any one who watches you or desires to do you evil, it is not a thing about which you need trouble yourselves much; especially since this act of grace was published on the birth of the most serene infant. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11716" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11731">And then the plague! the plague! This plague has effaced many things. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11732" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11764">Therefore if you like (to-day is Thursday) on Sunday I will publish your banns; for what happened on the former occasion now no longer counts for anything after such a length of time; and then I shall have the happiness of marrying you." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="26">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11765" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11774">"You know that we are come precisely for that," said Renzo. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="27">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11775" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11787">"Very good; I will serve you; and I will immediately inform his Eminence." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="28">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11788" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11793">"Who is his Eminence?" asked Agnese. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="29">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11794" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11806">"This Eminence," replied Don Abbondio, "is our Cardinal Archbishop, whom God preserve." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="30">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11807" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11872">"Oh! as to that, excuse me; for although I am a poor ignorant woman, I can assure you that he is not called so; for when we went the second time to speak to him, just as we might speak with you, one of the priests drew me aside, and instructed me how I was to address him, and told me that it was proper to say *Your Most Illustrious Lordship,* and *My Lord.*" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="31">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11873" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11912">"And now, if he were to instruct you, he would tell you to address him as his Eminence: do you understand? For the Pope, whom God also preserve! since the month of June has prescribed this title for the Cardinals. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11913" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11920">And do you know what induced him to form this resolve? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11921" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11947">It was owing to *Most Illustrious,* which was the title of the Cardinals, and of certain other princes, having, do you see, become so common;" and you know how willingly people assume it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11948" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11953">And what could the Pope do? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11954" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11956">Deprive all of it? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11957" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11967">That would only have occasioned remonstrances, hatred, trouble, misfortune, and after all, things would only have gone on as before. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11968" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11973">Therefore he discovered an excellent expedient. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11974" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12007">By little and little, the title of Eminence was given to bishops, then the abbots desired it, then the rectors, for such is the ambition of man; all desire to mount, always to mount! next the canons— </note>
        </p>
        <p n="32">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12008" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12013">"And then the curates," remarked the widow. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="33">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12014" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12040">"No, no," replied Don Abbondio, "the curates draw the cart: don't be alarmed lest the curates should be permitted to acquire bad habits; they will be their Reverence until the end of the world. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12041" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12068">I should be less surprised if the nobles, who are accustomed to hear themselves addressed as Most Illustrious and to be treated as Cardinals, should some day desire the Eminence for themselves. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12069" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12077">And if they should desire it, do you see, there will be plenty of people who will give it them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12078" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12092">And then the Pope who shall be then, will find something else for the Cardinals. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12093" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12110">But let us return to our affairs; on Sunday I will publish your banns in church; and meanwhile, do you know how I have thought of serving you? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12111" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12118">We will ask for a dispensation from the two other announcements. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12119" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12138">They must have a busy life of it there down in the court of justice, granting dispensations, if things go on everywhere as they do here. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12139" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12155">For Sunday, I have already—one—two—three; without counting you, and others may still arrive. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12156" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12170">No one wishes to live alone. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12171" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12189">Perpetua committed a great folly dying just then; for now is the moment, when even she might have found a customer. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12190" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12199">And at Milan, Signora, I imagine it must be the same. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="34">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12200" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12211">"Certainly: only imagine that in my parish last Sunday the banns for fifty couples were published!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="35">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12212" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12219">"Yes, indeed; the world will not come at an end. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12220" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12230">And, my good lady, have no hornets begun already to hum about you?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="36">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12231" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12240">"No, no; I don't think about such things, neither do I wish to." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="37">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12241" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12247">"Yes, yes; for you wish to be peculiar. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12248" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12252">Even Agnese, you see, even Agnese —" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="38">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12253" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12260">"Ah, you wish to joke," returned she. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="39">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12261" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12273">"Certainly, I wish to joke; and it seems to me that it is at length time. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12274" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12305">We have passed terrible days, have we not, my young friends? terrible days; and now we will hope that the few which yet remain for us on this earth may be happier. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12306" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12355">But, fortunate are you, who still have time left you to talk of past woes! I instead, am old, and — scoundrels may die; one may recover from the plague; but there is no remedy for old age; and as they say; *senectus ipsa est morbus.*" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="40">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12356" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12368">"Now," said Renzo, "you may talk as much Latin as you like; it no longer matters to me." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="41">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12369" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12403">"Thou art still quarreling with my Latin; well, well, I will manage that. When thou shalt come before me with this young girl on purpose to hear certain Latin words, I will say, — 'thou dost not like Latin; depart in peace.' </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12404" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12405">Will that please thee?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="42">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12406" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12443">"Ah, I know what I say!" replied Renzo: "it is not that kind of Latin that frightens me; that is a sincere, sacred Latin, such as the Latin of the mass. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12444" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12460">I speak of this rascally Latin, out of the church, which falls upon one treacherously in the midst of a discourse. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12461" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12506">For example, now that we are here, now that all is at an end, translate for me into the vulgar tongue, the Latin which you kept repeating, here in this very corner, when you gave me to understand that you could not marry us, and that many others were wanted!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="43">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12507" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12526">"Hush! you malicious fellow, hush! Don't begin reviving such subjects; for if we had to settle accounts, I don't know which of us would be in debt most to the other. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12527" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12540">I have pardoned every thing: we will speak no more about these affairs; but you played me plenty of tricks! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12541" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12567">Such conduct from thee does not astonish me, for thou art a good-for-nothing fellow; but I speak of this still-water, this little saint, this little Madonna, whom to have distrusted would have appeared a sin. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12568" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12581">But I know who instructed her, I know, I know." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12582" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12608">Saying this, he pointed to Agnes with his finger, which he had at first directed towards Lucia; and it would be impossible to describe with what a kind and pleasant air he made these reproaches. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12609" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12665">This news had inspired him with a joy, a flow of words which had for long been unusual to him; and we should be still far from the end, did we wish to report the remainder of this discourse, which he lengthened out, more than once detaining the company, who desired to depart, and pausing at the door to speak of trifles. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="44">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12666" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12720">The following day he received a visit, not less agreeable than it was unexpected. This was from the Marquis, of whom we have spoken; a man in middle life, whose appearance answered to the report of fame—open, courteous, placid, humble, dignified, and yet with a certain air of resigned melancholy. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12721" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12729">"I come," said he, "to bring you salutations from the Cardinal Archbishop." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="45">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12730" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12735">"O what condescension in both of you!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="46">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12736" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12772">"In taking leave of this incomparable man, who honours me with his friendship, he spoke to me of two young people of this parish, who were betrothed, and who have suffered much misery, owing to poor Don Rodrigo. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12773" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12776">My lord desired to have intelligence regarding them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12777" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12784">Are they alive? and are their affairs settled?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="47">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12785" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12787">"Every thing is settled. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12788" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12801">I had even proposed myself to write word to his Eminence: but now that I have the honour —" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="48">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12802" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12804">"Are they here?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="49">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12805" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12815">"Yes, here; and as soon as possible they will be man and wife." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="50">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12816" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12836">"And I pray you to be so good as to tell me whether I can be of service to them, and also to inform me of which will be the most suitable manner. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12837" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12857">Through this calamity I have lost my two only sons and their mother, and have become heir to three considerable fortunes. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12858" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12882">Even before these sad events, I enjoyed a superfluity of riches: therefore you see that affording me an occasion to employ my wealth, and especially an occasion such as the present, is really doing me a service." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="51">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12883" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12893">"Heaven bless you! why are not all —? but enough. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12894" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12925">I also thank you from my heart for these poor children; and since your illustrious lordship allows me to be so bold, I have, my lord, an expedient to suggest, which will not perhaps displease your lordship. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12926" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12982">Know then, that these good people are resolved to fix their abode elsewhere, and to sell the little property which they have here: a vineyard belonging to the young man, of about nine or ten perches, but wholly untilled; you can count upon the land, but nothing more; besides this, there is a small house belonging to him, and another to his bride; two mere rat-nests! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12983" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13000">A lord such as you cannot know how hard it goes with the poor when they wish to dispose of their possessions. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13054">The news always reaches the ears of some scoundrel, who has perhaps been gazing for some time with longing eyes at these few yards of land, and who when he hears that the other has a desire to sell, draws back and often succeeds in buying it for a morsel of bread, especially in circumstances like the present. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13055" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13067">The Lord Marquis will already have perceived the aim of my discourse. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13068" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13089">The greatest charity which your most illustrious lordship could do for these people is to extricate them from this embarrassment, by buying their small property. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13090" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13124">I, to confess the truth, give an interested piece of advice, since you see by this means I should receive into my parish your lordship as a parishioner; but your lordship will decide as appears best to you. I have spoken to obey your lordship." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="52">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13125" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13170">The Marquis most warmly praised this suggestion, thanked Don Abbondio, and prayed him to fix the price, and to fix upon a very high one. He then increased the good man's astonishment, by proposing that they should immediately proceed together to Lucia's house, where most probably the lover would be also. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="53">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13171" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13187">On the road, Don Abbondio, filled with joy, as you may well imagine, thought of and proposed another kind deed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13188" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13208">"Since your illustrious lordship is so much inclined to do good to these people, there is still another service you might render them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13209" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13299">There is a writ of arrest, a sort of banishment hanging over the young man, for some prank which he played at Milan two years ago, on the day of the great commotion, in the midst of which he had, without any evil intent, out of pure ignorance, found himself, just like a rat in a trap: it was nothing serious, you see; mere childish follies; he is incapable of doing any real evil; and this I can say, who have baptised him, and seen him grow up. And then, if your lordship would like to amuse yourself by hearing these poor people relate their adventures after their own manner, you could get them to tell their history, and then you will hear. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13300" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13342">Now as the offence is an old affair, no one will trouble himself about it; and besides, as I said before, the young man thinks of leaving the country; but in time, if he should return here, who can tell? it would certainly be best to find himself entirely free. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13343" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13362">The Lord Marquis is considered in Milan as a just man, and a powerful knight, and a great gentleman as he is——. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13363" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13375">No, no! allow me to speak, for truth must be spoken. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13376" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13391">A recommendation — a word from one like you, is more than necessary to obtain a complete discharge." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="54">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13392" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13398">"There are no strong charges brought against this young man?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="55">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13399" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13402">"No, no; don't imagine so. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13403" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13423">For the first moment people were very hot against him; but now I believe it is nothing more than a simple formality." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="56">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13424" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13436">"Such being the case, the thing will be very easy; and I willingly undertake it." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="57">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13437" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13447">"And yet your lordship does not like one to call "you a great man. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13448" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13459">I say it, and I will say it; in spite of you I will say it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13460" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13479">And even were I myself to keep silence, that would serve nothing, for already every one says the same thing; and *vox populi, vox Dei.*" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="58">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13480" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13486">They found, in truth, the three women and Renzo. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13487" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13521">I leave you to imagine the astonishment of these four individuals! Nay, I even believe that these bare rough walls, the paper windows, the wooden benches, and the various cooking utensils, wondered at receiving among them such an extraordinary visitor. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13522" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13539">The Marquis began the conversation by speaking of the Cardinal and of other things with open cordiality, yet, at the same time, with measured delicacy. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13540" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13549">He then went on to make the proposition about which he was come. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13550" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13600">Don Abbondio, besought by him to name the price, after hesitating some time, after some ceremony and excuses; that it was not his affair, that he could only give a rough guess, that he only spoke to obey his lordship, that he would refer it to some one else, at length made a proposal. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13601" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13728">The purchaser said, that for his part he was very well satisfied, and, as though he had misunderstood, named double the sum; he would not allow his mistake to be rectified, and cut short, or concluded every remark, by inviting the company to dinner at his castle the day after the wedding, where the agreement should be drawn up in form. "Ah!" said Don Abbondio to himself, when he had returned home, "if the plague always and everywhere altered things after this manner, it would, indeed, be a sin to call it an evil. There should almost be a plague every generation; nay, one would even endure falling sick oneself—to recover again, however." The dispensation was procured, the discharge granted, and the happy day having at length arrived, the Betrothed proceeded with an air of triumphal security to their own church, where, by Don Abbondio's own lips, they were pronounced husband and wife. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="59">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13729" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13770">Another, and still more singular triumph, was their visit to the castle; and we leave the reader to imagine what thoughts must have passed through their minds during the ascent thither, at their entrance through that portal; and what were the remarks made by each, according to his or her peculiar character. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13771" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13795">We will only notice, that in the midst of their joy, now one, and now another remarked, that, to complete the happiness of the festival, poor Father Cristoforo was wanting. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13796" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13805">"But," added they, "he himself is certainly happier than we." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="60">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13806" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13853">The Marquis received them with great attention; he conducted them into a dining hall, placed the married pair at table, together with Agnese and the good widow; and before retiring to dine elsewhere with Don Abbondio, stayed a short time with his guests, and even assisted in waiting upon them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13854" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13872">Let no one, however, take it into his head that it would have been much simpler to have had merely one table. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13873" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13898">I have told you that he was an excellent man, but not what would now be called an original; I have told you that he was humble, but not that he was a prodigy of humility. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13899" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13918">He was humble enough to wait upon these good people, but not to appear their equal. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="61">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13919" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13947">After the two dinners, the contract was prepared by a doctor, but this was not *Azzecca-garbugli!* He, or rather I should say, his remains, were and are still at Canterelli. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13948" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13963">And for such of my readers as are not out of that part of the country, I myself feel that an explanation is requisite. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="62">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13964" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14019">About half-a-mile above Lecco, and almost on the borders of the other village called Castello, is a place called Canterelli, where two roads cross; on one side of this place is seen an eminence, an artificial mound, with a cross upon it; and this is no other than an immense heap of dead bodies, the bodies of those who perished from the contagion. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14020" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14046">It is true tradition only says simply, of those who died during the plague; but assuredly it must be this plague of which we write, for it was the most terrible, and the last which is remembered. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14047" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14061">And you know very well, that traditions, unless you assist them, say but little by themselves. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="63">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14062" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14083">On their return there was nothing disagreeable, except that Renzo was somewhat incommoded by the weight of the quattrini which he carried away with him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14084" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14092">But, as you already know, he had endured far greater misfortunes. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14093" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14110">We will not speak of the labour of his mind (which, however, was not little), in considering which would be the best way to employ his money. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14111" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14146">To have seen all the various projects which passed through his mind, his reflections, his imaginations, and to have heard his reasons for and against agriculture or trade, you would have fancied that two academies of the last century had met for argument. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14147" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14195">But for him the embarrassment was by far greater, for being but one man, it was impossible to say to him, "What need is there to select? both one and the other are excellent; in substance both means are the same; they are two things like legs; two walk better than one." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14196" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14220">Now nothing more was to be thought of but packing up their possessions, and setting forth on their journey; the Tramaglino family for their new country, and the widow for Milan. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14221" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14231">Tears, expressions of gratitude, and promises to meet again, were many. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14232" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14258">Not less tender, with the exception of tears, was the leave-taking of Renzo with his friendly host; and do not imagine that the separation from Don Abbondio was a cold affair. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14259" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14282">These good creatures had always preserved a certain respectful attachment for their Curate; and even he, in the bottom of his heart, had always wished them well. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n189" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14283" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14290">It was all these blessed affairs which had troubled their affection. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="64">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n190" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14291" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14323">Some one may ask whether they experienced no grief at quitting their native village and mountains; certainly they did, for doubtlessly this grief is felt by all. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n191" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14324" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14350">However, it could not have been very strong, since they might have avoided it by remaining at home, now that the two great impediments, Don Rodrigo and the sentence of banishment, had been removed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n192" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14351" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14367">But already for some time they had accustomed themselves to regard as their home, the country whither they were going. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n193" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14368" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14392">Renzo had brought it into favour with the women, relating all the facilities which were there offered to workmen, and a hundred things about the delightful life that was led there. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n194" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14393" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14443">Besides, they had all of them passed many bitter moments in the country upon which they had turned their backs; and still the sorrowful memories of those times embittered the scenes connected with them. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="65">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n196" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14499" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14517">What will the reader say when he hears that Renzo had scarcely arrived and settled himself in his adopted country, before he found fresh annoyances ready prepared for him? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n197" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14518" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14528">These were vexations doubtless; but little is requisite to disturb a happy condition. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n198" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14529" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14534">Here, in a few words, is the cause of his trouble. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="66">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n199" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14535" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14599">The great talk which Lucia had occasioned in the place, long before she arrived there; the knowledge of Renzo's having endured so much for her sake, and his firmness and constancy; perhaps also a few words spoken by some partial friend, had given rise to a certain curiosity about the young girl, and had excited great expectation of her beauty. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n200" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14600" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14640">You know very well what kind of a thing is expectation; it is imaginative, credulous, and confident; and when disappointed, difficult to satisfy, and scornful: it never meets with as much as it desires, because, in fact, it does not know what it would have. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n201" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14641" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14688">When Lucia, therefore, appeared, many who believed she must have hair like very gold, cheeks like roses, and the most splendid eyes in the world, began to shrug their shoulders and turn up their noses, saying, "Ah, is this the girl? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n202" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14689" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14698">After so much time, so much talk, one expected something better. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n203" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14699" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14700">What is she then?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n204" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14701" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14704">A peasant girl, like many others. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n205" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14705" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14714">Why, there are plenty as handsome, and handsomer than her, everywhere. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n206" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14715" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14738">Then examining her minutely, one discovered this defect, another that; there were some even who found her ugly. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="67">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n207" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14739" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14758">However, as no one went and said these things to Renzo's face, there was no great evil so far. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n208" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14759" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14778">But what caused the mischief were certain remarks that got reported to him; and Renzo, as was but natural, was touched to the quick. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n209" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14779" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14805">He began to reflect upon these remarks, and complain about them, both to those who talked with him and to himself:— "What then does it concern you? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n210" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14806" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14810">What, did I say you should expect so much? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n211" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14811" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14823">Did I ever come to talk to you about her? to tell you that she was so beautiful? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n212" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14824" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14841">And when you asked me, did I ever tell you more than that she was an excellent girl? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n213" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14842" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14844">She is a peasant! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n214" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14845" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14853">Did I ever say that I should bring you a princess? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n215" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14854" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14859">She does not please you? then don't look at her. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n216" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14860" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14886">You have beautiful women, look at them." And only see how sometimes a trifle is enough to decide the condition of a man for the whole of his life! </note>
        </p>
        <p n="68">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n217" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14887" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14907">Had Renzo been obliged to pass his in this place, according to his first design, he would not have led a very gay one. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n218" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14908" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14915">From having been disgusted, he now, in his turn, became disagreeable. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n219" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14916" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14928">He was uncivil with every one, for each acquaintance might be one of Lucia's critics. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n221" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14954" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14989">There was something indescribably sardonic in all his words; in every thing he also found something to criticise; so that did it happen to rain two days together, he would exclaim, "O the delightful country!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n222" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14990" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15043">He was become disagreeable to all, even to persons who at first had wished him well; and in time, what with one thing and another, he would have found himself at war with almost all the population, without perhaps himself being aware of the first cause of so great an evil. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="69">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n223" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15044" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15059">But it might be said that the plague had taken upon itself to repair all his follies. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n224" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15060" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15114">It had carried off the master of another silk manufactory, situated almost at the gates of Bergamo; and the heir, a dissipated young fellow, who throughout the whole edifice could find nothing amusing, had determined to sell it even for half its value; but he desired to have the money paid immediately, in order to employ it directly in unproductive gratification. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n225" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15115" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15163">This reached the ear of Bartolo, and he hastened to see the manufactory; he treated—a better bargain could not be imagined: but then the condition of prompt payment spoilt all, for the money which he had laid aside, by little and little, was still far from amounting to the necessary sum. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n226" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15164" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15183">He partly gave his word to the proprietor; hastened back with speed; communicated the affair to his cousin, and proposed to him to join in the undertaking. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n227" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15184" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15203">Such an excellent proposal as this entirely put an end to Renzo's economical doubts, for he immediately decided upon trade, and agreed to his cousin's idea. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n228" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15204" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15210">They went together, and the agreement was made. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n229" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15211" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15261">When the new masters settled on their new property, Lucia, whom no one expected, not only escaped all critical remarks, but one may say that she did not even displease; and Renzo learned that more than one person had asked, "Have you seen the beautiful simpleton who has come here?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n230" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15262" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15266">The epithet made him pass over the substantive. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="70">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n231" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15267" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15280">And even the annoyance he had experienced in the other place remained a useful lesson for him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n232" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15281" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15302">Before, he himself had been a little too ready in passing his judgment, and was easily led to criticise other people's wives, or, in fact, anything else. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n233" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15303" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15331">Now he had learned that words spoken and heard are two different things; and he accustomed himself to reflect a little upon his own before he uttered them. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="71">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n234" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15332" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15342">Do not, however, imagine that even here our friends were exempt from all trouble. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n235" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15343" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15416">"Man," says our Anonymous—and the reader will already have learned from experience that he takes a strange pleasure in moralising on similar themes; and as this is for the last time, we will pardon him—man, as long as he remains on this earth, resembles a patient who lies upon a couch, more or less uneasy, and who, seeing around him others well made, smooth and level on the outside, imagines that upon them he must find greater repose. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n236" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15417" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15454">But should he even succeed in changing his quarters, scarcely is he settled before he begins to feel here something pricking, there something pressing against him; in short, he finds himself in pretty much the same condition as before. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n237" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15455" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15478">And on this account, adds the Anonymous, one ought to think more about doing well, than being well, and then in the end we shall find ourselves happy. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n238" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15479" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15494">This is certainly somewhat far-fetched, and belonging to the taste of the seventeenth century; but in the main he is right. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n239" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15495" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15549">Henceforth, continues he, there were for our good people no sorrows nor embarrassments of equal importance with those which we have related; they continued to lead so tranquil and happy a life, that were we to describe it, you would be wearied to death. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="72">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n240" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15550" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15576">Affairs on the whole, however, went on very well: at first there was a little trouble owing to the scarcity of workmen, and to the mistakes and pretensions of the few they could procure. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n241" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15577" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15598">Edicts were published, limiting wages; but, spite of all this, things in the end took a better course. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n242" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15599" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15634">Another and more reasonable edict arrived from Venice, exempting for ten years all strangers who should come to dwell in the Venetian States, from every kind of taxation. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="73">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n243" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15635" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15675">Before the end of the first year of their marriage, a beautiful creature came into the world; and as if to afford Renzo the opportunity of fulfilling his magnanimous promise, it was a little girl; and you can easily imagine that it was called Maria. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n244" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15676" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15717">In the course of time others made their appearance, I do not know how many, and of both sexes; and Agnese, carrying them about with her, one after the other, called them little rogues and smothered them with kisses. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n245" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15718" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15744">They were all well-disposed children; and Renzo wished them all to learn to read and write, saying, that since there was such a rascally thing in the world, they might at least profit by it. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="74">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n246" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15745" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15770">It was delightful to hear him relate his adventures, and to hear how he always concluded by telling the important pieces of experience he had learned. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n247" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15771" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15838">"I have learned," said he, "not to rush into tumults; not to preach in the market-place; not to drink more than I require; not to hold the knocker of a door in my hand when hot-headed people are about; and not to fasten a little bell to my feet before reflecting what may arise out of it." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n248" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15839" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15841">And a hundred other things. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="75">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n249" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15842" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15864">Lucia did not find this doctrine false in itself, but it did not satisfy her; it seemed to her that there was still something wanting. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n250" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15865" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15891">And having many times heard this same song, and having every time reflected upon it, she said one day to her moralist, "And what have I learned? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n251" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15892" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15907">I did not go in search of my misfortunes, they came in search of me. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n252" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15908" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15929">Unless," added she, sweetly smiling, "my folly was in wishing you well, and in promising myself to you." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="76">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n253" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15930" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15934">Renzo, at first, remained somewhat embarrassed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n254" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15935" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15992">After a long debate, and much reflection, they at length concluded, that misfortunes often arise from our own misconduct; yet that frequently the greatest prudence and innocence do not suffice to guard us from them; but that when they do come, either owing to our own fault or not, confidence in God softens them, and renders them useful in preparing us for a better life. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n255" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15993" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_16016">This conclusion, although it was drawn by poor peasants, appears to us so just, that we have thought of placing it here as the moral of our history. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="77">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n256" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_16017" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_16037">If this history should not have entirely displeased you, feel some kindly sentiment towards the Anonymous, and the one who has arranged his papers. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap38-n257" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_16038" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_16051">But if on the contrary, we have only succeeded in wearying you, rest assured that this was not our design. THE END OF THE BETROTHED. </note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>