<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CHAPTER XXXI.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>1845</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed Lovers: a Milanese Story of the Seventeenth Century. With The Column of Infamy by Alessandro Manzoni. In Three Volumes</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
          <date>1845</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Henry Francis C. Logan</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="English_1845_cap31">
        <p n="1">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10041">The plague, which the Tribunal of Health had feared might enter the Milanese with the German troops, had in truth entered with them. It is also well known, that it did not confine its ravages to the Milanese states, but invaded and desolated a good part of Italy. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10042" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10091">Conducted by the thread of our narrative, we now pass on to the relation of the principal events of this great calamity, as far, at least, as it affected the Milanese, or one might add, Milan almost exclusively; for, strange to say, the memoirs of those times treat almost exclusively of the city. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10092" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10146">And in this relation, to speak the truth, our object is not alone to describe the circumstances in which our characters were placed; but also to give, as far as we can in a brief form, a relation of a passage in Italian history which is more famous than understood. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="2">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10147" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10177">Among all the relations given by contemporary writers, there is not a single one, which in itself suffices to give the reader a clear and distinct idea of this fearful scourge. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10178" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10288">For each of these relations, not even excepting that of Ripamonti, which is far superior to all the rest, both from its length, from his selection of facts, and still more from his mode of observation; in every one of these relations, I say, are omitted essential facts, which fortunately, however, are to be found registered in others; in all are material errors, which may be recognised and rectified by the aid of some other, or by the few public edicts which yet remain. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10289" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10353">Through all these reigns a strange confusion both regarding times and events; there is a continual hastening from one circumstance to another, a want of a general design and of a clear arrangement of ideas. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10354" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10452">Strange to say, no writer of a later age has proposed to himself the examination and collation of these memoirs, so as to compile a connected series of events, a concise history of this plague. No wonder is it therefore, that the generally received idea of it should be somewhat confused; an idea but ill-defined, of the great evils and the great errors of those times (and to say the truth, both one and the other are almost beyond the power of imagination), an idea more founded upon judgments than upon facts. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10453" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10561">We, examining and collating with much diligence, if with nothing else, all the printed relations, more than one unedited one, and many official documents, have sought to draw up, not exactly such an account as might be wished, but something more than has yet been done. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10562" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10621">We have only endeavoured to signalize and verify the general and most important facts, to dispose them in the real order of their succession as far as reason and their nature will permit, to observe their mutual operation, and, in short, give a brief, but sincere and continuous, statement of this public disaster. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="3">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10622" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10639">Throughout the whole length of country traversed by the army had various corpses been found in the houses, and some upon the road. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10640" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10666">Shortly after, in this and in that village, people began to fall sick and die; single individuals, whole families, attacked by violent and strange pains, attended by symptoms unknown to the greater part of the survivors. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10667" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10708">Only a few old people remembered to have seen them before; and these few were those who had witnessed the plague which three and fifty years previous had desolated a good part of Italy, and especially the Milanese, where it was called and even still bears the name of San Carlo's plague. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10709" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10713">How powerful is the influence of charity and love! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10714" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10784">Amidst the various and solemn memories of a general calamity, it can cause the name of a single man to stand pre-eminent, for it has inspired this man with sentiments and actions even more memorable than these very evils; imprint this name in the hearts of thousands, as an epitome of all these woes, for it has caused him to appear as guide, benefactor, a living example, a voluntary victim; has made a public calamity for this man a glorious enterprise, and bestowed his name upon this misery, as though it were a conquest or a discovery! </note>
        </p>
        <p n="4">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10785" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10851">The first physician, Lodovico Settala, who had not only seen this plague, but who had, spite of his extreme youth, been one of the most active and intrepid of the medical attendants, now having his suspicions excited, made vigorous inquiries; and, on the 20th of October, informed the Tribunal of Health, that in the district of Chiuso (the last district in the territory of Lecco, and adjoining the Bergamascan frontier), the contagion had indubitably shewn itself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10852" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10868">According to Tadino, not one single resolution was formed upon the announcement of this danger. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10869" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10878">Immediately similar intelligence arrived from Lecco and Bellano. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10879" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10908">Upon this the Tribunal deliberated, and contented themselves by despatching a commissary, who, pursuing his route, should procure a medical man at Como, and carry him along with him to visit the various places indicated. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10909" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10961">Both of these, "either through ignorance or something else, allowed themselves to be persuaded by an ignorant old barber of Bellano, that this manner of sickness did not belong to the plague;" but was in some places caused by the autumnal exhalations from the marshes, in others by the misery and deprivations endured by the inhabitants during the march of the German troops. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10962" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10978">His assurance, reported to the Tribunal, appears to have set their minds at ease. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="5">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10979" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11008">But fresh and unceasing accounts of death in various quarters constantly arriving, two delegates were again sent forth to examine and take the necessary precautions; these were Tadino and another member of the Tribunal. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11009" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11028">When they arrived, the evil had propagated itself so fast, that examples presented themselves without their having the trouble of searching for them. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11029" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11101">They traversed the territory of Lecco, the Vallassina, the shores of the lake of Como, the districts denominated the Monte di Brianza, and the Gera d'Adda; and everywhere they found villages barricaded or utterly deserted. The inhabitants had fled, or were encamped in the fields, or dispersed; "they appeared," remarks Tadino, "so many wild creatures, every one carrying in his hand either a sprig of mint, of rue, of rosemary, or perhaps a phial of vinegar." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11102" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11123">They inquired after the number of deaths —the amount was terrific. They visited the sick and the dead; and they only too plainly discovered the signs of the pestilence. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11124" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11183">This melancholy intelligence was immediately communicated by letter to the Tribunal, who immediately upon its receipt, the 30th of October, "prepared," says the physician Tadino, "to prescribe the warrants for closing the gates of the city upon people arriving from those villages where the contagion had manifested itself." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="6">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11184" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11222">Meanwhile, the delegates in all haste employed those measures which appeared to them the best; but at length returned with the sorrowful persuasion that they would not suffice to remedy or arrest the progress of an evil which was too far advanced and too broadly diffused. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="7">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11223" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11252">Having arrived, on the 14th of November, the Tribunal ordered these commissioners to present themselves before the Governor, and explain to him the state of affairs. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11253" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11281">He replied that their communications caused him sorrow, that he was very much affected by them, but that the cares of war were much more pressing. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11282" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11317">This was the second time, if the reader remembers, that a similar reply had been returned to a similar application. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11318" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11374">Two or three days later, he published a proclamation, ordering public rejoicings to celebrate the birth of the Prince Carlo, eldest son of Philip IV., without imagining or troubling himself about the danger incurred by allowing such a vast concourse of people to assemble under the present circumstances; all was conducted as in ordinary times, and as though no fear of contagion had been entertained. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="8">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11375" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11449">This man, as we have already said, was the celecelebrated Ambrogio Spinola, and had been sent to conduct the war to a happier issue, to repair the errors of Don Gonzalo, and incidentally to govern; and here we may recall to our readers' minds that he died a few months later, in the midst of this same war, which he had always had so much at heart; and died, not of his wounds on the field of battle, but in his bed, of vexation and anger at the reproaches, the severe remonstrances and annoyances of every kind, which he had met with from those he served. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11450" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11501">History has deplored his fate, and blamed that ingratitude to which he fell a victim; she has described with much diligence his military and political enterprises, has praised his foresight, activity, and perseverance; but she should have at the same time inquired what use he made of all these fine qualities when the plague menaced, invaded a whole population, delivered over to his care, or rather to his mercy? </note>
        </p>
        <p n="9">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11502" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11545">But what diminishes our astonishment at his indifference, is the indifference of the people themselves, of that portion at least of the population who were not yet attacked by the contagion, but who had every reason to dread it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11546" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11601">At the fatal intelligence which arrived from those villages which were so terribly infected with it, from villages which formed as it were a semicircle round the city, and which at some points were not distant more than eighteen or twenty miles; who would not have expected a general emotion, a desire to take every precaution, or at the very least an unproductive anxiety? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11602" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11620">And yet if the memoirs of those times agree upon one point, it is to assure us that such was not the case. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11621" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11664">The famine of the preceding year, the exactions of the military, and mental suffering, appeared in the eyes of the world causes more than sufficient for this mortality; in the public squares, in shops, in houses, he who breathed a word regarding danger, or hinted at the plague, was received with a smile of incredulity, or with a scorn mingled with anger. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11665" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11685">The same disbelief, or rather let us say, the same blindness, the same obstinacy, prevailed in the Senate, in the Council of Ten, and in every magistracy. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="10">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11686" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11758">Cardinal Federigo, however, had scarcely received intelligence of the first cases of this contagious sickness, than he enjoined, among other things, in a letter addressed to his different curates, their making the people feel the urgent necessity of revealing every such death, and of consigning the infected or suspicious effects to the proper authorities; and this act also may be counted among his praiseworthy singularities. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="11">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11759" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11770">The Tribunal of Health besought, implored co-operation, but it obtained little or none. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11771" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11824">And even in the Tribunal itself, the eagerness was very far from being equal to the urgent necessity: it was only two physicians, affirms Tadino many times, who, persuaded of the gravity of the danger, stimulated the rest of the body, who in their turn endeavoured to stimulate others. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="12">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11825" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11859">We have already seen, upon the first announcement of the plague, how coldly the authorities commenced operation, and the search after information; here is another instance of slowness almost as preposterous, if it were not rather occasioned by obstacles raised by the superior magistrates themselves. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11860" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11884">The proclamation to prevent the entrance of strangers into the city had been projected on the 30th of October, had not been decreed until the 23rd of the following month, and was not published until the 29th. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11885" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11891">The pest had already entered Milan. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="13">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11990" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12012">Our historians, both one and the other, relate that it was an Italian soldier in the service of Spain, who first introduced the plague; for the rest, they are not agreed, even regarding his name. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12013" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12039">He was, according to Tadino, one Pietro Antonio Zovato, out of the territory of Lecco; according to Ripamonti, one Pier Paolo Locati, from Chiavenna. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12040" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12071">They also differ regarding the day of his entrance into Milan: the former considers it the 22d of October, the latter about a month later; but one can rely upon neither one nor the other. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12072" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12082">Both epochs are at utter variance with others which are much better authenticated. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12083" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12124">Yet Ripamonti, writing at the command of the Council of Ten, must have had many means of gaining necessary information; and Tadino, by reason of his charge, might more easily than any one else have informed himself regarding a fact of this description. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12125" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12175">Suffice it, however, to say, that upon comparing other and more exact data, we discover this happened even before the publication of the proclamation already mentioned; nay, even were it necessary, we could prove, or very nearly, that it must have been in the early days of the same month. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="14">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12176" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12246">Let that have been as it may, this unfortunate soldier, and bearer of misfortune, entered Milan with a large bundle of clothes, bought or stolen from German soldiers; he went to lodge with some relations in the suburb of the Eastern-gate, near to the Capuchin convent; but scarcely had he arrived, when he fell sick, and was carried to the hospital, where a plague-spot, which shewed itself below the arm-pit, excited the suspicion of his medical attendant. The fourth day he died. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="15">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12247" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12274">The Tribunal of Health commanded the house which he had inhabited to be condemned, and his relatives to be confined within it. His clothes and the bed upon which he had died at the hospital were burned. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12275" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12298">Two servants, who had waited upon him, and a good friar who had visited him, fell ill a few days afterwards, and all three of the plague. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12299" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12330">The suspicion which had been entertained from the first in the hospital, and the precautions used in consequence, prevented the contagion from propagating itself farther there. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="16">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12331" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12345">But the soldier had left without the hospital, seeds which were not long in germinating. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12346" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12392">The first whom it attacked was the master of the house where he had lodged, Carlo Colonna, a player on the lute. Upon this all the inhabitants of the house were conducted to the lazaretto, by command of the Tribunal of Health, where the greater number fell sick; several died in a short time, evidently of contagious disease. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="17">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12393" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12462">The seeds which had been disseminated by these first victims, through their furniture carried away by relatives, by the landlord, by people in their service, or also at the search and burning instituted by the Tribunal, to say nothing of fresh infection brought into the city, caused the plague secretly and slowly to circulate through the population all the rest of that year, and in the first months of the following one, 1630. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12463" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12513">From time to time, now in this quarter, now in another, some persons were attacked with it, and others died; but the very rarity of these cases prevented all suspicion of the pest, and only confirmed the multitude the more in their stupid and murderous confidence that there was no such thing. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12514" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12565">Many physicians also, echoing the cry of the people, derided the gloomy omens, and threatening warnings of the few. They had always ready the names of common diseases with which to qualify every case of plague which they might be called upon to attend, whatever might be its symptoms. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="18">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12566" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12623">Information of these cases, if it reached the ears of the Tribunal, generally arrived too late, and was for the most part very uncertain. The terror of the lazaretto sharpened all wits; the sick were concealed; the grave-diggers and their superintendents were corrupted; false certificates even were purchased from the subalterns of the Tribunal itself, who were deputed by it to inspect the dead bodies. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="19">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12624" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12685">Yet upon every discovery which they succeeded in making, the Tribunal ordered the burning of property, the sequestration of houses, the sending of whole families into the lazaretto; therefore it is easy to infer what must have been the anger and murmurs of the people, of the nobility, of the merchants, and of the lower classes, persuaded as they all were, that these were only useless and ridiculous annoyances. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12686" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12720">The principal odium fell upon Tadino and the senator Settala, son of the head physician; and to such a height had this feeling risen in the public mind, that they could no longer traverse the public squares without being insulted, if not stoned. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12721" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12781">And certainly the condition of these men was most singular, and deserves to be mentioned; for months they saw adadvancing this horrible scourge, exerted themselves in every manner to avert its progress, and everywhere encountered obstacles, where they sought assistance and good-will, and were made at once the sport of the decrees, and proclaimed enemies of their country. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="20">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12782" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12810">A portion of this odium fell also upon those other physicians who, also convinced of the reality of the contagion, suggested precautions and sought to communicate their sorrowful certainty to others. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12811" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12834">The more discreet accused them of credulity and obstinacy; for the others, all this was manifest imposture, a cabal by which to get rich upon the public fear. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="21">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12835" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13033">The head-physician, Lodovico Settala, at that time little less than eighty years of age, who had been professor of medicine at the university of Pavia, then professor of moral philosophy at Milan, author of many works of high reputation, and who had been solicited as professor by the universities of Ingolstadt, Pisa, Bologna, and Padova, had nearly fallen a victim to this popular fury. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="22">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13034" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13087">One day, as he was going in his litter to visit his patients, the people began to assemble around him, crying that he was the head of those who would insist that the plague was in the city, and that it was he who caused all this alarm with his long face, and all to give the doctors something to do. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13088" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13112">The crowd and their fury continued to increase; and the bearers of the litter, perceiving how affairs stood, fled with their master to the house of one of his friends, which fortunately was near at hand. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13113" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13208">All this happened to him, because, having seen clearly the real danger incurred by the city, he had spoken boldly, and would have saved many thousands of lives; whilst, when once by his miserable counsel he had co-operated in causing a poor unhappy girl to be tortured, pinched with hot pincers, and burnt for a sorceress, because one master with whom she lived felt strange pains in his stomach, and another former master had been desperately enamoured of her, he had only won fresh praises for wisdom from the populace, and what is intolerable to think of—a new title of merit. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="23">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13209" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13271">But towards the end of March, at first in the suburb of the Eastern-gate, and then in other quarters of the city, illness and death, accompanied by strange spasms, palpitations, lethargy, delirium, and those sad livid plague-spots, began to be more frequent. And these deaths were mostly rapid, violent, and not rarely unexpected and unattended by any previous sign of disease. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13272" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13353">The physicians who had been opposed to the opinion of contagion, not wishing now to confess that which they had derided, and yet being forced to give a generic name to this new disease, which had become too general and too manifest longer to remain without one, fixed upon that of malignant fever, of pestilential fever—a miserable transaction this cheat of words, and one which did infinite mischief; for, feigning to recognise the truth, it still prevented that from being believed which it was the most important should be both believed and seen, the fact that this disease attacked people by means of contact. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13354" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13391">The municipal authorities, like people awakened out of a profound sleep, began to pay a little more attention to the proposals of the Tribunal, and set about seeing their edicts put into execution, as well as the sequestrations and quarantines prescribed by the Tribunal. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13392" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13436">The Tribunal also besought a continuation of supplies for the daily increasing expenses of the lazaretto, and for other uses; and it besought them of the Council of Ten, inasmuch as it was decided that such expenses should belong to the city, or the royal treasury. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13437" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13503">Moreover, the High-chancellor, at the command of the Governor, who had again departed to lay siege to this poor Casale, solicited the Council of Ten; the senate solicited that they should consider the means of victualing the city before the contagion, unhappily having spread itself, they should be cut off from all intercourse with other places; and that they should also find the means of maintaining a considerable number of the population who were out of work. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13504" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13540">The Council of Ten sought to raise money by way of taxes and imposts; and of that which was raised, a little was given to the Tribunal, a little to the poor, and a little grain was purchased. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13541" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13548">But as yet, the great misery had not arrived. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="24">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13549" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13620">In the lazaretto, where the population daily increased, there was another arduous task to be performed, and that was to insure attendance and subordination, to preserve the prescribed separation, and, in short, to maintain, or rather to establish the government ordered by the Tribunal of Health; for, from the very commencement, every thing had been in a state of confusion, through the recklessness of many of the patients, and through the negligence or connivance of the attendants. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13621" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13665">The Tribunal and Council, not knowing what was to be done, had recourse to the Capuchins. They conjured the chief commissary of the province, who supplied the place of the Father Provencal, dead a short time before, to grant them certain Fathers who might be capable of governing this kingdom of desolation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13666" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13725">The commissary proposed to them as principal, one Father Felice Casati, a man of mature age, who enjoyed a great fame for charity, activity, and gentleness, together with great strength of mind—a fame well merited, as the sequel will prove. Another Capuchin, Father Michele Pozzobonelli, still young, but grave and severe both in thought as well as in appearance, was assigned as his companion. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13726" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13738">These two men were accepted with great joy; on the 30th of March they entered the lazaretto. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13739" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13775">The President of the Tribunal of Health conducted them through the building, as though installing them; and having assembled the attendants and underlings of every grade, he declared the Father Felice, in presence of all, the president of that place, endowed with all authority. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13776" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13805">Gradually as the livid crowd of dying wretches increased, other Capuchins hastened thither; they became, superintendents, confessors, administrators, sick-nurses, cooks, keepers of the wardrobe, laundresses, in short, filled any office which might be required. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13806" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13859">The Father Felice, always indefatigable and always eager, paced by day and by night through the porticoes, the chambers, and the vast area, sometimes bearing a lance, sometimes undefended save by his friar's dress; he encouraged all, regulated every thing; calmed the tremulous, appeased all dissensions; menaced, punished, reprimanded, comforted, and both shed and wiped away tears. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13860" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13876">He himself took the plague in the beginning; recovered from it, and applied himself with fresh vigour to his former cares. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13877" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13890">The greater number of his brethren lost their lives, but all joyfully. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="25">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13891" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13956">Certainly, such a system of government was a strange remedy—strange as the calamity and as the times; and even, were this all, to see men intrusted with so important a duty, obliged to resign their office, and resign it too, to men who by their station were the farthest removed from such a task, would be a sufficient argument to prove a very rude and ill-regulated state of society. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13957" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13990">But, at the same time, the spectacle of these men so bravely undertaking such a charge is no ignoble example of the strength and power which charity can bestow in all times and under all circumstances. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13991" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14058">And it was indeed beautiful, their having accepted it from the simple reason that there was no one else who would, without any other object than that of serving, with no other hope in this world than that of a death much more enviable than envied; it was beautiful, their having offered themselves solely because it was so difficult and dangerous an undertaking; and from this it is to be inferred that they possessed energy and presence of mind, qualities then so necessary and so rare. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14059" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14109">The deeds and the hearts of these friars deserve to be remembered with admiration, with tenderness, and with that species of gratitude which is due towards great services rendered by men to their brothers, and all the more due towards such as do not expect it as a recompense. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14173" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14227">According to Ripamonti, the persons who were received into the lazaretto during the seven months Father Felice was its governor, were about fifty thousand; he also says, with reason, that had he been relating things which would do honour to the city, instead of its misfortunes, he ought to have been equally express in his mention of such a man. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14228" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14278">Even among the people, the obstinate denial of the plague naturally died away as the disease gradually diffused itself by means of contact and intercourse, and yet more when, having been confined solely to the lower orders, it began to attack individuals of greater notoriety. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14279" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14296">And among these, as being the most memorable instance of all, we must make especial mention of the physician Settala. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14297" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14305">Did the people then confess that the poor old man had spoken with reason? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14306" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14308">Who can tell? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14309" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14321">He fell ill of the plague, he, his wife, two sons, and seven members of his household. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14322" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14331">He and his sons recovered: the others died. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14332" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14372">"These cases," says Tadino, "having occurred in the city, in the houses of the nobility, caused both the nobles and the people to reflect, and both the incredulous physicians, and the ignorant and rash mob, began to press their lips together, to close their teeth, and to arch their brows." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="26">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14373" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14491">Being no longer able to deny the terrible effects of the disease, yet not wishing to recognise the true cause, for that would have been confessing themselves at once guilty of a great error and a great fault, the incredulous party imagined another one, entirely in character with the prejudices of the times. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14492" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14530">Unfortunately this cause was only too easily to be found in the ideas and generally received traditions, not only of Italy, but of the whole of Europe, in the belief that there existed magical arts, diabolical operations, and people leagued together to spread the plague by means of contagious poisons and sorcery. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14531" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14553">Already the same and similar things had been supposed and believed in many other pestilences, and especially in the one of the previous century. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14554" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14594">Besides which, towards the close of the preceding year, a despatch, bearing the signature of the king Philip IV., had been received by the Governor, informing him that there had escaped from Madrid four Frenchmen, suspected of having spread abroad poisonous and pestilential substances; and that he should be on his guard, if these individuals should ever arrive in Milan. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14595" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14618">The Governor had communicated this despatch to the Senate and the Tribunal of Health; but it does not appear that at the time much attention was paid to it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14619" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14648">However, when the plague had really broken out and was recognised by every one, this communication recurring to the public mind, might serve to confirm the vague suspicion of a criminal fraud; it might even be the origin of the suspicion itself. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="27">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14649" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14687">But two incidents, one occasioned by blind and unrestrained fear, the other by I know not what wicked design, converted this undefined suspicion of a possible attempt into a belief, and with many people into the certainty, of an actual attempt and a real plot. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14688" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14792">Some individuals, who imagined they had seen on the evening of the 17th of May, certain persons in the cathedral occupied in anointing a wooden partition, which served as a division to the spaces assigned to the two sexes, caused, during the night, this partition and a quantity of benches to be carried out of the church. The President of the Tribunal of Health hastened, with four members of the Tribunal, to inspect the partition, the benches, and the cisterns of holy water; he discovered nothing which could confirm the ignorant suspicion of such a diabolical plot; yet to gratify the public frenzy, and rather through an excess of precaution than from any necessity, he decreed that the partition should be washed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14793" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14813">This vast quantity of woodwork, all heaped up together, excited a great sentiment of terror in the minds of the multitude, with whom an object so easily becomes an argument. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14814" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14836">It was generally said and believed, that the anointers had smeared all the benches and the walls of the cathedral—nay, even the very ropes of the bells. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14837" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14904">It was not alone the vulgar belief, but all contemporary writers, and even some of later years who mention this fact, speak of it with equal certainty; and we should have been left to guess at the true nature of the history, had not the explanation been found in a letter from the Tribunal addressed to the Governor—a letter which is preserved in the archives called those of San Fedele; it is from this letter we have drawn our view of the subject, and from this letter we have taken the words printed in italics. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="28">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14905" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14923">The following morning, a new spectacle, still more strange and significant, presented itself to the eyes and imaginations of the citizens. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14924" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14953">In all parts of the city were seen the doors and walls of the houses smeared with long streaks of I know not what manner of filth, of a whitish yellow colour, which seemed to have been applied with a sponge. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14954" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15021">Whether this was merely a wicked joke played off to excite a still more general terror, or whether it was done with the more criminal design of augmenting the public disorder, or let the motive have been what it may, the circumstance is so well attested, that it would appear less reasonable to attribute it to the dreams of a many, than to the acts of a few; a circumstance, in short, which would have been neither the first nor the last of its kind. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15022" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15051">Ripamonti, who when speaking of the anointers, often derides, and still oftener deplores, the popular credulity, affirms that he has seen this smearing, and describes it: *et nos quoque vivimus vivere. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15052" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15076">Maculæ erant sparsim inequaliterque manantes, ut si quis haustam spongia sanien adspergisset, impressisset re parieti: et januae passim, ostiaque ædium eadem adspergine contaminata cerncebantur*, p. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15077" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15078">75. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15079" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15145">In the above quoted letter, the Signors of the Tribunal of Health relate the fact in the same terms; they speak of examinations, of experiments which had been tried with this material upon dogs, from which no bad effects had resulted; adding, that it is their opinion, that such an act of temerity rather proceeded from insolence than from any evil intent: a thought which indicates that until that time they had preserved sufficient calmness to prevent them from seeing what did not exist. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15146" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15189">The other contemporary writers, in relating the event, also hint that, at first, many people were of opinion that it had been an act of pleasantry or folly; yet not one writer speaks of a single individual who denied the fact—and most certainly they would have spoken of such had they existed—were it only to have called them ridiculous unbelievers. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15190" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15257">I have considered it not unreasonable thus to refer to and collect these particulars regarding so celebrated a delirium, particulars so little known or so entirely forgotten; for it appears to me in errors, and especially in the errors of the multitude, that what is most interesting and most instructive is the course which they have taken, their appearance, and the means by which they have been able to enter and govern the minds of men. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="29">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15258" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15282">The city already excited was now seriously alarmed; the masters of the houses were seen with burning straw purifying the anointed places; the passers-by stopped, gazed, and shuddered with horror. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15283" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15306">Strangers who were merely suspicious because they were strangers, and who were easily recognised by their apparel, were arrested in the streets by the populace and conducted to justice. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15307" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15328">There were examinations of the arrested, of the arrestors, and of witnesses; but no criminal was discovered: the public mind was still able to doubt, to examine, and to understand. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15329" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15461">The Tribunal of Health published a proclamation in which a reward and impunity were offered to whosoever should bring to light the author or the authors of this deed. *In no wise, it appearing decent,* say the Signors in the letter which we have already quoted, bearing date the 21st of May, but which was evidently written on the 19th, the day given in the printed edict, *that this crime should remain unpunished, especially in times of so much danger and suspicion; and for the consolation and quiet of the people, and to obtain information, we have this day published a proclamation, etc.* In the proclamation itself, however, there appears no sign, or at least no clear one, of the reasonable and pacifying conjecture which they imparted to the Governor; a silence which at once accuses the people of a mad obstinacy, and then of a condescension all the more blameable as it was pernicious. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="30">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15462" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15473">Whilst the Tribunal sought after the cause, the public imagined that they had already discovered it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15474" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15533">Among those who believed in a poisonous anointing, some considered this a deed of vengeance perpetrated by Don Gonzalo Fernandez de Cordova, for the insults received upon his departure; others, a scheme of Carcardinal Richelieu, to depopulate Milan, and thus render himself master of the city without any trouble; others, and from what reason one cannot tell, maintained that its author was Collalto; others, Wallenstein; others, certain Milanese gentlemen. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15534" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15564">There were not, however, wanting, as we have already observed, those who only saw in this deed a foolish joke, and who attributed it to certain students and gentlemen, or to officers who were annoyed at the siege of Casale. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15565" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15601">But when it was observed that the infection and universal mortality which had been foreboded, did not immediately follow, it is probable that the first terror was calmed, and thus the circumstance had, or at least appeared to have, passed into oblivion. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="31">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15602" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15617">Beside, a certain number of people still remained unpersuaded of the real existence of the plague. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15618" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15666">And because sometimes in the lazaretto, as well as in the city, a few recovered (the last arguments put forth to support an opinion which is thoroughly confuted by evidence are always curious), "it was said by the people, and even by a certain number of obstinate physicians, that this was not the true plague, otherwise all would have died." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15667" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15693">To remove every doubt, the Tribunal of Health discovered an expedient proportionate to the necessity, a mode of speaking to the eyes of the multitude, which the times might perhaps have demanded, or might even perhaps have suggested. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15694" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15741">Upon a certain day, during the Feast of Pentecost, the citizens were accustomed to repair to the cemetery of San Gregorio, situated without the Eastern-gate, to pray for those who had died during the former pestilence, and who were interred there; and, making this act of devotion an occasion for display and diversion, they went, every one arrayed in his gayest attire. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15742" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15753">There had died that very day of the plague, besides many others, an entire family. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15754" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15797">In the hour when the concourse was the greatest, in the midst of the carriages, of the people on horseback, and on foot, the corpses of this family were, by order of the Senate, conducted to the cemetery, naked in a cart, in order that in them the crowds might behold the manifest signs of the pestilence. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15798" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15822">A cry of disgust and horror rose wherever this cart passed along; a long murmur was heard when it had passed, another murmur preceded it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15823" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15848">The plague was more generally believed, but it continued daily acquiring for itself belief; and this very concourse itself must have contributed no little to its propagation. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="32">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15849" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15864">Thus, in the commencement there was no plague, absolutely none whatsoever—the very word even was prohibited. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15865" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15874">Then it was a pestilential fever; the idea was admitted, only changing the noun into an adjective. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15875" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15903">It was not the true plague; that is to say, it was the plague, but only in a certain sense; it was not the regular plague, but something for which no other name could be found. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15904" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15939">Finally, it was the plague, without the slightest doubt or dispute; but already another idea seized upon the public mind, the idea of poison and sorcery, which changed and confounded the express idea of that word which could no longer be kept behind. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="33">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15940" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15961">It is not necessary to be deeply versed in the history of ideas and words, to perceive that many have taken a similar course. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15962" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15997">But, by the grace of heaven, there are not many of a similar nature and of an equal importance, not many which have conquered their evidence at such a fearful price, and which have been followed by such fatal consequences. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15998" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_16032">It would, however, be possible, as well in small things as in great, to avoid in a considerable degree the long and crooked path, by adopting the method proposed so long ago, that of observing, listening, comparing, and reflecting, before speaking. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="34">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap31-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_16033" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_16059">But this one thing, *speaking*, is in itself so much easier than the others, that we, I say, we, men in general, are a little to be pardoned. </note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>