<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CHAPTER IV.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>1845</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed Lovers: a Milanese Story of the Seventeenth Century. With The Column of Infamy by Alessandro Manzoni. In Three Volumes</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
          <date>1845</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Henry Francis C. Logan</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="English_1845_cap4">
        <p n="1">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10024">The sun had scarcely appeared above the horizon, when Father Cristoforo issued forth from the convent of Pescarenico to ascend to the cottage where he was expected. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10025" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10064">Pescarenico is an insignificant hamlet on the left bank of the Adda, or rather of the lake, but a short distance from the bridge. It is a little group of houses, inhabited for the most part by fishers, and adorned here and there with fishing-nets hung out to dry. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10065" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10094">The convent was situated—and the fabric still exists at the present day—beyond the hamlet opposite to the entrance of the village, half way on the road between Bergamo and Lecco. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10095" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10150">The heaven was perfectly serene; gradually as the sun rose behind the mountains, his light was seen to descend from the summits of the opposite hills, spreading itself rapidly beneath on the slopes and in the valleys; a gentle autumnal breeze, detaching from the branches the leaves already loosened by the frost, carried them away to fall some few paces from the tree. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10151" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10187">On the right and left, in the vineyards, his still oblique rays glowed upon the foliage, tinted with various hues of red; and the freshly ploughed land shewed itself brown and distinct in the fields of stubble, white and glittering in the dew. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10188" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10204">The scene itself was joyous; but every human figure which shewed itself saddened the countenance and the thought. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10205" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10224">At each instant you were met by ragged and thin beggars, grown old in the trade, or driven to it by necessity. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10225" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10267">They passed silently by Father Cristoforo, looking at him piteously; and having nothing to expect from him, as a Capuchin never touches money, made him a reverence of gratitude for the alms they had received, or were going to receive, at the convent. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10268" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10279">In the spectacle of the labourers dispersed over the fields, there was something even more doleful. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10280" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10311">Some threw in their seed sparingly, with parsimony and ill-will, as though they were risking something of the utmost importance to them; others pushed their spades into the earth with difficulty, and carelessly turned over the clods. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10312" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10351">The meagre little girl who held by a cord the thin dry cow at pasture, looked round her, and bent down in haste to rob the cow, for food for the family, of some herb, in which famine had taught the poor, that men also could find nourishment. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10352" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10384">These sights increased at every step the melancholy of the friar, who was travelling on already with a sad presentiment in his heart that he was about to hear some misfortune. But why did he take so much thought about Lucia? </note>
        </p>
        <p n="2">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10385" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10401">And why at this first intimation had he set out with such solicitude, as though at the call of the Father of the province? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10402" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10414">And who was Father Cristoforo? It is necessary to satisfy all these demands. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="3">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10415" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10429">Father Cristoforo da — was a man nearer sixty than fifty. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10430" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10471">His head shaven, with the exception of a little crown of hair, which according to the rite of the Capuchins encircled it, was raised from time to time with a movement which betrayed an indescribable something of pride and disquiet, and then immediately lowered itself with reflection and humility. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10472" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10513">The beard, white and long, which covered his chest and chin, threw out still more his noble features, to which an abstemiousness long time habitual to him, had added gravity without taking away anything from their expression. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10514" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10566">His deep-sunken eyes were generally cast towards the earth, but they sometimes sparkled with a most unexpected vivacity; as two fiery horses conducted by the hand of a coachman, whom from habit they know they must obey, will from time to time let themselves be carried away by their impetuosity, but will soon again resign themselves to the bit. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="4">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10567" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10586">Father Cristoforo had not always been thus, neither had he always been Cristoforo: his name of baptism was Ludovico. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10587" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10625">He was the son of a merchant of * * * (these asterisks are owing to the circumspection of my Anonymous), who in the latter years of his life, finding himself sufficiently provided with riches, and left with this only son, had renounced trade and commenced the life of a Signor. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10626" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10671">In his new idleness he became most heartily ashamed of the only time he had spent in being useful in this world, and ruled by such a fancy, he studied in every way to make his having been a merchant forgotten; he would have wished to forget it himself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10672" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10702">But the warehouse, the bales of goods, the ledger, the yard-arm, appeared always in his memory, like the ghost of Banquo to Macbeth, even amidst the pomp of the festival and the smiles of parasites. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10703" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10726">It would not be possible to say the care which these poor creatures took to avoid every word which might appear to bear any allusion to the former condition of their host. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10727" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10779">One day, to relate an instance of this, one day near the end of the feast, in a moment of the liveliest and freest mirth—when it would have been difficult to say who most enjoyed himself, the guest who cleared the table, or the patron who furnished it—he was rallying one of the revellers, one of the most honest eaters in the world. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10780" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10802">The guest, carrying on the joke, without the slightest shadow of malice, with the sincerity of a little child, replied, "Ah! I turn a deaf ear to you, I make the merchant's ear." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10803" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10841">He himself, struck immediately with the sound of these words as they escaped his lips, looked with uncertainty at the countenance of the patron, which had become clouded. Both would have wished to return to their former discourse, but that was not possible. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10842" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10872">Each guest thought to himself how to suppress this little scandal, and to direct the general attention; but thinking, they were silent, and in this silence the scandal was even still more obvious. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10873" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10891">Each one avoided the eyes of the other, each one felt that all were occupied with one thought, which all desired to dissemble. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10892" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10912">Joy, for this day, had taken its departure, and this imprudent, or more justly speaking, this unfortunate one, never again received an invitation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10913" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10965">Thus the father of Ludovico passed his last years in constant anxiety, fearing to be ridiculed, never reflecting that selling is a thing no more ridiculous than buying, and that the profession which he was now ashamed of, he had without remorse exercised many years in the presence of the public. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10966" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11000">He had his son nobly educated according to the manners of the times, and as far as laws and customs permitted him; he gave him both masters for learning and for knightly exercises; and died leaving him rich and young. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11021">Ludovico had contracted lordly habits, and the flatterers among whom he had grown up, had accustomed him to see himself always treated with respect. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11022" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11074">But when he desired to mingle with the nobles of his city, he found treatment very different from that which he was accustomed to, and saw that did he wish to be of their society, as he would have done, he must go through a new school of patience and submission, always remain their inferior, and every moment swallow some indignity. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11075" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11090">Such a mode of life did not accord with Ludovico's education or character. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11091" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11094">He withdrew himself from them in pique. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11095" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11119">But then he remained at a distance from them with sorrow, since it appeared to him that these ought truly to have been his companions, only he would have wished them rather more amiable. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11120" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11160">With this mingling of inclination and rancour, it was impossible to frequent their society familiarly, and yet wishing to have intercourse with them in some way or other, he began to compete with them in luxury and magnificence, buying thus with ready money, envy and ridicule. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11161" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11177">His nature, at once honourable and violent, embarked him early in other and more serious contentions. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11178" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11216">He felt a spontaneous and sincere horror in beholding oppressions and injuries. A horror rendered still more lively in him by the quality of those persons who mostly committed these deeds in broad daylight, and who were precisely those against whom he had more than this one cause of aversion. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11217" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11269">To appease or to exercise these passions at once, he willingly took the part of a weak and oppressed man, and priding himself in opposing the oppressor, he introduced himself into one quarrel, which led him into another, so that by little and little he began to consider himself as the protector of the oppressed, and the revenger of wrongs. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11270" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11286">The task was a grave one; and one need not ask whether Ludovico had enemies, occupations, and many thoughts. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11287" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11328">Besides the external war, he was continually troubled by inward contests; since in order to succeed in an undertaking (not to speak of those in which he remained the vanquished party), it was necessary that he also should adopt subterfuges and violence, of which his conscience could never approve. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11329" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11366">He was obliged to maintain around him a good number of bravoes; and thus for his security as well as for having in them a more vigorous assistance, he was obliged to select the most daring, that is to say, the most licentious, and to live with scoundrels through his love of justice. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11367" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11434">So much so, that more than once, when discouraged after an unfortunate issue, or disquieted by some imminent danger, wearied of this continual state of defence, loathing his companions, and thinking of the future, since his fortune diminished day by day in these good and brave works, the thought came into his mind of turning friar, which in these times was the most common method of escaping out of embarrassments. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11435" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11462">But this which would perhaps only have remained a fancy all his life, owing to an accident the most serious which had yet befallen him, became a resolution. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="5">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11463" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11494">One day he passed through a street of his native city, followed by two bravoes, and accompanied by a certain Cristoforo, who had formerly been an assistant in the shop, but who, since this had been closed, was become steward of the household. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11495" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11531">He was a man of about fifty, and attached from his youth to Ludovico, whose birth he had witnessed, and who between his salary and gifts bestowed upon him wherewith not only to live himself, but also enough to maintain and bring up a numerous family. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11532" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11585">Ludovico observed in the distance a certain signor, an arrogant man, and an oppressor by profession, with whom he had certainly never spoken in his life, but whose cordial enemy he nevertheless was, and who most fully returned his sentiments; since it is one of the advantages of this world to be able to hate and be hated without being personally known to one another. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11586" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11607">This man, followed by four bravoes, advanced straightforward with a proud step, his head high, his mouth drawn together with arrogance and contempt. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11608" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11660">Both walked along close to the wall, but Ludovico (pay attention to this) slid along it with his right side, and this, according to an established usage, gave him the right (and where- will not a right intrude itself!) not to move away from the said wall in order to make way, let the person be whosoever he might; a thing which was then considered a matter of great importance. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11661" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11686">The other imagined, on the contrary, that the right should alone belong to him as the noble, and that it was for Ludovico to go into the middle of the street, and this by reason of another usage. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11687" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11731">However, in this, as in many other affairs, there were two opposite usages in force, without its having been decided which of them was the best, and this gave occasion to warfare every time that one hard head struck against another of the same quality. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11732" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11746">These two approached each other, drawn close up to the wall, like two walking figures in basso-relievo. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11747" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11774">When they found themselves face to face, the Signor regarding Ludovico, his head thrown back, and with an imperious frown, said to him in a corresponding tone of voice—"Make way!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="6">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11775" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11783">"Make way to you!" replied Ludovico; "the right is mine." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="7">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11784" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11789">"With such as you the right is always mine." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="8">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11790" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11801">"Yes, if the arrogance of such as you were law to such as myself." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="9">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11802" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11855">The bravoes of both gentlemen remained each one behind his patron, looking askance at each other, with their hands on their daggers prepared for battle; the populace, who arrived from all sides, held themselves in the background to observe the fray, and the presence of these spectators animated still more the punctilio of the contending parties. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="10">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11856" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11869">"Into the middle, vile mechanic! or I will teach thee for once how to behave towards a gentleman." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="11">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11870" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11879">"You lie when you say I am vile." "Thou liest, saying I lie." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="12">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11880" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11884">(This answer was logic). </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11885" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11911">"And if thou wert a cavalier, like myself, thou shouldst see by the point of my sword that the liar is thou." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="13">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11912" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11925">"This is certainly a good pretext to exempt yourself from sustaining the violence of your words by deeds." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="14">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11926" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11936">"Throw this fellow into the mud," said the gentleman, turning round to his people. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="15">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11937" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11949">"Let us see that!" said Ludovico, stepping back, and laying his hand upon his sword. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="16">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11950" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11965">"Rash fool!" cried the other, drawing his; "I will break this sword when it shall be stained with thy vile blood!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="17">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11966" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11981">In this manner they rushed upon each other; the servants of both parties flew to the defence of their masters. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11982" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12017">The combat was unequal by numbers, and also because Ludovico aimed sooner to escape the blows and disarm his antagonist, than to injure him; but the enemy desired his death at any price. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12018" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12058">Ludovico had already received from one of the bravoes a dagger-wound in his left arm, and a slight scratch in his cheek, and his principal enemy was laying on most violently behind him, to put an end to his life; when Cristoforo seeing his master in this extreme danger, fell upon the Signor from behind with his dagger. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12059" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12072">And this one, turning all his anger against his new assailant, ran him through with his sword. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12073" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12098">At this sight, Ludovico, as though out of his mind with rage, thrust his sword into the body of the Signor, who fell—dead almost at the same instant, with poor Cristoforo. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12099" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12154">The gentleman's bravoes, seeing that he had fallen, took to flight in very bad condition; those of Ludovico, hurt and discomforted, seeing no one to oppose, and not wishing to find themselves embarrassed by the people, who already ran that way, took to flight in the opposite direction; and poor Ludovico found himself alone, with his two unfortunate companions at his feet, in the midst of a crowd. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="18">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12155" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12236">"How has it happened?—There is one—there are two.—He has a wound in his belly.—Who has been killed?—This oppressor!—Oh, holy Maria, what destruction! Who seeks, finds!—Once pays for all!—Even he is done for!—What a blow!—It will be a serious business!—And the other unfortunate!—Mercy!—What a spectacle! Help! Save him, save him!—He's also badly off!—See what a fine trim he's in!—He drops blood from every part!—Escape, escape!—Don't let yourself be taken!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="19">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12237" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12266">These words, which more than any others made themselves heard above the confused hum of the crowd, expressed the general opinion; and with counsel came also assistance. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12267" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12299">The deed had taken place near a church of the Capuchins, an asylum, as every one knows, at that time impenetrable to constables and all that complication of things and people which called itself justice. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12300" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12346">The wounded murderer, who had almost lost his senses, was conducted or rather carried there by the crowd. The Brothers received him from the hands of the people, who recommended him to them, saying, "He is a good man, who has killed a proud oppressor; he did it in his own defence." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="20">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12347" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12404">Ludovico had never before shed blood, and although homicide was in those times a thing so common that the ear was accustomed to hear it related, and the eye to witness it, yet still the impression which the sight of the man who had died for him, and of the man who had-died by his hand, was new and indescribable; it was a revelation of feelings until then unknown. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12405" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12440">The corpse of his enemy, the alteration of this countenance, which changed in one moment from menace and fury to the helplessness and solemn quiet of death, was a sight which transformed in one second the soul of the murderer. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12441" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12492">Dragged along to the convent, he scarcely knew where he was, or what was going forward. When he returned to consciousness, he found himself in a bed of the infirmary, under the hands of the chirurgeon of the convent (the Capuchins have generally one in each convent), who was arranging lint and bandages upon the two wounds he had received in the encounter. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12493" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12520">A Father, whose peculiar duty it was to attend the dying, and who had often had to render this service in the street, was immediately called to the scene of combat. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12521" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12553">Returned a few moments after, he entered the infirmary, and advancing towards the bed where Ludovico lay, "Console yourself," said he; "at least he has died well. He has charged me to crave for him your pardon, and to bring you his." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12554" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12601">These words caused poor Ludovico to return entirely to consciousness, and revived more vividly and distinctly the confused sentiments which crowded his mind; sorrow for the friend, consternation and remorse for the blow which had been given by his hand; and, at the same time, an agonizing compassion for the man he had murdered. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12602" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12607">"And the other?" demanded he anxiously from the Friar. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="21">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12608" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12612">"The other had expired when I arrived." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="22">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12613" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12649">Meanwhile, the precincts and every approach to the convent swarmed with a curious populace: but a body of constables having arrived, had made the crowd disperse, and then placed itself in such a manner that no one could leave the convent unobserved. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12650" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12703">A brother of the dead man, his two cousins, and an old uncle came, moreover, armed, cap-à-pie, with a numerous attendance of bravoes, and paced round the convent, regarding, with an air of threatening disdain, the curious, who did not dare to say, "It was well done," but who had this, nevertheless, written in their countenances. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="23">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12704" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12753">Scarcely had Ludovico collected his thoughts than he called a Father-confessor, prayed him to seek out the widow of Cristoforo, and to ask pardon, in his name, for all the misery which he had, however involuntarily, caused her; and at the same time to inform her that he would take upon himself the support of her family. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12754" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12809">Reflecting then upon his own situation, he felt return more livingly, and more seriously than ever, the idea of becoming a friar—an idea which formerly had passed through his mind. It seemed to him that God himself had placed him in this path, and had given him a sign of His will, in causing him, at this juncture, to arrive at a convent; his resolution was taken. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12810" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12819">He sent for the Superior, and expressed his desire to him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12820" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12835">The Superior replied, that he must guard himself from precipitate resolution, but that if he persisted, this should not be refused him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12836" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12878">Then he caused a notary to be sent for, and made a donation of all his remaining property (which was still considerable) to the family of Cristoforo, a sum to the widow as a second dowry, and the remainder to the eight sons which Cristoforo had left behind him. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="24">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12879" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12899">This resolution of Cristoforo's arrived most opportunely for his hosts, who, on his account, found themselves in a most terrible difficulty. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12900" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12921">To send him away from the convent, and expose him to the pursuit of justice, that is, to the vengeance of his enemies, was not, however, a line of conduct to be put in deliberation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12922" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12966">This would have been the same as renouncing their privileges, discrediting the convent with the populace, drawing upon themselves the censure of all the Capuchins in the universe for having allowed the rights of all to be violated, and exciting against themselves the ecclesiastical authorities, who considered themselves as the guardians of this right. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12967" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12997">On the other hand, the family of the murdered man -very powerful in itself, and through its adherents—had prepared to avenge itself, and declared every one an enemy who attempted to place any obstacle in its path. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12998" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13033">History does not say that they grieved much over their murdered kinsman, nor even that a single tear had been shed over him among all the kindred; it only says that they all were furious to have in their clutches the murderer, either alive or dead. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13034" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13042">Now his assuming the habit of a Capuchin would accommodate every thing. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13043" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13068">He made, in a certain manner, an amends—imposed upon himself a penance—declared himself implicitly in fault—retired from every contention—was, in short, an enemy who lays down his arms. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13069" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13093">The relations of the dead could then, even if it pleased them, believe and boast that he had turned monk through desperation and fear of their anger. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13094" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13131">At all events, to reduce a man to disinherit himself—to shave his head—to walk barefoot—to sleep upon sack-cloth—to live upon alms—might appear a sufficient punishment to the offended party, even the most proud. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="25">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13132" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13202">The Superior presented himself with the most dexterous humility before the brother of the dead man, and after a thousand protestations of respect for the very illustrious house, and of his desire to please the family in every thing which was possible, spoke of the penitence of Ludovico, and of his resolution, making gracefully felt that the family might be contented with this, and insinuating then gently, and with a manner even more crafty, that please or not please the thing must be. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13203" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13222">The brother broke forth into a rage; which the Capuchin allowed to evaporate, saying from time to time, "It is too just a sorrow." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="26">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13223" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13263">He gave the Capuchin to understand, that in any situation his family would have known how to take satisfaction, and the Capuchin, whatever he might think, took care not to say no. Finally he demanded and imposed as a condition, that the murderer should immediately quit the city. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13264" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13293">The Superior, who had already deliberated whether this might be, said that it should be done; leaving the other to believe if it pleased him, that this was an act of obedience, and thus all was concluded. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13294" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13385">The family, who came off with honour, was satisfied; the Friars, who saved at once a man and their privileges, were satisfied; the lovers of chivalry, who saw an affair terminate in so praiseworthy a manner, were satisfied; the populace, who saw a man to whom they wished well relieved from his embarrassments, and who admired at the same time a conversion, were satisfied; and finally our Ludovico, in the midst of all his grief, was satisfied, and more than all the others satisfied, thus to begin a life of atonement and usefulness, to be able, if not to repair, at least to pay for his evil deeds, and blunt the intolerable sting of remorse. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13386" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13417">The suspicion that his resolution might be imputed to fear, afflicted him a moment, but he consoled himself quickly that even this unjust judgment would be a chastisement for him, and a means of expiation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13418" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13454">Thus, at thirty, he wrapped himself in sack-cloth, and being obliged, according to custom, to renounce his own name and take another instead, he selected one which would remind him of that which he had to expiate, and called himself Cristoforo. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="27">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13455" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13480">Scarce had he assumed the robe, than the Superior intimated to him that he would have to perform his noviciate about sixty miles off, and that on the morrow he must depart. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13481" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13546">The novice bowed himself profoundly, and demanded a favour: "Permit me, Father," said he, "that before I leave this city, where I have spilt the blood of a human being—where I must leave a family cruelly offended,—that I endeavour to make amends to the family for this affront; or at least shew them my grief for not being able to repair the injury, by demanding pardon from the brother of the murdered man, and if God help my intention, by removing all rancour from his breast." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13547" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13581">To the Superior it appeared that such a step, besides being good in itself, would serve still more to reconcile the family with the convent, and he went immediately to the Signor to signify to him the request of Fra Cristoforo. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13582" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13600">At a proposition thus unexpected, the brother felt, together with wonder, an ebullition of anger, yet not without a sentiment of satisfaction. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13601" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13611">After having thought a moment, "come to-morrow," he said, and assigned the hour. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13612" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13621">The Superior returned to carry to the novice the desired consent. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="28">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13622" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13662">The Signor thought immediately, that the more solemn and impressive this satisfaction was, the more he should increase his credit with his kindred and with the public, and knew (to express it with modern elegance) that this would be a beautiful page in the history of his family. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13663" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13688">He informed in haste all his kindred that to-morrow at noon they should come to him, to receive a general satisfaction. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13689" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13727">At noon-day the palace was all a-stir with nobles of both sexes and all ages; there was a moving and mingling of great cloaks, of waving plumes, of dangling Durlindanas, an agitation of starched and crisp frills, an embarrassing trailing of brocaded dresses. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13728" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13744">The antechambers, the courts, and the street, swarmed with servants, pages, bravoes, and curious idlers. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13745" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13883">Fra Cristoforo saw this preparation, and divining well the motive of it, experienced a slight perturbation, but, after an instant, he said to himself,—"It is well; I have murdered him in public, in the presence of many of his enemies; that was the dishonour, this is the reparation." Thus with his eyes cast down, with the attending Friar at his side, he passed through the door of this palace, crossed the court, between a crowd which regarded him with a very unceremonious curiosity, ascended the staircase, and passing through the middle of the lordly crowd, which opened before him, followed by a hundred eyes, arrived in the presence of the master of the house, who, surrounded by his nearest of kin, stood erect in the middle of the hall, his eyes fixed upon the ground, his head thrown back, grasping with his left hand the hilt of his sword, whilst with the right he held tightly together, upon his breast, the collar of his cloak. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="29">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13884" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13914">There is sometimes in the countenance and appearance of a man, such a sudden expression, or what may rather be called such an effusion of the inward soul, that in a crowd of spectators, the judgment regarding this mind will be unanimous. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13915" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13944">The countenance and appearance of Fra Cristoforo spoke to the bystanders that he had neither become a Friar, nor humbled himself thus, through human fear, and this began to reconcile the crowd to him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13945" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14002">When he saw the offended brother, he hastened his step, knelt at his feet, crossed his hands over his breast, and inclining his shaven head, pronounced these words: "I am the murderer of your brother; God knows that I would willingly restore him to you at the cost of my own blood, but being unable to make you other than ineffectual and tardy excuses, I supplicate you to receive them for the love of God." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14003" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14021">All eyes were fixed immoveably upon the novice, all ears were directed towards the personage to whom he spoke. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14022" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14037">When Fra Cristoforo ended, throughout the whole hall rose a murmur of pity and respect. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14038" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14105">The gentleman, who stood in an attitude of forced dignity, and repressed anger, was troubled by these words, and bending towards the kneeling Brother,— "Rise!" said he, with an altered voice, "the offence—truly, the deed—but the habit you wear—not only from this, but also on your own account—rise, Father—my brother—I cannot deny it—was a cavalier—was a man—a little impetuous—a little hasty—but all happens by the disposal of God. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14106" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14110">Speak no more of this. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14111" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14119">But, Father, you must not remain in such a position." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14120" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14126">And taking him by the arms, he made him rise. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14127" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14146">Fra Cristoforo risen, but with his head bent, replied, "I may then hope that you have granted me your pardon! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14147" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14156">And if I obtain it from you, from whom may I not hope for it? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14157" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14166">Oh, if I could only hear from your lips this word, pardon!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14167" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14176">"Pardon?" said the gentleman, "you have no longer need of it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14177" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14190">But since you desire it, certainly—certainly. I pardon you from my heart, and all——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="30">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14191" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14198">"All, all!" cried with one voice the bystanders. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14199" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14228">The countenance of the Friar beamed with a grateful joy, under which, however, still shewed itself an humble and profound compunction for the evil deed, which the pardon of men could not repair. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14229" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14254">The gentleman, conquered by this aspect, and carried away by the general emotion, threw his arms round his neck, and gave and received the kiss of peace. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="31">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14255" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14281">A "bravo! well done!" burst forth from all parts of the hall; all were in motion, all pressed round the Frate, servants immediately arrived with a copious supply of refreshments. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14282" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14307">The gentleman again approached Cristoforo, who seemed about to take leave, and said to him,—"Father, accept something; give me this proof of your friendship." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14308" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14340">And he began to serve him before any one else; but the Friar drew back with a certain friendly resistance, saying, "These things are no longer for me; but it shall never be said that I refused your gifts. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14341" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14374">I am going to set forth on my journey, vouchsafe to order me a little loaf of bread, so that I may be able to say that I have enjoyed your charity, that I have eaten of your bread, that I have a sign of your pardon." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14375" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14411">The gentleman much affected, ordered this to be done, and immediately a chamberlain arrived in gala costume, carrying a little loaf upon a silver dish, and presented it to the Father, who, taking it and returning thanks, placed it in his basket. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14412" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14498">He then took leave; and after embracing the master of the house again, and after all those who were near him had seized upon him, he succeeded in disengaging himself; he had to combat in the antechamber, in order to free himself from the servants, and even from the braves, who kissed the hem of his robe, his cord, and his hood; and he found himself in the street carried along as in triumph, and accompanied by a crowd even to the gate of the city, through which he passed, and commenced his pedestrian journey towards the place of his noviciate. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="32">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14499" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14528">The brother and the relations of the murdered man who had expected this day to experience the miserable joy of pride, found themselves instead filled with the serene joy occasioned by pardon and benevolence. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14529" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14552">The company conversed some time with an unusual kindness and cordiality, in speeches which no one was prepared for in going there. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14553" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14575">Instead of satisfaction taken, of injuries avenged, engagements cancelled; praises of the novice, reconciliation and mildness were the themes of conversation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14576" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14624">And a certain one who for the fiftieth time would have related how the Count Murzio, his father, had managed upon a famous occasion to subdue the Marquis Stanislao, who was a bully as every one knows, spoke instead of the penitence and admirable patience of a Fra Simone, dead many years before. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14625" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14713">The company departed, the master still much disturbed, examining with himself with wonder what he had heard, and all that he himself had said, muttered between his teeth—"the devil of a friar!"—(we must transcribe his precise words)—"the devil of a friar!—had he remained much longer there on his knees, why I myself should have craved pardon that it was my brother he had murdered!" Our history expressly notices that from this day forth, this Signor was a little less hasty, and a little more tractable. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="33">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14714" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14741">Father Cristoforo travelled on with a satisfaction which he had never felt since that terrible day, for the atonement of which his life should be consecrated. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14742" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14768">The silence prescribed to the novices he observed without being aware of it, absorbed as he was in the thoughts of the fatigues, of the privations, and humiliations which he had gone through, in order to deduct from his guilt. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14769" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14801">Stopping at the hour of refection at the house of a benefactor, he ate with a kind of delight his bread of pardon; but nevertheless spared a morsel of it, and placed it again in his basket, in order to preserve it as an eternal remembrance. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="34">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14802" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14856">It is not our design to give the history of his conventual life. We will only say that he always fulfilled with great pleasure and with great care, the duties which were prescribed him, those of preaching and assisting the dying; and that he never allowed any opportunity to escape him of conciliating differences, and of protecting the oppressed,—duties which he himself had imposed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14857" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14888">In this humour entered, without his being aware of it, something of his old habits, and a remnant of his warlike spirit, which humiliations and mortifications had not been entirely able to efface. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14889" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14931">His language was generally calm and humble; but when justice or truth were attacked, he became at once animated with his ancient impetuosity, which, moderated and mingled with a solemn emphasis arising from his habit of preaching, gave his language a singular character. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14932" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14961">His manner, as well as his appearance, announced a long struggle between a fiery and impetuous nature and an opposing will, habitually victorious, always upon its guard, and directed by superior motives and inspirations. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14962" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_15010">A brother and friend who knew him well, compared him one day to those words too expressive in their original form, which certain persons, otherwise well educated, half pronounce, when carried away by passion, changing some letters; words, however, which spite of the metamorphosis remind you of their primitive energy. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="35">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_15011" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_15067">If a poor unknown girl in the sad situation of Lucia had demanded the aid of Father Cristoforo, he would have immediately flown to her assistance; but as it was Lucia who was concerned, he hastened with all the more solicitude, since, besides knowing and admiring her innocence, he already imagined her danger, and felt a holy indignation against the base persecution of which she was become the object. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_15068" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_15116">Besides, having counselled her, as the least evil course to pursue, not to trouble herself and to remain quiet; he feared now that this counsel might have produced some bad effect, and to the christian solicitude which was inherent in him, joined itself in this instance that scrupulous fear, which often torments the good. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="36">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap4-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_15117" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_15158">But whilst we have been relating the acts of Father Cristoforo, he has reached and appeared upon the threshold. The women, leaving the handle of the spindle, which they made spin and scream, are risen, saying both together, "Father Cristoforo! God be with you!" </note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>