<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CHAPTER VI.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>1845</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed Lovers: a Milanese Story of the Seventeenth Century. With The Column of Infamy by Alessandro Manzoni. In Three Volumes</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
          <date>1845</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Henry Francis C. Logan</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="English_1845_cap6">
        <p n="1">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10014">“In what can I obey you?” said Don Rodrigo, planting himself in the middle of the hall. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10015" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10040">Such was the sound of the words, but the manner with which they were uttered said clearly, remember before whom thou art, weigh thy words and be brief. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="2">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10041" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10060">To give courage to our Fra Cristoforo, there was no means more sure or more speedy than to assume an arrogant manner. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10061" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10110">He who stood wavering, hunting after words, and making the heads of his rosary slip quickly between his fingers, as though he hoped to find his exordium in one of them, at this haughtiness of Don Rodrigo felt more words rise to his lips than he had need of. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10111" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10156">But thinking how important it was not to spoil the affairs of others, he corrected and tempered the phrases which had presented themselves to his mind, and said, with a humble circumspection:— </note>
        </p>
        <p n="3">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10157" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10187">“I am come to propose an act of justice, to supplicate an act of charity: certain people of ill fame have made use of the name of your illustrious lordship in order to frighten a poor curate, and deter him from performing his duty, as well as to torment two innocent young people. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10188" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10230">Your lordship with one word can confound these men, restore to the law its force, and console them to whom so cruel a violence has been done; you can do this, and being able, your conscience, your honour — ” "I will speak to you about my conscience, when I shall come to confess myself to you. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10231" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10266">As to my honour, you ought to know that of it I am the guardian, and I alone, and that I regard as a foolhardy and impertinent knave any one who shall take upon himself to divide this care with me." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="4">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10267" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10332">Fra Cristoforo, warned by these expressions that the Signor sought to draw the worst meaning out of his words in order to turn the discourse into a dispute, and thus not to give him time to come to an explanation, devoted himself all the more to patience, and resolving to swallow whatsoever the other might choose to say, answered immediately, in a tone of submission: "If I have said anything which has displeased you, certainly it was contrary to my intention. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10333" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10348">Correct me, reprove me, if I do not know how becomingly to address you; but deign to listen to me. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10349" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10400">For the love of heaven, and of that God before whom we all must appear —," saying these words, he took between his fingers and raised before the eyes of his frowning auditor, the little skull which was attached to his rosary, "do not be obstinate in refusing a justice so simple, and which you owe so much towards these poor people. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10401" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10421">Think that God has his eyes upon them, and their prayers are heard on high. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10422" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10426">Innocence is powerful before His —" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="5">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10427" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10464">"Ah, Father!" interrupted Don Rodrigo, roughly, "the respect which I bear towards your robe is great, but if anything could make me forget this, it would be to see it upon the back of one who has the audacity to come into my house to play the spy." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="6">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10465" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10497">These words made the colour mount suddenly into the Friar's cheeks; but with the air of one who swallows a very bitter medicine, he replied,--"You do not believe that such a title suits me. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10498" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10515">You feel in your own heart that the step which I now take here, is neither vile nor despicable. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10516" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10536">Listen to me, Don Rodrigo, and heaven forbid that the day may come in which you will repent of not having listened to me. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10537" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10556">Do not place your glory—and what glory, Signor Don Rodrigo! what glory before men and before God! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10557" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10561">You can do much here on earth; but——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="7">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10562" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10598">"You know," said Don Rodrigo, interrupting him with anger yet not without horror; "you know that when the fancy seizes me to hear a sermon, I can go to church, as other people do; but in my own house! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10599" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10616">Oh!" continued he, with forced irony, "you do me too much honour. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10617" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10620">A preacher in my house! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10621" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10625">It is only princes who have them." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="8">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10626" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10667">"And this God, who demands accounts from princes of that Word which he makes them hear in their palaces; this God, who gives you now a sign of his mercy in sending one of his ministers, an unworthy and miserable one, but his minister nevertheless, to pray for an innocent girl——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="9">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10668" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10698">"In short, Father," said Don Rodrigo, in the act of leaving the room, "I do not know what you would say. I understand nothing, except that there is some girl who interests you very much. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10699" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10720">Go and make your confidential communications to those whom they please, and do not any longer take the liberty of wearying a gentleman." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="10">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10721" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10774">At this movement of Don Rodrigo, our Friar had placed himself before him, but with great respect, and raising his hands as though to implore and direct him at the same time, continued—"She interests me it is true, but not more than you do; they are two souls, both of which interest me more than my own life. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10775" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10792">Don Rodrigo, I can do nothing for you, but pray to God; but this I will do from my heart. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10793" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10807">Do not say no to me; do not keep in agony and terror a poor innocent girl. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10808" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10814">A word from you can do all." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="11">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10815" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10836">"Well," said Don Rodrigo, "since you believe I can do so much for this person, and since this person lies so near your heart —" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="12">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10837" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10861">"Well?" demanded anxiously Father Cristoforo, who, spite of Don Rodrigo's tone and manner, did not abandon the hope which his words seem to announce. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="13">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10862" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10872">"Well, counsel her to come and place herself under my protection. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10873" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10886">She shall want for nothing, no one shall dare to molest her, or I am not a cavalier." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="14">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10887" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10898">At such a proposition the indignation of the Friar, until then repressed with great difficulty, broke forth. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10899" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10927">All his fine projects of prudence and patience went off in smoke. The old man found himself in accord with the new man, and in circumstances such as this Fra Cristoforo was truly worth two. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10928" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10963">"Your protection!" exclaimed he, taking two steps backwards, planting himself firmly on his right foot, placing his right hand upon his hip, raising the forefinger of the left towards Don Rodrigo, and fixing his two flaming eyes upon his countenance—"Your protection! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10964" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10977">It is well that you have spoken thus, that you have made me such a proposition. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10978" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10986">You have filled up the measure, and I fear you no more." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="15">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10987" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10989">"How dost thou speak, Friar?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="16">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10990" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11005">"I speak as one who speaks to a man abandoned by God, to one who can no longer cause fear. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11006" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11008">Your protection! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11009" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11039">I know well that this innocent is under the protection of God; but you! you now make me feel this with so much certainty, that I have no longer need to spare you in speaking of it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11040" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11056">Lucia, I say, see how I pronounce this name with an unabashed mien, and unmoving eyes—— </note>
        </p>
        <p n="17">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11057" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11060">"How! In this house——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="18">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11061" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11071">"I have compassion for this house, a curse hangs over it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11072" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11089">Do you expect that divine justice will regard four walls and the suggestion of four bullies? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11090" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11107">You have imagined that God has made a creature after his own image, in order to give you the pleasure of tormenting it? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11108" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11115">You have imagined God would not know how to defend it? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11116" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11121">You have despised His warnings. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11122" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11124">You are judged. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11125" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11138">The heart of Pharaoh was hard like yours, God knew how to break it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11139" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11163">Lucia is safe from you, I tell you, poor friar as I am; and as to yourself, hear well what I promise you; a day will come——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="19">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11164" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11193">Don Rodrigo had until then remained, between rage and astonishment, unable to find a single word. But as he thus heard a prediction thundering over his head, a secret and mysterious fear joined itself to his anger. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="20">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11194" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11218">Suddenly staying this menacing hand, and elevating his voice to cut short this terrible prophecy, he cried, "Out of my sight, vile, insolent, hooded poltroon!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11219" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11229">These words thus clear, calmed in an instant Father Cristoforo. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11230" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11280">To the idea of injury and disdain was for so long a time, and so nearly associated the idea of sufferance and silence, that at this compliment his anger and enthusiasm fell, and no other resolution remained, except that of listening tranquilly to all that it might please Don Rodrigo to add. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11281" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11321">Therefore, removing quietly his hand from the Signor's grasp, he bowed his head, and remained immoveable, as when the wind falling in the midst of a tempest, a tree tossed about in the storm, settles its branches, and receives the hail as heaven sends it. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="21">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11322" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11331">"Unmannerly villain!" continued he. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11332" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11358">"Thou expressest thyself like thy equals; but return thanks to the sack which covers thy beggar's shoulders, and saves them from the caresses which one bestows upon those who resemble thee, in order to teach them to speak. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11359" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11369">Out with thee!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11370" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11406">And, saying this, he opened, with an imperious and contemptuous air, a door opposite to the one by which they had entered. Father Cristoforo bowed his head, and went out, leaving Don Rodrigo to measure with hasty steps the field of battle. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="22">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11407" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11450">When the Brother had closed the door behind him, he saw in the room he had entered a man retiring very quietly along the wall, so as not to be seen in the hall where the conversation had taken place. He recognised in him the old servant who had come to receive him at the portal. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11451" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11475">This man had served forty years in this house, that is before Don Rodrigo was born, for he had entered the service of the old lord, who was quite another kind of man. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11476" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11547">The old Signor being dead, and the new master dismissing all the family and forming quite a new household, had, however, retained this old servant, who, although aged, and of maxims and habits quite different to his own, compensated for these defects by two good qualities; a high opinion of the dignity of the house, and a great practice in ceremonial, the most ancient traditions and minutest particulars of which he knew better than any one else. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11548" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11625">In the presence of the Signor, the poor old man would never have dared to let his disapprobation of the scenes he every day witnessed be observed, much less have expressed it. He scarcely allowed exclamations and reproaches to escape his lips, even when among his fellow-servants. They, however, amused themselves at his expense, and took pleasure sometimes in touching this note, in order to make him say more than he would have wished, and to hear him sing the praises of the former mode of life in this house. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="23">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11626" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11655">These censures, however, never reached his master's ears, unless accompanied by the relation of the many jokes which had been occasioned by them, so that they became for Don Rodrigo rather a subject of amusement, than of anger. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11656" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11670">But upon days of invitation and reception, the old servant became a very serious and important personage. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="24">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11671" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11714">Father Cristoforo seeing him, saluted him, and continued his way; but the old man approached him mysteriously, placed his forefinger upon his lips, and then with the same made a sign inviting him to enter a dark passage. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11715" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11730">Arrived there, he said in a low voice, "Father, I have heard all, and I want to speak with you." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="25">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11731" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11734">"Speak quickly, good man." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="26">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11735" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11753">"Not here. Woe to me, if my master should perceive—but I know many things, and I will come to-morrow to the convent." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="27">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11754" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11756">"Is there any design?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="28">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11757" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11781">"That there is something in the air is certain, I have already been able to perceive that,—but now I shall be on the watch, and I shall know all,—leave that to me. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11782" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11802">I am obliged to hear and see things—strange things; I am in a house—but I wish to save my soul." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="29">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11803" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11834">"The Lord bless you!" and pronouncing these words in a low voice, the Brother placed his hands upon the head of the old servitor, who, although much older than Fra Cristoforo, bent before him like a child. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11835" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11846">"God will recompense you," continued he, "do not fail to come to-morrow." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="30">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11847" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11863">"I will come," replied the servitor; "but set off quickly, and—for the love of heaven—don't betray me." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11864" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11907">Saying this and looking behind him, he entered by another door of this passage a little hall, which opened into the court. Having seen the coast clear, he called to the good friar to come forth, whose countenance replied to the old man's last words more clearly than protestations could have done. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11908" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11919">The servitor opened the door, and he without another word went forth. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="31">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11920" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11931">This domestic had listened at his master's door. Had he done well? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11932" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11940">Had Father Cristoforo done well in praising him for this? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11941" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11960">According to the most ordinary and generally received rules, this was a very dishonourable action; but may not this case be regarded as an exception? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11961" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11971">And are there not exceptions to the most absolute of rules? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11972" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11984">These are questions for the reader to solve if it please him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11985" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11997">As for us, we do not pretend to give advice, it is enough to have to recount facts. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="32">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11998" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12040">Having turned his back upon this house of horrors, Fra Cristoforo breathed more freely; he hastened on quickly towards the descent, his face on fire, excited and agitated as one can well imagine from what he had both heard and said. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12041" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12087">But this unexpected meeting with the old servant was a great restorative to him. It appeared to him as though God had given him a visible sign of protection. Here is a thread, thought he,—a thread which Providence places in my hand; and in this very house too! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12088" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12122">And without even my dreaming of searching for it. Whilst he was thus ruminating, he raised his eyes towards the west, and saw the setting sun, which had already touched the summit of the mountain, and thought that but little of the day remained for him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12123" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12175">Then, although he felt his bones bruised and heavy from the various exertions of the day, he hastened his pace so as to carry intelligence, such as it was, to his protégées, and then to arrive at the convent before nightfall; since this was one of the laws the most absolute and most rigorously maintained by the code of the Capuchins. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="33">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12176" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12195">During this time, in Lucia's cottage projects had been started, of which it is necessary to inform the reader. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12196" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12261">After the departure of the friar, the three remained for some time silent. Lucia prepared sorrowfully the dinner; Renzo was on the point of leaving every moment, so as to remove himself from the sight of her affliction, and yet he was unable to tear himself away; Agnese, apparently, was only occupied with the reel which she made spin round, but in fact she was maturing a project,—and when this was matured, she broke silence in these terms— "Listen, children! </note>
        </p>
        <p n="34">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12262" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12300">If you will have sufficient courage and address, if you will confide in your mother (this your made Lucia ponder), I engage "myself to draw you out of this difficulty, better perhaps, and more speedily, than Father Cristoforo himself, although he is such a man." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="35">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12301" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12333">Lucia stood still and regarded her with a countenance which expressed more astonishment than confidence in such a magnificent promise. Renzo cried suddenly, "Courage? address? Only tell me what there is to do!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="37">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12334" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12359">"Is it not true," continued Agnese, "that if you were married it would be a fine advance, and that we should be able more easily to find a remedy for the rest?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="38">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12360" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12387">"Who doubts this?" said Renzo. "Were we married—all the world is our country; and at two steps hence beyond Bergamo, he who can work in silk is received with open arms. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12388" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12426">You know how many times Bartolo, my cousin, has solicited me to go there to stay with him, where I should make my fortune as he has done; and if I have never given heed to him—it is—why need I to tell? it was because my heart was here. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12427" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12453">Married, we can go there all together, keep house there, and live in holy peace, out of the clutches of this rogue, removed from all temptation to commit a folly. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12454" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12456">Is it not true, Lucia?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="39">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12457" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12461">"Yes," said Lucia, "but how?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="40">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12462" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12476">"I have said how!" returned the mother, "courage and address, and the thing is easy." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="41">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12477" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12492">"Easy!" exclaimed the two at once, to whom the thing had become so strangely and sadly difficult. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="42">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12493" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12498">"Easy, knowing how to manage it," replied Agnese. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="43">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12499" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12505">"Listen attentively to me, and I will endeavour to make you comprehend it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12506" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12541">I have heard said by people who understand these matters, and I have seen a case of this kind myself, that in order to perform a marriage, a curate is certainly necessary, but that it is not necessary that he consent to it; it is sufficient if he be only there." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="44">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12542" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12547">"How is that?" demanded Renzo. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="45">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12548" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12550">"Listen, and you will comprehend. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12551" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12559">It is necessary to have two witnesses very agile, and both of accord. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12560" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12575">You go towards the priest. The point is to seize him unexpectedly before he has time to escape. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12576" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12592">The man says, 'Signor Curato, this is my wife;' the woman says, 'Signor Curato, this is my husband.' </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12593" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12614">It is only necessary that the curate hears, and that the witnesses hear, then the marriage is as firm and sound as though the Pope himself had performed it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12615" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12633">When these words are once uttered, the curate may scream, may storm, may play the devil,—it is all useless, you are man and wife." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="46">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12634" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12636">"Is it possible!" exclaimed Lucia. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="47">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12637" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12660">"How?" said Agnese. "Do you expect that I have learnt nothing in the thirty years which I passed in the world before you were born? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12661" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12693">The thing is as I tell you. For example, one of my friends, who wished to marry against the will of her parents, doing in this manner, obtained her desire. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12694" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12736">The curate, who had some suspicion, stood upon his guard; but the two witnesses managed so cleverly, that the lovers pronounced the words just in the right moment, and were man and wife, although the poor child repented before three months were past." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="48">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12737" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12815">Agnese had spoken the truth regarding the possibility, and regarding the fear of not succeeding in it; since no person had recourse to this expedient, except such as had met with obstacles and refusals in the ordinary course. The clergy were very careful to escape from this forced co-operation; and when one of them happened to be surprised by such a couple, accompanied by witnesses, he endeavoured by every means in his power to escape from them, like Proteus from the hands of those who wished to make him prophesy by force. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="49">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12816" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12826">"If this were true, Lucia?" said Renzo, regarding her with an air of supplicating expectation. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="50">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12827" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12832">"How, if it were true?" returned Agnese. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12833" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12838">"And you also believe I tell lies? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12839" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12858">I torment myself for you, and then I am not even believed! Good, good, extricate yourselves as you can. I wash my hands of the affair." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="51">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12859" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12874">"Ah, no! do not abandon us," said Renzo; "I speak thus because the thing appears to me to be excellent. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12875" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12886">We are in your hands. I consider you as my veritable mother." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="52">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12887" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12905">These words caused the slight anger of Agnese to disappear, caused her also to forget a resolution which, in truth, was not serious. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="53">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12906" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12927">"But why then, mother," said Lucia with her submissive look, "why then did not this come into Father Cristoforo's mind?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="54">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12928" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12939">"Come into his mind?" replied Agnese; "dost thou imagine it did not come into his mind? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12940" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12945">But he would not speak of it." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="55">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12946" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12953">"Why!" demanded both the young people at the same time. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="56">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12954" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12970">"Because, because—since you wish to know—the clergy say it is a thing which is not good." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="57">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12971" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12986">"How can it be a thing which is not good, and yet be good after it is done?" said Renzo. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="58">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12987" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12993">"What do you wish me to say?" replied Agnese. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12994" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13009">"They have made the laws as it pleased them, and we poor people cannot understand every thing. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13010" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13039">And then how many things — For instance, it is like giving a Christian a blow with your fist; it is not good; but when you have given it him, not even the Pope can remove it." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="59">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13040" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13051">"If this is a thing which is not good, one must not do it," said Lucia. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="60">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13052" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13065">"What?" said Agnese. "I will counsel thee, perhaps, against the fear of God! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13066" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13099">If this were contrary to the will of thy relatives, if it were to marry a good-for-nothing fellow; but the marriage pleases me, and it is to take this good youth. He who causes all these difficulties is a scoundrel, and the Signor Curato—" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="61">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13100" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13106">"It is so clear that every one can understand it." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="62">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13107" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13150">"There is no need to speak of this to Father Cristoforo before it is done," continued Agnese; "but done, and successfully done too, what dost thou think the Father will say to thee?—'Ah, daughter, this is a foolish thing that thou hast done!' Friars must always speak thus. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13151" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13161">But believe, nevertheless, that in the bottom of his heart he will be satisfied—even he." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="63">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13162" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13185">Lucia, without finding anything to answer to their reasoning, did not, however, appear convinced; but Renzo, quite encouraged, said, "If it is thus, the thing is done." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="64">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13186" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13191">"Gently," said Agnese; "and the witnesses? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13192" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13201">How to find two who will and can remain silent? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13202" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13217">And then how to catch the Signor Curato, who for two days has remained in the house? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13218" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13251">And then how to" keep him there? For, although he may be of a heavy nature, I tell you that, as soon as he sees you appear in this manner, he will become as nimble as a cat, and will escape from you like the devil from holy water. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="65">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13252" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13288">“I have found the way! I have found it!” said Renzo, striking his fist upon the table until he made the dinner things dance again; and thereupon he expounded his project to Agnese, who entirely approved of it. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="66">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13289" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13296">“These are stratagems,” said Lucia; “this is not open dealing. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13297" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13317">Until now we have acted sincerely; let us continue to act with faith, and God will assist us. Father Cristoforo has told us this; let us listen to his advice.” </note>
        </p>
        <p n="67">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13318" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13331">“Allow thyself to be guided by those who know more than thou,” said Agnese, with a grave air. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13332" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13337">“What need is there to ask advice? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13338" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13342">God says, ‘help thyself, and I will help thee.’ </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13343" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13349">We will relate all to the Father, when it is done.” </note>
        </p>
        <p n="68">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13350" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13356">“Lucia,” said Renzo, “will you now disappoint me? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13357" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13366">Have we not acted like good Christians? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13367" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13373">Ought we not already to have been man and wife? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13374" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13384">Had not the Curate fixed the day and the hour? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13385" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13398">And where is the crime, if we are now obliged to assist ourselves with a little address? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13399" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13402">No, you will not disappoint me. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13403" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13408">I go, and shall return with the answer.” </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13409" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13424">And saluting Lucia with a supplicating air, and Agnese with an air of intelligence, he sets forth in haste. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="69">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13425" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13467">Tribulation sharpens the intellect. Renzo, in the straight and even path which he had until then trode, had never had occasion to sharpen his, but in this circumstance he imagined a stratagem which would have done honour to a lawyer. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13468" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13518">He went straight, as he had projected, to the cottage of a certain Tonio, who was his neighbour. He found him in the kitchen, with one knee on the hearth, holding the handle of a pot placed on the hot ashes, stirring with a bent spoon a *polenta* of buck-wheat. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13519" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13552">The mother, brother, and wife of Tonio, were seated round the table; and three or four little children crowded round their father waiting, with their eyes fixed on the pot, the moment of emptying it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13553" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13572">But there was not here that joyous air which the sight of dinner ought to occasion those who have earned it by their labour. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13573" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13612">The quantity of the pudding was in accordance with the times, and not with the number and desire of the guests. Each one regarded the common dish with a grim look of rabid love, and seemed to think of the portion of appetite which would still remain over to him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13613" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13644">Whilst Renzo exchanged greetings with the family, Tonio poured out the pudding into the wooden dish which stood ready to receive it, and it appeared a little moon in a great circle of vapour. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13645" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13692">Nevertheless the women said courteously to Renzo, "Will you partake with us?" a compliment which the peasants of Lombardy (and who knows of how many other countries?) never fail to make to whosoever happens to be present at a meal, should the invited be a rich gourmand risen but that moment from table, and the peasant reduced to his last mouthful. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="70">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13693" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13722">"I thank you," replied Renzo; "I am only come to say a word to Tonio; and if thou wilt, Tonio, not to disarrange the women, we will go and dine at the public-house, and talk there." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13723" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13763">The proposition was all the more agreeable to Tonio, since it was so little expected, and the women and also the little lads (upon this subject children early begin to reason) did not see without pleasure a competitor, and the most formidable one too, remove himself away from the pudding. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13764" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13773">The invited one did not stay to demand his share, but set off with Renzo. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="71">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13774" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13832">Arrived at the public-house, and seated at their ease in perfect solitude, for the misery had cleared away all frequenters of this place of delights, and when he had ordered the little which the place afforded, and a bottle of wine to be brought, Renzo said, with an air of mystery, to Tonio, "If thou wilt render me a little service, I will render thee a greater." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="72">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13833" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13846">"Speak, speak; only command me," replied Tonio, pouring out the wine; "I would throw myself into the fire for thee to-day." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="73">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13847" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13865">"Thou art in debt five-and-twenty lire to the Signor Curato, for the rent of his field which thou hadst last year." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="74">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13866" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13872">"Ah, Renzo, Renzo! thou spoilest thy liberality. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13873" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13878">What hast thou just now said? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13879" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13885">Thou hast driven away my good humour." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="75">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13886" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13905">"If I speak of this debt," said Renzo, "it is because, if thou wilt, I intend giving thee the means of paying it." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="76">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13906" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13907">"Dost thou really say that?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="77">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13908" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13908">"Really! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13909" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13911">Shalt thou be satisfied?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="78">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13912" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13917">"Satisfied? *Perdiana!* whether I shall be satisfied? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13918" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13941">Yes, if it were only no longer to see the ugly faces, and signs with the head, which the Signor Curato makes every time we meet! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13942" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13953">It is always Tonio, recollect! Tonio, when shall I see thee about this little affair? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13954" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13980">And it is now come to such a pass, that in the pulpit, when he fixes his eyes upon me, I always fear he is going to say in public,—"Well these five-and-twenty lire, Tonio!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13981" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13986">Cursed be these five-and-twenty lire! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13987" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14004">And then he will have to return me the gold necklace of my wife, which he would change into so much pudding; but —— </note>
        </p>
        <p n="79">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14005" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14018">"But, if you will render me a little service, the five-and-twenty lire are ready." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="80">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14019" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14020">"Speak quickly." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="81">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14021" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14028">"But," said Renzo, laying his fore-finger on his lips. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="82">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n189" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14029" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14036">"Is there need of this? Thou knowest me." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="83">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n190" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14037" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14059">"The Signor Curato has assigned certain bad reasons for delaying my marriage, and I, on the contrary, want to hasten it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n191" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14060" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14090">I have heard that two betrothed presenting themselves before him with two witnesses, and saying, this is my wife, and Lucia saying, this is my husband,—that then the marriage is good and firm. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n192" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14091" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14093">But hast thou understood me?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="84">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n193" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14094" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14099">"Thou wishest me to go as witness?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="85">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n194" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14100" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14101">"Precisely so." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="86">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n195" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14102" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14108">"And thou wilt pay the five-and-twenty lire for me?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="87">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n196" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14109" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14110">"I intend to do so." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="88">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n197" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14111" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14113">"He is a vagabond who neglects to do this." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="89">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n198" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14114" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14119">"But it is necessary to find another witness." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="90">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n199" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14120" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14133">"I have found him; my poor simpleton of a brother, Gervano, will do anything I tell him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n200" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14134" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14138">Thou wilt pay him in drink?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="91">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n201" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14139" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14143">"And in eating too," returned Renzo. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n202" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14144" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14151">"We will bring him with us here to make merry." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="92">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n203" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14152" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14168">"I will teach him; thou knowest also that I have received his share of brains!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="93">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n204" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14169" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14169">"To-morrow." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="94">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n205" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14170" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14170">"Good." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="95">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n206" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14171" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14172">"Towards evening." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="96">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n207" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14173" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14173">"Very good?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="97">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n208" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14174" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14183">"But ----," said Renzo, placing his fore-finger again upon his lips. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="98">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n209" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14184" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14205">"Bah ----!" returned Tonio, inclining his breast towards his right shoulder, and raising his left hand with an air which said, 'thou do'st me injustice.' </note>
        </p>
        <p n="99">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n210" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14206" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14216">"But if thy wife should ask thee, as she will doubtless ----" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="100">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n211" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14217" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14238">"I owe my wife some lies, and so many that I do not know whether ever I shall be able to balance accounts. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n212" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14239" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14248">I will find some little lie to put her heart in peace." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="101">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n213" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14249" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14260">"To-morrow morning we will talk more fully about this, so as better to understand every thing." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="102">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n214" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14261" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14284">With this they left the hostelry; Tonio returned home to study the lie which he should tell the women, and Renzo to give account of the measures concerted. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="103">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n215" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14285" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14328">In this interval, Agnese had wearied herself in vainly endeavouring to persuade her daughter, who opposed to every phrase, now this, now that horn of her dilemma, "either it is a bad action, and, therefore, one ought not to do it; or it is not a bad action, and, therefore, why not communicate it to Father Cristoforo?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n216" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14329" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14365">Renzo arrived all triumphant; he made his report, and terminated it by an "ahn?"—a Milanese interjection, which signifies, am I, or am I not a clever fellow? Could you find a better? Should you have ever had this idea? and a hundred other similar things. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="104">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n217" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14366" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14414">Lucia shook her head gently; but the other two paid no attention to this; but behaved as people are accustomed to do towards a child whom they despair of persuading, but whom they will at length be able to lead, either by prayers or authority, to do all that is required of him. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="105">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n218" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14415" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14426">"That is well," said Agnese, "that is very well; but you have not thought of every thing." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="106">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n219" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14427" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14431">"What is wanting?" demanded Renzo. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="107">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n220" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14432" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14438">"Perpetua! You have not thought of Perpetua. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n221" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14439" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14467">She will easily let Tonio and his brother enter; but you! but you two!—Only think of this! She has doubtless stricter orders to keep you away from the Curate, than a little lad from a pear-tree laden with ripe fruit." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="108">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n222" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14468" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14474">"How shall we manage?" said Renzo, somewhat troubled. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="109">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n223" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14475" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14479">"Here it is; I have thought of it:—see, I will go with you. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n224" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14480" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14503">I have a secret to attract her with, and enchant her in such a manner that she will never perceive you, and you can enter. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n225" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14504" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14512">I will call her. I will touch a string. You shall see." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="110">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n226" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14513" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14525">"Heaven bless you!" cried Renzo. "I have always said you were our good angel in everything." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="111">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n227" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14526" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14547">"But all this helps nothing," said Agnese, "if you cannot persuade this girl, who persists in saying that this is a sin." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="112">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n228" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14548" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14562">Renzo brought his eloquence into the field, but Lucia would not let herself be moved. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="113">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n229" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14563" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14593">"I do not know what to answer to your arguments," said she, "but I see that, in order to do this thing as you say, it is necessary to employ subterfuge, lies, fraud. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n230" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14594" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14636">I wished to be your wife,"—it was not possible for her to pronounce this word, or express this intention, without the crimson mounting to her cheeks,—"I wished to be your wife by the straight road, in the fear of God, and before the altar. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n231" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14637" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14660">Let us leave all things on earth to His direction; do you not think that He will know better how to assist us, than we should with all this falseness? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n232" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14661" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14667">And why make a mystery of it to Father Cristoforo?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="114">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n233" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14668" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14707">The dispute had already lasted long, and did not yet appear nearly ended, when a hasty sound of sandals, and a noise of an agitated robe, like that of the wind in spread sails, announced Father Cristoforo. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap6-n234" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14708" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14727">They became silent, and Agnese had scarcely time to whisper in Lucia's ear, "Take care and don't tell him anything!" </note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>