<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CHAPTER IX.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>1845</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed Lovers: a Milanese Story of the Seventeenth Century. With The Column of Infamy by Alessandro Manzoni. In Three Volumes</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
          <date>1845</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Henry Francis C. Logan</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="English_1845_cap9">
        <p n="1">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10026">The shock of the boat against the shore aroused Lucia. After having dried her eyes in secret, she raised her head as though she had been sleeping. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10027" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10052">Renzo got out first, and gave his hand to Agnese, who followed next, and who in her turn gave her hand to her daughter, and then the three returned thanks to the boatman. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10053" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10111">"For what?" said he, "we are here on earth to assist each other," and he drew back his hand almost with fear, as though they had been proposing to him to steal, when Renzo endeavoured to slip into it a portion of the *quattrinelli* which he had about him, and which he had this evening taken with the intention of regaling generously Don Abbondio, when he against his own will should have served him. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10112" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10134">The cart was ready; the driver greeted the three expected travellers, made them mount, said a word to his horse, gave a crack with his whip, and away. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="2">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10135" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10163">Our author does not describe this nocturnal journey, he is even silent regarding the name of the country whither Fra Cristoforo had directed them, nay, even protests expressly that he does not wish to tell it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10164" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10204">In the progress of the history, the reason of this reticence reveals itself; the adventures of Lucia, during this sojourn, becoming entangled in the blank intrigues of a person belonging to a family, as it appears, very powerful at the time our author writes. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10205" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10239">To assign some reason for the strange conduct of this person in this particular instance, he has been obliged briefly to relate her preceding life, and the family there plays such a singular part that you will easily recognise what family it is, do you only take the trouble to read. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10240" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10260">But that which the circumspection of the poor man has desired to conceal from us, our diligence has found elsewhere. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10261" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10325">A Milanese historian, who has had to mention this personage, names, it is true, neither her nor her country, but says there was a town, old and noble, which to be a city only required the name; says, moreover, that the Lambro flows past it; and moreover, also, that there is an archbishop. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10326" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10336">Comparing these evidences, we deduce that this can be no other than Monza. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10337" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10355">In the vast treasure of erudite induction, there may be more subtle, but that there is a more certain induction, we will not believe. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10356" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10399">We could, even upon a well-founded conjecture, name the family, but although it is already sometime extinct, we will leave the name in the pen, in order not to risk injuring the dead, and also to leave the learned this subject of research. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="3">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10400" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10436">Our travellers arrived then, at Monza, a little after sunrise. The driver entered an hostelry, and there, as familiar with the place and acquainted with the host, he had a room assigned to the travellers, and accompanied them there. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10437" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10477">Between his thanks, Renzo endeavoured to make him also receive some money, but he, like the boatman, had another recompense in view, more distant, but more abundant. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="4">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10478" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10548">After an evening, such as we have described, after a night, such as every one can imagine, passed in the society of such thoughts, with the constant fear of some disagreeable rencontre, exposed to the breath of a breeze more than autumnal, and to the repeated jolting of the inconvenient cart, which rudely roused them up before they had scarcely closed their eyes, it hardly appeared to the three a reality to sit upon a bench which stood firm, and in a chamber, let this be never so homely. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10549" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10572">They made a repast, such as was permitted by the misery of the times, by their means; small in proportion to the accidental wants of an uncertain future, and by their little appetite. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10573" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10594">The three thought of the banquet which two days before they had expected to enjoy, and each one heaved a deep sigh. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10595" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10626">Renzo would have wished to remain there, at least all that day, to see the women lodged, and to render them the first services they might require, but the Father had recommended to Agnese and Lucia to speed him forth immediately on his journey. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10627" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10664">They assigned these orders, and a hundred other reasons; such as people would make remarks, that the separation longer delayed would be still more sorrowful, and that he could soon return and give and receive information. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10665" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10677">They concerted, as well as they were able, the manner of seeing each other again, more quickly than was possible. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10678" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10704">Lucia did not hide her tears, and Renzo had difficulty to restrain his, and squeezing Agnese's hand very tightly, said in a stifled voice, "Till I see you again," and set forth. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="5">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10705" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10736">The women would have found themselves much embarrassed had it not been for the good driver, who was ordered to conduct them to the convent of the Capuchins, and to afford them every other assistance which they might require. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10737" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10754">With him, then, they set out to the convent, which, as every one knows, was a few paces distant from Monza. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10755" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10776">Arrived at the door, the driver pulled the bell, and asked to see the Superior, who came immediately, and received the letter on the threshold. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10777" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10783">"O, from Fra Cristoforo!" said he, recognising the handwriting. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10784" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10800">The tone of his voice and the expression of his countenance plainly shewed he pronounced the name of a very dear friend. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10801" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10857">It is necessary here to mention that our good Cristoforo had in this letter recommended the two women most warmly, and related their case with much feeling; therefore the Superior, from time to time, gave signs of surprise and indignation, and at length raising his eyes from the page, fixed upon the women a certain look of pity and interest. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10858" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10879">When he had finished reading, he remained some time in thought, then said, "There is only the Signora—if the Signora would take upon herself this affair." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="6">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10880" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10931">He then drew Agnese aside upon the space before the convent, and made several inquiries, upon all of which she satisfied him, and then turning towards Lucia, he said, "My good women, I will endeavour to do something; I hope to be able to provide you an asylum more than secure, more than honourable, until the time when God shall provide for you in a better manner. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10932" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10935">Will you come with me?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10936" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10994">The women respectfully replied "Yes," and the Friar continued, "Good, I will conduct you immediately to the convent of the Signora; but, however, keep a few paces distant from me, since the world delights in saying ill-natured things, and God knows how much fine gossip it would make if the Father Superior were seen in the street with a beautiful girl—with women I would say." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="7">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10995" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11032">Saying this he went on in advance; Lucia blushed, the driver smiled and looked at Agnese, who let a half-smile escape her, and all the three followed behind about ten paces removed from the good Superior. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11033" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11050">The women then demanded from the driver that which they had not dared to demand from the Father—who was the Signora? </note>
        </p>
        <p n="8">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11051" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11064">"The Signora," he replied, "is a nun; but she is not a nun like the others; not that she is the abbess, nor the prioress, since, as people say, she is one of the youngest nuns; but she is of the rib of Adam. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11065" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11232">Her family in former times were very great people, who came from Spain, from whence those who command in these parts come; and on this account they call her the Signora, to shew that she is a great lady; and the country calls her by this name, since it is said that in this convent there never before has been a person like her; and her relations at Milan are people of great account, and are of those who are always in the right, and even of still greater account at Monza, since her father, although he does not live here, is the first person in the country, and on this account she can do as she pleases in the convent; and even out of it the people bear her a great respect. If she takes an affair in hand, she succeeds always in making it victorious; thus, if this good monk can obtain her permission to place you in her hands, and she accept you, I can assure you that you are as safe as though before the altar." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="9">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11233" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11299">Arrived at the gate of the town, flanked by a small old tower, half in ruins, and by a piece of an old castle, also ruined, which perhaps some of our readers may remember to have seen still standing, the Superior stopped and turned round to see whether the others were coming, then entered, and directed his steps towards the convent; when he had arrived there, he paused again upon the threshold, waiting for the little company. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11300" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11334">The Father begged the driver to return in a few hours for the answer to Fra Cristoforo; he promised this, and took leave of the women, who loaded him with thanks and commissions for their good friend at Pescarenico. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11335" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11361">The Superior made the mother and daughter enter the first court of the convent; he introduced them into the stewardess's room, and then went alone to ask the favour. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11362" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11394">After some time he reappeared quite joyful, and said that they must come with him; and indeed it was already time that he returned, for the mother and daughter knew no longer how to disengage themselves from the pressing inquiries of the stewardess. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11395" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11410">Crossing a second court, he gave the women some instructions regarding the manner in which they should behave towards the Signora. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="10">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11411" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11425">"She is well disposed towards you, and she can do a great deal for you. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11426" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11448">Be humble and respectful; reply with sincerity to the questions it will please her to ask you; and when not questioned, leave all to me." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="11">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11449" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11481">They entered a room on the ground floor, which led to the parlour; before setting foot there, the Superior, pushing the door open, said in an under voice to the women, "She is here," as though to remind them of all his instructions. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="12">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11482" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11553">Lucia had never before seen a convent; when she was in the parlour she looked around her, seeking everywhere the Signora, to whom to make her rever presence, and not perceiving any one, stood like a person enchanted; but seeing the Father and Agnese going towards a certain corner, she looked in this direction, and saw a window of a singular form, with two great thick iron grates, and behind them a nun standing. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11554" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11577">Her appearance, which denoted perhaps the age of five-and-twenty, made at first sight an impression of beauty, but of beauty cruelly treated, withered, and one might almost say destroyed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11578" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11642">A black veil thrown over the head, and drawn horizontally across her brow, fell on each side at an equal distance from the face; under this veil a bandeau of linen, of a dazzling whiteness, girded a forehead of a different whiteness, but not of an inferior brilliancy; another bandeau in folds surrounded the face, even underneath the chin, then was wrapt round the neck, and extended over the bosom so as to cover the slope of the black robe. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11643" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11760">But this forehead became often wrinkled, as by a painful contraction; and then the two black eyebrows approached each other with a rapid movement; two eyes, also very black, fixed themselves upon you with a proud investigation, then suddenly lowered themselves as though seeking concealment: in certain moments an attentive observer would have believed they demanded affection, sympathy, pity; in others he would have thought to gather in them the instantaneous revelation of an indescribable something of menace and ferocity; when they remained immoveable and listless, he would have imagined there a proud satiety which might be the work of some secret thought, of some pre-occupation of the mind, stronger than the interest excited in her by surrounding objects. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11761" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11779">The very pale cheeks descended into a delicate and graceful contour, but were changed and rendered somewhat sharp by a slow extenuation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11780" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11807">Her lips, although scarcely tinted with a pale rose, stood forth startlingly in the midst of this paleness; their motion was like that of the eyes, sudden, quick, full of expression and of mystery. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11808" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11839">The well-proportioned height of her person became less observable through a certain negligence of deportment, and was disfigured by certain unlooked-for movements, unusual and too decided for a woman, not to say for a nun. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11840" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11903">Even in her dress there was here and there something studied or negligent, which announced a nun of a singular character; her figure was attired with a certain temporal care, and from under the bandeau issued forth a little lock of black hair, a circumstance which proved either forgetfulness or disregard of the rule which prescribes the always keeping shaven the hair cut in the solemn ceremony of taking the veil. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="13">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11904" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11952">These things made no impression upon the women little accustomed to distinguish one nun from another; and the Superior, who did not see the Signora for the first time, was, like many others, used to the singularity which shewed itself in her person as well as in her manners. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="14">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11953" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11986">The Signora was, as we have said, in this moment standing behind the grate, with one hand negligently placed upon it, her very white fingers twisted among the bars. She gazed with great attention at Lucia, who came hesitatingly forward. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="15">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11987" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12023">"Reverend mother, illustrious Signora," said the Superior, his head bowed, his hand on his breast; "this is the poor girl for whom you have made me hope your powerful protection; and this is her mother." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="16">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12024" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12059">The two women thus presented made very low courtesies; the Signora signed to them with her hand that this was sufficient, and said, turning to the Father, "It is a great pleasure for me to be able to do anything agreeable to our good friends, the Capuchin Fathers. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12060" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12081">But," continued she, "tell me a little more, particularly the case of this girl, so that I may see better what can be done for her." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="17">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12082" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12088">Lucia became crimson, and bowed her head. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="18">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12089" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12122">"You must know, reverend mother," began Agnese, but the Superior, by a glance, cut short the words in her mouth, and replied, "this girl, illustrious Signora, comes to me recommended, as I have said, by one of my brethren. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12123" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12158">She has been obliged secretly to quit her country to escape great dangers; and has need of an asylum for some time, where she can live in security, and where no one will venture to disturb her, where——" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="19">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12159" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12175">"What dangers!" interrupted the Signora; "if you please Father Superior, do not tell me the thing thus in enigmas. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12176" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12189">You know that we nuns love to hear histories most minutely told." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="20">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12190" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12205">"They are perils which can scarcely be lightly hinted at to the chaste ears of the reverend mother." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="21">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12206" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12214">"O certainly!" said in haste the Signora, blushing somewhat. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12215" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12216">Was this modesty? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12217" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12250">He who should have observed the rapid expression of disdain which accompanied this blush would have doubted this, and he would have doubted still more had he compared it with the colour which spread itself over Lucia's cheeks. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="22">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12251" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12319">"It is sufficient to say," replied the Superior, "that a gentleman, an oppressor (not all the great of this world make use of the gifts of God for His glory, and for the advantage of the poor, as does the very illustrious Signora, a gentleman, after having a long time pursued this young creature with unworthy flatteries, and seeing that they were useless, has had the heart to pursue her openly with violence, and the unfortunate has been obliged to fly her home. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="23">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12320" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12331">"Approach, young girl," said the Signora to Lucia, making a sign with her finger. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12332" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12351">"I know that the Father Superior is the mouth of truth, but no one can be better informed than you in this affair. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12352" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12363">It is for you to say whether this cavalier was an odious persecutor." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12364" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12374">As to the order to approach, Lucia obeyed this instantly, but to answer was another affair. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12375" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12410">An inquiry upon this subject, even had it been made by one of her equals, would have embarrassed her not a little; made by this Signora, with a certain air of malicious doubt, it was impossible for her to answer. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12411" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12422">"Signora,—reverend mother—" she stammered, and gave no sign of having anything else to say. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12423" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12442">Here Agnese believed herself, as being next to Lucia assuredly the best informed, authorised to come to her assistance. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12443" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12481">"Illustrious Signora," said she, "I can testify that my daughter hated this cavalier, as much as the devil hates holy water; I would say that he was the devil himself, but the Signora will pardon me if I express myself ill, since we are people without ceremony. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12482" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12552">The fact is, that the poor child was promised to a youth, our equal, who lives in the fear of God, and who is well off in the world; and if the Signor Curato had been a little more like one I know—I am aware that I speak of a clergyman,—but Father Cristoforo, the friend of the Father Superior here, is a man of God, and is full of charity; and if he were here he could attest —— </note>
        </p>
        <p n="24">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12553" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12574">"You are very ready to speak without being questioned," interrupted the Signora, with a haughty and angry air, which almost made her appear hideous. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12575" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12594">"Be silent, I only know too well myself that parents have always an answer to give in the name of their children!" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="25">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12595" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12614">Agnese, mortified, cast a glance which meant to say, "Thou seest what has happened to me through thy timidity." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12615" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12642">The Superior also signed to the young girl, glancing and nodding, that this was the moment to exert herself, and not leave her poor mother in embarrassment. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="26">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12643" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12656">"Reverend Signora," said Lucia, "what my mother has said is the pure truth. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12657" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12672">The youth who asked me for his wife," and here she became crimson, "I would accept of my own will. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12673" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12688">Pardon me, I speak boldly; but I do this lest you should think ill of my mother. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12689" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12705">And as to this Signor, God pardon him! I would sooner die than fall into his hands. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12706" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12754">And if the Signora does us the charity to place us in security, since we are reduced to the extremity of demanding an asylum, and of incommoding the rich,—but if the will of God be done, be assured, Signora, that no one will pray for you more from their hearts, than we poor women." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="27">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12755" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12772">"I believe you," said the Signora, with a softened voice; "but I wished to have the pleasure of hearing one by one. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12773" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12797">Not that I have need of other explanations and other motives to make me serve the wishes of the Father Superior," added she, suddenly turning round to him with a studied complaisance. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12798" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12816">"Nay," continued she, "I have already thought of it; and this is what appears to me the best to be done in the present moment. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12817" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12828">The stewardess of the convent has married a few days since the last of her daughters. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12829" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12848">These women can occupy the room left at liberty by this girl, and can render the small services which she used to do here. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12849" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12899">"Truly,—" here she signed to the Superior, who came nearer the grate, and then continued, "truly, considering the dearth there is this year, we did not think of substituting any one in her place, but I will speak to the Lady Abbess, and a little word from me, and as a wish of the Father Superior,—in short, I consider the thing as arranged." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12900" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12925">The Superior began to return thanks, but the Signora interrupted him, "ceremonies are not necessary. Also I, in any circumstance, in any need, should avail myself of the assistance of the Capuchin fathers. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12926" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12949">After all," continued she with a smile, through which transpired an indescribable something of irony and bitterness, "after all, are we not brothers and sisters?" </note>
        </p>
        <p n="28">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12950" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12988">Having said this, she called a lay sister (two such by a singular distinction were assigned to her particular service), and ordered her immediately to inform the Lady Abbess of what had taken place, and then make the necessary arrangements with the stewardess and Agnese. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12989" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12996">She then sent away Agnese, took leave of the Superior, and kept Lucia with herself. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12997" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13033">The Superior accompanied Agnese to the door, giving her new instructions, and then went to write the letter of information for his friend Cristoforo. A very giddy person, this Signora, thought he to himself on his way home,—really a very curious person. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13034" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13048">But he who knows how to manage her weaknesses, can make her do what he likes. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13049" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13061">My Cristoforo will certainly not expect that I have served him thus quickly and well. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13062" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13078">The good man! There is no remedy for it. He must needs always take upon himself some troublesome affair or other, but he does it always for good. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13079" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13109">Fortunate for him this time that he has found a friend who, without much noise, without much preparation, without much difficulty, has conducted the affair to a good port. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13110" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13215">He will be satisfied, this good Cristoforo, and will see also that we here are good for something. The Signora, who in the presence of a poor Capuchin had studied her attitudes and words, at length, left alone with an inexperienced country girl, thought no longer of restraining herself; and her discourse became by degrees so strange, that, instead of relating it, we consider it more in place briefly to recount the history of this unfortunate, or at least so much as is necessary to explain the something so mysterious and extraordinary which we have seen in her, and in order that the motives of her conduct in those facts which we have yet to relate, may be somewhat understood. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="30">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13216" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13234">She was the youngest daughter of the Prince —, a powerful Milanese gentleman, who might be counted among the most opulent of the city. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13235" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13275">But the high opinion which he entertained of his title made his revenues appear to him scarcely sufficient, nay, even inadequate, to sustain it with honour, and his one thought was how, as much as depended upon himself, to preserve this revenue, as it then was, in the possession of one person. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13276" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13323">How many children he had, history does not expressly say; we are only given to understand that he had destined to the cloister all the younger branches of either sex, so as to leave the revenue untouched to his eldest son, destined to preserve the family, that is to give being to children, in order to torment himself and to torment them after the same manner. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13324" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13341">Our unfortunate had not yet seen the light, when her condition was irrevocably fixed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13342" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13366">It only remained to be decided whether it should be a monk or a nun; for the decision of which, not her consent, but her presence was needed. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13367" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13397">When she came into the world, the Prince, her father, wishing to give her a name which should immediately reveal the idea of the cloister, and one which had been borne by a saint of high birth, called her Gertrude. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13398" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13439">Dolls dressed as nuns were the first toys put into her hands; then little saints which represented nuns; and these presents were always accompanied with the injunction to take great care of them as very precious things, and with the affirmative interrogation, "It's beautiful, is it not?" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13440" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13480">When the Prince or the Princess, or the little Prince, the only male child brought up in the house, wished to praise the good look of the little girl, it appeared as though they could only well express their idea by the words, "the pretty Lady Abbess!" </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13481" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13490">No one, however, ever directly said to her, "thou must become a nun." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13491" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13505">This was an understood thing, and was touched upon incidentally in every conversation which regarded her future destiny. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13506" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13551">If now and then the little Gertrude was guilty of arrogant or imperious behaviour, which her disposition easily led her to be, "thou art a little girl now," they would say to her, "these manners are not becoming to thee,—when thou art the Abbess, thou canst command and do just as thou pleasest." </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13552" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13627">At other times, the Prince, reprimanding her for certain other manners too free and too familiar, into which she was equally liable to fall, "Ah, ah!" he would say, "this is not behaviour for one of thy rank. If thou desirest one day that people should shew thee that respect which is due to thy rank, learn early to govern thyself, remember that in every thing thou must be the first in the convent, since thy noble blood remains everywhere the same." </note>
        </p>
        <p n="31">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13628" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13660">All words of this kind impressed in the brain of the little girl the idea that she should become a nun; but those which came from the mouth of her father produced more effect than all the others together. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13661" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13704">The bearing of the Prince was habitually that of a severe master; but when he spoke of the future condition of his children, in his countenance and in his words shewed itself such an immovability of purpose, such a dark jealousy of command, that it impressed you with the feeling of a fatal necessity. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="32">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13705" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13734">At six years old, Gertrude was placed, for her education, or rather for her training to the imposed vocation, in the convent where we have seen her. The choice of this place was not made without design. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13735" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13780">The good conductor of the two women had said that the father of the Signora was the greatest personage at Monza, and comparing this testimony, such as it is, with other indications which the Anonymous lets heedlessly escape him here and there, we can even assert that he was the feudatory lord of the country. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13781" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13818">However this may be, he at least enjoyed at Monza a great authority; and thought that here, better than anywhere else, his daughter would be treated with those distinctions and attentions which would induce her to select the convent for her perpetual abode. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13819" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13891">He did not deceive himself; the Abbess and some other intriguing nuns, who, as the saying is, "have the ladle in their hands," exulting in seeing thus offered to them the pledge of a protection so extremely useful in every occasion, and always so glorious, accepted the proposition with expressions of gratitude, not exaggerated, although they were strong, and responded fully to the intentions which the Prince had let transpire regarding the permanent establishment of his daughter—intentions which so perfectly coincided with their own. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13892" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13950">Gertrude, scarcely entered into the convent, was called by Antonomasia, the *Signorina*, had a place reserved for her at table and in the dormitory, had her conduct cited to the others as an example, was fondled and caressed with many endearments, seasoned with a half-respectful familiarity, which pleases children so much when they observe it in those who are accustomed to treat other children with an habitual air of superiority. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13951" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14025">It was not, however, that all the nuns were plotting to draw the poor child into this snare: there were many of them simple-hearted creatures, far removed from every species of intrigue, to whom the thought of sacrificing a girl to interested motives would have excited horror,—but they were all attentive to their own particular occupations; some did not perceive these plots; others did not distinguish how much in them was bad; some abstained from making any examination; others remained silent, in order not to excite useless scandal. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14026" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14071">Even a few who remembered having been conducted by similar arts to profess that which they afterwards repented of, felt compassion for the poor little innocent, and consoled themselves by lavishing upon her tender and melancholy caresses; she, however, was far from suspecting that there was a mystery in all this. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14072" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14088">And thus the affair progressed, and would perhaps have progressed successfully to the very end, had Gertrude been the only young girl in the convent. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14089" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14103">But among her companions in education here were some who knew that they were destined for marriage. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14104" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14148">The little Gertrude, nourished in her idea of superiority, spoke magnificently of her future destiny as Abbess — as Princess of the convent, and wished to be an object of envy to all. She saw with astonishment and with displeasure that many of these did not shew themselves in the least moved by this proud destiny. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14149" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14186">To the majestic, but somewhat cold and circumscribed images which the pre-eminence in a convent can furnish, they opposed the brilliant and varied pleasure of weddings, of festivals, of balls, of rural parties of pleasure, of rich dresses, and equipages. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14187" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14211">These images produced in Gertrude's mind that movement, that stir, which a great basket, full of freshly gathered flowers, would produce when placed before a beehive. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14212" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14255">Her parents and her instructresses had cultivated and drawn forth her natural vanity, in order to make her love the cloister; but when this passion was excited by ideas much more in accordance with her nature, she threw herself upon them with an ardour much more lively, much more spontaneous. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14256" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14327">Not to remain beneath her companions, and to deliver herself to this new humour, she replied, that, after all, no one could place the veil upon her head without her consent; that she also could marry, live in a palace, and enjoy the world, better even than any of them; that she could do this, if she had wished it; that she should and did wish it, and, in fact, really did. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14328" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14362">The idea of the necessity of her consent,—an idea which until that moment had remained, as it were, unperceived, and shrunk back in a corner of her brain,—unfolded itself there, and shewed itself in all its importance. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14363" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14377">She called it forth every moment to her succour, to enjoy more tranquilly the images of a joyous future. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14378" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14423">Behind this idea, however, always infallibly arrived another; this consent had to be refused,—the Prince, her father, who considered, or appeared to consider, it as already given,—and at this idea the mind of the young girl was far from enjoying the security which her words boasted. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14424" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14448">She compared herself then with those companions who were very differently sure of their future, and experienced bitterly herself the envy which in the beginning she had thought of making them experience. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14449" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14476">Envying, she hated them; sometimes her hatred evaporated in spites, in rudeness, in cutting words; sometimes the conformity of desires and hopes calmed her, and gave birth to an apparent but fugitive intimacy. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14477" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14530">At other times, wishing to enjoy meanwhile something real and of the present, she was pleased with the preference shewn her, and made every one feel her superiority; at other times, being no longer able to support the solitude of her fears and desires, she would go all full of kindness to these comrades, as to implore benevolence, counsel, courage. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14531" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14580">In the midst of these deplorable little combats with herself and with others she had passed her childhood, and found herself in that age so critical, when it seems as though a mysterious power enters into the soul, which excites, adorns, invigorates all inclinations, all ideas, and sometimes transforms and turns them into an unforeseen channel. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14581" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14628">That which Gertrude until then most distinctly desired in her visions of the future was pomp and outward splendour; but an indescribable something, soft and affectionate, which at first had been lightly diffused there, and as it were shrouded in mist, now began to develop itself, and to exceed every thing else in her imagination. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14629" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14695">She had made for herself, in the most secret recess of her mind, as it were, a splendid retreat; here she took refuge from the present, here she received certain strange personages formed out of the confused memories of her infancy, out of the little she could have seen of the exterior world, and out of that which she had learned from her conversations with her companions; with these visitors she conversed, answered in their names, commanded them, and received from them homage of every kind. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14696" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14711">From time to time religious thoughts disturbed these brilliant and fatiguing festivals. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14712" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14742">But religion, such as it had been taught to our poor child, and such as she had received it, did not banish pride; on the contrary, even sanctified and promoted it, as a means of obtaining a terrestrial felicity. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14743" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14757">Thus deprived of its essence, it was no longer religion, but a vain phantom like the others. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14758" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14816">In those intervals in which this phantom occupied the first place in her imagination, and there played the great person, the unfortunate girl, overpowered with confused terrors and a confused idea of duty, imagined that her repugnance to the cloister, and her resistance to the wishes of her family in the choice of her condition of life, was a crime, and she promised in her heart to expiate this by voluntarily shutting herself up in a convent. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="33">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14817" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14881">There was a law, that a young woman could not be accepted as a nun before having been examined by an ecclesiastic, called the Nuns' Vicar, or by some one deputed by him, to the end that it might be known certainly whether she entered the convent by her own choice; and this examination could not take place until a year after she had expressed her desire to the vicar in writing. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14882" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14920">The nuns who had taken upon themselves the sad office of making Gertrude bind herself for ever, with the least possible knowledge of what she did, seized one of these moments to make her transcribe and sign such a supplication. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14921" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14962">In order more easily to lead her to take this step, they did not fail to say and represent to her, that after all this was but a mere formality which (and this was true) would have no efficacy, except by the other acts which should follow, and which would depend upon her own will. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14963" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14982">Nevertheless, the supplication had not yet arrived at its destination, before Gertrude had repented of having signed it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14983" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15000">She repented then of having been penitent, passing thus days and months in an incessant change of sentiment. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15024">She kept a long time concealed from her companions what she had done; sometimes in the fear of exposing to their contradictions a resolution which she considered good, sometimes restrained by the terror of making public a folly. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15025" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15036">At length came the desire of alleviating her mind, and of demanding counsel and encouragement. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15037" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15065">There was another law, which was that a young girl could not be admitted to this examination before having passed at least a month out of the cloister where she had been educated. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15066" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15110">The year had almost elapsed since the supplication had been sent, and Gertrude was informed that in a short time she should be removed from the convent, and conducted to the paternal house, there to pass this month, and to take all the necessary steps for the completion of the work she had begun. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15111" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15149">The Prince, and the rest of the family, held all for certain, as though the affair were terminated; but the young girl had something quite different in her head; instead of taking these other steps, she thought how she should withdraw the first. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15150" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15170">In such anxious circumstances she resolved to open her heart to one of her companions, to the frankest and the one most ready to give resolute counsel. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15171" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15197">This one suggested to Gertrude to inform her father, in a letter, of her new resolve, since she had not courage enough to speak boldly to his face a denial, or would not. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15198" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15221">And since gratuitous advice in the world is so rare, the counsellor gave hers with much bantering about her dulness. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15222" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15241">The letter was concerted among four or five confidants, written in secret, and sent to its destination by means of much studied artifice. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15242" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15306">Gertrude waited with much anxiety for an answer, which never came; except that some days afterwards the Abbess sent for her to her cell, and with an air of mystery, disgust, and compassion, gave her an obscure hint of a great anger of the Prince, and of a fault which she must have committed, giving her, however, to understand that by conducting herself well in future she hoped this would be forgotten. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15307" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15316">The little girl understood, and did not dare to demand more. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="34">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15317" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15324">At length arrived the day so much dreaded, yet so much desired. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15325" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15365">Although Gertrude knew she went forth to a combat, yet the going out of the convent, the leaving these walls in which for eight years she had been shut up, the drive in the carriage through the open country, the seeing again the city, the palace, were sentiments full of a tumultuous joy. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15366" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15466">As far as the combat was concerned then, the poor little creature had already, by the direction of her confidants, taken measures, and, as we should now say, laid her plans. "Either they will wish to force me," thought she, "and then I shall stand firm; or they will be humble and respectful, but then I will not consent—the question is only not to say another yes, and that I will not say; or they will treat me with gentleness, and then I will be more gentle than they; I will weep, I will pray, I will move them to compassion; after all, I only demand not to be sacrificed. But, as it often happens with similar foresight, neither one thing nor the other took place. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15467" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15495">Days passed on without the father speaking of either the supplication, or the recantation, without the slightest proposition being made either with caresses or menaces. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15496" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15508">Her parents were serious, cold, severe towards her, without telling her the wherefore. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15509" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15544">She only perceived that she was regarded as a criminal, as an unworthy person — a mysterious anathema seemed weighing upon her, which separated her from her family, allowing her only sufficient intercourse with them, to make her feel her subjection. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15545" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15561">Very rarely, and only at stated hours, was she admitted to the society of her parents and eldest brother. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15562" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15584">Between these there appeared to reign a very great confidence, which rendered the abandonment in which Gertrude was left still more perceptible and bitter. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15585" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15616">No one turned the discourse towards her; and if timidly she hazarded a word not absolutely necessary, it was either not attended to, or answered with a look of absence, of disdain, or of severity. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15617" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15667">But if, unable longer to support so bitter and humiliating a distinction, she insisted and endeavoured to familiarize herself with her family, or if she even implored a little love, the subject of the choice was immediately touched upon, and she was clearly made to feel that this was the means of acquiring the affection of her family. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15668" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15714">Thus Gertrude, who would never have desired affection on this condition, was obliged to draw herself back, refuse the first signs of kindness which she had so much longed for, and retire of her own accord, to her post of excommunication, and moreover, remaining there, appear to a certain degree to be herself in fault. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="35">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15715" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15741">Such sentiments and objects of reality made a sad contrast to the joyous visions with which Gertrude had been so much occupied, and with which she still always occupied herself in the secrecy of her mind. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15742" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15766">She had hoped, in the splendid and much-frequented paternal house, to have enjoyed some real proof of the things which she had imagined, but she found herself in all deceived. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15767" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15802">The imprisonment was as sure and severe as in the convent; neither was a drive or walk ever spoken of; and a little passage which led out of the house into a neighbouring church, deprived her even of the least possibility of setting foot in the street. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15803" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15814">The society was graver, scarcer, and less varied, than in the convent. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15815" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15839">At every announcement of a visitor, Gertrude was obliged to mount up to the top of the house, there to shut herself up with some old waiting-women, and to dine there, was there any guest. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15840" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15916">The domestics conformed their manners and discourses to the example and intentions of their master; and Gertrude, who, following her own inclination, would have treated them with a lordly familiarity, and who in the situation in which she now found herself would have been grateful for any demonstration of affection from them, as to one of their equals, and who condescended even to beseech it, remained humiliated and grieved to see her advances received with a manifest carelessness, although accompanied by a slight obsequiousness of ceremony. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15917" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15939">She observed, however, that one page, very different from the others, shewed her respect, and seemed to feel a particular kind of compassion for her. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15940" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15971">The behaviour of this boy was what Gertrude had seen the nearest approaching the order of things so much contemplated in her imagination, the most resembling the behaviour of her ideal creatures. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15972" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16016">By little and little an extraordinary something shewed itself in the manners of this young girl—an unaccustomed tranquillity and watchfulness,—the manner of one who has found something which concerns her much, which she would look at every moment, and preserve from the gaze of others. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16017" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16055">She was watched more than ever; so much so that one morning she was surprised by one of her waiting-women folding a paper, upon which she would have done better to have written nothing. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16056" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16075">After a short struggle the paper remained in the hands of the waiting-women, and from them was passed into those of the Prince. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="36">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16076" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16101">The terror of Gertrude, at the sound of his footsteps, can neither be described nor imagined; it was this terrible Father; he was irritated, and she felt herself guilty! </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16102" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16126">But when she saw him appear, with that frown, with that paper in his hand, she would have wished to be a hundred feet under ground,—not to say in a convent. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16127" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16183">His words were not many, but terrible; the intimated chastisement was not immediate,—being shut up again in the chamber under the guardianship of the woman who had made the discovery; this was only the beginning, a remedy for the moment, but another chastisement, obscure, undetermined, and therefore all the more fearful, was promised, was dimly seen in the future. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="37">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16184" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16208">The Page was suddenly dismissed, as was only natural, and even he was also menaced with something terrible, if ever he dared to breathe a word on the subject. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16209" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16233">Giving him this intimation, the Prince administered two solemn boxes on the ear, thus to associate with the adventure a remembrance which should deprive the boy of any temptation to boast of it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16234" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16257">It was not difficult to find some pretext for the dismissal of the Page; as to the daughter, it was said that she was indisposed. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="38">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16258" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16293">Thus she remained with the beating of her heart, with shame, with remorse, and terror of the future, alone with this woman, hateful to her as the witness of her guilt and the cause of her disgrace. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16294" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16323">She in return hated Gertrude, on whose account she found herself reduced, without knowing for how long, to the wearisome life of a gaoleress, and become for ever the keeper of a dangerous secret. </note>
        </p>
        <p n="39">
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16324" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16356">The first confused tumult of these sentiments calmed itself by degrees; but then returning one by one into her mind, they increased there, and fixed themselves to torment her more distinctly and at their leisure. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n189" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16357" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16365">What could this punishment be, thus menaced in enigmas? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n190" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16366" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16380">Many, various and strange, presented themselves to the ardent and inexperienced fancy of Gertrude. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n191" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16381" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16419">What appeared to her the most probable was to be conducted to the convent of Monza, to reappear there no longer as the Signorina, but as a culprit, and remain shut up there, who knows how long? Who knows with what treatment? </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n192" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16420" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16439">Perhaps the most distressing idea which an imagination like hers, thus full of painful images, could present to her, was the apprehension of this disgrace. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n193" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16440" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16505">The words, the phrases, the commas, on this unfortunate sheet of paper, passed and repassed through her mind; she imagined them, looked at and weighed by a reader, so unforeseen, so different to the one for whom it was destined; she imagined it could have fallen under the eyes of her mother, of her brother, and of who knows how many others besides; and in comparison with this, the rest appeared a mere nothing. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n194" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16506" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16547">The image of the one who had been the first cause of all this scandal, was not wanting to torment the poor recluse; and you can imagine what a strange contrast this phantom must have made, seen among others so different, so serious, cold, and menacing. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n195" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16548" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16592">But precisely because she could never separate it from them, nor return one moment to these fugitive joys, without the present sorrows which were the consequence of their stepping forth, she commenced by little and little to return to it less frequently, to chase it from her remembrance, and to divert her mind from it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n196" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16593" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16619">Neither so long, nor so willingly, did she dwell among those gay and brilliant fancies of a former time; these were too much opposed to real circumstances, and to every probability of the future. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n197" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16620" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16647">The only castle in which Gertrude could imagine a tranquil and honourable retreat, which was not a mere fancy, was the convent, therefore she resolved to enter it for ever. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n198" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16648" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16668">Such a resolution she could not doubt would accommodate every thing, pay every debt, and change in a moment her situation. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n199" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16669" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16715">Against this proposition, it is true, opposed themselves the thoughts of all her life; but times were changed. In the abyss into which Gertrude had now fallen, and in comparison with what she had to fear at certain times, the condition of a nun, feted, considered, and obeyed, appeared to her sweet and enviable. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n200" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16716" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16774">Two other sentiments of very different natures contributed also by intervals to diminish her ancient aversion; sometimes remorse for her error and a fantastic tenderness of devotion, sometimes her pride, imbittered and irritated by the manners of her gaoleress, who often, one must confess, provoked by her, revenged herself now in frightening her with the menaced chastisement, now by making her blush for her transgression. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n201" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16775" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16788">At other times, when she wished to shew herself amiable, she assumed a tone of protection more odious even than insult. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n202" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16789" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16835">On such occasions the desire which Gertrude felt to escape from the clutches of this woman, and to appear to her in a condition elevated above her anger and her pity, became so lively and violent, that it made every thing seem lovely which could lead to its gratification. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n203" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16836" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16885">At the end of four or five days' imprisonment, one morning, Gertrude, wearied out and exasperated to an excess by one of these disputes with her guardian, hid herself in a corner of the chamber, and there, her face concealed by her hands, remained some time endeavouring to devour her rage. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n204" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16886" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16901">She felt an overpowering yearning to see other looks, to hear other words, to be treated differently. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n205" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16902" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16912">She thought of her father and of her family. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n206" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16913" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16932">But it flashed across her mind, that it depended alone upon herself to find in them friends, and she experienced a sudden joy. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n207" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16933" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16948">This joy was followed by shame, and an extraordinary penitence for her fault, and an equal desire to expiate it. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n208" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16949" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16967">Not that now her will had fixed upon the determination, but it had never before entered into it with so much ardour. </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845_cap9-n209" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16968" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_17009">She rose, went to a little table, took the fatal pen, and wrote a letter to her father, full of affection and of hope, imploring his pardon, and shewing herself irrevocably decided, and ready to do every thing that should please him, and every thing which he should command. </note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>