<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>2022</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed: a novel</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
          <date>2022</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Michael Moore</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="english_2022_cap12">
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10007">It was the second year of a bad harvest. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10008" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10047">The previous year, past surpluses had compensated for the shortage, to an extent. And the people had made it to the 1628 harvest—the moment we have reached in our story—neither sated nor starving, but quite unprepared. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10048" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10085">This eagerly awaited harvest turned out to be more meager than the year before, partly because of the more inclement weather (not only in the Milan area but throughout the surrounding countryside), and partly because of man. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10086" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10146">The ravages and waste of the war—that lovely war I mentioned earlier—were so great that, in the areas closest to the battlefields, more farmlands than usual lay fallow and abandoned by the peasants. Rather than procure bread for themselves and others through their labor, they were forced to beg for charity. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10147" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10229">I said “more than usual” because the unsustainable taxes, levied with bottomless greed and inanity, and the habitual behavior of the troops garrisoned in the towns, even during peacetime—behavior that the heartrending annals of those times compared to an invading army’s—as well as other reasons that I won’t mention here, had already had a dire effect on the whole state for quite some time. The particular circumstances I am describing here were like the sudden spike of a chronic illness. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10230" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10278">And no sooner had that meager harvest been stored when the provisioning of the army, and the waste that always accompanies it, left such a hole that shortages were immediately felt, and with the shortages came a rise in prices: painful, corrective, and inevitable. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10279" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10317">Once prices reach a certain point, however, many people become convinced (or so far they always have, and if they still do today, after so many reports written by experts, can you imagine back then!) that the shortages are not to blame. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10318" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10365">They forget that they had feared and predicted them, and suddenly imagine that there is enough wheat, and the real culprit is that not enough is being sold for consumption: assumptions that are neither in heaven nor on earth but are based in equal parts on anger and wishful thinking. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10366" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10430">The grain-hoarders, real or imagined; the landowners who did not sell everything immediately; the bakers who bought the grain: anyone, in short, who had either a little or a lot, or was reputed to have some, was blamed for the shortages or the high prices. They became the object of universal complaints and abuse by both the rich and the poor. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10431" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10483">The masses were certain that the storage vaults and granaries were full, overflowing, towering. Exaggerated figures were given for the number of bushels. Other people were sure that huge quantities of grain were being secretly dispatched to towns whose residents were probably just as sure, and just as upset, that their own grain supplies were being sent to Milan. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10484" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10521">The magistrates were implored to adopt the measures that the masses have always, at least until today, felt were so fair, so simple, so suitable for flushing out the grain that was hidden, walled up, buried, as they believed, and would bring back the times of plenty. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10522" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10547">The magistrates did take some actions, such as setting a maximum price on certain goods, threatening penalties against those who refused to sell, and issuing other decrees along these lines. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10548" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10600">Yet no measure in the world, no matter how vigorous, has the power to lower the need for food, nor to obtain crops out of season. And they certainly had no power to extract it from non-existent surpluses. So the hard times continued and grew worse. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10601" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10624">The masses blamed this on the weakness and insufficiency of the remedies, and loudly demanded more generous and decisive steps. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10625" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10634">Unfortunately for them, they found a man after their heart. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10635" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10662">In the absence of the Governor, Don Gonzalo Fernández de Córdoba, who was busy leading the siege on Casale Monferrato, another Spaniard, Grand Chancellor Antonio Ferrer, had stepped in to perform his duties in Milan. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10663" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10699">Ferrer saw—and who would not?—that a fair price for bread is a very desirable thing. He thought—and this was his mistake—that all it would require was an order from him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10700" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10740">He set the bread meta (as they called the tariff on foodstuffs) at a price that would have been fair if the average price for grain had been thirty-three liras a bushel, when in reality it sold for as much as eighty. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10741" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10756">He acted like an aging woman who thinks she can be young again by simply altering her birth certificate. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10757" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10797">Orders less inane and unfair had not been executed, on more than one occasion, since they were so unrealistic. But the masses made sure that this one was, and once their wishes had been converted to law, they ran to the bakers immediately to demand bread at the set price. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10798" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10829">And they demanded it in a resolute and threatening manner stemming from a combination of passion, force, and the law. The people, with a vague sense of something violent in the air, were constantly laying siege to the bakeries, to enjoy the days of plenty while they lasted. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10830" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10836">Did the bakers protest? They didn’t dare! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10837" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10882">All day long, without pause, they moistened the flour, kneaded the dough, and baked and cooled the loaves. Toiling away, as I was saying, wearing their fingers to the bone, and losing money in the process: I’m sure you can see how much fun it must have been for them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10883" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10938">But on the one side were the magistrates, issuing penalties; and on the other was the mob, wanting to get its way, and every time a baker hesitated, the mob would insist, protest loudly, and threaten to mete out its own brand of justice, the worst kind in the world. There was no redemption. The bakers had to mix, bake, cool, and sell. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10939" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10970">But they needed more than orders or intimidation for them to keep up with the demand. What they needed was the capacity to do so. And if the situation had gone on for much longer, they wouldn’t have been able to. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_10971" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11011">They showed the magistrates that the burden imposed on them was unfair and unsustainable. They protested that they wanted to throw their baker’s peels in the oven and leave. In the meantime they kept on baking, wishing and hoping that sooner or later, the Grand Chancellor would come to his senses. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11012" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11065">Antonio Ferrer, however, was what we would call nowadays a “man of character.” He replied that in the past the bakers had benefited greatly, and then some, and that they would benefit greatly, and then some, in the future, when the days of plenty returned. He added that he might consider paying them damages, but in the meantime they should carry on. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11066" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11116">Either he was truly persuaded by his beliefs, which he attributed to others, or—knowing how unrealistic his decree was—he preferred to leave to others the unpopular task of repealing it. Well, who knows what he was thinking? The fact remains that he did not budge from his decision. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11117" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11153">Finally the Council of the Decurioni (a municipal magistracy consisting of noblemen, which continued to exist until the ninety-sixth year of the last century) sent the Governor a letter informing him of the state of things. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11154" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11197">It was Don Gonzalo’s job to find a solution, and to get things running again. Don Gonzalo, who was up to his ears in the business of war, did what I am sure the reader assumed he would do: He appointed a junta to which he delegated the authority to set a price for bread that might work, a price that would make both sides happy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11198" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11256">The deputies met, or as they used to say in the hispanized bureaucratic jargon of the times, they “joined.” And after a thousand and one payings of respects, compliments, preambles, sighs, adjournments, proposals, prevarications—everyone being forced toward a decision by a commonly felt need, knowing full well that they were playing a controversial card, but convinced that nothing else could be done—they decided to raise the price of bread. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11257" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11263">The bakers breathed a sigh of relief. The people howled with rage. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11264" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11312">The evening before Renzo’s arrival in Milan, the streets and squares were teeming with people, possessed by a single fury, and dominated by a single thought. Friends and strangers clustered into groups, spontaneously, almost accidentally, like raindrops on a hillside. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11313" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11328">Speeches were made that reinforced the persuasions and passions of the listeners as much as they did the orators. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11329" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11387">Among the many hotheads there were also cooler spirits who were quite pleased to see that the waters were getting choppy; they plotted to take advantage and make them even choppier with arguments and stories that the cunning are inclined to concoct, and the irate are inclined to believe. They wanted to make the waters even choppier until they had caught a few fish. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11388" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11405">Thousands of men went to bed with the vague feeling that something had to be done, and that something would be done. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11406" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11479">Before daybreak the streets were once again crowded with groups gathering at random: children, women, men, the elderly, workers, the poor. Here a muddled buzzing of many voices. There one man preaching while the others applauded. Here another man asked his neighbor the same question that had been asked of him. There a man repeating the exclamation that was echoing in his ears. All around were complaints, threats, shock, and a small number of words became the raw material for many long speeches. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11480" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11499">All that was missing was an occasion, a spark, an instigation of some sort to transform words into action: It would come soon enough. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11500" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11523">At daybreak the delivery boys emerged from the bakeries carrying large baskets on their backs, filled with bread to deliver to the usual houses. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11524" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11546">The first appearance of one of these hapless boys was like a firecracker landing on a powder keg. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11547" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11555">“Who says there’s no bread!” shouted a hundred voices as one. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11556" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11587">“There’s bread for the tyrants! They’re swimming in abundance and want us to starve to death,” said one man. He went up to the boy, grabbed hold of the basket, gave it a yank, and said, “Let’s have a look.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11588" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11615">The boy turned red, then pale. He was trembling and wanted to say, “Let me go!” but the words died in his mouth. He let his arms go slack and tried to free them from the straps. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11616" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11621">“Drop the basket,” shouted voices all around. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11622" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11645">Many hands grabbed for it at the same time, and then it was on the ground. The cloth cover was cast aside. A warm fragrance filled the air. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11646" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11681">“We’re Christians, too. We need to eat, too!” said the first man. He took a round loaf of bread, held it up to show the crowd, and sunk his teeth into it. More hands on the basket, more bread in the air. In a split second, the banquet was over. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11682" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11711">The people who were left empty-handed, irritated at the sight of the others’ bounty, and encouraged by how easy the enterprise had been, herded off in search of more baskets, emptying as many as they came across. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11712" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11742">There was no need to assault the delivery boys. At the sight of the marauders, the boys unlucky enough to be out and about were only too happy to set down their baskets and hightail it out of there. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11743" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11788">Still, there were very many empty mouths, the conquerors wanted more, and mixing into both groups were instigators who were plotting an even more flagrant disorder. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11789" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11794">“To the bakeries, to the bakeries!” came the cry. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11795" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11853">On the street called the Corsia de’ Servi, there used to be, and still is, a bakery whose name has remained the same. In the Tuscan dialect, its name would be Il Forno delle Grucce (the Crutches Bakery), but in Milanese, it consists of words that are so bizarre, so hard to pronounce, and so barbaric, that the Italian alphabet can barely approximate the sound: El prestin di scanse. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11854" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11859">The crowd was heading in that direction. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11860" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11897">The shopkeepers were questioning their poor delivery boy, who had come back empty-handed and, shocked and traumatized, was stuttering out the story of his sorry adventure, when the sound of a stampede arose and an outcry grew louder and closer. The forerunners of the mob appeared. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11898" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11921">Lock the doors, lock the windows. Hurry, hurry! One man in the shop runs to ask for help from the police commissioner. The others quickly close the doors and board up the windows. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11922" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11935">The crowd starts to gather outside, shouting, “Bread! Bread! Open up! Open up!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11936" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11948">A few minutes later, the police commissioner arrives with an escort of soldiers armed with halberds. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11949" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11966">“Make way, make way, people: Go home, go home. Make way for the police commissioner,” he and the soldiers call out. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11967" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11995">The crowd, which is still sparse, makes room for the officers of the law to come forward and station themselves, in a disorderly cluster, in front of the shop entrance. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_11996" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12005">“My children,” the chief preached from the doorway, “what are you doing here? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12006" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12009">Go home. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12010" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12014">What has happened to your fear of God? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12015" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12020">What would the Lord our Savior say? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12021" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12028">We don’t want to hurt you, so go home. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12029" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12030">Be good! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12031" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12037">What the devil are you doing here, all riled up? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12038" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12047">Whatever it is, it’s no good for the body or the soul. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12048" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12051">Go home, go home!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12052" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12102">But even if the people who saw the speaker’s face and heard his words had been inclined to obey, there was no way they could, since they were being pushed and shoved by the people behind them, who were being pushed in turn by those behind them, in wave after wave, all the way to the outer circle of the mob, which was growing by the minute. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12103" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12109">The police commissioner felt as if he were suffocating. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12110" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12125">“Make them back up so I can breathe,” he ordered the soldiers, “but don’t hurt a soul. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12126" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12133">And then let’s try to enter the shop: Beat them back; use your fists if you must!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12134" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12149">“Get back! Get back!” cry the soldiers, charging the front line and driving it back with the poles of their halberds. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12150" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12198">The people shout and retreat as best they can, shoving their backs into chests, elbows into stomachs, heels onto toes of the people behind them. Between the pushes and the shoves, the people caught in the middle would have paid anything to be somewhere else. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12199" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12247">In the meantime a small empty space had been carved out in front of the door. The police commissioner knocked once, twice, demanded that the shop open up. The workers inside looked out from upstairs, ran down, and opened the door. The chief rushed in and called the soldiers, who squeezed their way in, one by one, the last men holding back the crowd with their halberds. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12248" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12271">Once they were all inside, they bolted the door and boarded it up. The police commissioner raced upstairs and looked out a window: What a mob! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12272" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12282">“People!” he shouted. The crowd looked up. “People, go home. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12283" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12290">I’ll grant a general pardon to all who go home.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12291" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12307">“We want bread! We want bread! Open up! Open up!” were the only words that could be discerned in the crowd’s terrifying reply. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12308" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12315">“Use your heads, my children! Be careful. It’s not too late! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12316" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12320">Come now, go home. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12321" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12329">You’ll get your bread, but this is not the right way. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12330" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12334">Hey…hey! What are you doing down there? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12335" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12340">Hey! You at the door! Eh no! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12341" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12349">I can see you: Use your head! Be careful! That’s a crime, you know. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12350" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12353">You’ll have me to answer to! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12354" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12362">Hey! What are you doing with those iron rods? Put them down! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12363" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12363">Shame on you! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12364" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12376">The people of Milan are known the world over for their goodness! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12377" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12385">Listen to me, listen: You have always been good chil— You dirty dogs!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12386" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12417">His sudden change of speech was provoked by a rock, launched from the hands of one of his “good children,” that struck the chief in the forehead, on the left protrusion of the metaphysical cavity. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12418" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12429">“You dirty dogs!” he continued to shout, quickly shutting the window and taking cover. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12430" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12458">But no matter how loud he hollered, his words, both good and bad, were scattered and defeated in midair by the storm of protests that rose from below. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12459" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12501">What he later reported seeing was a great battering of stones and iron (anything people could lay their hands on) against the door to break it down, and against the windows to tear out the gratings. The operation was already well underway. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12502" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12542">In the meantime from the upstairs windows, the shop masters and apprentices cursed and shouted at the people below to stop. They held up stones and threatened to start throwing them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12543" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12550">When that didn’t work, they really did start to throw them, and not a single one missed its mark. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12551" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12575">The crowd was so tightly packed that, as the saying goes, not even a millet seed would land on the ground. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12576" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12579">“You scoundrels! You villains! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12580" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12588">So this is the bread you give to the poor? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12589" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12590">Uh! Ow! Wait! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12591" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12596">Ouch!” they shouted from below. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12597" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12606">A few people were injured, two boys were killed, and the mob’s fury rose to a peak. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12607" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12627">The door was broken down, the grating torn out, and the crowd flooded through every gap. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12628" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12662">Seeing things take a turn for the worse, the people inside fled to the attic. The police commissioner, the soldiers, and some of the shop boys stayed behind, huddled in the corners. Others, escaping through the garret, took to the rooftops like cats. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12663" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12675">At the sight of the spoils, the conquering army dropped all plans for a gory revenge. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12676" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12685">They raided the pantries and looted the bread. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12686" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12716">Some people raced to the cash drawer, broke the lock, took the tills, grabbed coins by the fistful, stuffed them in their pockets, and left the bakery weighted down with money, only to come back to steal any bread that was left. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12717" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12722">Then the crowd dispersed to the storerooms. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12723" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12835">People grabbed hold of sacks of flour, dragged them out and turned them upside down. Some men stuck a sack between their legs, loosened the opening, and to reduce the load to a manageable amount, tossed out some of the contents. Others shouted, “Wait, wait!” stooped down while holding out an apron, a handkerchief, or a hat to receive the divine grace. One man ran to the kneading trough and grabbed a lump of dough that stretched and slipped every which way. Another, who had conquered a sieve, carried it through the air. There was a coming and going of men, women, children, with pushes and shoves and shouts, and the white powder settling everywhere, flying everywhere, coating and clouding everything. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12836" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12864">Outside two processions moved in opposite directions, crossing and crashing into each other, one coming out with its loot, the other going in to plunder its own. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12865" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12880">While the bakery was being torn apart, none of the other shops in the city were safe. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12881" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12932">But the people did not go rushing to them in large enough numbers to stage an attack. At some the masters had gathered auxiliaries and were ready to defend themselves. At others, finding their numbers too small, the masters came to a kind of détente: They distributed bread to those who had started to gather in front of the shops, in order to make them go away. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12933" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12976">And the looters left, not because they were satisfied but because the halberdiers and the police officers—who had kept their distance from the conflagration at the Crutches Bakery—made their presence felt elsewhere in sufficient force to scare away the stragglers who couldn’t muster a crowd. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_12977" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13011">And so the turmoil continued to escalate at the first hapless bakery; everyone who was itching for trouble raced there, where their friends had the upper hand, and their immunity was guaranteed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13012" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13043">It was at this moment that Renzo, with no bread left to munch on, was walking through the Porta Orientale neighborhood, unaware that he was heading to the heart of the unrest. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13044" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13073">He moved quickly, except when held back by the crowd. As he made his way, he looked around and listened carefully, to see if he could extract from the hubbub of voices more definite news about the situation. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13074" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13092">Here, more or less, are the words he was able to discern: </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13093" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13113">“Now the shameless lies of those crooks are out in the open. And they said there was no bread or flour or wheat!” shouted one man. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13114" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13130">“No more pretending. Now it’s clear as day. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13131" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13132">Long live the days of plenty!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13133" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13159">“This is all a waste of time!” said another. “A drop in the bucket! Things are only going to get worse until true justice is done. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13160" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13178">Prices on bread will go down, but they’ll put poison in it to make us poor die like flies. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13179" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13215">They’re already saying there’s too many of us. That’s what the junta said, and I know it for a fact. I heard it with my own two ears, from a neighbor of mine who’s friends with a relative of one of their scullery boys.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13216" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13241">Words I can’t repeat were uttered by a man who was foaming at the mouth, holding a ragged handkerchief over his tousled, bloodied hair. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13242" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13250">Some passersby echoed his sentiments, as if to console him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13251" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13289">“Make way, make way if you please, gentlemen. Let a poor father of five get through so he can bring some food to his poor family,” said a man who was staggering along with a huge sack of flour. Everyone did their best to step back and let him pass. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13290" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13303">“You want to know what I think?” whispered another to his companion. “I don’t give a damn. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13304" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13313">I’m a man of the world, and I know how these things end up. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13314" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13333">The same half-wits who are making such a stink today will be at home quaking with fear tomorrow or the next day. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13334" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13366">I’ve already seen a few faces, certain gentlemen making the rounds, snooping about, taking note of who’s here and who isn’t. When this is all over, like it or not, someone’s going to have to pay the price.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13367" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13385">“The bakers are protected,” a boisterous voice shouted, “by the Commissioner of Provision.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13386" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13391">“They’re all crooks!” said another man nearby. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13392" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13400">“Yes, but Antonio Ferrer is the biggest crook of them all,” the first man retorted. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13401" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13441">The Governor had selected the Commissioner of Provision from among six noblemen nominated by the Council of Decurioni. The Commissioner served as chairman of the Council and of the Tribunal of Provision, consisting of twelve men, who were also aristocrats. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13442" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13482">Its various duties included the rationing of food. Whoever held this position was, in times of famine and ignorance, inevitably blamed for shortages: unless he behaved like Ferrer, whose ideas he shared, but not his authority. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13483" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13511">“Scoundrels!” exclaimed another. “How much worse can it get? The mob even called the Grand Chancellor a senile old fool, just to discredit him and take over the government themselves. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13512" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13530">We should build a big cage, put them inside, and make them live on pigfeed and weeds, the way they wanted to treat us.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13531" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13557">“Bread?” said one man who was trying to slip away quickly. “It was more like stones, tons of them, and they came raining down like hail, crushing my ribs! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13558" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13564">I can’t wait to get home.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13565" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13589">Amid all this talk, which he was either familiar with or shocked by (I don’t know which), and jostled this way and that, Renzo finally arrived in front of the bakery. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13590" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13618">The crowd had already thinned, so he was able to contemplate the fresh and brutal destruction: the walls battered and pockmarked by stones and bricks, the windows torn off their frames, the door bashed in. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13619" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13643">“This isn’t right,” said Renzo to himself, “if they destroy all the bakeries, where do they expect to bake bread? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13644" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13646">In the wells?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13647" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13692">Here and there someone would walk out of the bakery with a drawer, a cupboard, or a thresher, a rolling pin, a bench, a bread basket, a ledger: anything, in other words, that belonged to that poor bakery. Shouting, “Make way, make way,” they would pass through the crowd. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13693" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13705">Everyone was walking in the same direction, toward a clearly agreed-on place. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13706" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13764">“What is happening here?” Renzo wondered. He followed a man who had tied together a bundle of broken boards and splinters, hoisted it on his back, and was heading, like the others, down the street along the north side of the Duomo, which was named after the staircase that used to be there until a few years ago. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13765" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13794">Renzo’s wish to see what was happening could not keep him from stopping to gaze up at the grand monument, mouth open, when he found himself in front of the cathedral. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13795" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13839">He then started to walk more briskly to get back on the trail of the man he had selected as his guide. He turned the corner, took a look at the façade of the Duomo—which was still rough-hewn, for the most part, and far from complete—and continued to follow the man, who was headed toward the middle of the piazza. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13840" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13872">With each step, the crowd grew more compact, but it opened up for the wood-bearer. He parted the waves of the people and Renzo, close behind, reached the center of the crowd. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13873" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13890">There in the middle was an empty space with a pile of embers as well as the vestiges of the tools and equipment looted from the bakery. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13891" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13908">All around there was a great clapping of hands and stamping of feet, the roar of a thousand cries of triumph and a thousand curses. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13909" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13944">The man threw his bundle on the pile. Another man was trying to get the fire going again with one end of a charred pole. The smoke billowed and grew thicker. The fire started up and the shouts grew louder. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13945" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13946">“Long live the days of plenty! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13947" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13949">Down with the hoarders! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13950" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13952">Down with the famine! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13953" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13958">Death to the Tribunal of Provision! Death to the junta! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13959" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13961">Long live bread!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_13962" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14003">The destruction of the thresher and kneading troughs, the devastation of the bakeries, and the harassment of the bakers, are hardly the most efficient ways to bring back bread, but this is a philosophical subtlety that escapes the comprehension of the masses. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14004" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14035">Without being a great philosopher, however, an individual will sometimes grasp this truth instinctively the first time the question presents itself. But after voicing his own opinion and hearing the opinions of others, he loses that ability. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14036" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14054">Renzo, in fact, was quick to realize how counterproductive the destruction was, as we have seen, and he kept returning to the thought. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14055" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14078">He kept his thoughts to himself, however, because none of the many faces surrounding him seemed willing to say: “Brother, if I am wrong, correct me, and I will be eternally grateful.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14079" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14124">The fire had died down again. No one else arrived with more wood, and the people started to get bored. Then the rumor started that at Cordusio (a nearby piazza), another bakery was under siege. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14125" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14134">In circumstances such as these, it is often the announcement itself that makes something happen. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14135" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14165">As the rumor spread, the mob was filled with the desire to rush over there. “I’m going, are you? Come on, let’s go!” could be heard all around. The crowd split up and turned into a march. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14166" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14205">Renzo lingered in place, almost motionless, until he was dragged along by the force of the mob. He debated whether he should leave the uprising and return to the monastery and Padre Bonaventura, or continue on to witness this second assault. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14206" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14210">Once again his curiosity prevailed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14211" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14237">Still he resolved not to throw himself into the mix and get his bones bruised or worse, but rather to keep a distance and observe. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14238" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14260">Finding himself already off to the side, he took the second loaf of bread from his pocket and, biting into it, headed for the rear of the tumultuous army. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14261" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14285">From the square, the crowd had already entered the short and narrow street of Pescheria Vecchia, and from there, through the slanted archway, to the Piazza de’ Mercanti. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14286" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14359">When passing by the loggia of the building formerly known as the Collegio dei Dottori, there was hardly anyone who did not glance at a statue in a niche. There, prominent, was the stern, forbidding, scowling face—I could say more—of King Philip II, who, even in marble, commanded a kind of respect, and with his outstretched arm, seemed to be saying, “You’ll have to answer to me, you rabble.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14360" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14368">By a unique set of circumstances, the statue is no longer there. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14369" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14404">Almost one hundred and seventy years after the events I am relating, one day the head was altered, and the scepter removed from its hand and replaced with a dagger. The statue was renamed Marcus Brutus. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14405" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14476">It would remain in this configuration for a couple of years until one morning, some individuals who had no particular liking for Marcus Brutus, and indeed must have held a secret grudge against him, threw a rope around the statue, pulled it down, and abused it every possible way. They then dragged it through the streets, mutilated it, and reduced it to a shapeless torso. Finally, completely exhausted, their eyes popping out and their tongues hanging, they rolled it off to God knows where. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14477" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14485">If the artist, Andrea Biffi, had only known its fate when he was carving it! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14486" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14506">From Piazza de’ Mercanti, the mob squeezed into Via de’ Fustagnai, through the other archway, and from there flooded into the Cordusio. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14507" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14518">As each person emerged, they immediately looked in the direction of the bakery that had been mentioned. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14519" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14559">Rather than the multitude of friends they expected to find in action, however, they saw only a few, standing back, as if hesitating, at some distance from the shop, which was closed. The windows were manned by armed individuals, ready to defend themselves. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14560" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14590">At the sight some marveled, some swore, some laughed. Some turned around to tell the others who were arriving in a steady stream. Some stopped, some wanted to turn back, some said, “Onward, onward!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14591" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14609">There was a pushing forward and a holding back, a kind of lull, an indecision, a confused buzzing of disagreements and consultations. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14610" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14637">In the midst of all this, a cursed voice exploded from the crowd, “Near here is the house of the Commissioner of Provision. Let’s take justice into our own hands and ransack it!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14638" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14649">This shout rang out more like a common decision than a fresh proposal. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14650" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14661">“To the Commissioner’s! To the Commissioner’s!” became the only cry that could be heard. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap12-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14662" targetEnd="quarantana/cap12.xml#c12_14679">The crowd surged forward in unison to the street where you find the house that had just been mentioned at this evil hour. </note>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>