<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>2022</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed: a novel</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
          <date>2022</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Michael Moore</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="english_2022_cap16">
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10022">“Run, good man, run. There’s the monastery, here’s the church, over here, over there,” shouted the passersby at Renzo from every corner. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10023" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10032">Run? He hardly needed to be told. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10033" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10075">From the moment that glimmer of hope appeared, he had been making calculations and decided, if he managed to escape the policemen’s clutches, to keep going without stopping until he was well beyond both the city and the state of Milan. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10076" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10144">“They’ve got my name in their damn books,” he thought, “it doesn’t matter anymore how they got it. With my first and last name, they can come and nab me whenever they want.” What about sanctuary? He wouldn’t go seeking it until the police were well behind him. “Why be a bird in a cage, when I can be a bird in the wild.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10145" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10174">So he decided that his refuge would be the village near Bergamo where his cousin, Bortolo, lived (if you remember, he had invited Renzo to move there several times). </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10175" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10182">But finding the way, there was the rub. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10183" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10215">Left to his own devices in a strange part of a strange city, Renzo had no idea which city gate led to Bergamo. Even if he had, he still wouldn’t have known how to get there. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10216" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10310">He was about to ask directions from one of his rescuers, but in the half second available to reflect on his situation, he remembered the much-obliging swordsmith, father of four, from the night before. So to be on the safe side, he decided not to reveal his designs to the crowd, in case it held another man of that ilk, and focused instead on getting away from there as fast as possible. He’d ask directions someplace where no one knew who he was or why he was asking. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10311" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10348">“Thanks, boys,” he told his rescuers, “God bless you.” Then, making his way through a space that had immediately opened up for him, he set off at a run, down an alley, up a street, racing for a stretch without knowing quite where he was going to. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10349" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10385">When he felt far enough away, he slowed his pace to avoid raising suspicions and started to look around for a person he could ask, someone with a face that inspired trust. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10386" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10390">But this, too, was a tricky matter. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10391" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10448">The question itself was suspicious. Time was running out. The police, as soon as they had gotten over their little setback, would set off on the trail of the fugitive. Word of his escape might have already reached this corner of the city. And in these dire straits, Renzo had to scrutinize about a dozen faces before he could find one that was reassuring. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10449" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10521">There was the portly gentleman standing in his shop doorway, legs spread wide, hands behind his back, belly out, chin up, and a fat wattle draped below it. Seeming to have nothing better to do, he alternated between raising his tremulous mass on tiptoe and rocking back on his heels. But he had the appearance of a nosy windbag who, rather than give an answer, would have only asked more questions. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10522" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10550">A man coming toward Renzo, eyes staring straight ahead and lips in a pout, seemed to barely know his own way, much less be able to offer quick and correct directions to a stranger. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10551" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10587">The overgrown boy who looked smart, but also mischievous; he would have probably gotten a kick out of sending a poor peasant in the wrong direction. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10588" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10599">Indeed, for a man in trouble, everything turns into a new source of trouble! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10600" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10631">Finally, catching sight of a man walking quickly, Renzo was willing to bet that someone with a pressing engagement would answer immediately, without a lot of small talk. As he came near, Renzo could overhear him talking to himself, and he sounded like an honest man. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10632" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10648">He approached the stranger and asked, “Excuse me, sir. Which way do I go for Bergamo?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10649" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10652">“For Bergamo? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10653" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10655">Porta Orientale.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10656" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10663">“Thank you. And to get to Porta Orientale?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10664" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10675">“Take this street here to the left. It’ll bring you to Piazza Duomo, and then…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10676" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10681">“That’ll do, sir. I know the rest of the way from there. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10682" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10685">God bless you.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10686" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10695">Having been set straight, he started off in the direction pointed out to him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10696" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10729">The man watched him for a minute, and putting together that question with his haste, said to himself, “Either he did something wrong, or someone wants to do him wrong.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10730" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10836">Renzo arrives in Piazza del Duomo. As he crosses it, he passes a pile of ashes and spent coals, and recognizes the remains of the bonfire he witnessed the day before. He walks by the steps to the Duomo and sees the Forno delle Grucce again, half demolished and guarded by soldiers. And he goes straight down the road from which he had come with the mob. He reaches the Capuchin monastery. He casts a glance at the piazza and the door to the church, and says to himself, sighing, “I should have listened to what the friar told me yesterday: ‘Stay in church, wait, and do a good deed.’ ” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10837" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10880">Here he stopped for a moment to carefully study the gate through which he had to pass. From the distance he could see that it was heavily guarded. Given the circumstances, and his overheated imagination (you have to sympathize: He had his reasons, after all), he was reluctant to attempt to cross. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10881" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10900">Now he found himself close by a place where he could ask for sanctuary and, with that letter, he would be welcomed in. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10901" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10913">He felt a strong temptation to enter, but he immediately summoned his courage and thought, “I should be like a bird in the wild, for as long as I can. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10914" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10916">No one’s heard of me. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10917" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10956">The police have enough on their hands. It’s not like they’re waiting for me at every gate.” He turned around to see if anyone was coming from behind. He saw neither the police nor anyone else who appeared to be looking for him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10957" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10979">He continued on, slowing the pace of his damn legs, which always wanted to run when it was more advisable to walk. In this way, slowly but surely, whistling softly all the while, he arrived at the gate. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_10980" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11065">A group of customs officers were gathered at the crossing point in addition to some Spanish musketeers, as reinforcement. But their attention was directed outside of the city, to prevent the entry of anyone who, at the news of the rioting, might flock to the scene like crows to an abandoned battlefield. So Renzo, with a carefree air, his eyes lowered, and going at a pace suited for either a long journey or a short stroll, was able to leave the city without being noticed. But his heart was pounding. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11066" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11087">Spotting a lane to the right, he veered off to avoid the main road, and walked for a stretch before daring to turn around. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11088" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11113">He walked and walked, passing farmsteads and villages, continuing on without stopping to ask their names. He knew he was getting farther from Milan and hoped he was headed toward Bergamo. For the moment, that was enough. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11114" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11144">Every so often he would look back. Every so often he would stare down at and rub first one wrist and then the other. They were still sore, covered with crimson bruises left by the handcuffs. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11145" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11194">His thoughts, as you can imagine, were a jumble of regrets and anxiety, rage and tenderness. He struggled to piece together the things said and done the night before, to identify the missing pieces of his awful experience, wondering in particular how they had learned his name. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11195" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11208">His suspicions fell naturally on the swordsmith, to whom he clearly remembered having blurted it out. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11209" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11242">Thinking back on the way it had been extracted from his mouth, and on the stranger’s overall demeanor, the courtesies that always seemed to be asking for something, his suspicions became almost a certainty. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11243" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11289">Yet he also had a vague recollection of having continued to converse after the swordsmith’s departure. But with whom? He could only guess. And about what? His memory, no matter how deeply he searched it, revealed nothing: except that it had been temporarily absent. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11290" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11335">The poor boy wracked his brain. He was like someone who had signed a stack of blank checks and entrusted them to a man he believed was a model of integrity; after learning that the man was a swindler, he wanted to understand his own predicament. But understand what? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11336" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11359">All he could see was confusion! At the same time, he struggled to come up with a feasible plan for the future, but all the options were either fanciful or depressing. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11360" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11372">Soon, however, the most painful conflict became how he would find his way. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11373" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11390">After walking what you might call aimlessly, he realized he could not figure out the route on his own. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11391" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11419">But he was still reluctant to even say “Bergamo,” as if the word itself were suspicious or rude, but he could not continue on without naming his destination. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11420" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11441">So he decided to do what he had done in Milan, and ask the first passerby with a friendly face, which is what he did. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11442" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11469">“You’re going the wrong way,” the man answered, and after reflecting for a moment, he indicated the route for the main road, using both words and gestures. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11470" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11513">Renzo thanked him and headed in that direction, pretending to follow the man’s instructions. It was his intention, however, to get close to the blessed main road, keep it in sight, and walk parallel to it for as long as he could without setting foot on it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11514" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11523">But his plan was easier to conceive than to execute. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11524" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11603">Eventually, by going right and then left, in a sort of zigzag, partly by following other directions he had found the courage to elicit here and there, partly by adjusting them to his own whims and intentions, and partly by letting the roads themselves guide him, our fugitive had walked about twelve miles, but was still no more than six miles away from Milan. As for Bergamo, he’d be lucky if he wasn’t farther away than before. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11604" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11623">He began to realize that he was getting nowhere fast, so he tried to come up with another solution. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11624" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11681">He decided to figure out, through subterfuge, the name of a town near the border that could be reached by back roads. Then, by asking for that town, he would find his way, without leaving a trail of questions about Bergamo, which could suggest escape, flight, or criminality. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11682" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11704">As he sought a way to elicit this information without raising suspicions, he saw a leafy branch hanging from a solitary house on the outskirts of a village: the symbol of an inn. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11705" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11732">For some time, he had been feeling a growing need to replenish his energy. He thought it would be just the place to kill two birds with one stone and entered. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11733" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11747">The only person there was an old woman with a distaff by her side and a spindle in her hand. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11748" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11794">He asked for a bite to eat and was offered a little stracchino cheese and some good wine. He accepted the stracchino and declined the wine (which he had come to detest, after the trick it had played on him the night before). And he sat down, asking the woman to be quick. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11795" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11830">In a minute she had the cheese on the table, and immediately started to pester her guest with questions about himself and the goings-on in Milan, rumors of which had reached as far as this village. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11831" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11860">Renzo managed not only to easily deflect her questions, but, taking advantage of this dilemma, turned the old woman’s curiosity to his own purposes. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11861" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11895">When she asked where he was headed, he replied, “I have to go to a lot of places, and if I find some time to spare, I’d also like to take a moment to stop by that good-size town on the road to Bergamo, the one near the border but still in the Duchy of Milan…What’s its name again?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11896" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11908">He said to himself, “There has to be one.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11909" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11914">“You mean Gorgonzola?” asked the old woman. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11915" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11925">“Gorgonzola!” Renzo repeated, as if to commit the word to memory. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11926" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11932">“Is it very far from here?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11933" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11941">“I’m not sure. It must be ten, maybe twelve miles. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11942" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11952">If one of my sons were here, he could tell you.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11953" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11974">“And do you think a person could get there on a nice old country road? It’s way too dusty on the main road. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11975" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11979">It hasn’t rained for months!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11980" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11998">“I think so. You can ask in the first village you reach down the road there to the right,” and she gave its name. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_11999" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12041">“Good,” said Renzo. He stood up and took a piece of bread that was left from his meager lunch, a bread quite different from the loaf he had found at the foot of the San Dionigi cross the day before. He paid his bill, left, and went straight down the road. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12042" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12066">To make a long story short, he went from village to village with the name “Gorgonzola” on his lips, and arrived about an hour before nightfall. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12067" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12084">While walking, Renzo had already decided to stop in Gorgonzola for a little while, to have a somewhat more substantial meal. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12085" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12106">His body could have used a bed, too, but he would sooner have let it collapse on the road, exhausted, than surrender to that pleasure. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12107" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12135">His plan was to find out in town how far it was to the Adda, tease out information about side roads that would take him there, and head in that direction immediately after eating. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12136" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12194">Having been born and raised at the so-called second source of the river, he had often heard that the Adda formed a border between the states of Milan and Venice. At which point and for how long, he did not know exactly. For the moment, the most urgent question was how to get across, no matter where. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12195" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12232">If he didn’t succeed that day, he had decided to keep walking as long as the hour and his strength would allow, and then to wait for daybreak, in a field or a wasteland, wherever God pleased, so long as it wasn’t an inn. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12233" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12270">A few steps into Gorgonzola, he spotted a sign for a tavern. Entering, he asked the host for a bite to eat and a half carafe of wine: The extra miles and late hour had helped him to overcome his extreme, fanatical distaste for it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12271" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12284">“Please be quick,” he added, “because I need to be on my way again.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12285" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12324">He said this not only because it was true, but also for fear that the host would imagine he wanted to sleep there, and start up with questions about his first and last name, where he was coming from, and what his business was…Beware of all that! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12325" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12347">The host replied that the food would be coming right up, and Renzo sat down at the far end of the table, near the door: the bashful corner. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12348" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12421">In the room there were a few of the village sluggards who, after discussing and commenting about the events in Milan the day before, were eager to learn a little about what had happened on the present day, too. Especially since the first tidbits were always more likely to arouse curiosity than to satisfy it. An uprising, neither suppressed nor victorious, suspended rather than ended by nightfall, seeming more like the end of an act than the end of the play. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12422" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12438">One of the men broke away, walked up to the newcomer, and asked whether he was arriving from Milan. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12439" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12447">“Who, me?” asked Renzo, caught off guard and trying to buy time before answering. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12448" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12453">“Yes, you, if you don’t mind the question.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12454" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12489">Renzo shook his head, pursed his lips, and made an inarticulate sound. “Milan,” he replied, “from what I’ve heard…is no place to go right now, unless you really have to.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12490" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12501">“So the rioting is still going on?” asked the busybody, more insistently. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12502" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12508">“You’d have to be there to know,” said Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12509" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12514">“But aren’t you coming from Milan?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12515" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12528">“I’m coming from Liscate,” the young man replied quickly, having finally managed to find an answer. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12529" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12569">Strictly speaking, he actually was coming from there, since he had passed through. He had learned the name from a traveler on the road who had explained that it was the first village he would pass on his way to Gorgonzola. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12570" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12584">“Oh!” said the friend, clearly wishing Renzo had come from Milan. Nothing he could do about it, though. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12585" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12594">“And in Liscate,” he continued, “didn’t they hear any news from Milan?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12595" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12612">“I wouldn’t be surprised if someone did,” replied Renzo, “but not me. I didn’t hear a thing.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12613" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12628">He uttered these words in a particular manner, as if to say, “Enough.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12629" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12644">The busybody went back to his place and, a moment later, the innkeeper arrived with the food. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12645" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12667">“How far is it from here to the Adda?” Renzo mumbled, feigning disinterest, as we’ve seen him do other times. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12668" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12672">“To the Adda? To a crossing?” said the host. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12673" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12675">“I mean…yes…to the Adda.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12676" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12686">“Do you want to cross by the Cassano bridge or the Canonica ferry?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12687" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12693">“It doesn’t matter…I’m only asking out of curiosity.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12694" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12713">“What I mean is, since those are the places where honest men cross, people who have nothing to hide.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12714" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12718">“I see. So how far is it?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12719" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12735">“Figure that it’s about six miles to either place, give or take.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12736" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12742">“Six miles! I didn’t realize it was so far,” said Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12743" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12768">“Well, if somebody needed to take a shortcut, are there other places where one could cross?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12769" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12796">“Of course there are,” replied the innkeeper, staring into Renzo’s face with two eyes brimming with malicious curiosity, and an expression that quashed the other questions the young man was about to ask. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12797" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12819">Renzo pulled the plate toward himself and, staring at the carafe the host had set down, asked, “Is this an honest wine?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12820" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12841">“As good as gold,” said the innkeeper, “anyone from around here will say the same.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12842" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12848">With that, he returned to the others. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12849" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12940">“Damn innkeepers!” exclaimed Renzo to himself. “Each one is worse than the next.” Nonetheless, he settled down to eat with a hearty appetite. At the same time, pretending it didn’t concern him, he listened carefully, trying to read the minds of the locals, and discover their thoughts on the great events in which he himself had played no small part. Above all, he wanted to see whether, among them, there might be one honest man whom he could trust enough to ask for directions without fear of being cross-examined and forced to discuss his private affairs. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12941" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12954">“Well,” said one of them, “this time it looks as if the people of Milan mean business. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12955" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12962">Anyway, we’ll find something out tomorrow, at the latest.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12963" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12974">“I wish I’d gone to Milan this morning,” said another. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12975" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12988">“If you go tomorrow, I’ll go, too,” said a third, then another, and then another. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_12989" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13018">“What I want to know,” continued the first, “is whether the fine gentlemen of Milan will spare a thought for the poor country folk, or if they’ll still go ahead and make laws that are only good for themselves. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13019" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13022">You know how they are. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13023" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13034">Uppity city folk. Everything for themselves. And the others? As if they didn’t exist!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13035" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13076">“We’ve got mouths, too. For eating and speaking our minds!” said another, in a voice as modest as his proposal was bold, “And once the ball gets rolling…” but he thought better than to finish the sentence. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13077" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13098">“Milan isn’t the only place where they hoard the grain,” began yet another man with a dark, malicious tone. Just then they heard a horse approaching. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13099" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13109">Everyone ran to the door and, recognizing the new arrival, went out to meet him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13110" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13144">He was a merchant from Milan who went to Bergamo several times a year on business, and tended to spend the night at the inn. Since he always found the same company there, he knew everyone, and they crowded around him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13145" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13155">One held the bridle, another the stirrup. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13156" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13161">“Welcome! Welcome!” “Good to see you!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13162" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13165">“How was your trip?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13166" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13171">“Excellent, and you boys? How are you?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13172" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13173">“Fine, fine. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13174" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13179">Any news from Milan?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13180" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13197">“Ah, always the same questions,” said the merchant as he dismounted, leaving his horse in the care of a stable boy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13198" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13214">“And then, and then,” he continued, entering the tavern with the group, “at this hour you probably know more than me.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13215" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13226">“No, we really don’t,” said more than one, hands over their hearts. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13227" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13230">“Really?” said the merchant. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13231" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13238">“Then I’ll tell you the good…and the bad. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13239" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13247">Hey, innkeeper, do you have my usual bed? Good. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13248" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13276">A glass of wine, and my usual bite to eat, right away. I want to go to bed early so I can leave early tomorrow morning and reach Bergamo by lunchtime.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13277" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13304">Settling down across the room from where Renzo sat, silent and attentive, he continued. “You men don’t know about all the ruckus yesterday?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13305" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13307">“Yesterday? Yes, we do.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13308" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13317">“So you see,” the merchant went on, “you do know the latest. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13318" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13331">I thought as much, since you’re always here keeping watch, scrutinizing every passerby…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13332" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13336">“But what about today? What happened today?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13337" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13338">“Today? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13339" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13342">You don’t know anything about today?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13343" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13348">“Nothing! No one has come by.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13349" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13403">“Let me wet my lips first, and then I’ll tell you everything…” He filled his glass and raised it in one hand, while with two fingers of the other he curled his mustache and stroked his beard. Then he had a sip and went back to his story. “Today, my dear friends, came close to being as turbulent as yesterday, or worse. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13404" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13434">I can scarcely believe I’m here chatting with you, since earlier I had set aside any thought of traveling, in order to stay put and guard my poor shop.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13435" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13441">“What the devil happened?” asked one of his listeners. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13442" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13445">“Devil’s the right word: You’ll hear just how right.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13446" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13462">After cutting up the food on his plate, and taking a bite, he went on with his story. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13463" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13502">His companions, standing around the table, listened with their mouths agape. Renzo, from his corner, while pretending it didn’t concern him, paid close attention, more than anyone else, and chewed his last morsels of food very slowly. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13503" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13542">“So this morning those same rabble-rousers, the ones who made such an awful ruckus yesterday, arrived at the appointed places (there was already a secret pact: Everything had been planned). They gathered and started up again with their usual rigamarole, going street to street, crying out to attract more people. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13543" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13563">You know, it’s like when you’re sweeping the floor, with all due respect. The more you sweep, the higher the dirt heap. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13564" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13598">When they felt they had enough people, they headed for the house of the Commissioner of Provision. As if their attacks on him yesterday weren’t bad enough! On a gentleman like him! What scoundrels! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13599" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13606">And the things they said about him! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13607" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13632">All lies! He’s an honest, proper man. Take it from someone who knows. I’m a frequent visitor to his house. I supply him with cloth for his servants’ livery. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13633" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13663">You should have seen the riffraff marching on his house! The faces on them! They passed right in front of my shop! Faces that…worse than even the Jews in the paintings of the Stations of the Cross! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13664" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13686">And the things that came out of their mouths! I’d have plugged my ears except that it didn’t seem wise to draw attention to myself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13687" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13697">So there they were, marching with every intention of looting. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13698" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13717">Until…” and here, raising his left hand in the air and opening it, he placed the tip of his thumb on the tip of his nose. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13718" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13723">“Until?” asked all of his listeners as one. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13724" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13754">“Until,” the merchant continued, “they found the road blocked with carts and crossbeams, and behind that barricade, a neat row of Spanish musketeers, with their guns arranged to give them the welcome they deserved. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13755" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13763">When they saw that fine display…what would you men have done?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13764" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13765">“Retreat.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13766" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13769">“Of course. And that’s exactly what they did. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13770" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13781">But you tell me if it wasn’t the devil himself leading the parade. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13782" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13864">They were on Piazza Cordusio, where they saw the bakery, the same one they’d been wanting to loot since yesterday. And what was happening in that shop? They were busy giving away bread to every customer. Noblemen, plenty of noblemen, were there, too, making sure that everything went smoothly. So in came the riffraff (possessed by the devil, if you ask me, them and the ones egging them on), pouring in like furies. It was a free-for-all; they grabbed anything that wasn’t nailed down, whatever they could lay their hands on. In the blink of an eye everything was upside down: gentlemen, bakers, customers, bread loaves, counter, benches, bins, cupboards, sacks, threshers, wheat bran, flour, dough.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13865" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13867">“What about the musketeers?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13868" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13884">“They were busy guarding the Commissioner’s house. You can’t both sing in the choir and carry the cross. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13885" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13902">It all happened in the blink of an eye, I tell you. They cleared the place out. Anything worth taking was taken. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13903" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13923">And then they started up again with that idea from yesterday, of carrying everything left out into the piazza and setting it on fire. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13924" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13947">The scoundrels had already started throwing stuff outside. Then can you guess the brilliant idea that occurred to the biggest crook of them all?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13948" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13950">“No, tell us.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13951" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13968">“To pile everything up inside the shop, and set fire to the pile and to the house with the same match. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13969" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13970">No sooner said than done.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13971" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13974">“Did they set the fire?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13975" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13975">“Wait, there’s more. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13976" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13983">A good soul from the neighborhood had a divine inspiration. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_13984" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14018">He ran upstairs looking for a crucifix. He found one, attached it to the window frame, and from a headboard took two holy candles, lit them, and placed them on the windowsill on either side of the crucifix. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14019" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14023">The crowd looked up. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14024" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14038">One thing you can say about the people of Milan, they still have the fear of God in them. Everyone came to their senses. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14039" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14071">Most everyone, I mean. There were still some devils who’d set fire to heaven itself if they could loot it. But when they saw the crowd turn against them, they had to stop what they were doing and calm down. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14072" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14076">And guess who should suddenly appear? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14077" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14152">All the cardinals from the Duomo, in procession, dressed in full canonicals, with the cross raised high. Monsignor Mazenta, the archpriest, started to preach on one side, while Monsignor Settala, the Father Confessor, spoke to the other, and the rest of the cardinals did the same. ‘Good people! What has gotten into you? Is this any example to set for your children? Go home! Don’t you realize that bread is cheap again, cheaper than before? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14153" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14154">Go see for yourselves. There’s a bulletin on the corners.’ ” “Was it true?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14155" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14155">“Are you kidding? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14156" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14169">Do you think the monsignors of the Duomo would arrive in cappa magna to talk rubbish?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14170" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14174">“So what did the people do?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14175" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14192">“Little by little they left. They ran to the corners where the price was there to see for anyone who could read. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14193" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14201">Guess how much? An eight-ounce loaf for one soldo.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14202" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14203">“That’s cheap!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n189" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14204" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14211">“Indeed. Let’s see how long it lasts. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n190" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14212" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14222">Do you have any idea how much flour was wasted between yesterday and this morning? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n191" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14223" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14229">Enough to feed the Duchy for two months!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n192" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14230" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14240">“What about outside of Milan? Did they pass any laws for our benefit?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n193" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14241" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14252">“What was done in Milan was done at the city’s expense. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n194" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14253" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14265">God will have to provide for you. What else can I say? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n195" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14266" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14272">Anyway, the riots are over. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n196" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14273" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14280">But I haven’t told you everything. Now comes the good part.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n197" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14281" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14283">“What else is there?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n198" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14284" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14305">“Last night or this morning, there were a lot of arrests. And word got out that the ringleaders would be hanged. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n199" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14306" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14325">As soon as the rumor began to spread, everyone took the fastest road home to avoid being included in their number. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n200" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14326" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14335">By the time I left Milan, it looked like a monastery.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n201" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14336" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14338">“Will they really hang them?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n202" type="comm" status="insertion">“You bet they will. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n203" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14339" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14344">And quickly, too,” the merchant replied. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n204" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14345" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14357">“And the people of the city, what will they do?” asked the same man who had asked the previous question. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n205" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14358" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14365">“The people? They’ll go to watch,” said the merchant. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n206" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14366" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14386">“What were they expecting? They were so eager to string up a Christian in the open air, the scoundrels. They thought they would stick it to the Commissioner of Provision? Think again. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n207" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14387" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14412">Instead of him, it’s going to be four wretches swaying in the wind, treated to all the formalities, accompanied by the Capuchins and the Happy Death Confraternity. They deserve it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n208" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14413" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14420">You see, it’s an act of Providence. It had to happen. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n209" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14421" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14454">They were already getting into the habit of entering shops and helping themselves without reaching into their pockets. If we let them get away with bread, the next thing you know it’ll be wine, and so on and so forth. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n210" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14455" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14467">Do you think they’d give up such a convenient practice of their own free will? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n211" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14468" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14485">And let me tell you, for an honest man who keeps his shop open, it’s not a very comforting thought!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n212" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14486" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14490">“You’re right,” said one of his listeners. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n213" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14491" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14497">“You’re right,” repeated the others as one. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n214" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14498" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14515">“And,” continued the merchant, patting his beard dry with the napkin, “the plans had been laid well in advance: There was a conspiracy, did you know?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n215" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14516" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14518">“A conspiracy!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n216" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14519" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14521">“A conspiracy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n217" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14522" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14558">A plot cooked up by the French court, by that cardinal, you know the one I mean! The man with a Turkish-sounding name, who every day thinks up a new way to disrespect the Spanish Crown. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n218" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14559" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14580">He’s set his sights on Milan, since he knows all too well, the smart aleck, that it’s the King’s stronghold.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n219" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14581" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14581">“Of course.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n220" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14582" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14585">“Do you want proof? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n221" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14586" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14605">Who made the most noise yesterday? The foreigners! Faces the likes of which Milan had never seen before. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n222" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14606" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14617">In fact, I forgot to tell you something I heard from a trusted source. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n223" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14618" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14653">The police had nabbed someone at an inn…” Renzo, who hadn’t missed one syllable of the conversation, felt his blood run cold, and gave a start before he could think to contain himself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n224" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14654" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14695">No one noticed, however, and the speaker, without interrupting the thread of his story, went on. “They still don’t know where he came from, who sent him, or what type of man he is. But he was definitely one of the ringleaders. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n225" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14696" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14726">Well, yesterday, at the peak of the uproar, he was raising hell. And then, as if that wasn’t enough, he started making speeches, and proposing—how kind of him!—to kill all the nobles. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n226" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14727" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14727">The scoundrel! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n227" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14728" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14738">How could the poor survive if all the nobles were killed? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n228" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14739" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14778">The police, who’d been keeping an eye on him, arrested him. They found a bundle of letters on him, and were dragging him off to jail, when what should happen but his partners, who’d surrounded the tavern, came running in great numbers and freed the bloody murderer!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n229" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14779" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14782">“And what happened to him?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n230" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14783" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14836">“Who knows? He’s either fled Milan or is still in hiding. People like that have neither a house nor a roof, but they still find places everywhere to take cover and hole up. Sooner or later, though, even the devil’s luck runs out. They end up behind bars when they least expect it. Because when the pear is ripe, it has to fall. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n231" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14837" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14867">For now, what we know for certain is that his letters are in the hands of the police, and they describe the whole plot, and the rumor is that many people are caught up in it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n232" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14868" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14882">Serves them right. They ransacked half of Milan and were ready to do even worse. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n233" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14883" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14888">They say that the bakers are crooks. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n234" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14889" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14898">I agree. But they should only be hanged after a proper trial. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n235" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14899" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14902">Wheat is being hoarded. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n236" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14903" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14906">We all know that. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n237" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14907" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14931">But it’s up to our rulers to have a good network of informants, find the stockpiles, and string up the hoarders alongside the bakers. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n238" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14932" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14978">And if our rulers do nothing about it, then it’s up to the city to petition the Crown, and if the first petition is turned down, then petition it again and again. Because if you insist, you will eventually win, but you can’t let the criminal habit take root of walking into shops and warehouses and taking whatever you want with impunity.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n239" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14979" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14988">The little that Renzo had eaten stuck in his throat. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n240" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_14989" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_15012">He felt as if a thousand years had elapsed since he’d been outside and far away from that inn and that village. More than ten times he must have repeated to himself, “Get going, get going!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n241" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_15013" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_15035">But his fear of arousing suspicion, which had grown by leaps and bounds and tyrannized his every thought, kept him nailed to his seat. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n242" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_15036" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_15061">In his panic, he knew that sooner or later this windbag would have to stop talking, so he decided that he would get moving as soon as he heard the conversation shift to another subject. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n243" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_15062" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_15098">“That’s why I stayed home,” said one member of the group. “I know how these things turn out, and know that a riot is no place for an honest man, so I didn’t let curiosity get the better of me.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n244" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_15099" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_15106">“What about me? Did you see me budge?” said another. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n245" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_15107" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_15130">“And me?” added a third. “If I’d found myself in Milan by chance, I’d have dropped everything and gone straight back home. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n246" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_15131" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_15144">I’ve got a wife and children. Not to mention that I don’t much care for all the noise to be honest.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n247" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_15145" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_15166">Just then, the innkeeper, who had also been listening, went to the other end of the table, to see how the stranger was doing. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap16-n248" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_15167" targetEnd="quarantana/cap16.xml#c16_15213">Renzo took the opportunity to gesture to him and ask for the bill. He paid it without haggling, although his funds were dwindling. And then, without another word, he went straight to the door, crossed the threshold, and with Providence as his guide, set off in the opposite direction from which he had come. </note>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>