<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>2022</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed: a novel</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
          <date>2022</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Michael Moore</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="english_2022_cap10">
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10055">There are moments when the spirit, particularly of youth, is so vulnerable that the slightest nudge will make it accept anything with the appearance of virtue and sacrifice; like a flower that has just bloomed, it collapses gently onto its fragile stem, ready to surrender its fragrances to the first breath of air. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10056" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10086">Such moments, which others should admire with timid respect, are seized upon by self-interest to fetter an unguarded will. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10087" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10104">Upon reading his daughter’s letter, Prince *** immediately spied an opening for his long and unwavering ambition. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10105" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10123">He summoned Gertrude, and prepared to strike the iron while it was hot. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10124" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10147">She appeared and, without raising her eyes to look her father in the face, threw herself on her knees before him, with barely enough breath to say, “Forgive me!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10148" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10193">He gestured for her to stand up, but in a voice unsuited for encouragement, he responded that it was not enough to want or ask for forgiveness. That would be too easy, too natural, for someone who had done wrong and feared punishment. Forgiveness, in short, had to be earned. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10194" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10202">Trembling and chastened, Gertrude asked what she had to do. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10203" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10247">The Prince (at a moment like this I don’t have the heart to call him her father) did not answer directly, but instead started to speak at length about her error. His words stung the poor girl’s spirit, like a calloused hand rubbing a wound. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10248" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10299">He went on to say that, even if…perhaps…he had earlier harbored some intention of finding a situation for her outside the convent, she had created an insurmountable obstacle, since a man of honor, like himself, would not stoop to offering another gentleman the hand of a signorina who had given such proof of her character. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10300" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10365">The poor girl was mortified. Then the Prince, gradually softening the tone of his voice and his words, went on to say that, nevertheless, for every error there was redress and mercy; that hers was of the kind for which redress was most clearly prescribed; that she should see this sinful lapse as a warning that the secular life was too full of danger for her… </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10366" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10384">“Oh, yes!” exclaimed Gertrude, shaken by fear, prepared by shame, and moved in that moment by a sudden fit of tenderness. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10385" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10393">“Ah! So you do understand!” the Prince continued relentlessly. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10394" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10403">“Well, then, let us speak no more of the past. All is forgotten. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10404" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10452">You have chosen the only honorable, suitable path still open to you. But since you have done so of your own free will, and in the proper manner, it is my duty to make sure that you are gratified everywhere and in everything. It is my duty to restore your every privilege and merit. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10453" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10457">I shall see to it.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10458" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10478">At this, he shook the bell on the side table, and to the servant who came in he said, “The Princess and the young prince. At once!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10479" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10501">He then told Gertrude, “I want to share my consolation with them immediately. I want everyone to start treating you properly at once. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10502" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10517">You have experienced a part of what the severe father can be. From now on you shall feel the whole loving father.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10518" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10524">At these words, Gertrude was dumbstruck. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10525" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10578">She wondered how that “yes” which had slipped out could portend so much. She tried to think of a way to retract it or restrict its significance. But the Prince’s conviction seemed so complete, his joy so jealous, his benevolence so conditional, that Gertrude did not dare utter a word that might disturb him in the least. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10579" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10596">A few moments later, the summoned parties arrived. They were skeptical and surprised to see Gertrude, and they stared her up and down. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10597" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10625">But the Prince, with a joyful, loving demeanor that commanded them to act likewise, said, “Behold the lost lamb. May this be the last reminder of a painful memory. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10626" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10630">She is the consolation of our family. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10631" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10648">Gertrude no longer requires advice. Now she desires of her own accord what we had wanted for her own good. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10649" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10686">She has made up her mind, and told me”—here she raised her eyes toward her father with a look both terrified and imploring, as if to beg him to stop, but he continued undeterred—“that she has decided to take the veil.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10687" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10717">“Brava! Wonderful news!” exclaimed mother and son in unison, each giving her a hug. She received their welcome with tears, which they interpreted as tears of consolation. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10718" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10736">The Prince then expounded on the things he would do to make his daughter’s future splendid and joyful. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10737" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10776">He spoke of the privileges she would enjoy in the convent and the town. That she would be treated like a princess, the representative of her family. That as soon as she came of age, she would be elevated to the highest rank. And in the meantime, she would be a subordinate in name alone. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10777" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10796">The Princess and the young prince continued to shower her with congratulations and praise. Gertrude felt as if she were in thrall to a dream. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10797" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10814">“We should set the date to go to Monza to make the request to the abbess,” the Prince said. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10815" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10817">“She’ll be so happy! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10818" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10831">I can tell you, the whole convent will appreciate the honor Gertrude bestows upon them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10832" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10837">In fact…why don’t we go today? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10838" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10843">Gertrude will be glad to get a little fresh air.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10844" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10848">“Yes, why don’t we?” said the Princess. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10849" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10856">“I’ll go to give the orders,” said the young prince. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10857" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10860">“But…” Gertrude started to say, submissively. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10861" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10884">“Wait a minute, now,” the Prince continued, “we should let her decide. Perhaps she does not feel ready today, and would rather wait until tomorrow. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10885" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10891">Tell me: Would you like us to go today or tomorrow?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10892" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10910">“Tomorrow,” was the faint reply of Gertrude, who still thought she could accomplish something by taking her time. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10911" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10921">“Tomorrow,” said the Prince solemnly. “She has decided that we shall go tomorrow. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10922" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10934">In the meantime, I will go to the vicar of the nuns to set a date for the examination.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10935" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10959">No sooner said than done. The Prince left and went to the vicar himself (no small concession), and they agreed that she would appear in two days. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10960" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10973">For the rest of the day, Gertrude did not know a moment’s peace. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_10974" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11025">She would have preferred to rest from all the commotion, to clear her head, so to speak, to take stock of what she had done and still had to do, to know her mind, and to delay, for a moment, the machine that, only just set into motion, was already moving so precipitously. But there was no stopping it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11026" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11034">Her obligations came fast and furious, one on top of the other. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11035" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11058">Immediately after the Prince’s departure, she was led to the dressing room of the Princess, where her mother had her own maid comb Gertrude’s hair and had her dress. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11059" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11072">The finishing touches had not even been applied when the announcement came that dinner was served. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11073" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11116">Gertrude passed between servants bowing to express their congratulations on her recovery. At the table, she found some of her closest relatives, who had been quickly assembled to pay homage to her and to celebrate two happy occasions: her restored health and the announcement of her vocation. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11117" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11156">The little bride (as young novices were called, and as everyone greeted Gertrude when she appeared) had her hands full responding to the compliments raining down on her from every side. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11157" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11173">She could clearly hear that her every answer was a form of acceptance and confirmation. But how else could she respond? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11174" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11182">From the table, the party moved immediately to the hour of the trottata. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11183" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11197">Gertrude got into the carriage with her mother and two uncles who had been at dinner. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11198" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11233">Following the usual route, they came out on Strada Marina, which in those days crossed the space occupied today by the public gardens, and used to be where the nobility arrived in their carriages for restoration from the fatigues of their day. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11234" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11321">The uncles spoke with Gertrude, as required by the occasion. One of them, more than the other, who seemed to know every person, every carriage, every livery, and in every moment had something to say about this gentleman or that lady, suddenly turned to her and said, “Aren’t you the smart one, turning your back on all this rubbish! Very clever! You’re leaving us poor society folk in this mess, withdrawing from the world to lead a holy life, and going to heaven in a horse-drawn carriage!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11322" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11342">Later that afternoon they returned home. The servants, hurrying down the stairs with torches, informed them that quite a few visitors were waiting. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11343" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11358">The word had spread and the relatives and friends were coming to pay their respects. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11359" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11363">They entered the reception room. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11364" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11372">The little bride was the idol, the plaything, the victim. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11373" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11417">Everyone wanted her for him- or herself: This one made her promise to send him sweets, that one promised to visit, one mentioned her relative, Madre something or other, one her acquaintance, Madre someone else, this one raved about the Monza sky, that one chatted, with great delight, of the fine figure she would cut in the convent. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11418" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11447">Others, who hadn’t managed to penetrate the throng besieging her, looked for an opportunity to come forward, and felt a bit guilty until they had paid their respects. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11448" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11469">Little by little, the crowd thinned out. Everyone departed free of guilt, and Gertrude was left alone with her parents and her brother. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11470" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11485">“Finally,” said the Prince, “I have had the consolation of seeing my daughter treated in the manner to which she was born. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11486" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11514">I have to admit, however, that some of the credit is hers, for she showed that she will have no problem leading the convent and upholding the family reputation.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11515" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11528">They dined quickly in order to retire immediately and be ready to depart early the next morning. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11529" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11585">Bitter, vexed, and at the same time a bit swellheaded from all the flattery, Gertrude remembered her suffering at the hands of her prison-keeper. Seeing her father so ready to grant her every wish but one, she sought to take advantage of this favorable juncture to appease the first of the passions that tormented her. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11586" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11599">So she expressed her great distaste at finding herself with that woman, and complained loudly about her manners. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11600" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11608">“What!” said the Prince. “She failed to show you respect? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11609" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11616">Tomorrow I’ll give her the scolding she deserves. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11617" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11631">Leave it to me, I’ll remind her of who she is, and who you are. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11632" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11651">In no event should a daughter with whom I am so pleased have to lay eyes on someone not to her liking.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11652" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11688">At this, he summoned a different woman and ordered her to serve Gertrude, who meanwhile, ruminating on and savoring the satisfaction she had received, was surprised to find how little it fulfilled her expectations. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11689" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11743">Despite herself, she was overwhelmed by how much closer that day had brought her to the cloister, and by the realization that turning back now would take more strength and determination—which she could feel were sorely lacking—than even a few days before. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11744" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11788">The woman assigned to her chamber was an elderly member of the household, the young prince’s former governess, who had taken charge of him the minute he was out of swaddling clothes, raised him until he was an adolescent, and invested in him all her pleasures, hopes, and glory. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11789" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11872">She could not have been happier with that day’s decision than if it had been her own good fortune. As her final entertainment, Gertrude had to suffer the old woman’s congratulations, praise, and advice, and listen to her prattle on about certain of her aunts and great-aunts who had been delighted to be nuns. As members of such a distinguished house, they had always received preferential treatment, always been able to keep one foot outside the convent, and had achieved things in their parlors that the grand dames, in their salons, could only dream of. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11873" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11911">She described the visits she would receive: One day soon, the young prince would arrive with his bride, who would most certainly be a grand signora. And on that day not only the convent but the whole town would be abuzz. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11912" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11939">The old woman kept on talking while she was undressing Gertrude, and while Gertrude lay in bed. She was still talking when Gertrude fell asleep, her thoughts overcome by youth and exhaustion. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11940" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11970">Although her sleep was troubled, agitated, and full of bad dreams, it was unbroken until the old woman’s shrill voice woke her up to get ready for the trip to Monza. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11971" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11988">“Up, up, my little bride! The day is dawning! It’ll take at least an hour to get you dressed and your hair combed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_11989" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12001">The Princess is getting dressed. They woke her four hours earlier than her usual. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12002" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12021">The young prince has already gone down to the stables, come back, and is ready to leave at any moment. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12022" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12043">Quick as a hare, that little devil. Has been ever since he was a little boy. Take it from me, who carried him in my arms. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12044" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12062">But when he’s ready to go, you’d best not keep him waiting. He’s good-natured, that he is, but having to wait is the one thing that’ll make him lose his temper and start carrying on. Poor thing. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12063" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12083">You have to understand. It’s his nature. And you can hardly blame him on a day like today, because he’s going to all this trouble for you. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12084" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12100">You’d best steer clear of him when he’s like this! He’s got no regard for anyone, except the Prince himself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12101" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12114">After all, the only person above him is the Prince, and one day he himself will be prince. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n87" type="comm" status="insertion">Let’s not get ahead of ourselves, though! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12115" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12117">Come, come, Signorina! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12118" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12122">Why are you looking at me in such a daze? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12123" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12129">At this hour you should already be out of the nest!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12130" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12156">At the image of the impatient young prince, all the other thoughts that had crowded into Gertrude’s awakening mind took off like a flock of sparrows at the sight of a hawk. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12157" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12176">She obeyed, dressed quickly, allowed her hair to be combed, and made her appearance in the drawing room, where her parents and brother were already assembled. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12177" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12209">She was seated in the place of honor, and offered a cup of hot chocolate, the equivalent in those days of the toga virilis for the ancient Romans. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12210" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12237">When the announcement arrived that the carriage was ready, the Prince drew his daughter to the side and said, “Now, Gertrude. Yesterday you were a credit to yourself. Today you have to do even more. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12238" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12257">It’s a question of making a solemn appearance at the convent in the town where you are destined to be a leading citizen. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12258" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12273">They are waiting for you…” Needless to say, the Prince had notified the abbess the day before. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12274" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12282">“They are waiting for you, and all eyes will be upon you. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12283" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12285">Dignity and self-assurance. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12286" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12294">The abbess will ask you why you are there: It’s a formality. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12295" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12322">You should respond that you are requesting admission to the convent, to wear the veil in the place where you received such a loving education, and where you were treated with such courtesy. Which is the God’s honest truth. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12323" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12345">Say these few words in a relaxed manner. You don’t want people to think you’re just repeating things that were put in your mouth, or that you can’t speak your own mind. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12346" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12375">The good sisters know nothing about what happened. It’s a secret that must remain buried in the family. So don’t go looking contrite or hesitant, which might raise suspicions. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12376" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12399">Show them your breeding: well-mannered, modest. But remember that there, away from the family, no one will be your superior.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12400" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12422">Without awaiting a reply, the Prince started to leave. Gertrude, the Princess, and the young prince followed him. They all descended the palace stairs and climbed into the carriage. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12423" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12449">The troubles and annoyances of the world, and the blissful life in the convent, especially for girls of noble blood, were the subjects of conversation during the trip. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12450" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12468">Near the end of the road, the Prince renewed his instructions to his daughter, and repeated to her over and over the formula for the expected response. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12469" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12501">As they entered Monza, Gertrude felt her heart sink. She was momentarily distracted when a cluster of gentlemen (I don’t know their names) stopped the carriage to pay some sort of customary homage (which I also don’t know). </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12502" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12523">Then their journey to the convent resumed at a snail’s pace, amid the gawking of the curious, who came running from every direction. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12524" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12543">When the carriage came to a halt, before that familiar wall, before that familiar gate, Gertrude could feel her heart sinking even lower. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12544" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12556">She alighted between two rows of onlookers that the servants held back. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12557" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12601">Every eye was on the poor girl, making her painfully aware of her every move. But what made her most uneasy, more than all these eyes put together, were the eyes of her father, whose gaze, despite her terror, she could not avert for even a second. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12602" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12618">And those eyes, like invisible reins, controlled her movements and her expression. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12619" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12641">Once she had crossed the first courtyard, she entered another from which she could see the gate to the inner cloister, opened wide, and filled up with nuns. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12642" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12666">In the first row was the abbess, surrounded by the older nuns. In the next, an assortment of other nuns, some on tiptoe. At the very back were lay sisters standing on footstools. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12667" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12714">Here and there you could see the glimmer of some brighter eyes, some faces that stood out from among the habits: They were the bravest and sharpest of the schoolgirls who, by poking and squeezing their way between the nuns, had managed to open up a space so that they, too, could enjoy the spectacle. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12715" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12730">A clamor arose from that crowd and arms could be seen waving to signal their welcome and their joy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12731" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12744">They had arrived at the door. Gertrude found herself face-to-face with the Mother Abbess. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12745" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12773">After some initial greetings, the latter asked, with a mixture of gaiety and solemnity, what Gertrude desired in that place, where no one could deny her anything. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12774" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12808">“I am here,” Gertrude began. But on the verge of uttering the words that would irrevocably seal her fate, she hesitated for a moment and stared into the crowd assembled before her. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12809" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12839">And in that moment she saw one of her old schoolmates, staring at her with both pity and malice, as if to say, “So, you didn’t have the pluck to resist!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12840" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12935">That sight inflamed her old feelings and also restored a little of her old courage. She was already searching for a response other than the one that had been dictated to her, when she looked up at her father, as if to test her mettle. In his face she detected such a dark apprehension, such a menacing impatience, that she changed her mind as quickly as you’d flee a terrifying object. She then said, “I am here to request admission to wear the religious habit, in this convent, where I was raised so lovingly.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_12936" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13017">The abbess replied at once, saying how sorry she was, on such an occasion, that the rules would not allow her to give an immediate answer, which had to come from the general vote of the sisters and be approved by the ecclesiastical authorities, but that Gertrude, knowing how everyone felt about her there, could predict the answer with certainty. And in the meantime, no rule forbade the abbess and the nuns from expressing their joy at her request. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13018" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13026">At that a clamor of congratulations and applause arose. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13027" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13043">Large trays piled high with sweets appeared, and were presented first to the little bride and then to her parents. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13044" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13072">While some nuns fawned over her, others complimented the mother, and still others the young prince, the abbess conveyed an invitation to the Prince to approach the grate of the parlor, where she would be waiting for him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13073" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13136">She was accompanied by two elderly nuns. “Your Lordship,” she began, “to honor the rules…to discharge an indispensable formality, although in this case…still it is my duty to tell you…that every time a daughter asks to take the veil…the Mother Superior, of whom I am the unworthy…is required to advise the parents…that if, by any chance…they had forced the daughter against her will, they would be excommunicated. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13137" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13138">My deepest apologies…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13139" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13142">“Excellent, Reverend Mother, excellent. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13143" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13154">I admire your scrupulousness. It is quite appropriate…But how can you doubt…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13155" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13165">“Please understand, your Lordship…I have spoken as I am required to…Besides which…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13166" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13169">“Of course, Mother Abbess, of course.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13170" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13207">Having exchanged these few words, they bowed to each other and took their leave, in mutual discomfort. And each went back to join his or her respective group, one beyond, the other within the threshold of the cloister. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13208" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13231">After a little more small talk: “Come, come,” said the Prince, “Gertrude will soon be able to enjoy the company of the good sisters at her leisure. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13232" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13237">We have inconvenienced them enough for now.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13238" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13255">At this he made a bow, and the family followed suit, renewed their compliments, and left. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13256" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13264">Gertrude had no desire to speak on the way back home. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13265" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13318">Terrified by the step she had taken, ashamed of her ineptitude, annoyed at both herself and others, she made a grim count of the occasions left for her to say no, and promised herself, vaguely and feebly, that on one of those occasions, she would be stronger and more adept. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13319" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13377">Despite these thoughts, her fear of her father’s scowl had not subsided in the least. She stole a glance at him and could tell that every trace of anger was gone from his face. When she saw that he appeared to be quite satisfied with her, she felt that it was good, and, for a moment, was happy as can be. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13378" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13398">Once home, they had to freshen up and change; then there was lunch, then visitors, then the trottata, then the reception, then dinner. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13399" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13414">After all of this, the Prince brought up another matter: the choice of a sponsor. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13415" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13485">That’s what they called the lady who, at the parents’ request, became the guardian and chaperone of the young postulant in the period between the request and the admission into the convent: a period that was spent visiting churches, public palaces, receptions, country estates, shrines: all the most notable things in the city and its environs, in short, so that girls, before making an irrevocable vow, could have a good look at what they were leaving behind. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13486" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13517">“We will need to think of a sponsor,” said the Prince, “because tomorrow the vicar of the nuns will be here, for the formality of the examination, and immediately after that Gertrude’s name will be submitted to the chapter of nuns for their acceptance.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13518" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13537">At this, he turned toward the Princess. Believing he was asking for her advice, she started to say, “Well, there is…” but the Prince interrupted her. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13538" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13579">“No, no, your Ladyship. The sponsor should above all be a person whom the little bride likes. And while it is traditionally the parent’s decision, Gertrude is so wise, so sensible, that she has earned the right to an exception.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13580" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13631">Here, turning toward Gertrude, as if to bestow a special favor, he continued, “Each of the ladies who came to our reception this evening has the qualifications to sponsor a daughter of our house. There is no one, I daresay, who would not feel honored to be selected: The choice is yours.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13632" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13666">Gertrude could see that making this choice was yet another form of consent. But the proposal was made with such ceremony that to reject it, however humbly, might seem disrespectful, or, at the very least, fickle and coy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13667" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13716">So she took yet another step forward, and gave the name of the lady who had appealed to her the most that evening. The one, that is to say, who had fawned over her the most, flattered her the most, and treated her with the affectionate and caring familiarity that, in the early moments of an acquaintance, masquerades as an old friendship. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13717" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13727">“Excellent choice,” said the Prince, who had wanted and expected that same lady. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13728" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13772">It was like a card trick played by a magician. He fans a deck of cards before your eyes, tells you to think of one, and then guesses which card it was; but, whether by chance or design, he had fanned them out in such a way that you only saw one. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13773" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13800">That lady had hovered about Gertrude the whole evening, and so monopolized her that the girl would have needed a leap of the imagination to think of anyone else. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13801" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13850">Nor were these attentions so innocent. The lady had long set her eyes on the young prince as a future son-in-law. So she already regarded the affairs of that house as her own and, of course, cared as much for dear Gertrude as she did for her closest relatives. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13851" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13885">The next day, Gertrude woke up thinking of the examiner who was scheduled to come. While ruminating on if and how best to seize this decisive occasion to turn back, she was summoned by the Prince. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13886" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13900">“Now child,” he began, “up until this point you have behaved admirably. Today you have to coronate the endeavor. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13901" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13911">Everything done so far has been done with your consent. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13912" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13944">If any doubts, any regrets, any youthful whims had crossed your mind, you should have said so. But it’s too late now for any mischief. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13945" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13976">The honest man who is coming today will ask you a hundred questions about your vocation: whether you are becoming a nun of your own free will, and why, and how, and what not. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13977" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13988">If you hem and haw in your answers, who knows how long he might go on. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_13989" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14004">For you it would be annoying, or rather, agonizing. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14005" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14051">What’s worse, after all the public displays, the least hesitation on your part would compromise my honor. People might think I had mistaken one of your whims for a firm decision, that I had rushed this business, that I had…Who knows what they might think? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14052" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14145">In that case, I would find myself having to choose between two painful options: either to let society form an unfortunate opinion of my conduct, which I do not deserve in any manner, shape, or form; or reveal the true reason for your decision, and…” Seeing that Gertrude had turned crimson, her eyes were swelling, and her face was shrinking like a flower in the sweltering heat before a storm, he dropped the subject and, in a calmer tone of voice, said: “Come now, everything depends on you and your good judgment. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14146" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14168">I know how smart you are, and that you’re not the type of girl who would spoil something at the end that had started out so well. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14169" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14193">So not another word about this. We shall agree that you will answer frankly, in such a way as not to plant any doubts in the head of that righteous man. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14194" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14201">In this way you’ll get it over with more quickly.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14202" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14240">At this point, after suggesting answers to the most likely questions, he resumed his usual talk about the delights and pleasures that awaited Gertrude in the convent. And he continued in this vein until a servant appeared to announce the arrival of the vicar. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14241" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14258">The Prince quickly repeated his main warnings, then he left his daughter alone with the man in accordance with the rules. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14259" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14287">The righteous man came somewhat predisposed to believe that Gertrude had a strong vocation for the cloister, since this is what the Prince had told him when he issued the invitation. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14288" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14354">The good priest knew that skepticism was one of the main requirements of his office, and he made it a rule to distrust similar claims and beware of preconceived notions. But the forthright assertions of a person of authority, on any subject, rarely leave the listener’s mind untainted. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14355" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14400">After the initial greetings, “Signorina,” he said, “I have come here to play the devil’s advocate. I have come to cast doubt on the certainties that you have provided in your application. I have come to show you the difficulties of this life and to ascertain that you have considered them carefully. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14401" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14407">Will you allow me to ask you a few questions?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14408" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14411">“Please do,” replied Gertrude. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14412" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14423">The good priest then began to question her in the prescribed form. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14424" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14435">“In your heart do you feel a free, spontaneous resolution to become a nun? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14436" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14442">Have you received threats or enticements? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14443" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14453">Have you been threatened by any authority to force you into this? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14454" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14483">Please speak freely and honestly to a man whose duty it is to know your true will, in order to prevent you from being subjected to any type of coercion.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14484" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14499">The true answer to that question leapt to Gertrude’s mind with a terrifying clarity. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14500" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14517">To give that answer, she would have to explain what had happened, say who had threatened her, tell the story…The unhappy girl shrank from this idea in fear. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14518" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14546">She hastened to find another answer, and found only one, the one farthest from the truth, which would free her from that torment swiftly and surely. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14547" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14561">“I am becoming a nun,” she said, hiding her agitation, “I am becoming a nun of my own free will.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14562" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14574">“How long have you felt this way?” the good priest continued his questioning. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14575" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14591">“For as long as I can remember,” replied Gertrude, who once she had taken that first step, had become better at lying to herself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14592" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14603">“What is your main reason for wanting to become a nun?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14604" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14632">The good priest did not realize what a terrible nerve he had touched. Gertrude made a great effort to keep her face from revealing the effect of those words on her spirit. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14633" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14647">“The reason,” she said, “is to serve God and to escape the dangers of the world.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14648" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14656">“Could it not be a feeling of revulsion instead? Or…forgive me…a whim? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14657" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14681">Sometimes a moment’s reason might seem permanent, but when that reason ceases to exist, you change your mind, and then…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14682" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14694">“No, no,” Gertrude quickly replied. “The reason is the one I gave you.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14695" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14721">The vicar, more from a sense of duty than any belief that there was a need, pressed on with his questions. But now Gertrude was determined to deceive him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n189" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14722" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14776">In addition to her revulsion at the idea of revealing her weakness to that austere and righteous man, who seemed to harbor no suspicions of her, the poor girl knew that while he could prevent her from becoming a nun, his authority over her, and his protection, would end here. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n190" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14777" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14784">Once he was gone, she would be alone with the Prince. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n191" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14785" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14843">And no matter what she came to suffer in that house, the good priest would know nothing of it, or, if he did, with even the best intentions, he could do little more than feel pity for her, the peaceful, moderate pity generally accorded, as a courtesy, to anyone who has given a reason or an excuse for the wrongs they suffer. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n192" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14844" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14904">The examiner grew tired of questioning the unfortunate girl before she grew tired of lying. Hearing the consistency of her answers, and finding no reason to doubt their sincerity, he finally changed his tone. Congratulating her, he apologized, in a manner, for having taken so long to perform his duty. He added a few words of encouragement to support her good intentions, and took his leave. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n193" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14905" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14937">As he was crossing the antechambers, he ran into the Prince, who seemed to be there by chance. The priest complimented him on the excellent disposition he had found in the Prince’s daughter. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n194" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14938" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14992">Until that moment the Prince had been in a state of painful suspense. At the news he breathed a sigh of relief. Forgetting his customary severity, he almost ran to Gertrude, and showered her with praise, with hugs, with promises, with a cordial jubilation, and with a tenderness that was mostly sincere: Such is the muddle of the human heart. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n195" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_14993" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15005">I shall not accompany Gertrude on her tour of sights and entertainments. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n196" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15006" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15038">Nor shall I describe, in detail and in order, her feelings during that time. It would be a story of sorrow and mood swings, too monotonous and too similar to what I have already related. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n197" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15039" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15076">The charms of the places, the variety of the objects, the simple pleasure of moving about in the open air, made her detest even more the idea of the place where she would alight for the last time, and forever. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n198" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15077" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15088">More painful still were the impressions she gathered at the receptions and balls. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n199" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15089" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15133">The sight of “brides” who were given this title in the more common, obvious sense of the word filled her with envy and an unbearable anguish; and sometimes the appearance of a young man made her feel that to be called by that title herself would be the peak of happiness. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n200" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15134" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15178">Sometimes the luxury of the palaces, the splendor of the decorations, the joyful hustle and bustle of the balls, so elated her and made her yearn for a life of gaiety that she swore to withdraw her request, to suffer anything rather than go back to the cold, dead shadows of the cloister. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n201" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15179" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15198">But all those resolutions evaporated when she collected her thoughts and pondered how hard it would be, or when she simply looked her father in the face. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n202" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15199" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15238">And sometimes, the thought of having to abandon those pleasures forever made this small taste more bitter, more painful, like a thirsty patient who glares at and almost scornfully rejects the teaspoon of water that the doctor reluctantly allows him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n203" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15239" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15259">Meanwhile the vicar of nuns had issued the necessary certification, and permission was granted to call a meeting of the chapter of nuns for the acceptance of Gertrude into the order. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n204" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15260" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15281">The chapter was held: As expected, the required two-thirds of the secret votes were in favor, and Gertrude was accepted. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n205" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15282" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15298">She herself, tired of the long torment, asked to enter the convent as soon as possible. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n206" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15299" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15307">There was certainly no one who would stand in her way, so her wish was granted. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n207" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15308" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15320">Conducted to the convent with great ceremony, she donned the habit. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n208" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15321" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15369">After a twelve-month novitiate, filled with regrets and regret for her regrets, the time came for her to take her vows, the time ordained to either utter a no that would be stranger, more unexpected, and more scandalous than ever, or repeat the yes already said so many times. She repeated it, and became a nun, forever. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n209" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15370" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15394">One of the unique and incommunicable powers of the Christian faith is its ability to guide and console anyone, in any circumstance, and at any time, who turns to it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n210" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15395" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15437">If there is a way to correct past misdeeds, the Faith prescribes it, administers it, and provides the light and strength to apply it, whatever the cost. If there is not, it finds a way to actually and effectively do what the proverb says, and make of necessity a virtue. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n211" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15438" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15487">It teaches us to continue with wisdom that which was begun almost lightheartedly. It persuades the soul to embrace willingly something imposed by force, and endows a choice that was rash, but irrevocable, with all the sanctity, all the wisdom, and, let us say openly, all the joy of the vocation. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n212" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15488" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15526">No matter the labyrinth or the precipice from which a man has come, the moment he sets foot on this path he can walk safely and willingly and arrive joyfully at a joyful end. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n213" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15527" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15542">In this way, Gertrude could have become a nun who was pious and content, despite the manner in which she took the veil. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n214" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15543" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15562">But instead, the unhappy girl tried to shake off the yoke, and consequently suffered even more under its weight and its jolts. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n215" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15563" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15590">Endless regret for her lost freedom, hatred of her present state, and an all-consuming yearning for desires that would never be requited: This is how she occupied her mind. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n216" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15591" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15631">She brooded over her bitter past, recollected all the circumstances that had brought her there, and a thousand times undid in her mind, to no avail, what she had done through her actions. She accused herself of ineptitude, and others of tyranny and treachery. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n217" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15632" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15668">And she wasted away. She both idolized and lamented her beauty, deplored a youth that was destined to fade away in a slow agony, and envied, at times, any woman, of any status, or any morals, who could freely enjoy these gifts in the world. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n218" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15669" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15685">She detested the nuns who had taken her hand and led her in. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n219" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15686" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15710">She remembered the cunning and the tricks they had adopted, and repaid them with rudeness, with teasing, and even with open criticism. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n220" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15711" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15779">Most of the time they thought it best to put up with her in silence: The Prince had tyrannized his daughter just enough to force her into the cloister, but once he had achieved his goal, he would not easily tolerate others trying to get the better of his own blood. Any complaint they made could lead to the loss of his patronage, or even turn their patron into an enemy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n221" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15780" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15830">You might think that Gertrude would be better inclined toward the nuns who had played no part in those intrigues and who, without having wanted her as a companion, still loved her as one of their own. Pious, diligent, and cheerful, their example showed her how one could not only live, but also thrive, within the walls. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n222" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15831" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15840">Yet she hated them, too, for another reason. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n223" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15841" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15878">In their piety and good cheer she saw a criticism of her restless and eccentric behavior. She never missed an opportunity to make fun of them behind their backs as bigots, or to accuse them of being hypocrites. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n224" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15879" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15909">Her feelings toward them might have been less hostile if she had known or guessed that these same women were the ones who had cast the only votes against her acceptance into the convent. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n225" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15910" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15948">The little consolation she did seem to find, at times, was in giving orders, receiving courtesy visits from outside persons, bestowing a favor, extending her protection, and in hearing herself called “La Signora.” But what consolations were these? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n226" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_15949" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16009">Her heart, so unfulfilled, would have occasionally liked to lengthen this list, and add the consolations of religion. But its consolations cannot be enjoyed unless the others are abandoned: Like the shipwrecked man, he must let go of the seaweed he had seized in a furious instinct if he wishes to grab onto the plank that will lead him to safety and the shore. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n227" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16010" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16030">Shortly after taking her vows, Gertrude became the school mistress. Now you can imagine how those young girls must have fared in a school like hers. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n228" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16031" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16060">Her old confidants were all gone, but her grudges from those days were alive and well, and, one way or another, her pupils had to bear the brunt. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n229" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16061" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16111">Whenever it crossed her mind that many of them were destined to live in a world shut off from her forever, she felt a resentment and, at times, a desire for revenge toward her girls. So she humiliated them, mistreated them, made them pay in advance for the pleasures they would one day enjoy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n230" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16112" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16136">In moments like those, anyone who heard the magisterial scorn with which she berated them for the least infraction would have thought her a woman of savage, excessive spirituality. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n231" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16137" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16156">At other times, her aversion for the cloister, for the rules, for the vow of obedience, would explode into tantrums of the opposite humor. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n232" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16157" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16198">Then she would not only tolerate her pupils’ rowdiness but encourage it, joining in their games and making them more unruly than ever. She would intrude into their conversations and lead them in directions beyond their original intentions. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n233" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16199" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16241">If anyone had a word to say about the Mother Abbess’s droning, the teacher would imitate it at length, turning it into a scene from a comedy. She would mimic one nun’s facial expression, another’s style of walking. Then she would let out a boisterous laugh, but this laughter left her feeling no happier than before. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n234" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16242" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16264">She went on in this manner for several years, finding neither the leisure nor the opportunity to make her disdain any clearer, until, to her misfortune, an opportunity appeared. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n235" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16265" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16291">Among the other distinctions and privileges granted to Gertrude was her own separate suite, to compensate for not being abbess. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n236" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16292" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16336">Her side of the convent abutted a house inhabited by a young man, a criminal by trade, one of the many, in those days, who thanks to their henchmen and their association with other criminals could, to an extent, scoff at the police and the law. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n237" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16337" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16346">Our manuscript only gives his first name, Egidio, without mentioning his family. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n238" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16347" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16384">From a window that overlooked a courtyard in that corner of the convent, he sometimes saw Gertrude walking by or wandering around. One day, tempted rather than frightened by the danger and the impiety of the endeavor, he dared to call out to her. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n239" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16385" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16387">And she gave her fateful reply. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n240" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16388" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16400">At first she felt a happiness that, while it was certainly not pure, was very much alive. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n241" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16401" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16442">The tedious void in her spirit was now filled with a strong and constant occupation and, I would almost say, a powerful life. But that happiness was like the restorative drink that the ancients, in their ingenious cruelty, used to pour for a condemned man, to give him the strength to survive longer under torture. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n242" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16443" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16506">At the same time, a great change could be seen in her behavior. She suddenly became more settled, more peaceful. She stopped her teasing and grumbling, and indeed showed herself to be affectionate and considerate. The sisters rejoiced at this happy turn, little suspecting the true reason, or realizing that her newfound virtue was nothing more than the addition of hypocrisy to her old flaws. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n243" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16507" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16563">This outward appearance, however, this whitewashed façade, did not last long, at least not with continuity and consistency. Soon her usual insults and whims were back, and her curses and derision of the cloistered prison could be heard, sometimes expressed in language unfamiliar to that place, and even to those lips. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n244" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16564" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16586">But each of these outbursts was followed by remorse, by efforts to make people forget them through flattery and kind words. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n245" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16587" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16604">The sisters tolerated these mood swings as best they could, blaming them on the Signora’s eccentric and fickle nature. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n246" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16605" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16678">For a while no one seemed to give the Signora too much thought. But one day she berated a lay sister over some trifle, and mistreated her so excessively, so relentlessly, that the girl, after putting up with it and biting her lip, finally lost her patience and blurted out that she knew something, and that at the right time and place she would talk. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n247" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16679" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16689">From that moment on, the Signora knew no peace. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n248" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16690" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16743">One morning, however, the lay sister failed to appear for her usual duties. The nuns went looking for her in her cell, but she wasn’t there. They called out her name. She didn’t answer. They searched here and there, round and round, high and low. She was nowhere to be found. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n249" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16744" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16776">Who knows what people might have imagined if, in the middle of the search, they had not discovered a breach in the garden wall. This made everyone assume she had slipped through it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n250" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16777" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16806">A search was carried out in Monza and the outlying areas, mainly in Meda, the girl’s hometown. Letters were dispatched to various other districts, but not even a shred of news came back. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n251" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16807" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16824">They might have learned more if, rather than searching far and wide, they had dug a little closer to home. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n252" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16825" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16846">With much dismay, since no one thought her capable of such a thing, and after much talk, the conclusion was reached that she must have gone far, far away. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n253" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16847" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16878">And since one nun declared that “She’s definitely fled to Holland,” it was immediately said, and long believed, both inside the convent and out, that she had fled to Holland. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n254" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16879" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16888">The Signora, however, did not seem to share this belief. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n255" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16889" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16941">Not that she expressed her doubts, or gave any particular reasons for disagreeing with the general opinion: She indeed had her reasons, but she kept them concealed. Nor was there anything that she avoided more readily than stirring up that story again, or that seemed to interest her less than getting to the bottom of that mystery. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n256" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16942" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16950">But the less she spoke about it, the more she thought about it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n257" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16951" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16973">How many times a day did the image of that girl suddenly invade her thoughts, and plant itself there without budging! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n258" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_16974" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17005">How many times did she wish she could see her in the flesh, alive and well, rather than haunting her thoughts, rather than being accompanied, day and night, by that ghostly, frightening, stone-cold shape! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n259" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17006" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17051">How many times did she wish she could hear her voice, no matter what it might threaten, rather than always having in her mind’s ear the imaginary whispering of that same voice, and hearing words repeated with an insistence, with a relentless tenacity, beyond the power of any living soul! — </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n260" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17052" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17077">Almost one year had gone by since that incident when Lucia was introduced to the Signora and had the conversation with her that I interrupted to tell you this tale. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n261" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17078" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17123">The Signora asked her more and more questions about Don Rodrigo’s harassment, and pried into certain details with a boldness that surprised Lucia, and understandably so, for she had never imagined that nuns might be so curious about such subjects. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n262" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17124" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17138">No less strange were the comments that the Signora sprinkled or insinuated into her questions. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n263" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17139" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17199">She seemed to be mocking the revulsion Lucia had always felt for that gentleman, and asked whether he really was such a monster to have provoked such fear. She acted as if the young girl’s aversion was unreasonable or foolish, except for the fact that she preferred Renzo, of whom she also had some questions that left the girl shocked and embarrassed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n264" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17200" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17240">Realizing that she may have let her tongue run away with her, the Signora tried to correct her lapse and more properly express herself. But Lucia could not help but be left with an unpleasant dismay and a puzzled surprise. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n265" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17241" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17269">As soon as Lucia was alone with her mother, she confided her feelings to her. But Agnese, as the more experienced of the two, solved all her doubts with a few words, explaining the whole mystery. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n266" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17270" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17290">“Don’t be surprised,” she said. “When you know the world as well as I do, you’ll see that there’s nothing to be surprised at. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n267" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17291" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17310">Nobles are all a little bit mad: some more, some less, some in one way, some in another. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n268" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17311" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17330">It’s best to just let them talk, especially when you need them. Pretend that you’re taking them seriously, as if they were saying reasonable things. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n269" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17331" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17344">Did you hear how she jumped down my throat, as if I’d said something completely improper? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n270" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17345" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17352">I paid her no mind. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n271" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17353" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17355">They’re all the same. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n272" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17356" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17377">Anyway, thank heavens this Signora seems to have taken a liking to you, and really does want to protect you. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n273" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17378" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17399">If you make it through this alive, my daughter, and happen to deal with nobles again, oh the things that you’ll hear! The things that you’ll hear!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n274" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17400" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17460">The Signora was genuinely predisposed to take the fate of the two poor refugees to heart by virtue of her wish to gratify the Father Guardian the satisfaction of being able to grant her protection, the thought of the good image she would gain through such a saintly favor, a certain sympathy for Lucia, and also a feeling of relief in doing a good deed for an innocent child, by aiding and consoling the oppressed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n275" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17461" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17486">At her request, and out of respect for her, mother and daughter were lodged in the stewardess’s quarters, adjacent to the cloister, and treated as if they were servants of the convent. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n276" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17487" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17503">Agnese and Lucia rejoiced that they had so quickly found a safe and respectable shelter. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n277" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17504" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17557">They would have been even happier to be ignored by all, but that was not easy in a convent. Especially since there was a man quite eager to get news about one of them, a man whose earlier passion and obstinacy had been thwarted and disappointed, leaving him rankled. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap10-n278" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17558" targetEnd="quarantana/cap10.xml#c10_17580">And we, leaving behind the women in their refuge, shall return to his palace, at the hour in which he was awaiting the outcome of his vile expedition. </note>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>