<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CHAPTER 1</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>2022</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed: a novel</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
          <date>2022</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Michael Moore</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="english_2022_cap1">
<p>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10111">The branch of Lake Como that turns south between two unbroken mountain chains, bordered by coves and inlets that echo the furrowed slopes, suddenly narrows to take the flow and shape of a river, between a promontory on the right and a wide shoreline on the opposite side. The bridge that joins the two sides at this point seems to make this transformation even more visible to the eye and mark the spot where the lake ends and the Adda begins again, to reclaim the name lake where the shores, newly distant, allow the water to spread and slowly pool into fresh inlets and coves. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10112" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10203">Formed from the sediment of three large streams, the shoreline lies at the foot of two neighboring mountains, the first called San Martino, the second, in Lombard dialect, the “Resegone”—the big saw—after the row of many small peaks that really do make it look like one. So clear is the resemblance that no one—provided they are directly facing it, from the northern walls of Milan, for example—could fail to immediately distinguish this summit from other mountains in that long and vast range with more obscure names and more common shapes. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10204" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10238">For a good stretch the shore rises upward into a smooth rolling slope. Then it breaks off into small hills and ravines, steep inclines and flat terraces, molded by the contours of the two mountains and the erosion of the waters. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10239" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10275">The water’s edge, cut by the outlets of the streams, is almost all pebbles and stones. The rest is fields and vineyards, dotted with towns, villages, and hamlets. Here and there a woods climbs up the side of the mountain. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10276" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10320">Lecco, the capital that lends its name to the province, stands at a short remove from the bridge, and is on and indeed partly inside the lake when the water rises. Nowadays it is a large town well on its way to becoming a city. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10321" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10403">At the time of the events I am about to relate, this already good-sized village was also fortified, which conferred upon it the honor of a commander in residence, and the benefit of a permanent garrison of Spanish soldiers, who taught modesty to the girls and women of the town, gave an occasional tap on the back to a husband or father, and, at summer’s end, never failed to spread out into the vineyards to thin the grapes and relieve the peasants of the trouble of harvesting them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10404" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10505">Roads and footpaths used to run—and still do—from town to town, from summit to shore, from hill to hill. Some are more or less steep; some are level. In places they dip, sinking between two walls, and all you can see when you look up is a patch of sky and a mountaintop. In others they climb to open embankments, where the view encompasses a broader panorama, always rich, always new, depending on the vantage point and how much of the vast expanse can be seen, and on whether the landscape protrudes or recedes, stands out from or disappears into the horizon. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10506" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10597">One piece, then another, then a long stretch of that vast and varied mirror of water. Over here, the lake—terminating at the far end or vanishing into a cluster, a procession of mountains—slowly growing wider between yet more mountains that unfold before the eyes, one by one, whose image, alongside that of the towns by the lake, is reflected upside down in the water. Over there, a bend in the river, then more lake, then river again disappearing into a shiny ribbon curling between the mountains on either side, and slowly descending to vanish on the horizon. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10598" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10683">The place from which you contemplate these varied sights offers its own display on every side. The mountain along whose slopes you walk unfolds its peaks and crags above and around you, distinct, prominent, changing with every step, opening and then circling into ridges where a lone summit had at first appeared. The shapes that were reflected in the lake only minutes before now appear close to the summit. The tame, pleasant foothills temper the wild landscape and enhance the magnificence of the other vistas. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10684" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10732">Along one of these footpaths, on the evening of the seventh day of November in 1628, Don Abbondio, the parish priest of one of the villages just mentioned, was making his way home from a leisurely walk. (Neither here nor elsewhere does the manuscript give the name of his parish or family.) </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10733" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10831">He was calmly reciting the Liturgy of the Hours. Occasionally, between one psalm and another, he would close his breviary, keeping his right index finger inside as a bookmark. Clasping his hands together behind his back, he would continue his walk, staring at the ground and kicking toward the wall any stones that got in the way. Then he would look up, let his eyes wander idly, and gaze at the wide and uneven splashes of purple on the cliffs, painted there by the light of the setting sun that had peeked through crevices in the mountain on the opposite shore. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10832" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10866">After opening his breviary again and reciting another passage, he came to a curve in the path where it was always his custom to look up from his book and stare straight ahead. Today was no different. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10867" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10919">Past the curve, the road continued straight for another sixty steps or so and then split into two lanes, in a Y shape. The path to the right went up the mountain and toward the rectory. The one to the left went down to the valley as far as a stream. On that side the wall was only waist high. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10920" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10995">The inner walls of the two lanes converged not on a corner but on a roadside shrine painted with long, wavy figures that ended in a point. In the intentions of the artist and to the eyes of the neighborhood residents they depicted tongues of fire, alternating with vague figures representing souls in purgatory. The souls and flames were brick-red against a gray background that was mottled in spots where the plaster had flaked off. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_10996" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11020">As he turned the corner and directed his gaze, as usual, toward the shrine, the priest noticed something unexpected that he would rather not have seen. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11021" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11070">Two men were facing each other at the spot where the two lanes meet. The first was sitting astride the low wall, one leg dangling on the outside and one foot planted on the ground. His companion stood, leaning against the opposite wall, arms folded over his chest. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11071" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11093">Their clothing, demeanor, and expression—or what little the priest could discern from a distance—left little doubt as to their station in life. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11094" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11193">Around his head each man was wearing a loose-knit green stocking cap underneath which a thick forelock poked out; the cap hung down to the left shoulder and ended in a large tassel. Both had a long mustache curled to a tip; a shiny leather belt with two pistols attached; a small powder horn dangling over his chest like a pendant; a knife handle sticking out of one pocket of his wide, baggy britches; and a longsword whose large hilt was covered with shiny brass fretwork in the shape of a monogram. At a glance you could see they were letting themselves be known as members of the bravi species. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11194" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11208">This species, which is extinct nowadays, flourished in Lombardy at that time and already had for decades. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11209" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11238">For those who know nothing about them, here are some excerpts from original documents that indicate their main characteristics, the efforts made to eradicate them, and their hardy, enduring vitality. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11239" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11409">On the eighth of April in the year 1583, the Most Illustrious and Excellent Don Carlos of Aragon, Prince of Castelvetrano, Duke of Terranuova, Marquis of Avola, Count of Burgeto, Grand Admiral, and Grand Constable of Sicily, Governor of Milan, and Captain-General of His Catholic Majesty in Italy, fully apprised of the intolerable misery in which this city of Milan has lived and lives, by reason of bravi and vagrants, published a decree against them. He hereby declares and defines as included in this decree, to be deemed bravi and vagrants, all those who…whether foreign or native, having no occupation or, having one, do not exercise it…but rather, without a salary, or even with one, attach themselves to some member of the nobility or the gentry, an official or a merchant…to protect and serve him, or in truth, as can be presumed, to do injury to others…He ordered all of them to leave the city within six days, threatened the recalcitrant with jail, and gave the officers of the law the broadest and most indefinite emergency powers to execute the order. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11410" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11460">But the following year, on the twelfth of April, the same nobleman, observing that this City is still filled with said bravi…who have gone back to living as they previously had, without any alteration in their behavior or decrease in their numbers, issued another more vigorous and remarkable decree in which, among other things, he ordered: </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11461" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11566">That any person, whether of this City or foreign, whom two witnesses testify is deemed and commonly reputed to be a bravo, and bears such a title, even if he has committed no crime…for the sole reputation of being a bravo, without any other evidence, can by said judges and by each and every one of them be interrogated through the corda and torture…and even if he does not confess to any crime, can nevertheless be sent to the galleys for a three-year sentence solely for having the reputation and title of bravo. All this, and more that I have omitted, because His Excellency is resolved to be obeyed by all. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11567" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11599">Such bold and confident words, from such a figure, and accompanied by such orders, might lead you to believe that, at the mere sound of them, the bravi had all disappeared forever. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11600" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11619">But the testimony of a nobleman no less authoritative, and no less decorated with titles, compels us to believe the contrary. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11620" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11732">I am referring to the Most Illustrious and Excellent Juan Fernández de Velasco, Constable of Castile, Lord High Chamberlain of His Majesty, Duke of the City of Frias, Count of Haro and Castelnovo, Lord of the House of Velasco, and of the House of the Seven Infantes of Lara, Governor of the State of Milan, etc. On the fifth of June in the year 1593, likewise fully apprised of the rack and ruin brought…by the bravi and vagrants, and the deleterious effect that this sort of person has on the public good, and in violation of the law, he ordered them once again, within six days, to clear out of the city, repeating almost the exact same prohibitions and threats as his predecessor. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11733" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11859">Then on the twenty-third of May in the year 1598, having with no small displeasure been informed that…every day in this City and State the number of these [bravi and vagrants] is growing, nor is any news heard about them, night and day, other than deliberately inflicted wounds, murders and robberies, and every other type of crime, to which they lend themselves willingly, confident that they will be protected by their leaders and advocates…prescribed once again the same remedies, doubling the dose, the way you might treat a stubborn illness. Everyone therefore, he concludes, shall always and everywhere beware of disobeying any part of the present decree, because rather than enjoy the clemency of His Excellency, he will suffer the severity of his wrath…since he is resolute and determined that this shall be the final and ultimate warning. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11860" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11956">But such was not the persuasion of the Most Illustrious and Excellent Don Pietro Enriquez de Acevedo, Count of Fuentes, Captain, and Governor of the state of Milan. And for good reason. Fully informed of the misery in which this City and State lie because of the large number of bravi that abound in it…and resolved to completely eradicate this most pernicious seed, he issued, on the fifth of December in the year 1600, a new decree also containing the harshest punishments, with the firm resolution that, with all severity, and without hope of remission, shall be executed in all of its parts. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_11957" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12047">There is reason to believe, however, that the Count did not invest in the decree all the goodwill he had put into hatching plots and rallying enemies against his great enemy, Henry IV, the King of France. Since history illustrates primarily the manner in which he armed the Duke of Savoy against said king, thereby causing the latter to lose more than one city; and how he managed to enlist the Duke of Biron in a plot against him, thereby causing him to lose his head. As for the bravi, however, that “most pernicious seed,” they were still alive and well on the twenty-second of September in the year 1612. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12048" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12072">On that day the Most Illustrious and Excellent Don Juan de Mendozza, Marquis de la Hynojosa, Lord etc., Governor, etc., dedicated serious thought to eradicating them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12073" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12097">So he sent the usual decree, corrected and expanded, to the royal printers, Pandolfo and Marco Tullio Malatesta. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12098" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12191">But the bravi were still thriving on the twenty-fourth of December in the year 1618, when they were likewise and more heavily struck by a decree from the Most Illustrious and Excellent Don Gomez Suarez de Figueroa, Duke of Feria, etc., Governor, etc. But, since that effort failed to kill them off, the Most Illustrious and Excellent Gonzalo Fernández de Córdoba, under whose rule Don Abbondio was taking his walk, found himself forced to revise and republish the usual decree against the bravi, on the fifth day of October 1627: that is to say, one year, one month, and two days before this memorable encounter. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12192" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12215">Nor was this the final decree, but I see no need to mention the others, since they fall outside the period of our story. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12216" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12253">I will cite only one, on the thirteenth of February 1632, in which the Most Illustrious and Excellent Duke of Feria, Governor for a second term, advises us that the greatest atrocities are committed by the so-called bravi. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12254" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12268">This should reassure us that, during the period I am describing, the bravi were still around. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12269" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12302">— It was all too clear that the two men described above were waiting for someone. But what most displeased Don Abbondio was the forced realization, from certain gestures, that the someone they were waiting for was him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12303" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12355">Because as soon as he appeared, they exchanged glances and raised their heads, as if they had both just said: “It’s him.” The sitting man stood up, lowering his leg to the path. His partner peeled himself off the wall. Both started moving toward him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12356" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12389">Keeping his breviary open in front of him, as if he were reading, Don Abbondio forced himself to look up, to keep an eye on their movements. Seeing them advance toward him, he was suddenly assailed by a thousand thoughts. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12390" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12419">He quickly asked himself whether between the bravi and himself there was not perhaps some way out, to the right or left. Just as quickly he remembered there was none. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12420" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12451">He conducted a rapid self-examination, wondering whether he had offended some powerful man, someone vindictive. But even in the midst of his agitation, he was somewhat reassured by the consoling testimony of his conscience. Still the bravi approached, staring straight at him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12452" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12497">He placed the index and middle fingers of his left hand inside his collar, as if to adjust it. And while the two fingers circled his neck, he turned his head to look back at the same time as he twisted his mouth into a grimace. From the corner of his eye, he tried to see as far as he could whether someone else was coming. But he saw no one. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12498" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12517">He stole a peek over the low wall toward the fields: no one. A cowering glance at the road ahead: no one except the bravi. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12518" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12536">What was he to do? Turn back? Too late. Take to his heels? He might as well say, “Come and get me,” or worse. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12537" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12561">Unable to avoid the danger, he rushed into it, since the uncertainty was so painful that all he wanted was to get it over with. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12562" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12607">He quickened his step, recited a verse in a louder voice, settled his face into as calm and cheerful an expression as he could manage, and made every effort to prepare a smile. Once he found himself before these two upright citizens, he said to himself, “Here we go,” and stopped in his tracks. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12608" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12619">“Reverend Father,” said one of the two, staring him in the face. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12620" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12640">“At your service,” Don Abbondio immediately replied, looking up from his book, which remained open in his hands, as if resting on a lectern. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12641" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12670">“Is it your intention,” the second man continued, with the angry, menacing look of someone who has caught an underling in the act of doing some mischief, “is it your intention to marry Renzo Tramaglino and Lucia Mondella tomorrow?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12671" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12678">“Beg your pardon,” replied Don Abbondio, his voice shaking, “beg your pardon. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12679" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12691">My good sirs, you are men of the world. You know perfectly well how these matters go. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12692" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12724">The poor priest has nothing to do with it! Young people make a mess of things and then…and then they come to us, the way you’d go to a bank for money. And we…we are servants of the common good.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12725" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12748">“Well, then,” the bravo said in his ear, but in the solemn tone of a command, “this marriage ain’t gonna happen. Not tomorrow, not never.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12749" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12776">“But, my good sirs,” Don Abbondio replied, in the mild, gentle voice used to persuade the impatient, “but, my good sirs, be so gracious as to put yourselves in my shoes. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12777" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12794">If it were up to me…you must know that I’m none the richer for any of this…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12795" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12811">“Enough talk!” interrupted the bravo. “Running your mouth isn’t going to fix this. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12812" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12824">Not another word out of you. Consider this fair warning…Have we made ourselves clear?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12825" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12832">“My good sirs, you are too kind, too reasonable…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12833" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12872">“But,” broke in the second man, who had not spoken so far, “the marriage ain’t gonna happen, or else…” he uttered a loud expletive, “or else the man who performs it won’t have the time to regret it, and…” another expletive. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12873" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12903">“Shut up!” the first speaker cut in. “The Reverend Father is a man who knows the ways of the world. And we are honorable men who mean him no harm, so long as he does the right thing. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12904" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12914">Reverend, the illustrious Don Rodrigo, our lord and master, holds you in high esteem.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12915" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12942">The name flashed across Don Abbondio’s mind like a bolt of lightning at the peak of a nighttime storm, illuminating everything in disarray for a moment and creating even greater panic. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12943" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12954">Almost instinctively he made a deep bow and said, “If you could suggest a way out…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12955" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12975">“What! You, who speak Latin, want our suggestions?” the bravo interrupted again, with a laugh that was both uncouth and savage. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12976" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12978">“I’m sure you can think of something. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_12979" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13006">Above all, don’t breathe a word of this warning. We’re telling you for your own good. And if you do talk…snick…it would be as bad if you’d gone ahead and married them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13007" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13019">So, do you have any message for the illustrious Don Rodrigo?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13020" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13022">“My respects…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13023" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13025">“Speak up!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13026" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13045">“Always…always at his disposal,” and as he uttered these words, not even the priest himself could tell whether he was making a promise or paying a compliment. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13046" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13057">The bravi took it, or pretended to take it, in the more serious sense. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13058" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13071">“That will be fine, and good night, sir,” one of the men said as he departed with his partner. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13072" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13092">Don Abbondio, who moments earlier would have given his eyeteeth to steer clear of them, now attempted to prolong the conversation and the negotiation. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13093" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13122">“Sirs…” he began, closing the book between his hands. But without paying him further heed, they took the path by which he had come, singing a bawdy song as they went that I would rather not transcribe. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13123" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13156">Poor Don Abbondio was left with his jaw hanging, as if he were under a spell. Then he took the path that led to his house, struggling to move his legs, which felt as if they had cramped up. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13157" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13180">How he felt inside is a matter we’ll understand better once I’ve said a few things about his character and the times in which he happened to live. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13181" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13196">Don Abbondio (as the reader will have already noted) was not born with the heart of a lion. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13197" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13230">From his earliest years, the notion was forced upon him that, in those days, nothing could be worse than to be an animal without claws or teeth yet no inclination to be devoured. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13231" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13251">The police did nothing to protect the law-abiding, inoffensive man who had no means to intimidate others. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13252" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13262">Not that there was any lack of laws and punishments against acts of personal aggression: Indeed, there was an overabundance of them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13263" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13333">The crimes were enumerated and defined at tedious, meticulous length. The punishments were wildly exorbitant. As if that were not enough, in almost every case they could be increased, at will, by the Governor himself and by one hundred officers of the law. Trials were designed solely to free the judge from any impediment to passing sentence. The excerpts from the decrees against the bravi I have reported are only a small but representative sample. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13334" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13396">Despite or rather largely because of this, the decrees, republished and reinforced from one government to the next, served as little more than bombastic proof of their authors’ impotence. When they did produce an immediate effect, it was mainly to add to the many vexations that the weak and law-abiding already suffered at the hands of their tormentors, and to increase the cunning and violence of the latter. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13397" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13411">Impunity was systematic and had roots that the decrees did not touch or could not dislodge. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13412" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13454">Such were the immunities and privileges of certain classes, partly recognized by the law, partly tolerated in resentful silence or contested in vain protests, but maintained and jealously guarded by the social classes themselves through self-serving and defensive actions. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13455" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13481">At every threat and every insult, this impunity—threatened and offended but not eliminated by the decrees—had, of course, to make new efforts and find new means to preserve itself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13482" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13516">And this is, in effect, what happened. The moment a decree appeared, the violent found new, more opportune means, through their power, to continue doing exactly what the decrees had sought to repress. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13517" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13562">At every turn they could easily harass and lock up an honest citizen who had no power or protection of his own. Because in order to keep every man under control, and to prevent or punish every crime, the decrees subjected every move by a private citizen to the arbitrary will of any number of executors. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13563" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13628">But any man who, before committing a crime, had arranged to seek ready sanctuary in a monastery or a palace where the police would never dare to set foot; and any man, with no protection other than the livery that bound a powerful family, indeed an entire social class, to defend him for the sake of its vanity and interests, was free to do as he liked, and could scoff at the bombast of the decrees. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13629" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13681">The men appointed to enforce the decrees included some who belonged by birth to the privileged class, and others who depended on its patronage. Both groups—by education, self-interest, custom, and imitation—had embraced that class’s principles and were loath to offend them in deference to the broadsheet decrees posted on street corners. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13682" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13741">Even if they had been as daring as heroes, obedient as monks, and inclined to sacrifice as martyrs, the men appointed to promptly execute the laws would still have been unable to perform their duties, since they were fewer in number to the men they were supposed to subdue, and in all likelihood they would be forsaken by those who, in the abstract and in theory, so to speak, had given them their orders. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13742" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13776">Not to mention that the enforcers were generally the most abject criminals of their day, reviled even by the men who should have feared them. Their very title was used as an insult. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13777" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13837">So rather than take risks or throw away their lives on a hopeless enterprise, they sold their inaction or even their collusion to the powerful, of course, and reserved the exercise of their detested authority and the powers they enjoyed for occasions when there was no danger; namely, the oppression and harassment of the law-abiding and defenseless. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13838" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13853">The man who wishes to offend, or forever fears receiving offense, will naturally seek out allies and partners. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13854" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13886">In those days there was a peak in the tendency of individuals to affiliate in social classes and form new ones, and for each to accumulate as much power as he could for his own class. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13887" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13907">The clergy vigilantly supported and extended its immunities, the nobility its privileges, the military its exemptions. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13908" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13928">The merchants and skilled craftsmen enrolled in corporations and confraternities, the jurists established a league, and even the doctors formed a guild. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13929" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13963">Each of these little oligarchies had its own special power. And within each the individual benefited from the combined forces of the many, which he could exploit in proportion to his authority and skill. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13964" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_13999">The most honest used this advantage only for self-defense. The cunning and the violent exploited it to commit their crimes—for which their personal means alone would have been insufficient—with full impunity. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14000" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14060">The forces of these various leagues were not evenly matched, however. In the countryside, a rich, violent nobleman, surrounded by a band of bravi and a peasant population that regarded itself—out of family tradition, self-interest, or coercion—as subjects and soldiers of the master, could wield a power that other factions of the league would find hard to resist. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14061" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14101">Our Don Abbondio was neither noble, nor rich, nor especially courageous. He realized, even before reaching the age of discretion, that in such a society he was like a clay pot forced to travel in the company of many an iron kettle. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14102" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14114">So he readily obeyed his parents’ wish for him to become a priest. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14115" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14162">The truth is he hadn’t given much thought to the duties and noble purposes of his chosen ministry. Procuring a life of ease and a position in a strong, revered class seemed more than sufficient reason for such a choice. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14163" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14188">But a person can be protected or kept safe by his class only up to a point. No class affiliation dispenses him from developing his own particular system of defense. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14189" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14215">Don Abbondio, constantly absorbed in thoughts of his own peace of mind, did not concern himself with advantages that required hard work or a modicum of risk. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14216" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14234">His system consisted primarily in avoiding all conflict and backing down from the ones he could not avoid. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14235" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14284">He offered unarmed neutrality in all the wars erupting around him, from the frequent disputes that used to break out between the clergy and the secular mayors, soldiers and civilians, nobleman and nobleman, all the way down to disputes between two peasants sparked by a word and settled by fists or daggers. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14285" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14336">When he was forced to choose between two contenders, he always sided with the stronger party, but always cautiously, taking care to show the other party that he had no choice in the matter, as if to say, “Why couldn’t you have been the stronger man? Then I would have taken your side.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14337" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14396">By steering clear of bullies, pretending not to notice their momentary, capricious abuses, responding meekly to the ones with graver, more premeditated intentions, and forcing even the gruffest and most contemptuous to smile, through his bowing and jovial deference, when he ran into them on the street, the poor man had managed to make it past the age of sixty without much trouble. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14397" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14456">Not that he did not harbor some resentment. The constant testing of his patience, the frequent concessions to others, the many bitter pills swallowed in silence, had exasperated him so much that his health would surely have suffered had he not occasionally vented. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14457" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14503">But since in the end there were people in the world, close to him, that he knew could do him no harm, he could take out his long repressed annoyance on them, and indulge in the pleasure of losing his temper and unleashing some misdirected shouts. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14504" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14527">He was a harsh critic of men who did not behave like him, but only when he could voice his criticism without even the most remote danger. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14528" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14541">The defeated man had at the very least been imprudent. The murdered man had always been a troublemaker. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14542" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14589">And if a man’s head had been split open after standing up for himself against someone stronger, Don Abbondio could still find some fault in him. Which was easy enough, since right and wrong are never so neatly divided that each side is either one or the other. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14590" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14611">He was especially critical of his fellow priests who, at their own risk, took the side of a weak victim against a powerful bully. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14612" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14641">He considered it begging for trouble, a wish to straighten the legs of dogs. More sternly he called it meddling in worldly affairs, and tarnishing the dignity of the sacred ministry. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14642" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14674">He railed against such priests, although always one-on-one or to a small group, all the more vehemently when they were known to have no interest in things that regarded him personally. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14675" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14709">He had a favorite sentence which he always used to conclude his harangues on such matters: No harm comes to an honest man who minds his own business and knows his place. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14710" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14726">Dear readers, all twenty-five of you, imagine the impression the meeting with the two bravi must have made on the poor man! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14727" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14783">The shock of seeing those horrid faces and hearing those horrid words. A threat from a nobleman known to never issue one in vain. A peaceful life that had taken years of study and patience, overthrown in an instant. And a situation that he did not think he could easily escape. All these thoughts buzzed noisily in the lowered head of Don Abbondio. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14784" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14809">“If Renzo could be sent on his way with a firm no, then why not? But he’ll want to know why, and what can I answer, for the love of heaven? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14810" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14829">And, and, and he’s another headstrong one. If no one bothers him he’s a lamb, but as soon as someone crosses him, watch out! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14830" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14840">And then, and then, so smitten by Lucia, as in love as…foolish children. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14841" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14867">For lack of better things to occupy their minds, they fall in love, want to marry, and can think of nothing else. They don’t care about the troubles they create for an honest man! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14868" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14885">Poor me! Why did those two goons have to plant themselves on my road and pick on me? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14886" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14888">What’s it got to do with me? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14889" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14893">I’m not the one who wants to get married. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14894" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14900">Why didn’t they go speak with…There you have it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14901" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14923">Just my luck. The things I should have said come to me a minute too late. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14924" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14936">If I had only suggested that they convey their message to…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14937" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14975">He suddenly realized how wrong it was to regret not having aided and abetted that wrong, and directed the full brunt of his annoyance at the other person who had robbed him of his peace of mind. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_14976" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15019">He did not know Don Rodrigo except by sight and reputation, nor had he ever had any dealings with him other than to push his chin into his chest and sweep the tip of his hat against the ground the few times he had encountered him on the street. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15020" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15057">More than once he had found occasion to defend the nobleman’s reputation against men who, under their breath and raising their eyes to heaven, had cursed one of his misdeeds. Hundreds of times he had said that Don Rodrigo was a respectable gentleman. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15058" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15084">But in this moment he uttered in his heart all the names he had never allowed others to call the man without quickly cutting them off with a “now, now.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15085" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15128">His head filled with these vexing thoughts, Don Abbondio reached his house at the far end of the village. Key already in hand, he turned it in the lock, opened the door, entered, and carefully closed the door behind him. Eager to find trusted company, he immediately called out, “Perpetua! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15129" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15146">Perpetua!” while walking toward the dining room where she would almost certainly be setting the table for supper. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15147" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15233">Perpetua, as anyone could see, was Don Abbondio’s maid. An affectionate, loyal maid who knew how to obey or command, as the occasion warranted, when to put up with the grumblings and whims of the master, and when to make him put up with her own. Her grumbling had grown more frequent by the day, ever since she passed the canonical age of forty, still unmarried, having rejected every suitor, according to her, or never having found a dog who wanted her, according to her friends. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15234" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15304">“I’m coming,” she replied, setting a flask of Don Abbondio’s favorite wine on the table, in the usual place, and biding her time. Yet before she had set foot on the threshold of the parlor, in he came, with a gait so stiff, a look so glum, a face so distraught, that it hardly took her expert eyes to realize at a glance that something extraordinary had happened to him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15305" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15308">“Mercy me! What’s wrong, master?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15309" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15320">“Nothing, nothing,” Don Abbondio replied, dropping into his chair, gasping for air. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15321" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15322">“What do you mean, nothing? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15323" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15332">You expect me to believe you, with that look on your face? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15333" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15337">Something terrible has happened!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15338" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15342">“Oh, for the love of heaven! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15343" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15355">When I say nothing I mean either nothing or something that I can’t say.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15356" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15362">“That you can’t tell even me? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15363" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15369">The one who looks after you? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15370" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15374">The one who offers you advice?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15375" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15386">“Come now, be still, and don’t put anything else on the table. Fetch me a glass of my wine.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15387" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15420">“And you claim that nothing is the matter with you?” said Perpetua, filling the glass and then withholding it, like a reward for the secret that was so slow in coming. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15421" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15446">“Give it here, give it here,” said Don Abbondio, taking the glass with his shaky hand and emptying it quickly, as if it were medicine. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15447" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15488">“So do I have to go asking around to find out what happened to my master?” said Perpetua, standing right in front of him, with her hands on her hips and elbows jutting forward, staring at him, as if to suck the secret from his eyes. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15489" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15504">“For the love of heaven! Enough of this talk! Stop making such a fuss! It’s a matter of…life and death!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15505" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15506">“Life and death!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15507" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15508">“Life and death.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15509" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15526">“You know very well that every time you’ve told me the honest truth, in confidence, I have never…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15527" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15529">“Exactly! Like the time…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15530" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15574">Perpetua could see that she had struck the wrong chord, so she immediately changed her tone. “Master,” she said in a moving voice meant to move his heart, “I have always been fond of you, and if I ask what’s wrong, it’s because I care, because I’d like to help you, offer you advice, lift your spirits…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15575" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15633">Don Abbondio’s desire to unburden himself of his painful secret might, in fact, have been as great as Perpetua’s desire to know it. So after half-heartedly spurning her renewed and more insistent assaults, after making her swear more than once that she would not breathe a word of it, finally, amid many hesitations, many gasps of “woe is me,” he told her the whole wretched story. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15634" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15684">When he came to the terrifying name of the instigator, Perpetua had to swear yet another solemn oath. And having uttered the name, Don Abbondio slumped back in his chair with a huge sigh, raised his hands in a gesture of both command and supplication, and said, “For the love of heaven!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15685" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15688">“Up to his old tricks!” exclaimed Perpetua. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15689" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15701">“That scoundrel! That tyrant! That Godless man!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15702" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15708">“Will you be quiet? Or do you want to ruin me completely?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15709" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15716">“Pshaw! We’re alone and no one can hear us. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15717" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15722">But what will you do, my poor master?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15723" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15738">“So that’s it,” said Don Abbondio crossly. “That’s the fine advice you have to offer me? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15739" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15755">You ask me what I’ll do, as if you were the one in trouble and it was up to me to get you out of it!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15756" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15767">“Well, as a matter of fact I do have my two cents to put in, but then…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15768" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15770">“But then? Let’s hear it.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15771" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15829">“My advice would be this. Everyone says that our archbishop is a holy and brave man who’s not afraid of anyone. He’s only too happy to put one of these bullies in their place when he can, to support a parish priest. So what I would say, what I do say, is that you write him a nice long letter to inform him how—” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15830" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15833">“Will you be still? Will you be quiet? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15834" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15841">Is this the advice you would give a poor man? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15842" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15855">If I were shot in the back by a bullet, God help us, would the Archbishop come to extract it from me?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15856" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15876">“Come now, they hardly give bullets away like candy! I won’t live to see the day that those dogs bite every time they bark! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15877" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15916">In my experience the people who know how to show their teeth, to demand respect, are given respect. And since you never want to fight back, everyone around here feels free to come and—” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15917" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15918">“Will you please be quiet?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15919" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15941">“I’ll be quiet in a minute, but let me tell you one thing. When everyone knows that a man hasn’t got the guts to—” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15942" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15943">“That’s enough! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15944" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15950">Is this any time to talk such rubbish?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15951" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15971">“That’s all I have to say. Think about it tonight but meanwhile try not to make yourself feel worse, and get sick. Have a bite to eat.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15972" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15987">“I’ll think about it,” Don Abbondio replied, grumbling, “I will. There’s definitely a lot to think about.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_15988" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_16007">He stood up, continuing, “I don’t want to eat anything. Nothing at all. What I want is something else. I know that it’s up to me to think of something. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_16008" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_16015">Ah! Why should this have to happen to me, of all people.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_16016" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_16032">“At least try to drink another drop,” Perpetua said, pouring from the bottle, “you know it always settles your stomach.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_16033" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_16042">“It’ll take more than that. Much more.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_16043" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_16070">As he spoke he took the lamp and, still grumbling, “A bagatelle! For a gentleman of my stature! And what will tomorrow bring?” and other such complaints, began to climb the stairs to his bedroom. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap1-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_16071" targetEnd="quarantana/cap1.xml#c1_16096">At the doorway he turned toward Perpetua, held his finger over his lips, and in a slow, solemn tone whispered, “Sssh! Don’t tell a soul, for the love of heaven!” and disappeared. </note>
</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>