<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>2022</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed: a novel</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
          <date>2022</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Michael Moore</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="english_2022_cap17">
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10020">Sometimes, all it takes is a single urge to deny a man a moment’s peace. So imagine two at once, and in competition with each other. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10021" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10058">For hours, poor Renzo had been driven by the urge to run and the urge to hide. The merchant’s cursed words had abruptly increased both one and the other. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10059" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10095">So his adventure had created an uproar. So they wanted him at all costs. Who knew how many police were out trying to track him down? Or what orders had been issued to search the towns, the taverns, the roads? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10096" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10148">He realized that ultimately there were only two policemen who could identify him, and his name was hardly written on his forehead. But he also remembered stories he had heard of fugitives who had been detected and captured through strange combinations: betrayed by their gait, their suspicious air, or other telltale clues. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10149" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10196">He was unnerved by it all. As he left Gorgonzola, the clock was striking five and the shadows were lengthening, making the dangers of being spotted slowly recede. Still, he hesitated to take the main road, preferring the first side road that seemed to lead to his destination. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10197" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10218">At first, he ran into an occasional wayfarer, but with his imagination prey to such terrible fears, he didn’t dare to approach anyone to ask for directions. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10219" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10247">“The man said six miles, he did,” Renzo thought to himself, “if going off the main road means the miles turn into eight or ten, then my legs will just have to hold up a little longer. They’ve already carried me this far. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10248" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10257">I’m certainly not headed toward Milan, so I must be headed toward the Adda. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10258" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10265">Keep walking and I’ll get there sooner or later. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10266" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10282">The Adda is nice and loud. So when I’m close, I won’t need anyone to show me the route. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10283" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10314">And if I find a boat that’ll take me, I can cross right away. Otherwise I’ll wait till morning, in the middle of a field, in a tree, like a sparrow. Better to sleep in a tree than in prison.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10315" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10324">He soon came upon a narrow road on the left, and he took it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10325" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10348">If he had run into someone at that hour, he would no longer have been reluctant to ask directions, but he didn’t see or hear a living soul. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10349" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10357">So he followed wherever the road might lead, thinking to himself: </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10358" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10362">“Me? Raise hell? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10363" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10367">Me, kill all those gentlemen? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10368" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10415">I’d give my eye teeth to find myself face-to-face with that merchant on the other side of the Adda (whenever I do finally cross that blessed river!). I’d stop him and ask, by the way, sir, where did you dig up those little stories? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10416" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10509">Let me tell you, my dear sir, what really happened. The only hell I raised was to help Ferrer as if he were my brother. And those scoundrels who, according to you, were my friends? They wanted to trick me because, for a second, I put in a word as a good Christian. While you were guarding your shop, I was getting my ribs crushed to save his Lordship, the Commissioner of Provision, whom I’ve never seen or met. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10510" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10518">I’ll think twice before helping out a nobleman again. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10519" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10529">I know, I know. They’re still our fellow man, and we should lend a hand out of the goodness of our hearts. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10530" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10564">Oh, and that big bundle of letters describing the whole plot, which—as I’m sure you know—is now in the hands of the law? Want to bet I can show it to you right now, without the devil’s help? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10565" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10570">Curious? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10571" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10575">Well, here it is…Only one letter, you say?…Yes, sir, only one letter. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10576" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10640">And this letter, if you must know, was written by a priest who could teach you a thing or two about the Catechism. One hair of his chin is worth more than your whole beard, no offense. And this letter was written, as you can see, to another priest, a man like him…Now you know the criminals I associate with. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10641" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10653">So watch what you say next time, especially about your fellow man.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10654" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10674">After a while, these and similar thoughts ceased, and the poor pilgrim dwelled solely on his present circumstances. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10675" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10703">The fear of being followed or found out that had burdened his trip during the day no longer bothered him. But so many other things made it even more unpleasant! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10704" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10775">The darkness, the solitude, his growing and now aching exhaustion. A quiet breeze was blowing, steady and sharp, that was cold comfort to a man wearing the same clothes he had donned to get married around the corner, thinking he would soon be coming home in triumph. And everything was made worse by having to wander aimlessly, like a blind man, so to speak, looking for a safe place to rest. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10776" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10810">Whenever he passed through a village, he would walk very slowly, looking around to see if any doors were still open. But he never saw a sign of life, except for the occasional flicker of candlelight through the shutters. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10811" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10831">At times he would stop on the road beyond the settlements and listen in vain for the blessed voice of the Adda. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10832" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10853">But the only voices he heard were the whimpering of dogs floating on the air, both plaintive and menacing, from some isolated farmhouse. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10854" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10903">As he approached, the whimpering became a rapid, angry barking. When he passed by the door he could hear and almost see the beast, its nose against the crack in the door, howling even louder, which quelled any temptation to knock and ask for shelter. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10904" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10925">Even without the dogs. “Who’s there?” he imagined people saying, “What do you want at this hour? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10926" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10929">How did you get here? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10930" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10931">Tell us who you are. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10932" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10936">Couldn’t you stay at an inn?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10937" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10962">“If I knock, that’s the greeting I’ll get—if I’m lucky!” he said to himself. “Either that or a fearful soul who can’t sleep and, to make matters worse, will start screaming, ‘Help! Thief!’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10963" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10976">I’d better have an answer good and ready. But what could I answer? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_10977" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11045">The first thing that comes to mind when you hear a sound in the night are thieves, criminals, tricks: You never stop to think that an honest man might find himself on the road, unless he’s a gentleman in a carriage.” So he decided against knocking on doors as a last resort, and continued on, hoping to at least find the Adda, if not cross it, that same night. Otherwise, he would have to resume his search in broad daylight. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11046" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11062">On and on he went, coming to where the cultivated fields ended and untilled land began, with patches of fern and broom. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11063" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11084">He sensed, if not a sign then at least a suggestion of a river nearby, and he headed in that direction, along a path that cut through the fields. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11085" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11094">Every few steps he would stop to listen, but always in vain. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11095" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11131">As the vegetation grew wilder his journey became more unnerving. He could no longer see a mulberry bush, a vine, or any other signs of human cultivation, which earlier had kept him a kind of company. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11132" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11169">Still he pressed on. Every time he started to remember frightening images and apparitions from tales told to him as a child, he banished or quieted them by saying prayers for the souls of the dead. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11170" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11185">With each step the trail became more overgrown with hawthorn, scrub oak, and brambles. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11186" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11220">Quickening his step, with more impatience than desire, he began to spot the occasional tree amid the brush. Farther along the same trail, he realized he was entering a forest, and shuddered at the thought of venturing in. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11221" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11247">But he overcame his qualms and continued on, reluctantly. The deeper in he went, the more his dread grew, and the more everything repelled him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11248" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11296">The trees in the distance looked like strange, twisted monsters. He was unnerved by the shadows cast by the swaying treetops, which quivered on the trail between patches of moonlight. Even the rustling of leaves underfoot was unbearable. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11297" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11318">His legs were gripped by a fury, an urge to run while at the same time struggling to support his body. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11319" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11359">He felt the night air blowing more harshly and cruelly against his brow and cheeks, slipping between his clothes and his skin, rippling through them, penetrating more deeply into his already weary bones and depleting his last ounce of strength. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11360" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11380">All at once that dread, the undefined horror that his spirit had been fighting for hours seemed to overwhelm him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11381" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11405">He was on the verge of losing his mind, but frightened most of all by his own fear. He mustered his former courage and commanded it to resist. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11406" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11447">His composure briefly restored, he paused for a moment of reflection. He resolved to get out of there immediately, retrace his steps, and go straight back to the last village he had passed, return to the company of men, and seek shelter, even at the tavern. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11448" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11474">As he stood still, no longer crushing the leaves underfoot, everything around him fell silent. He started to hear a sound, a murmuring, the murmuring of running water. He listened more carefully. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11475" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11482">There was no mistaking it. “It’s the Adda!” he exclaimed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11483" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11491">It was like finding a long-lost friend, a brother, a savior. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11492" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11538">His exhaustion almost disappeared. His pulse returned: He could feel the blood flowing through his veins, free and warm, his thoughts becoming more confident, and the uncertainty and gravity of things largely evaporate. He did not hesitate to venture deeper into the forest, in pursuit of that friendly sound. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11539" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11565">In a few moments he reached the far end of the forest, on the edge of a deep riverbank. Looking down through the dense underbrush, he could see the water sparkling and flowing. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11566" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11602">Looking up, he saw a vast plain on the opposite bank, dotted with towns, and beyond them the hills, and on one of them, a large white patch that had to be a city: Bergamo, no doubt. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11603" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11641">He descended the bank a short ways, separating and pushing aside the brambles with his hands and his arms, and looked around for a boat moving on the river. He listened for oars slicing the water, but he did not see or hear a thing. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11642" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11668">Had it been a less powerful river, Renzo would have immediately gone down and tried to wade across, but he knew all too well that the Adda was not to be trusted. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11669" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11683">So he calmly pondered what decision to take. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11684" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11717">To climb a tree and wait six or more hours for dawn, so thinly dressed, with the wind, the cold, would freeze him to the bone. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11718" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11752">To pace up and down the whole time would do little against the harsh open air and demand too much from his poor overworked legs. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11753" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11804">He remembered seeing a thatched hut, built from tree trunks and branches, then plastered with mud, in one of the fields closest to the untilled farmland. The peasants in the Milanese countryside used to store their crops in these huts during summer and take shelter in them at night to keep watch. For the rest of the year they were empty. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11805" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11826">He immediately settled on this as his refuge. He retraced his steps, went back through the forest, the undergrowth, and the untilled farmland, and headed for the hut. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11827" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11863">A dilapidated, worm-eaten door was ajar, neither locked nor chained. Renzo opened it and went in. He saw a wicker mat hanging in the air like a hammock, tied to the walls by braided saplings, but he didn’t bother getting into it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11864" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11880">On the ground he saw some straw and thought it would be good enough for his tired bones. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11881" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11913">Before lying down on the bed that Providence had prepared, however, he dropped to his knees to give thanks for the blessings and for all the help he had received from God on that awful day. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11914" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11979">He said his usual prayers and then asked God’s forgiveness for not saying them the night before, or as he put it, for going to bed like a dog. “And that is why,” he added to himself, placing his hands against the straw and prostrating himself on the ground, “I got such a rude awakening this morning.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_11980" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12031">He gathered all the straw that was strewn about, piled it on top of himself as a kind of blanket to repel the bitter cold, which had penetrated the hut, and huddled underneath, eager for a deep sleep, while feeling that he had paid too high a price for it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12032" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12068">Scarcely had he closed his eyes, however, when he began to remember or imagine (which of the two I can’t say), a coming and going of people, so dense, so incessant, that any hope of sleep disappeared. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12069" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12102">The merchant, the notary, the police, the swordsmith, the innkeeper, Ferrer, the Commissioner, the gang at the inn, the mob on the street, then Don Abbondio, then Don Rodrigo: anyone and everyone to whom Renzo wanted to speak his mind. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12103" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12141">Only three images appeared to him unaccompanied by bitter memories, free of anxiety, and completely benign. Two in particular, quite different to be sure, but closely connected in the young man’s heart: a black braid and a white beard. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12142" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12160">Yet not even the consolation he felt in pondering them was pure and untroubled. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12161" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12191">Thoughts of Padre Cristoforo made him feel deeply ashamed of his escapades, sinful intemperance, and the fine use he had made of the good friar’s fatherly advice. And his thoughts of Lucia? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12192" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12207">We won’t even try to describe how he felt. The reader knows the circumstances, and can imagine for him- or herself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12208" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12215">And poor Agnese, how could he forget her? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12216" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12255">Agnese, who already considered him the spouse of her only child? Even before he could call her “Mother” she had welcomed him into her language and her heart, and demonstrated her affection through her deeds. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12256" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12316">Worse still was the realization that it was because of these loving attentions, the great fondness she felt for him, that the poor woman now found herself homeless, almost a vagrant, uncertain of the future, and suffering trials and tribulations from the very thing she had hoped would be the peace and joy of her final years. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12317" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12320">What a night for poor Renzo! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12321" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12329">On what was supposed to have been the fifth night of marriage! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12330" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12331">In such a room! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12332" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12334">In such a wedding bed! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12335" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12338">At the end of such a day! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12339" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12368">Without knowing what tomorrow, and the days to follow, would bring! “God’s will be done,” was his answer to the most distressing thoughts. “God’s will be done. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12369" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12377">He has a plan. He is thinking of us, too. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12378" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12384">This is atonement for my sins. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12385" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12400">Lucia is so good! God cannot want her to suffer more and more and more!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12401" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12440">Lost in these thoughts, and despairing that sleep would ever arrive, the bitter cold forced him to shiver and shake every now and then. He yearned for daybreak, and impatiently counted the slow passing of the hours. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12441" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12462">Counted, I say, because every half hour, in the vast silence, he could hear the tolling of a clock striking the hour: I imagine it was the clock in Trezzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12463" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12505">The first time that sound was inflicted on his ears, so unexpectedly, from nowhere, it rang ominously, like a warning in an unknown voice from a person unseen. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12506" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12596">When the hammer finally struck eleven times, to mark five o’clock in the morning, the hour Renzo had chosen to rise, he roused himself, half-frozen, knelt down, and said his morning prayers with special fervor. He stood up, stretched high and wide, and shook his hips and his shoulders as if to reconnect his limbs, each of which seemed to have a will of its own. He blew on one hand, then the other, rubbed them together, and opened the door of the hut. Before venturing out, he glanced to the right and the left to see if anyone was around. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12597" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12615">Finding no one, he looked for the trail from the night before. He spotted it immediately and started off in that direction. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12616" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12650">The sky promised a beautiful day ahead. Off in a corner, the moon, pale and dim, stood out against an immense gray-blue field that faded slowly to pink and gold farther over to the east. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12651" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12721">Farther down, on the horizon, a few clouds stretched out in long uneven layers, ranging from blue to brown, the lowest one with a strip of fire along the bottom that slowly became sharper and more vivid. Looking southward, he could see other clouds rolled together, soft and light, glowing in a thousand nameless colors: the sky above Lombardy, so beautiful when it’s beautiful, so splendid, so serene. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12722" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12764">If Renzo had been out for a stroll, he would certainly have gazed at and admired the dawn, which was so different from what he was used to seeing from his own mountains. But he kept to the path and walked in long strides, to warm up and to get to the river quickly. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12765" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12822">He crossed the fields, the untilled farmland, the brush. He passed through the woods, looking around, laughing and embarrassed at his panic of a few hours earlier. He reached the top of the riverbank and looked down. Between the branches he spotted a fisherman’s boat moving slowly, against the current, and brushing against the banks. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12823" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12866">He immediately raced down the shortest path, cutting through the brambles, and reached the shore. He called out to the fisherman in a soft low voice. Pretending to ask for a small favor while unconsciously adopting an almost pleading manner, he gestured to the man to come near. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12867" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12898">The fisherman surveyed the river, gave a long and cautious look upstream, turned to see what was happening downstream, and then steered the prow toward Renzo and bumped against the riverbank. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12899" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12929">Renzo, who was standing there with one foot almost in the water, grabbed hold of the prow, jumped inside the boat, and said, “Would you do me the favor of taking me to the other side? I’ll pay you.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12930" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12939">The fisherman had guessed what he wanted and was already rowing in that direction. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12940" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12952">Renzo, noticing an oar on the floor of the boat, bent down and grabbed hold of it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12953" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12981">“Easy there,” said the owner, but when he saw how deftly the young man handled it, he said, “ah, so you’re one of us?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_12982" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13000">“You could say that,” replied Renzo, and he started to row with the strength and skill of an old hand. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13060">Every now and then, without pausing, he would glance suspiciously at the receding bank and impatiently at the one approaching, frustrated that there was no shorter route. The river was too strong at that point for a direct crossing, so the boat had to move diagonally, alternately fighting and following the current. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13061" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13116">As with every complicated affair, in which everything seems difficult at first, but in the doing turns out to be a matter of only a few details, now that the Adda was almost behind him, Renzo was anxious to know for certain whether it was indeed the border between the two states, or whether, having surpassed that obstacle, yet another remained. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13117" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13146">So he called to the fisherman and, nodding toward the white spot in the distance he had seen the night before, now appearing more distinct, he asked, “That town over there, is it Bergamo?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13147" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13153">“The city of Bergamo,” the fisherman replied. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13154" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13159">“And that bank there, is it in the territory of Bergamo?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13160" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13163">“In the land of Saint Mark.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13164" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13168">“Long live Saint Mark!” exclaimed Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13169" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13173">The fisherman said nothing. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13174" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13268">When they finally touched the other side, Renzo leapt to the riverbank. Thanking God under his breath and the fisherman out loud, he stuck his hand in his pocket and pulled out a berlinga that, given the circumstances, was no small expense. He held it out to the honest man who, taking another glance at the Milanese side, and up and down the river, extended his hand, accepted the gratuity, and pocketed it. He pursed his lips and placed a finger over them, accompanying this gesture with a complicit wink. Then he said, “Safe trip,” and started back across. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13269" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13326">Lest the reader be surprised at this prompt and discreet courtesy toward a stranger, I hasten to explain that the boatman was often asked to provide a similar service for smugglers and bandits, and was quite accustomed to complying. He did it more to avoid making enemies than for love of the pocket money he might earn. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13327" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13345">He provided it, I was saying, every time he could be sure that he hadn’t been spotted by customs officers, policemen, or spies. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13346" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13381">So without preferring one customer to the other, he tried to make everyone happy, with the impartiality that is the innate talent of anyone who is obliged to deal with certain types, while having to account for their actions to certain others. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13382" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13416">Renzo stopped for a moment to contemplate the land on the opposite bank, which shortly before had burned beneath his feet. “Ah, it really is behind me,” was his first thought. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13417" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13428">“Stay on your own side, damned country,” was his second, a farewell to the homeland. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13429" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13438">But his third went to the people he was leaving behind. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13439" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13480">He crossed his arms over his chest, heaved a sigh, lowered his eyes to the water flowing at his feet, and thought, “This same water passed under the bridge,” the general name by which the people in his village referred to the Lecco bridge. “Ah, what an evil world! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13481" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13486">Enough of this. God’s will be done.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13487" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13516">He turned his back on these sad thoughts and set out, using the white spot on the mountainside as his guiding point until he could find someone to show him the way. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13517" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13537">You should have seen how easily he approached other wayfarers now, and, without beating around the bush, said the name of the town where his cousin lived. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13538" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13552">The first person he spoke to told him that he still had nine miles to go. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13553" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13557">It was not a pleasant journey. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13558" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13594">Apart from the burden of his own troubles, heartbreaking sights all along the way saddened him, and he realized that the famine he thought he had left behind would be awaiting him in the country he was entering. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13595" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13643">At every step, especially in the villages and hamlets, he encountered people who were poor, not by vocation, whose misery showed more in their faces than in their clothes. He saw peasants, hill people, artisans, entire families, and heard a sad droning that was a mix of prayers, laments, and sobs. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13644" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13659">The sight filled him not only with compassion and melancholy but also with thoughts of his own circumstances. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13660" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13678">“Who knows,” he wondered, “whether I’ll manage to find a good position. Whether there’s even work. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13679" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13696">Let me stop worrying! Bortolo was fond of me. He’s a good soul and has made money. He’s invited me to come many times. He won’t let me down. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13697" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13708">And Providence has helped me so far. It will keep on helping me in the future.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13709" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13769">In the meantime his appetite had been nagging at him for a while, and was growing with each passing mile. At first Renzo thought he could resist, without much discomfort, for the two or three hours that might remain. On the other hand, he didn’t think it would be very polite to appear before his cousin like a beggar, and greet him with the words, “Give me something to eat.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13770" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13786">He emptied his pockets of his riches, dropped them into one hand, and figured out the sum. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13787" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13803">It was not a calculation that required much arithmetic, but there was more than enough for a little something to eat. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13804" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13821">He went to a tavern to set his stomach right, and in fact, once he’d paid, he still had a few coins left. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13822" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13890">On his way out, he saw two women slumped on the ground rather than sitting, and so close to the door that he almost tripped over them. One was elderly while the other was younger, with an infant attempting to nurse in vain first on one breast, then on the other, crying and crying. They all had the pallor of death. Standing near them was a man on whose face and limbs you could still detect the signs of his former strength, now depleted and almost spent by months of deprivation. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13891" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13915">All three held out their hands toward the man with the confident gait and revitalized appearance. No one spoke. Did their begging not speak for itself? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13916" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13948">“Here’s a gift from Providence!” said Renzo. Digging his hand into his pocket, he emptied it of the few coins he had left, dropped them into the closest hand, and continued on his way. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13949" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13968">The meal and his good deed comforted him and lifted his spirits (for we are made of both body and soul). </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13969" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13993">Certainly, being divested of the last of his money had given him more faith in the future than if he had come across ten times that amount. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_13994" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14057">Since Providence had set those starving people by the road that day to inspire a stranger, a fugitive, to give away his last coins, even though he was uncertain of how he would survive himself, then who could believe that it would forsake the instrument of this task, the man to whom it had given such a vivid sense of itself, so effective and resolute? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14058" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14077">This is more or less what the young man was thinking, but even less clearly than I have been able to express. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14078" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14089">For the rest of the way, as he pondered his situation, his musings grew brighter. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14090" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14123">Sooner or later, the famine had to end. Every year there is a new harvest. In the meantime, he had his trade and his cousin Bortolo. He also had a little money at home that he would send for immediately. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14124" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14205">And with that, come what may, he would manage to get by, day after day, until the times of plenty returned. “And once they finally have,” Renzo continued to imagine, “there will be an abundance of work. The masters will compete for workers from the state of Milan, who are the most skilled. And the workers from Milan will get cocky. Anyone who wants skilled workers will have to pay for them! I’ll make enough money for two, with some left over for savings. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14206" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14210">Then I can dictate a letter to the women, telling them to come…And then, why wait? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14211" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14230">With the little we’ve saved, weren’t we ready to make it through the winter? Well, we can make it through the winter here, too. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14231" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14236">As for priests, they’re everywhere. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14237" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14245">So let those two dear women come and we’ll set up house. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14246" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14297">What a pleasure it will be to walk down this same road together. To go for a ride in a cart as far as the Adda, and have a picnic there, right on the riverbank, and show the women where I stood looking for a boat, the briars I cut through, where I finally found someone to take me across.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14298" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14343">He reaches his cousin’s village. Before he sets foot inside, he spots a tall, tall house, with a series of long, long windows. He realizes it’s a spinning mill, goes in, and, amid the noise of cascading water and churning wheels, asks in a loud voice whether a certain Bortolo Castagneri works there. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14344" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14346">“Signor Bortolo? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14347" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14348">He’s over there.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14349" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14361">“They call him Signore? That’s a good sign,” thinks Renzo. He sees his cousin and runs up to him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14362" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14372">Bortolo turns around and recognizes the young man who’s shouting, “I’m here!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14373" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14385">A surprised “Oh!” Arms in the air, and then around each other in a hug. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14386" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14418">After that initial welcome, Bortolo drags our young man to another room, away from the screeching of the machines and curious eyes, and says, “I’m happy to see you. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14419" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14435">But you’re such a rascal: I’ve invited you so many times, and you never wanted to come. Now you’ve arrived at a rough moment.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14436" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14465">“To tell you the truth, I didn’t have much choice,” explained Renzo, and told him the whole sad story very briefly, but not without great emotion. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14466" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14473">“That’s a different matter,” said Bortolo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14474" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14476">“Poor Renzo! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14477" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14487">You’re counting on me. I won’t let you down. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14488" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14517">But I’ve got to tell you, they’re not looking for workers right now. In fact, everyone’s trying to hold on to the workers they’ve got, to avoid losing them and having to shut down. But the boss likes me and he’s got work. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14518" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14537">And let me tell you, between us, no boast, he owes a lot of it to me. He puts in the capital and I put in the little bit of skill I have. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14538" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14550">I’m the foreman, you know. To tell you the truth, I’m his right-hand man. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14551" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14553">Oh, but poor Lucia Mondella! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14554" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14577">I remember her like it was yesterday. A good girl. Always the best behaved in church. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14578" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14595">And when you passed her cottage…I can almost see it, the little cottage, just outside of town, with a beautiful fig tree that was higher than the wall…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14596" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14600">“Can we please not talk about it?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14601" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14617">“What I meant to say is that, when you passed that cottage, you could always hear the spinning wheel going, spinning, spinning, spinning. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14618" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14649">And that Don Rodrigo! He was already going down that road before I left. Now he’s the devil incarnate, from what I hear. Until God reins him in. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14650" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14666">Anyway, as I was saying, people are going hungry here, too…Which reminds me, how’s your appetite?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14667" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14672">“I ate a little while ago, on the road.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14673" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14677">“And how are we doing for money?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14678" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14692">Renzo held a hand up to his mouth and blew on it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14693" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14720">“It doesn’t matter,” said Bortolo, “I’ve got some. And don’t you worry. Soon enough, once things have changed, God willing, you’ll pay me back, and with enough left over for yourself.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14721" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14729">“I’ve got a little something at home that I’ll have them send to me.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14730" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14737">“Good. In the meantime you can count on me. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14738" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14760">God has been good to me so I can be good to others. And if not to family and friends, then to who?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14761" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14774">“I knew Providence would look after me!” exclaimed Renzo, shaking his good cousin’s hand affectionately. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14775" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14784">“So,” Bortolo resumed, “what an uproar in Milan. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14785" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14790">They all sound crazy to me. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14791" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14808">Word of it reached all the way up here, but you have to tell me the details. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14809" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14814">Boy, do we have a lot to talk about. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14815" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14832">Up here, you see, people are calmer and we do things a little more sensibly. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14833" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14866">The city bought two thousand bushels of grain from a Venetian merchant, grain from Turkey. Yes, from Turkey. You can’t be too picky when it comes to food! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14867" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14891">Wait until you hear what happened next. The governors of Verona and Brescia closed the roads and said, ‘We’re not letting any grain through!’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n189" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14892" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14896">So what did the people of Bergamo do? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n190" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14897" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14906">They sent a lawyer to Venice. And not just any lawyer: They sent Lorenzo Torre. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n191" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14907" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14925">He went right away, presented himself to the Doge, and said, ‘What’s gotten into the distinguished governors?’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n192" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14926" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14935">And what a speech he gave! A speech, they say, that was fit to print. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n193" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14936" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14944">That’s what it means to have a man who knows how to talk! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n194" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14945" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14970">An order went out immediately to let the grain through. And the governors were told not only to let it through, but to give it an escort, too. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n195" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14971" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14976">And it was on its way. They didn’t forget the countryside, either. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n196" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_14977" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15016">Giovanbattista Biava (another great man!), the envoy of Bergamo to Venice, let the Senate know that people were starving in the countryside, too, and the Senate ordered them four thousand bushels of millet, which can also be used to make bread. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n197" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15017" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15029">And you know what? If there’s no bread, we’ll eat meat. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n198" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15030" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15038">God has been good to me, as I was saying. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n199" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15039" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15056">Now I’ll take you to my boss: I’ve mentioned you to him many times, and he’ll be happy to meet you. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n200" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15057" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15065">A bighearted man from Bergamo, in the best tradition. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n201" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15066" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15074">He wasn’t expecting you now. But when he hears your story…He knows how to treat his workers. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n202" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15075" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15090">The famine will come and go, but business never stops. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n203" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15091" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15099">But first, I have to warn you about something. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n204" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15100" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15112">Do you know what they call us folks from the Duchy of Milan around here?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n205" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15113" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15115">“No, what?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n206" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15116" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15118">“They call us baggiani, blockheads.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n207" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15119" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15123">“That’s not very nice of them.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n208" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15124" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15139">“It is what it is. Anyone born in the Milan area who wants to live around here had better get used to it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n209" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15140" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15155">For them, calling a Milanese a blockhead is like saying, ‘sir,’ to a nobleman.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n210" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15156" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15165">“I’ll bet they only say it to people that let them.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n211" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15166" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15186">“My boy, if you can’t take being called a blockhead, you’d better not count on living here. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n212" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15187" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15225">You’d have to keep your hand on your dagger all the time. And let’s suppose you were able to kill two or three or four, someone would then come along to kill you, too—can you imagine what a pleasure it would be to appear on Judgment Day with the stain of three or four murders on your soul?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n213" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15226" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15247">“What about a Milanese who has a little…” He tapped his finger on his forehead, as he had at the Luna Piena tavern. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n214" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15248" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15256">“What I mean to say is, someone who’s a skilled craftsman?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n215" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15257" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15263">“It’s all the same. He’d still be called a blockhead. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n216" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15264" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15301">Do you know what my boss says when he talks about me with his friends? He says, ‘That blockhead was a godsend for my business. If I didn’t have that blockhead, I’d be in big trouble.’ It’s their custom.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n217" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15302" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15304">“Then it’s a stupid custom. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n218" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15305" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15330">And seeing what we know how to do (after all, we’re the ones who brought the art here, and we’re the ones who keep it going), how come it hasn’t changed?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n219" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15331" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15356">“So far it hasn’t. Maybe with time. Maybe with the next generation. But there’s no cure for the grown-ups. They’ve picked up the habit and now they aren’t going to change. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n220" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15357" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15359">What does it matter in the end? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n221" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15360" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15380">Nothing compared to the courtesies our dear compatriots paid to you, not to mention the ones they had in store.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n222" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15381" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15389">“You’re right. Well, if that’s the worst of it…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n223" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15390" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15398">“Now that you’ve been warned, everything will go smoothly. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n224" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15399" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15403">Come see the boss. Chin up.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n225" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15404" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15422">And, in fact, everything did go well, as Bortolo had promised, so there’s no need for a detailed report of what happened. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap17-n226" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15423" targetEnd="quarantana/cap17.xml#c17_15446">And it truly was Providence, because we are about to see how hard it would be for Renzo to get back the belongings and the money he had left at home. </note>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>