<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>2022</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed: a novel</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
          <date>2022</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Michael Moore</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="english_2022_cap18">
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10191">On that same day, the thirteenth of November, a messenger arrived to present the Mayor of Lecco with orders from Milan’s chief of police to conduct every investigation possible and necessary to determine whether a certain youth by the name of Lorenzo Tramaglino, silk-worker, who had escaped from the forces of praedicti egregii domini capitanei (the aforementioned Honorable Signor Capitano), had returned openly or clandestinely to his ignotum town, but verum in territorio Leuci (definitely in the territory of Lecco). Once these facts had been ascertained, the Mayor should attempt quanta maxima diligentia to capture and duly restrain him: with a good pair of metal handcuffs, given the proven insufficiency of twine restraints for said subject. He should then be escorted to prison, and kept there, under lock and key, until he can be handed over to the officers sent to take him away. And regardless of whether or not he is captured, thou shalt go to the domicile of Laurenti Tramaliini and facta debita diligentia, confiscate everything related to the case, and gather information of his depraved character, his life, and his accomplices. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n2" type="comm" status="insertion">And all that has been said or done, found or not found, confiscated or left in place, shall be diligently reported. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10192" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10229">The Mayor, having done everything humanly possible to ascertain that the subject had not returned, summoned the village Consul, and asked to be taken to the house indicated, with a large entourage of notaries and policemen. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10230" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10244">The house was locked. The person who had the keys could not or would not be found. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10245" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10264">So the door was broken in and a diligent search was conducted: In other words, the house was ransacked like a city under siege. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10265" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10330">Word of the investigation spread through the area immediately, reaching the ears of Padre Cristoforo. As shocked as he was pained, he made inquiries to shed some light on the reasons for such a surprising turn of events, but all he could gather were fanciful conjectures. He immediately wrote to Padre Bonaventura, from whom he hoped to receive more accurate information. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10331" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10365">In the meantime, Renzo’s friends and relatives were summoned to give depositions of what they might know about his depraved character. The name “Tramaglino” was now a curse, a shame, a crime. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10366" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10409">The town was turned upside down. Little by little, it was learned that in the heart of Milan Renzo had escaped from the police, and disappeared. The rumor circulated that he had done something terrible, but either no one could say exactly what it was, or they gave a hundred different versions. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10410" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10456">The worse it was purported to be, the less it was believed by the people in the village, who knew Renzo to be a good boy. Most people assumed, and whispered among themselves, that it was a plot cooked up by that tyrant Don Rodrigo to destroy his poor rival. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10457" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10479">Which goes to show that, to judge someone by inference, without the necessary knowledge of the facts, can sometimes do a great wrong, even to a scoundrel. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10480" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10522">What we can assert with the facts in hand, as the saying goes, is that while Don Rodrigo played no part in Renzo’s misfortune, he couldn’t have been happier than if he had arranged it himself. He boasted of it to his inner circle, especially Count Attilio. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10523" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10568">The Count would have already been in Milan by now, had he kept to his original plan, but at the first news of the riots, and of the mob roaming the streets, he thought it best to remain in the countryside until calm was restored, since he was in no mood for a thrashing. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10569" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10605">Especially since, having offended so many people, he had good reason to fear that some of the many—who had been restrained only by their powerlessness—would be emboldened by the circumstances to decide that the time had come for collective revenge. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10606" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10643">His respite did not last long. The warrant for Renzo’s arrest from Milan already indicated that things were calming down in the city. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10644" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10683">When that indication became a certainty, Count Attilio left for the city immediately, urging his cousin to persist in his campaign and achieve his goal, while promising, for his part, to handle the friar. On that front, his despised rival’s unlucky circumstances would play into his scheme perfectly. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10684" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10778">Shortly after Count Attilio left, Griso arrived from Monza, safe and sound, and reported to his master all the news he had managed to gather. Lucia had taken refuge in a certain convent, under the protection of a certain Signora. The girl was always cloistered, as if she, too, were a nun, never setting foot outside the door, and attending church services from behind the iron grille of a small window. This circumstance disappointed many of the townspeople, for having heard rumors of her adventures, and great things about her appearance, they longed to catch a glimpse of her for themselves. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10779" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10801">This same report put the devil in Don Rodrigo, or rather, aggravated the devil that already possessed him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10802" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10830">With so many circumstances favorable to his design, his passion—or that combination of obstinacy, rage, and capricious lust that constituted his passion—became even more inflamed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10831" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10898">Now that Renzo was gone, driven out, a fugitive, anything could be done to him with full legitimacy. Even his bride, in a way, could be considered fair game. The only man in the world who would and could take Renzo’s side, and in a voice loud enough to be heard from afar by the highest personages—the angry friar—would shortly be rendered harmless, in all probability. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10899" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10916">And now, lo and behold, a new obstacle did not only threaten to offset these advantages, but you could say it actually annulled them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10917" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10965">A convent in Monza—even if a princess hadn’t resided there—was too hard a nut for Don Rodrigo to crack. No matter how much his imagination might hover over that refuge, he could not envision any rhyme or reason that would remove Lucia from there, whether by force or trickery. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_10966" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11010">He was on the verge of giving up on his ambition. He was ready to set out for Milan—taking the long way to avoid passing through Monza—where he could surround himself with friends and festivities that would expel, through joyful thoughts, the failure that had now become so agonizing. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11011" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11021">But wait: his friends? Slow down. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11022" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11047">Rather than distraction, new displeasures might await him in their company, since Attilio would probably have already blurted out the story, and raised everyone’s expectations. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11048" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11059">Questions about the girl from the mountains would come at him from every corner, and he would have to explain that he had failed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11060" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11066">With all his desires, all his efforts, what did he gain in the end? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11067" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11100">He had made a resolution: An unworthy resolution, to be sure, but come now, you can’t always control your desires. The point is to satisfy them. And what had the result been? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11101" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11109">That a peasant and a friar had gotten the better of him? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11110" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11110">Impossible! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11111" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11147">And when an unexpected stroke of luck—without any effort on the part of his own no-good self—had removed the peasant from the scene, and a cunning friend had taken care of the friar, he hadn’t known how to take advantage of the situation, and instead beaten a cowardly retreat. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11148" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11170">More than enough reason to never again be able to hold his head high among his peers, or be forced to stand forever ready to draw his sword. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11171" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11234">And then, how could he return to live in that village, in that country, where, apart from the painful, incessant reminders of his passion, he would bear the scar of failure? Public opprobrium of him would rise while his status would sink. On the face of every lowlife, amid their bowing and scraping, he would be able to read a bitter, “Finally got a taste of your own medicine.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11235" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11270">“The road to iniquity,” says the manuscript at this point, “is wide but that does not mean it is easy. There are many bumps and rough patches along the way, and though the road goes downhill, it is arduous and tiring.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11271" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11337">Don Rodrigo didn’t want to get off the road, or go back, or stop, and he couldn’t move forward on his own. He did, however, hit upon a means through which he could press on: He could request the intercession of someone whose hands often reached where the eyesight of others could not. A man or devil for whom the harder the task, the more eager he was to take it on. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11338" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11384">But this option also had its drawbacks and its risks, which were even more serious than expected, since no one could predict where Don Rodrigo might end up once he had thrown in his lot with that man: a powerful ally, no doubt, but a tyrannical and dangerous commander. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11385" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11404">For days these thoughts kept Don Rodrigo hanging between a yes and a no, each of which was equally troubling. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11405" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11419">A letter arrived from his cousin in the meantime, saying that the plot was well underway. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11420" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11445">Shortly after the lightning came thunder. That is to say, one fine morning, he heard that Padre Cristoforo had been transferred from the Pescarenico monastery. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11446" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11496">This quick success, described in the letter from Attilio that both encouraged him and threatened him with ridicule, made Don Rodrigo more inclined to take the gamble. The final push came from the unexpected news that Agnese had returned home: one less impediment to Lucia. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11497" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11504">I will explain these two events, starting with the second. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11505" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11550">The two poor women had barely settled into their refuge when the news spread in Monza, and then in the convent, of the rioting in Milan. Then came a flood of details that was forever swelling and changing. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11551" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11578">The stewardess who, from her home, could keep one ear on the street and one on the convent, gathered news from both sources, and shared it with her guests. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11579" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11608">“Two, six, eight, four, seven men were thrown into prison. They’ll string them up, some in front of the Forno delle Grucce, some at the top of the road to the Commissioner of Provision’s house…And guess what? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11609" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11623">One of them got away! He’s from Lecco, or thereabouts. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11624" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11641">I didn’t catch his name, but I’m sure someone will come by and tell me. I wonder if you know him.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11642" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11697">This announcement, together with the knowledge that Renzo had arrived in Milan on that fateful day, left the women, especially Lucia, more than a little worried. So imagine how they felt when the custodian came back to tell them, “He’s from your same town, the man that got away before they could hang him. A silk-worker named Tramaglino: Do you know him?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11698" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11732">Lucia dropped the embroidery from her hands. She turned pale and lost her composure. The stewardess would certainly have noticed if she had been any closer, but she was standing in the doorway with Agnese. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11733" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11786">Lucia’s mother was also shaken, though not as much, and she was able to hide her reaction. By way of a reply, she said that in a small town everyone knows everyone else, so of course they knew him, but they couldn’t believe he could be mixed up in anything like that, since he was such a gentle soul. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11787" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11795">She then asked whether he really had escaped, and to where. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11796" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11824">“Escaped? Everyone says so. To where? Who knows? Maybe they’ll nab him again, maybe he’s safe. But if they do get their hands on him again, your gentle soul…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11825" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11843">At this the stewardess was thankfully called away. You can imagine how the mother and daughter felt. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11844" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11885">For the next few days, the poor woman and her desolate girl had to live with uncertainty, mulling over the how, the why, and the consequences of this heartbreaking news, and pondering, each to herself, or whispering to the other whenever they could, the awful words they had heard. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11886" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11896">Finally, on Thursday, a man came to the convent asking for Agnese. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11897" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11988">He was a fisherman from Pescarenico on his way to Milan to sell his catch, per his customary practice. When he passed through Monza, he had been asked by the good Fra Cristoforo to stop by the convent and give his regards to the women, tell them what was known about Renzo’s unfortunate situation, and advise them to be patient and trust in God. He was also to assure them that the friar would never forget them, and that he would look for every opportunity to help. In the meantime he would not fail to keep them apprised of the situation once a week, through the fisherman or another means. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_11989" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12035">The messenger had nothing new or concrete to report about Renzo, other than the visit to his house and the hunt to capture him. Every attempt had turned up empty, and it was known for certain that he had taken refuge in the Bergamo area. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12036" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12081">Needless to say, this came as a great relief to Lucia. Her tears began to flow more freely. She found even more comfort in her private emotional outpourings with her mother, and to all of her prayers she added words of thanks. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12082" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12111">Gertrude often invited Lucia to her private parlor, and sometimes kept her there for hours on end, enjoying the poor girl’s sweetness and innocence, as well as her constant words of appreciation and gratitude. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12112" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12145">She also confided in Lucia a part of her own story (the untainted part), and what she had suffered before coming to this place of suffering. Thus the dismay and suspicion that Lucia had initially felt toward Gertrude slowly turned into compassion. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12146" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12178">The story—aided by Agnese’s notions about the minds of the nobility—gave Lucia more than enough to explain the odd manners of her benefactress. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12179" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12230">Although she felt inclined to reciprocate the confidences that Gertrude had shared with her, she avoided mentioning her own latest concern, her latest misfortune, and telling her who the fugitive silk-worker was, to avoid spreading such painful and scandalous news. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12231" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12254">She also warded off, as best she could, the nun’s prying questions about her life before her engagement. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12255" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12282">This was not out of caution, but rather because it was a story more agonizing, more difficult to tell than all the ones she’d heard from the Signora (and even the ones still to come). </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12283" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12335">The nun’s stories were filled with cruelty, scheming, and suffering: things that were awful and painful but could still be named. Lucia’s stories, by contrast, contained a sentiment, a word that she didn’t feel she could utter when speaking about herself. A word she could never paraphrase in a way that didn’t seem too bold: The word was love! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12336" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12359">Once or twice Gertrude almost resented the girl’s reticence, yet Lucia’s tenderness, respect, appreciation, and even trust toward her also shone through! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12360" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12398">Sometimes she was irritated, perhaps, by Lucia’s modesty, so delicate, so mysterious. But all was forgotten in the comforting thought that came back to her whenever she looked at Lucia: “I am doing something good for this girl.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12399" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12417">And it was true, because in addition to providing her with a refuge, Gertrude had given Lucia tremendous comfort through her words and her affectionate caresses. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12418" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12479">Lucia also found solace in keeping busy, and she was forever asking to be given things to do. Even in the parlor she always brought along some work to keep her hands occupied. But painful thoughts have a way of intruding everywhere. As she sewed and sewed—almost a new handicraft for her—she was often reminded of her spinning wheel, and of so many things behind it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12480" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12503">On every second Thursday, the fisherman or another messenger would return, conveying the regards of Padre Cristoforo and confirming Renzo’s successful escape. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12504" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12570">There was no reliable news of his troubles because, as I have told the reader, the Capuchin had hoped to hear something from Padre Bonaventura in Milan, to whom he had referred Renzo. The friar wrote back saying that he had seen neither the man nor the letter, but that someone had indeed come to the monastery asking for him and, not finding him, had left and never returned. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12571" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12612">On the third Thursday, no messenger arrived. The poor women felt not only deprived of a hoped and longed for source of comfort, but—as is the case with every little thing for those in difficulty and distress—found further reason for concern and persistent suspicions. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12613" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12634">Agnese had already been contemplating a quick trip home. When the promised messenger did not show up, she made up her mind to go. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12635" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12669">For Lucia it was no small matter to be separated from her mother, but her resistance was overcome by her longing to know something and the security she felt in her protected sanctuary. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12670" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12709">So the two of them decided that Agnese would leave the following day and wait by the road for the fisherman, who should be passing by on his way from Milan. She would ask him for the courtesy of a ride on his cart, so she could be taken back to her mountains. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12710" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12747">Agnese managed to find the fisherman, and asked him first whether Fra Cristoforo had any message for her. But the man had been out fishing the whole day before his departure, and hadn’t heard anything from the good padre. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12748" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12783">He offered her a ride home even before she asked for the favor. She took her leave of the Signora and her daughter, and, not without shedding a few tears, promised to send her news as soon as she arrived, and to return soon. With that she left. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12784" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12790">Nothing special happened during the trip. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12791" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12808">The old woman and the fisherman spent part of the night at an inn, as was his custom. Then they departed before dawn so they would arrive in Pescarenico bright and early. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12809" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12841">Agnese got off in the piazza in front of the monastery, and said goodbye to her driver with many a “God bless you.” Since she was already at the monastery, she thought she might stop by to see her benefactor, the friar, before going home. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12842" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12854">When she rang the bell, who should open the door but Fra Galdino, the friar who collected walnuts. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12855" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12862">“My good woman. What wind blew you in?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12863" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12868">“I came here to see Padre Cristoforo.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12869" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12871">“Padre Cristoforo? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12872" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12873">He’s not here.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12874" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12878">“Oh? How soon will he back?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12879" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12891">“Who knows?” replied the friar, shrugging his shoulders and retracting his shaven head into his hood. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12892" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12893">“Where did he go?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12894" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12895">“To Rimini.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12896" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12896">“Where?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12897" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12898">“Rimini.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12899" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12901">“Where’s that?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12902" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12918">“Ehh,” replied the friar, with a hand gesture to indicate that it was quite a distance. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12919" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12921">“Oh, poor me! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12922" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12928">Why did he leave so suddenly?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12929" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12935">“He left at the bidding of the Provincial Father.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12936" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12944">“Why was he sent away, when he was doing so much good here? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12945" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12946">Oh Lord!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12947" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12962">“If our superiors had to explain the orders they give, what would become of obedience, dear woman?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12963" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12969">“Yes, but this will be my ruin!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12970" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12972">“Do you know what might have happened? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_12973" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13025">In Rimini they must have needed a good preacher (we have them everywhere, but sometimes you need just the right one). And the Provincial Father down there must have written to the Provincial Father up here, asking if he had such and such a person. And the Provincial Father here must have said, ‘This is a job for Fra Cristoforo.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13026" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13029">I’m sure that’s what happened.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13030" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13032">“God have mercy on us! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13033" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13034">When did he leave?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13035" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13035">“The day before yesterday.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13036" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13048">“If I had only followed my instincts and come back a couple of days ago! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13049" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13060">And you wouldn’t happen to know when he might be back, more or less?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13061" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13074">“Ah, my dear woman! Only the Provincial Father knows, if even he does. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13075" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13094">Once our preachers have flown the coop, there’s no guessing on which branch they might alight. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13095" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13112">They want them here, they want them there, and we’ve got monasteries in the four corners of the world. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13113" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13156">Let’s suppose that in Rimini Fra Cristoforo makes a great impression with his Lenten sermons. You see, he doesn’t always improvise them, like he did here, for the fishermen and peasants. For the city pulpits, he has beautiful sermons all written down, and plenty of them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13157" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13176">So the word gets out that there’s this wonderful preacher, and everyone will be demanding his services from…from I don’t know where! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13177" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13197">So he’d have to be sent off again. And since we live off the charity of the whole world, it’s only right that we should serve the whole world.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13198" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13199">“Oh Lord, oh Lord!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13200" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13211">Agnese exclaimed, on the verge of tears. “How will I manage without that man? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13212" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13218">He was like a father to us! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13219" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13223">With him gone we’ll be ruined.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13224" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13255">“Listen, my good woman. Yes, Fra Cristoforo really was a kind man, but we have others, too. Full of charity and talent. Men who know how to deal with both the rich and the poor. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13256" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13267">Would you like Fra Atanasio? Or Fra Girolamo? How about Fra Zaccaria? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13268" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13276">He’s a man of valor, he is, that Fra Zaccaria. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13277" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13316">And don’t, like certain idiots, dwell on the fact that he’s scrawny, with that tiny voice and that straggly beard. I’m not saying he’s much of a preacher—we each have our own talents— but he can give you good advice.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13317" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13378">“Oh, for heaven’s sake!” exclaimed Agnese, with that mix of gratitude and exasperation you feel when presented with an offer that expresses another person’s altruism rather than what you need. “What do I care what kind of man this one or that one is or isn’t, when the man I need is gone? He was the one who knew our situation and had everything ready to help us!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13379" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13382">“Then you will have to be patient.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13383" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13389">“That I know,” replied Agnese, “I’m sorry to have troubled you.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13390" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13399">“No trouble at all, my dear woman! I am sorry for your sake. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13400" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13417">If you decide to seek out one of our friars, the monastery will always be here. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13418" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13427">And you’ll be seeing me again soon, when I am out collecting olive oil.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13428" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13450">“Goodbye, then,” said Agnese. And she started walking toward her village, desolate, confused, and dismayed, like a blind man who’s lost his cane. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13451" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13465">Since I myself am somewhat better informed than Fra Galdino, I can tell you what actually happened. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13466" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13487">As soon as Attilio reached Milan, he paid a visit, as he had promised Don Rodrigo, to the uncle they shared, who sat on the Secret Council. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13488" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13519">(The Council was a group consisting, at that time, of thirteen leading men of the law and the sword that advised the Governor, and assumed temporary rule in the event of his death or forced vacancy.) </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13520" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13550">The Count, a jurist and a senior member, enjoyed a certain prestige within the Council, and had no rivals in exploiting this fact for his own benefit. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13551" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13591">He was a master of ambiguous words, significant silences, things left half-said, a wink of the eye that meant, “I’m not allowed to say,” flattery without promises, elaborately veiled threats. They all served a single purpose, and they all, more or less, worked in his favor. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13592" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13661">So much so that even a mere, “There’s nothing I can do about it”—often spoken truthfully, but in such a way as to insinuate otherwise—helped to increase the image and thus the reality of his power. Like those boxes you still see in apothecary shops, empty boxes with Arabic labels: They help to uphold the prestige of the shop. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13662" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13712">The Count’s prestige had been growing by tiny degrees for a very long time, but recently it had taken what you could call a giant step forward, thanks to a trip to Madrid he’d made on a mission to the Royal Court. You should have heard him describe the welcome he had received there. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13713" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13776">Suffice it to say that the Count-Duke of Olivares had treated him with special regard and taken him into his confidence, as shown, for example, by having once asked him—in the presence, you could say, of half the court—how well he liked Madrid, and, another time in the bay of a window, he told him that the Duomo of Milan was the largest church in His Majesty’s domains. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13777" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13833">After paying his respects to the Count Uncle and conveying those of his cousin, Attilio adopted a serious expression, which he knew how to adopt at the appropriate time, and said, “I think I am doing my duty, without betraying a confidence of Rodrigo, in bringing to my uncle’s attention a matter that, without your intervention, could become serious, and lead to consequences…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13834" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13837">“Another one of his messes, I presume.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13838" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13865">“In all fairness, I can’t say that my cousin is in the wrong this time, but he is quite worked up about it, and as I was saying, our dear Uncle is the only person who can…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13866" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13867">“Let’s hear it.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13868" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13887">“In those parts there is a Capuchin friar who has a grudge against Rodrigo, and things have reached the point that…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13888" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13903">“How many times have I told the two of you to let the friars stew in their own juices? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13904" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13918">They already give enough of a headache to those of us who have to…to those whose job it is…” At this he heaved a sigh. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13919" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13924">“But for the two of you, who are able to steer clear of them…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13925" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13940">“My dear Uncle, I feel obliged to tell you that Rodrigo would have steered clear of him, if he could have. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13941" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13956">It’s the friar who’s out to get him, who started provoking him every which way…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13957" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13964">“What the devil does this friar have against my nephew?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13965" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13982">“First of all, the friar’s a troublemaker. Everyone knows it, and he makes it his business to go after the nobility. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_13983" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14011">He’s taken it upon himself to protect, to advise, to—I don’t know!—a peasant girl from around there. He has a fondness for this girl, a fondness…that isn’t so much selfish as it is jealous, suspicious, and more than a bit ornery.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14012" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14048">“I see,” said the Count. From beneath the oafish face bestowed upon him by nature, and disguised beneath layers of diplomacy, a ray of malice flashed through that was beautiful to witness. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14049" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14069">“For some time now,” Attilio continued, “this friar has got it into his head that Rodrigo has some kind of designs on her…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14070" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14096">“He got it into his head? I know your cousin, and it’d take a better lawyer than you to acquit him in such an affair.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14097" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14157">“My dear Uncle, Rodrigo may well have teased this girl when he ran into her on the street. That much I would believe. He’s still young and he’s no Capuchin, after all. But it was all trivial stuff that doesn’t mean anything. What does matter is that this friar has started talking about Rodrigo as if he were a common criminal, and is trying to turn the whole village against him.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14158" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14161">“What about the other friars?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14162" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14198">“They’re steering clear of the matter because they know he’s a hothead, and for Rodrigo they have the utmost respect. On the other hand, the peasants look up to this friar, because he acts like some sort of saint, and…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14199" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14207">“I suppose he doesn’t realize that Rodrigo is my nephew.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14208" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14210">“On the contrary. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14211" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14221">It makes him even more ruthless.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14222" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14223">“What? What?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14224" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14275">“And he goes around saying—he enjoys baiting Rodrigo even more because he has a natural defender, a man of your stature. He says he’s not afraid of the great and powerful, since the cord of Saint Francis is mightier than the sword, and…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14276" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14278">“The nerve of that friar! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14279" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14282">Tell me his name.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14283" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14310">“Fra Cristoforo of ***,” said Attilio. The Count removed a small notebook from the drawer and, huffing and puffing, wrote down that poor name. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14311" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14324">Meanwhile, Attilio continued to speak. “He’s always been of that temperament. Everyone knows his background. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14325" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14359">He was a commoner who, after coming into a little money, wanted to keep up with the gentlemen of his town. Angry that he couldn’t get the better of them, he killed one of their members. And to avoid the gallows, he became a friar.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14360" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14363">“Well done! Splendid! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14364" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14374">We shall see. We shall see,” said the Count, huffing and puffing all the while. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14375" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14406">“And now,” Attilio continued, “he’s angrier than ever. A design that he cared about a great deal went wrong. This should show you what kind of a man he is. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14407" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14469">He wanted to arrange for the marriage of his little ward. Maybe to remove her from the dangers of the world—do I need to explain more?—or for some other reason. But he wanted her to get married at all costs, and he had found the right man: another one of his wards, a subject whose name you just might—or rather certainly do—know, since I’m sure that the Secret Council must have dealt with this worthy subject.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14470" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14472">“Who is he?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14473" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14480">“A silk-worker, Lorenzo Tramaglino, the one who—” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14481" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14486">“Lorenzo Tramaglino!” exclaimed the Count. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14487" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14491">“Excellent! Well done, Padre! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14492" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14506">Of course…He had a letter for…What a pity that…But it doesn’t matter now. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14507" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14538">And why didn’t Don Rodrigo say something to me about all this? Why did he let this go on without turning to someone who is ready and able to take this matter in hand and come to his assistance?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14539" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14587">“In all honesty,” Attilio said, “knowing how many problems, how many things our dear Uncle has on his mind…” (the Count, heaving a sigh of agreement, placed his hand on his head, as if to indicate how exhausting it was to bear) “…he hesitated to add something else to your burden. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14588" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14638">So I’ll tell you everything. From what I could gather, Rodrigo is so exasperated, so beside himself, so sick of the friar’s insults, that he’d rather take justice into his own hands than pursue legal means with the wisdom and the help of his dear Uncle. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14639" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14675">I tried to calm him down, but seeing things taking a turn for the worse, I felt it was my duty to bring it to the attention of our Uncle, who is ultimately the head of the family and the pillar of this house…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14676" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14683">“You would have done better to speak to me earlier.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14684" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14727">“You are right, sir. But I was hoping that the matter would take care of itself, or that the friar would finally come to his senses, or leave that monastery, as happens with the men of that order, who are here one day and gone the next. Then the whole story would be behind us by now. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14728" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14728">But…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14729" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14734">“Now it’s up to me to set things right.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14735" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14738">“That is exactly what I was thinking. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14739" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14771">I said to myself, ‘Our uncle, with his shrewdness, his authority, will know how to prevent a scandal, and at the same time, preserve the honor of Rodrigo, who shares his blood. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14772" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14799">This friar, I was saying, is always going on about the cord of Saint Francis, but there’s more than one way to use it, and not just around the waist. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14800" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14845">Our uncle must have a hundred means to…’ I don’t know. But I do know that the Father Provincial is very deferential toward you, as indeed he should be. And if our uncle thinks that, in this case, the best solution would be for the friar to have…maybe a change of scene, a couple of words to the right person…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14846" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14859">“Leave the thinking to me,” said the Count, rather gruffly. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14860" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14878">“Of course,” exclaimed Attilio, bowing his head and adopting a forlorn expression. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14879" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14887">“Who am I to give advice to our dear Uncle? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n189" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14888" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14901">I speak only out of the great love I reserve for the family honor. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n190" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14902" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14927">And I’m afraid I’ve made another mistake,” he added pensively. “I’m afraid I may have wronged Rodrigo in making our Uncle think poorly of him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n191" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14928" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14953">I could never forgive myself if I led you to believe that Rodrigo does not have every faith in you, as well as all the deference that is your due. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n192" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14954" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14962">Believe me, Uncle, in this case it was just…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n193" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14963" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14981">“Come. Come. What could ever come between the two of you? You will be friends forever, until one of you wises up. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n194" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_14982" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_15021">You’re a couple of rascals, always getting into trouble, and then I have to step in and patch things up…This might sound crazy, but the two of you give me more to worry about than [and here you can imagine how deeply he sighed] all these blessed affairs of state.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap18-n195" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_15022" targetEnd="quarantana/cap18.xml#c18_15054">Attilio uttered a few more apologies, a few more promises, a few more compliments. Then he took his leave and left, ushered out by a, “Don’t do anything stupid!” which was the Count Uncle’s customary farewell to his nephews. </note>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>