<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>2022</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed: a novel</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
          <date>2022</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Michael Moore</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="english_2022_cap13">
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10045">At that moment, the hapless Commissioner, lacking both an appetite and fresh bread, was struggling through a bitter repast. He waited anxiously to see how the storm would end, never suspecting that it was about to land with a shock on his doorstep. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10046" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10059">An honest man had raced ahead of the crowd to warn him of the impending danger. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10060" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10079">The servants, drawn by the noise outside the door, looked down the street with alarm. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10080" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10115">Even as they listened to the man’s warning, they could see the vanguard appear, and rushed to inform their master. While he fretted over whether or how to flee, another man arrived to announce that it was too late. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10116" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10127">The servants had barely enough time to close the door. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10128" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10154">They bolted it shut, boarded it up, and ran to shutter the windows, as if the sky were turning black and a hailstorm was expected any minute. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10155" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10189">The rising din of the crowd rumbled like thunder, echoing in the empty courtyard. Every rafter in the house shook, and in the midst of the vast and muddled clamor, a shower of rocks could be heard pelting the door. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10190" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10191">“We want the Commissioner! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10192" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10194">He’s a tyrant! A hoarder! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10195" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10199">Hand him over, dead or alive!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10200" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10230">The poor wretch paced from room to room, pale and out of breath, slapping his hands together, beseeching God—and his servants—to hold strong and find him a way to escape. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10231" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10235">But how? Where? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10236" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10277">He went upstairs to the attic. Through a peephole he looked down at the street apprehensively and saw that it was teeming with an angry mob. He could hear the voices calling for his death. More terrified than ever, he withdrew and went looking for the safest, most secluded hiding place. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10278" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10323">Huddled in a corner, he listened very, very carefully to see if the menacing noise had faded, and if the turmoil was subsiding. Instead he heard the roar of the crowd grow even louder and more savage, and the beating on the door double in intensity. Gripped by this new assault on his heart, he quickly plugged his ears. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10324" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10369">Then, like a mad man, gritting his teeth and furrowing his brow, he extended his arms and pointed his fists, as if that would keep the door shut…Well, what exactly he did no one knows, since he was alone, and history can only guess. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10370" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10373">A practice, luckily, to which history is accustomed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10374" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10390">This time Renzo found himself in the thick of the turmoil, not carried by the crowd but having placed himself there deliberately. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10391" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10428">At the first mention of blood he could feel his own blood boil. As for looting, he could not tell in this case whether it was a good or a bad idea. But the idea of killing filled him with a clear and immediate horror. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10429" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10502">He may have been persuaded—due to the fatal complaisance of passionate spirits before the passionate assertions of the multitude—that the Commissioner was the main reason for the famine and an enemy of the poor, but he had still resolved to join in the effort to save him from being killed, having overheard just such a threat at the first stirring of the crowd. It was with this in mind that he had plunged in, almost making it to the door, on which people were laying siege in a hundred different ways. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10503" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10556">Some were trying to break the nails on the lock with cobblestones. Others, armed with bars, chisels, and hammers, tried to work in a more conventional manner. Still others, having no better tools, wielded stones, blunt knives, nails, clubs, and even their fingernails to deface and destroy the walls of the house, intent on tearing out bricks to make a breach. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10557" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10612">Those who couldn’t reach the house shouted words of encouragement. But their pushing and shoving complicated an enterprise that was already complicated by the disorderly rivalry among the men trying to break into the house. Thank heavens, since the same thing that happens all too often in the service of good also happens in the service of evil: The most ardent advocates become an impediment to their own goals. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10613" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10643">The first magistrates to get the news of what was happening immediately sent a request for help to the castellan (which at the time was called the Porta Giovia Castle), who dispatched a few soldiers. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10644" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10679">But between the news, the order, the mobilization, the preparations to march, and the march itself, the house was already under siege from every side by the time they arrived. The soldiers came to a halt on the far edge of the crowd. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10680" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10688">The commanding officer could not figure out what to do. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10689" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10708">The crowd was nothing more—if you don’t mind my saying—than a riffraff of people of different ages and sexes, gawking. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10709" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10729">At the order to disperse and make way, they responded with a long, sullen grumble. No one budged. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10730" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10763">To fire above the crowd seemed, to the officer, not only cruel but also dangerous. Injuring the least threatening risked inflaming the most violent. Not to mention that he had been given no such instruction. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10764" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10794">The best line of action was to open up the outer circle, pushing the crowd to the right and left, and advance, bringing battle to those who were waging it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10795" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10828">But how? Who knew whether the soldiers would manage to advance in a compact and orderly fashion or, rather than split the crowd, disappear into it and, having provoked it, be at its mercy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10829" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10842">The indecision of the commander and inaction of the soldiers gave the appearance, rightly or wrongly, of fear. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10843" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10914">The people closest to them were happy to stare them in the face with an attitude that said, “I dare you.” The people farther away did not abstain from openly jeering and making faces. Still farther away, few knew or cared that the soldiers were even there. The vandals continued tearing at the walls, with no other thought than to succeed quickly in their enterprise, while the spectators egged them on with their cries. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10915" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10977">Standing out in the crowd was a man who was himself a spectacle, an old jailbird, his bloodshot eyes bulging from their sockets, his wrinkles contracted into a sneer of diabolical glee. In the air above his vindictive white head, his hands were shaking a hammer, a rope, and four long spikes with which he said he would nail the Commissioner’s body to the door, dead or alive. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_10978" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11014">“What! Shame on you!” escaped from the mouth of Renzo, appalled by the old man’s words and the sight of so many approving faces, but heartened to see others who, despite their silence, emanated his same feeling of horror. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11015" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11015">“For shame! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11016" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11025">Do we want to rob the executioner of his job? Murder a fellow Christian? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11026" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11038">How can we expect God to give us bread if we commit such an atrocity? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11039" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11046">He won’t send bread: He’ll strike us down with lightning!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11047" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11076">“Dog! Traitor!” shouted a man who overheard Renzo’s kind words in the midst of the commotion. Turning toward Renzo with a demonic face, he cried, “Look, everyone! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11077" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11089">Here’s a lackey of the Commissioner, disguised as a peasant! A spy! After him! After him!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11090" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11098">A hundred voices called out from every side, “What? Where? Who? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11099" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11102">The Commissioner’s lackey. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11103" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11104">A spy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11105" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11111">The Commissioner’s disguised as a peasant, and he’s escaping. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11112" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11115">Where is he? After him! After him!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11116" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11143">Renzo shut up and shrank into his skin, wanting to disappear. Some of his neighbors tried to hide him, making various loud shouts to confound the murderous voices. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11144" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11167">But what helped him most were cries of “Make way! Make way!” that emerged from nearby. “Make way! Help is here! Make way!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11168" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11168">What was it? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11169" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11186">A long ladder that some were bringing to prop against the house and climb in through a window. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11187" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11206">Fortunately, this device—which would have made the invasion easy—was not very easy to maneuver. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11207" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11271">The men who were carrying it—on both ends and on each side—were being crushed, harassed, and torn apart by the crowd, and were forced to move in waves. One bellowing man was weighted down as if he were under a shaking yoke, his head stuck between two rungs and the rails on his shoulders. Another was shoved away from his burden, causing the abandoned ladder to bang into shoulders, arms, and ribs: Can you imagine how the people who were struck responded? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11272" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11290">But others picked up the dead weight, diving underneath and placing it on their shoulders, with the shout, “Come on, men! Let’s go!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11291" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11297">The fatal machine advanced in starts, zigzagging its way through the crowd. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11298" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11361">It arrived just in time to distract and scatter Renzo’s adversaries. He took advantage of the confusion within the confusion and slipped away unnoticed, crouching low and then elbowing his way forward when that failed, intent on getting away from this unsavory place as soon as possible in order to see or wait for Padre Bonaventura. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11362" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11387">Suddenly an extraordinary wave rolls over the crowd, and a rumor passes from mouth to mouth: “Ferrer! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11388" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11388">Ferrer!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11389" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11418">Surprise, joy, rage, sympathy, or revulsion bursts out everywhere reached by that name. Some shout it, some want to stifle it, some proclaim it, some reject it, some bless it, some curse it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11419" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11421">“Ferrer is here!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11422" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11427">“No, he’s not!” “But he is! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11428" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11440">He is! Long live Ferrer! The man who brought down the price of bread!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11441" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11442">“He is not!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11443" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11448">“He is, too! He’s here! He’s here! In a carriage!” “Who cares! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11449" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11476">What’s he got to do with anything? We don’t want him!” “Ferrer! Long live Ferrer! Friend to the poor! He’s coming to toss the Commissioner in jail!” “No, no, we want our own justice! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11477" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11485">Get back! Get back!” “Yes! It’s Ferrer! Let Ferrer through! Off to prison with the Commissioner!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11486" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11503">Everyone stands on tiptoe and looks toward the place where the unexpected arrival was announced. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11504" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11524">And since everyone was standing, people could see neither more nor less than if their feet were flat on the ground, but they all stood anyway. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11525" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11592">At the far edge of the crowd, across from where the soldiers were posted, Antonio Ferrer, the Grand Chancellor, had in fact arrived in a carriage. Troubled, in all likelihood, by the awareness that his blunders and obstinacy had been the cause or at least the occasion for the uprising, he was now coming to placate and prevent the most dreadful and irreparable effects, willing to spend a popularity that had been won through wrongful means. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11593" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11666">In popular uprisings, there are always people who—in the heat of passion or by fanatical persuasion, sinister intentions, or an inclination for troublemaking—do everything they can to make matters worse. They propose or promote the most ruthless ideas, and blow on the fire whenever it starts to die down. Nothing is enough for them: They’d like to see the riots go on forever, uncontained. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11667" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11716">To compensate, there are always other people who, with equal ardor and equal determination, strive for the opposite effect, either motivated by friendship or affection for the persons threatened, or driven solely by a pious and spontaneous horror at bloodshed and atrocities. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11717" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11720">Heaven bless them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11721" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11742">Within each of these two opposing parties, even when there is no prior agreement, their singularity of purpose forges an immediate consensus once they take action. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11743" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11836">Those who form the mass and almost the material of the uprising are an accidental mix of people who tend toward one extreme or the other, by more or less indefinite gradations: a little excited, a little cunning, a little inclined toward a certain form of justice (in their understanding of the word), and a little eager to see something horrible happen. They’re primed for cruelty or mercy, to detest or adore, if and when the occasion arises to fully feel one way or the other. They’re always eager to know, to believe in that greater cause, since they need to either hail and applaud someone or to deride them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11837" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11923">“Dead or alive” are the words that spring most readily to their lips. The instigators who persuade the mob that a certain person doesn’t deserve to be drawn and quartered can just as easily convince it that the same person should be borne in triumph. They can be activists, spectators, tools, or obstacles, depending on how the wind blows. They’re even ready to shut up, when there are no more slogans to repeat; to stop, when there are no more instigators; to disband, when many concordant and uncontested voices say, “Let’s go”; and to return home, asking one another, “What was that all about?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11924" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11967">But since this mass can lend its greater numbers to whomever it chooses, each of the two active parties tries to outdo the other to attract and harness the mob, like two rival spirits fighting to enter that swollen body and dictate its movements. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_11968" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12042">They set their sights on whoever is best at spreading the rumors most apt to excite passions, to steer movements toward one purpose or the other; whoever is best at finding the piece of information that will arouse indignation or dampen it, that will rekindle hopes or fears; whoever can find the slogans that, when repeated by the many and the strong, simultaneously express, attest to, and create the vote of the majority, for one side or the other. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12043" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12111">The point of this digression is that, in the struggle between two contenders for the vote of the crowd assembled in front of the Commissioner’s house, the appearance of Antonio Ferrer lent almost immediate advantage to the humane, who had been in the minority, and who, if he had arrived any later, would have had neither the power nor the motivation to resist. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12112" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12138">The masses loved him because of the favorable rate on bread he had offered to consumers, and for his heroic rejection of every opposing argument. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12139" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12168">Those who were already so inclined were now even more enamored of the spirited, confident old man who, without guards, without apparatus, had come to face an irate mob. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12169" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12234">Then, when they heard that he had come to take the Commissioner to prison, the news had a wondrous effect on them. The fury of the crowd, which would have grown worse, making no concessions, if the Commissioner had been taken violently, was now retreating within the majority, thanks to the bone that Ferrer had tossed them: his promise of satisfaction. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12235" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12312">Once the partisans of peace had caught their second wind, they came to Ferrer’s rescue in a hundred different ways. The ones closest to him rallied the crowd again and again in his support, trying at the same time to get it to pull back and allow the carriage to pass through. The ones farther away, applauding, repeating, and spreading his words (or the ones they thought best), turned the latest passion of the volatile assembly against the angry and obstinate, and shamed them into silence. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12313" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12322">“What man among you won’t say, ‘Long live Ferrer!’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12323" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12333">Don’t you want bread to be cheap? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12334" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12356">Only a scoundrel wouldn’t want a Christian justice: Some of the loudest would even help the Commissioner escape! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12357" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12360">Lock up the Commissioner! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12361" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12362">Long live Ferrer! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12363" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12365">Make way for Ferrer!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12366" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12409">As the number of people voicing these sentiments grew, the boldness of their opponents shrank in proportion, until the peacemakers shifted from preaching to fighting, grabbing hold of and pummeling those who were still trying to tear down the walls, beating them back and seizing the weapons from their grip. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12410" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12431">The original rioters shook with rage, threatening, attempting to fight back, but they had lost their bloody cause. Now the prevailing cry was, “Prison! Justice! Ferrer!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12432" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12493">After a brief skirmish, they were pushed back. The peacemakers took possession of the door, both to defend it against new attackers and to prepare the way for Ferrer to enter. Some of them sent word to the people inside the house (which was now riddled with cracks), that help was on its way, and they should get the Commissioner ready. “To leave immediately…for prison: Have we made ourselves clear?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12494" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12530">“Is he the same Ferrer who helps write the decrees?” Renzo asked a nearby man, remembering the “vidit Ferrer” that Argle-Bargle had shouted into his ear, while showing him the signature at the bottom of the page. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12531" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12537">“That’s right, the Grand Chancellor,” came the reply. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12538" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12542">“He’s a decent man, right?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12543" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12579">“The best there is! He’s the one that brought down the price of bread. The others didn’t want to, and now he’s come to lock up the Commissioner, who didn’t do the right thing.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12580" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12590">Needless to say, Renzo immediately took Ferrer’s side. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12591" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12624">He wanted to go right up to him, which wasn’t easy, but by pushing and elbowing his way through the crowd like a true son of the mountains, he was able to make it to the front row, right next to the carriage. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12625" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12650">At that moment, the carriage was stuck in one of those jams that are inevitable and frequent on such an excursion. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12651" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12693">Old Ferrer looked out of one window and then the other with a humble face, filled with joy and affection, a face that he had always reserved for the times he found himself in the presence of King Philip IV, but was now forced to expend on this occasion. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12694" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12723">He was speaking, but the rumbling and the roar of so many voices, and the “hurrahs” rising around him, left very little for the very few to hear. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12724" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12778">So he added some gestures, placing his fingertips on his lips, then blowing a kiss that his hands, separating immediately, distributed to the right and the left, in appreciation of the benevolence of the people. One second he would reach out and slowly wave his hands from a carriage window to plead for a little space. The next he would lower them politely to request a little silence. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12779" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12804">When he obtained it, those closest to him heard and repeated his words: “Bread. Plenty for all! I have come here to bring justice: a little space, please.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12805" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12849">Then, overcome and almost suffocated by the din of so many voices, the sight of so many faces crowded together, of so many eyes upon him, he withdrew for a moment, puffed out his cheeks, let out a long sigh, and said to himself, “Por mi vida, que de gente!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12850" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12851">And they responded: “Long live Ferrer! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12852" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12854">Don’t be afraid! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12855" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12858">You’re our man. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12859" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12860">Bread! Bread!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12861" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12875">“Yes, bread! bread!” Ferrer replied. “Plenty for all, I promise,” and he placed his hand over his heart. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12876" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12914">“Make way,” he added immediately, “I’m here to take the Commissioner to prison, to give him the just punishment he deserves,” adding, in a whisper, “si es culpable.” Leaning toward the coachman, he said quickly, “Adelante, Pedro, si puedes.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12915" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12959">The coachman also smiled at the crowd with a noble indulgence, as if he, too, were a great personage. And with an ineffable grace, he swung his whip slowly but surely, to the right and to the left, to ask the nearby unfortunates to squeeze together a little and step back a little more. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12960" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12977">“Please, my good sirs,” he said, adding his own voice, “make a little room, just a little. Just enough to let us through.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12978" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12991">The most enthusiastic well-wishers jumped in to help make the room so graciously requested. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_12992" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13055">Those in front of the horses got the people to pull back by saying kind words, laying their hands over their chests, and giving them a gentle and well-aimed shove. “Over there. Get a move on it. Make a little room.” Others were doing the same on both sides of the carriage, so that it could pass through without its wheels crushing feet or putting a dent in someone’s face, which, in addition to hurting people, would have tarnished the aura of Antonio Ferrer. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13056" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13112">Renzo, after a few minutes of fantasizing about that dignified elder, and feeling hemmed in by the crowd, exhausted by the long day, but excited by a sense of urgency, embellished by the hope of removing a man from mortal danger…Renzo, I was saying, set aside all thoughts of leaving. He decided to help Ferrer and not to abandon him until he had achieved his purpose. No sooner said than done. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13113" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13130">He joined the others in opening up a path, and was certainly not among the least active. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13131" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13167">“Go on ahead,” said more than one man to the coachman while stepping back or running ahead to clear the way. “Adelante, presto, con juicio,” added Ferrer. And the carriage moved forward. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13168" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13232">Amid the greetings he was squandering on the masses, Ferrer uttered a special thanks, with a knowing smile, to those he saw laboring for his sake. More than one of those smiles was directed at Renzo, who really did deserve them, and who on that day was doing a better job of serving the Grand Chancellor than the best of his secretaries ever could have. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13233" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13248">And the young man, smitten by that good grace, felt almost as if he and Antonio Ferrer had become friends. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13249" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13265">Once the carriage started to move, it pressed forward, although rather slowly, and not without stopping every few yards. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13266" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13297">The destination was no more than a gunshot away, considering the time it took to get there, the journey seemed long, even to someone who was not in such a holy hurry as Ferrer. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13298" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13326">People were moving to the front and back, to the right and left of the carriage, like waves breaking against a ship sailing through a storm. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13327" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13339">But the pandemonium was even louder, more strident and deafening than a storm. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13340" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13391">Ferrer, looking first one way and then the other, posing and gesturing at the same time, tried to discern what was being said, to match his responses to the occasion. He wanted to entertain a brief conversation with that friendly gathering, but it was hard, maybe the hardest thing he had ever had to do in his many years as Grand Chancellor. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13392" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13425">Here and there, however, a few words in Italian, or even a few sentences, were repeated by a cluster of people as he passed by, and reached his ear like a rocket going off amid the immense crackling of fireworks. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13426" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13468">And he would try to devise a satisfactory response to those calls, adding in the next moment, for good measure, the words he knew to be most acceptable, while also repeating endlessly, “Yes, good sirs, bread, enough for all. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13469" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13479">I’ll conduct him to prison. He will pay for his crime…si es culpable. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13480" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13521">Yes, yes, I’ll issue the order: Lower the price of bread! Asi es…so it shall be, I mean to say: His Highness the King does not want his loyal vassals to go hungry. Ox! Ox! Guardaos: Watch out, kind sirs, you’ll get hurt. Pedro, adelante con juicio. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13522" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13523">Plenty for all, plenty for all. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13524" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13529">Make way, please. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13530" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13531">Bread, bread. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13532" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13535">Off to prison, off to prison. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13536" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13558">What?” He asked this last question to a man who had stuck his head through the window to shout something, either a request or a bit of advice or praise. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13559" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13583">But the man, before he even heard that “what,” was pulled back by someone who saw that he was about to be crushed beneath a wheel. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13584" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13622">Amid all this questioning and answering, both the endless praise and snatches of grumblings from the opposition were immediately muffled, Ferrer finally arrived at the Commissioner’s house, thanks mainly to the actions of those good helpers. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13623" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13648">The others, as I was saying, were already there with the same good intentions, and in the meantime were toiling to make and remake a little space. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13649" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13714">Ferrer implores, urges, threatens. He pushes, pushes harder, gaining ground here and there, with that doubling of willpower and renewal of strength that comes from seeing the coveted goal approach. He had finally managed to split the mob in two, and then to push back the two wings so there was a small empty space between the door and the carriage, which came to a halt at that spot. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13715" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13756">Renzo, part trailblazer, part bodyguard, had arrived at the same time as the carriage and was able to place himself in one of the two front rows of well-wishers, who were acting as both a phalanx to the carriage and an embankment against the two waves of people pressing in. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13757" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13776">By helping to hold back one of the waves with his powerful shoulders, he had also found a good vantage point. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13777" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13791">Ferrer heaved a sigh of relief when he saw the little square of free space and the door still closed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13792" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13840">By “closed” I mean, “not open,” since the hinges had been almost completely torn off the doorframe. Splintered, battered, forced, and misaligned, the door itself had a big crack down the middle through which you could see, on the other side, the crooked, loose bar, barely hanging to the door, holding the door in one piece, if even that. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13841" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13882">One of the good supporters appeared at that crack, hollering at them to open up. Another man quickly opened the carriage door. Old Ferrer stuck out his head, stood up, and grasping the man’s arm with his right hand, stepped down to the running board. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13883" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13914">On both sides, the crowd stood on tiptoe to catch a glimpse: a thousand faces, a thousand beards tilting upward. Their curiosity and attention created a momentary silence. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13915" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13958">Ferrer, from his perch on the running board, took a look around, greeted the multitude with a bow, as if he were on a pulpit, and, placing his left hand over his chest, shouted, “Bread and justice!” Confident, righteous, wrapped in his judicial toga, he set foot on the ground amid an acclamation that rose to the stars. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13959" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13992">In the meantime the people inside had opened, or rather finished opening the door, sliding back the bolt together with the brackets by which it was barely attached, and widening the crack just a little to let the awaited guest in. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_13993" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14018">“Hurry, hurry,” he said, “open wide enough for me to come in. And, you men, be good, hold back the crowd. Don’t let them pile on top of me…for the love of heaven! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14019" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14026">Make a little extra room for when I leave.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14027" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14053">“Hey! Hey! Just a minute,” he said to the people inside, “slow down with that bolt, let me through: Ouch! My toga! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14054" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14062">Watch out for my toga!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14063" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14091">And the toga would indeed have gotten stuck in the door if Ferrer had not deftly pulled in the outer hem, which disappeared like the tail of a snake retreating into its lair. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14092" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14099">Once the door was closed, it was roughly propped up again. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14100" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14134">Outside Ferrer’s self-appointed bodyguards were using their shoulders, arms, and loud voices to keep the space free, praying to God in their hearts that the Grand Chancellor would be quick. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14135" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14162">“Hurry, hurry,” Ferrer said from inside, beneath the portico, to the servants who had gathered around him, panting and crying, “Bless you, Excellency. Oh, Excellency, Excellency!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14163" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14169">“Hurry, hurry,” Ferrer repeated, “where is the blessed man?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14170" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14188">The Commissioner descended the stairs, half-dragged, half-carried by his other servants, looking as white as freshly washed bed linen. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14189" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14231">When he saw his savior, he let out a sigh of relief. His pulse came back. Some life returned to his legs and color to his cheeks. He rushed toward Ferrer as best he could, saying, “I am in the hands of God and of Your Excellency. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14232" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14236">But how can we escape from here? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14237" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14262">We’re surrounded by people who want me dead!” “Venga usted conmigo. Chin up! My carriage is right outside. Hurry, hurry!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14263" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14290">Ferrer took him by the hand and led him to the door, reassuring him the whole way, while at the same time saying to himself, “Acqui està el busilis; Dios nos valga!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14291" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14312">The door opens. Ferrer goes out first. The other man follows, crouching, attached to his rescuer’s toga like a child to its mother’s apron strings. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14313" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14356">The men who had kept the square clear are now holding up their hands and hats, like a screen, a cloud, to shield the Commissioner from the perilous sight of the mob. He is the first to get in the carriage, and huddles in a corner. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14357" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14363">Ferrer gets in next. The door is closed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14364" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14380">The mob struggles to see, to understand, to guess what has happened. And it unleashes a roar of applause and curses. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14381" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14455">The last part of the trip could have been the hardest and most dangerous, but the popular vote had shifted decisively from calling for the Commissioner’s death to allowing him to go to prison. While the carriage was stopped, many who had eased Ferrer’s arrival set about opening and then keeping open a path through the mob, so that the return trip might go a little faster and smoother. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14456" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14476">And as the carriage advanced once again, the two groups assembled on either side fell in together and then mingled in its wake. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14477" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14504">The minute Ferrer was seated, he leaned over to tell the Commissioner to keep his head down, for the love of heaven, but he need not have bothered. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14505" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14522">Ferrer, instead, had to show his face in order to occupy and attract the crowd’s full attention. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14523" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14572">For the whole trip back, as on the trip there, he spoke to the volatile audience, long on length but short on coherence, tossing in the occasional Spanish word that he would quickly whisper in the ear of his cowering fellow passenger. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14573" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14585">“Yes, my good men, bread and justice: to the castle, to prison with him, on my watch. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14586" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14589">Thank you, thank you, grazie tante. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14590" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14596">No, no, he won’t escape. Por ablandarlos. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14597" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14602">It’s only right. We will investigate, we will see. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14603" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14608">And I like you, too, kind sirs. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14609" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14617">A severe punishment. Esto lo digo por su bien. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14618" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14627">A fair price. An honest price, and punishment to the hoarders. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14628" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14633">If you could move to the side, please. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14634" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14642">Yes, yes, I’m an honest man, a friend to the people. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14643" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14654">He will be punished: Yes, it’s true, he’s a crook, a scoundrel. Perdone usted. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14655" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14664">He’s in for a hard time, he is…si es culpable. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14665" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14672">Yes, yes, we’re going to fix the bakers. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14673" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14682">Long live the King, and the good people of Milan, his faithful servants! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14683" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14686">He’ll pay for this, he’ll pay! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14687" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14692">Animo, estamos ya casi fuera.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14693" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14764">They had passed through most of the mob and were already close to being in the clear, when Ferrer, who had begun to give his lungs a rest, saw the Spanish soldiers riding to the rescue, arriving late to the scene. But in the end they were not completely useless, since with the support and the leadership of a few citizens, they helped keep the road open for the final escape. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14765" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14829">When the carriage passed, they stood in formation and saluted the Grand Chancellor, who once again gave a greeting to the right, a greeting to the left. And to the officer who came up to him to offer his own personal salute, he said, accompanying his words with a gesture of his right hand, “beso a usted las manos,” whose true meaning the officer understood. Namely, “Thanks for nothing!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14830" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14840">In reply, he saluted again and shrugged his shoulders. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14841" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14875">This would have been the perfect moment to say, “Cedant arma togae”—“Let arms yield to the toga”—but erudite quotations were the last thing on Ferrer’s mind.[*] His words would have fallen on deaf ears, anyway, since the officer did not understand Latin. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14876" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14898">In passing between these two rows of Spanish soldiers, between those muskets raised so respectfully, Pedro the carriage driver regained his former courage. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14899" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14939">He returned to his senses, remembered who he was and whom he was driving, and shouted, “Ohe! Ohe!” dropping all pretense of formality, before a crowd that had thinned enough to be mistreated. With a crack of his whip, he made his horses race toward the castle. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14940" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14984">“Levantese! Levantese! Estàmos ya fuera,” Ferrer told the Commissioner who, relieved by the dying down of the shouts, the speed of the carriage, and the words he had just heard, turned around, pulled himself together, and sat up in his seat. Feeling somewhat revived, he started to say “Thank you, thank you, thank you” to his rescuer. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_14985" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_15065">The latter, after expressing his condolences for the danger and his joy over the rescue, exclaimed, “Ah!” smacking his hand against his bald forehead, “Que dirà de esto su excelencia, who is already jinxed by that damned Casale Monferrato, which refuses to surrender? Que dirà el Conde Duque, the Count-Duke, who scowls if a leaf makes too much noise? Que dirà el rey nuestro señor, His Royal Majesty, who will, of course, have to be informed of such an uprising? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_15066" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_15073">And will that be the end of it? Dios lo sabe!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n189" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_15074" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_15115">“I want nothing more to do with it,” said the Commissioner, “I quit. I don’t want to hear another word about it. I place my resignation in the hands of Your Excellency, and I will go off to live in a cave, on a mountain, and become a hermit, far from these brutes.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n190" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_15116" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_15135">“Usted will do what is deemed most suitable por el servicio de su magestad,” was the Grand Chancellor’s solemn reply. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap13-n192" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_15155" targetEnd="quarantana/cap13.xml#c13_15183">What became of his proposal our author does not say, for after accompanying the poor man all the way to the castle, he makes no further mention of him. </note>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>