<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>2022</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed: a novel</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
          <date>2022</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Michael Moore</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="english_2022_cap14">
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10020">The rest of the crowd started to disperse, fanning out to the right and left, down this or that street. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10021" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10054">Some went home to look after their own affairs. Some took off for a little breathing room after hours of being hemmed in. Some sought out their friends, to regale them with stories of the day’s big events. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10055" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10086">There were so few people left behind that the Spanish troops were able to advance easily and take up position at the Commissioner’s house, meeting no resistance. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10087" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10149">Nearby some of the dregs of the uprising, if we can call them that, were still loitering about. A gang of troublemakers, unhappy with such a cold, imperfect end to such a great spectacle: Some grumbled, some swore, some conferred to see if anything else could still be done. As if to test the poor door to the Commissioner’s house, which had been roughly propped up again, they kept beating and pounding on it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10150" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10188">Upon the arrival of the troops, they all headed in the opposite direction, some immediately, others more reluctantly, leaving the battlefield open to the soldiers, who reclaimed it and stood guard by the house and the road. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10189" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10254">All the neighboring streets were still dotted with little clusters of people, however. Every time that two or three people would gather, another three, four, or twenty would join them. Here one might break away, but then, a whole cluster would move in unison, like a cloudbank that occasionally breaks apart to travel across the clear blue sky after a storm, leading a person looking up to say: “The weather is not getting any better.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10255" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10260">Imagine the babble of speech. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10261" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10345">Some people loudly described particular incidents they had witnessed. Some related what they themselves had done. Some were relieved that all had ended well, and praised Ferrer, predicting serious troubles ahead for the Commissioner. Some scoffed, saying, “They won’t kill him! Wolves never devour one another.” Some grumbled, irritably, that they’d done it all wrong, that they’d been duped, that they were crazy to have made such a ruckus and then allowed themselves to be fooled. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10346" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10371">In the meantime, the sun had set and everything had taken on the same hue. Many people, exhausted from the day and tired of chatting in the dark, started to head home. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10372" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10433">Our young man, Renzo, after helping the carriage pass for as long as help was needed, and walking behind it, between the rows of soldiers, as if in triumph, was relieved to see it moving freely and out of danger. He moved among the crowd for a bit and then broke away, at the first street corner, so that he, too, could breathe more freely. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10434" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10484">After a few steps in the clear, still overwhelmed by so many feelings and images jumbled together, he was overcome by the great need to eat and to rest. He turned his gaze upward, from one side of the street to the other, looking for a tavern sign, since it was too late to go back to the Capuchin monastery. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10485" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10511">Walking with his head in the clouds, he almost bumped into a cluster of people. He stopped for a second and overheard them speculating on and planning actions for the next day. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10512" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10538">As he listened, he could not resist putting in his own two cents, feeling he had every right after contributing so much to that afternoon. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10539" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10582">Everything he’d seen that day had persuaded him that, to get things done, all you had to do was win the sympathies of the passersby. “Good sirs,” he shouted, by way of an introduction, “may I also offer my modest opinion? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10583" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10640">Bakeries aren’t the only places cheating us. If there’s one thing we’ve learned today, it’s that when we raise our voices, we get justice. We have to keep going until every wrong has been made right, and the world is a little more humane. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10641" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10704">Is it not true, good sirs, that a handful of tyrants have twisted the ‘Thou shalt nots’ of the Commandments into ‘Thou shall’? The same men harass the meek—who pay them no mind—and do all kinds of bad things to them, but they’re always in the right? Indeed, when they’ve done something even worse than usual, they walk with their heads held higher, as if we should thank them for it! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10705" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10714">I’m sure that Milan has its share of them.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10715" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10719">“Unfortunately,” chimed in one voice. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10720" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10732">“Like I was saying,” continued Renzo, “where I come from, we’ve all heard the same stories. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10733" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10739">And the facts speak for themselves. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10740" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10772">Let’s say, for instance, that one of those tyrants lives part of the time in the country, and part in Milan. Now, if he’s a devil in one place, then he can’t be an angel in the other, seems to me. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10773" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10790">So tell me, good sirs, have you ever seen one of these crooks with his face behind bars? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10791" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10844">What’s worse (and this I know for a fact) is that to punish them, we’ve got decrees, good ones—signed, sealed, and printed. Not just words slapped on paper, either. Really well-written decrees! You couldn’t hope for better! They name the crimes in black and white, just the way they happen. And each crime has its own punishment. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10845" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10857">And they say: ‘These are for you, no matter who you are, country and common folk and I don’t know who else.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10858" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10893">But try asking the lawyers—that bunch of scribes and Pharisees!—to help you get justice with these decrees.[*] They’ll no sooner listen to you than the Pope will. It’s enough to make an honest man’s head spin. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10894" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10920">You can tell as clear as day that the King and the rulers want the bad guys to be punished, but nothing gets done because there’s a league of powerful men. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10921" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10966">Well, we need to break it up. Tomorrow morning we need to go to Ferrer: now there’s an upright man for you, someone you can talk to! Today you could see how happy he was to be with the people, how he was trying to listen to everyone, and how graciously he answered. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_10967" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11093">We have to go to Ferrer and tell him what’s going on. And boy, have I got some stories to tell. Things I’ve seen with my own two eyes: a decree, with the royal seal on top, signed by three bigwigs, and each one had his name printed at the bottom, and one of those names was Ferrer’s, I saw it with my own two eyes. Well, this decree was tailor-made for my case, and when I went to a lawyer, and asked him to help me get justice, like those three gentlemen intended—including Ferrer—this lawyer, the very man who showed me the decree, can you believe it? He acted like I was crazy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11094" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11129">And I’m sure when Ferrer, kind nice old man, hears the stuff they pulled on me, since he can’t know everything that’s going on, especially outside the city, well, he’ll want to set things straight, and he’ll fix it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11130" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11155">And the other guys, too: If they make the decrees, they must want to see them obeyed. Since to ignore them is also an insult, their name on an epitaph. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11156" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11177">And if the bullies refuse to fall in line, and keep acting crazy, we’ll help like we did today. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11178" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11201">I’m not saying that Ferrer himself has to go around in his carriage to round up all the crooks, bullies, and tyrants: He’d need Noah’s ark to do that! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11202" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11276">What he needs to do is order the guys in charge—and not just in Milan but everywhere—to do what the decrees say. And to bring to justice everyone who’s committed those crimes. When it says prison, send them to prison. When it says galleys, send them to the galleys. And tell the mayors to do their job! If they don’t, send them packing and appoint someone better. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11277" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11292">Like I say, we’ll be there to lend a hand. And order the lawyers to listen to the poor and to defend what’s right. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11293" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11296">Do you agree, good sirs?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11297" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11328">Renzo’s words were so heartfelt that, from the start, much of the crowd stopped talking, turned to him, and listened. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11329" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11346">His audience responded with a vague smattering of applause, a few shouts of, “Bravo, you’re right! Sad but true!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11347" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11351">There were also a few critics, however. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11352" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11366">“Yeah, right,” said one, “let’s listen to the hill people. They all think they’re lawyers!” Then he left. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11367" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11399">Another muttered, “Now every lowlife is going to speak his mind, and with everyone putting in their own two cents, the price of bread won’t come down, and that’s what we’re fighting for.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11400" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11415">But Renzo only heard the compliments. Some shook one hand. Some shook the other. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11416" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11437">“See you tomorrow!” “Where?” “Piazza Duomo.” “Very good. Very good.” “We’re going to do something. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11438" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11441">We’re going to do something.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11442" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11462">“Which of you kind sirs can show me the way to a tavern where a poor boy can get a bite to eat and a bed to sleep in?” asked Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11463" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11484">“At your service, young man,” said one man who had been listening carefully to his sermon, and hadn’t uttered a word. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11485" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11503">“I’ve got the very place for you. A tavern where I know the owner, a friend and an honest man. I’ll put in a good word for you.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11504" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11507">“Nearby?” asked Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11508" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11511">“Not far,” replied the man. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11512" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11531">The gathering broke up and Renzo, after shaking the hands of several strangers, headed off with this particular stranger, thanking him for his kindness. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11532" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11546">“Speak nothing of it,” the man replied, “one hand washes the other, and together they wash your face. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11547" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11554">Aren’t we supposed to help our neighbor?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11555" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11568">As they walked, he asked Renzo, as if to pass the time, first one, then another question. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11569" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11584">“Not to stick my nose into your business, but you look very tired. Where are you coming from?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11585" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11591">“I’m coming,” replied Renzo, “all the way from Lecco.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11592" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11594">“All the way from Lecco? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11595" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11597">You’re from Lecco?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11598" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11602">“Yes, from Lecco…from that area, I mean.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11603" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11617">“Poor boy! From what you were saying earlier, it sounds like they really put you through the mill.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11618" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11661">“Ah, my good man, I had to watch my words back there, and not talk about my business in public. But…enough. One day the truth will come out, and then…Ah, here I see an innkeeper’s sign, and for the life of me, I can’t take another step.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11662" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11677">“No, no, not here. The place I have in mind isn’t much farther,” said his guide, “you won’t like it here.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11678" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11714">“I don’t care,” replied the young man, “I’m not a little lord accustomed to sleeping on cotton. All I need is some food in my belly and a straw pallet to lie on. The sooner the better. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11715" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11716">My prayers are answered!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11717" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11729">With that he entered through a dilapidated doorway over which a sign hung depicting the full moon. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11730" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11744">“All right, if you insist,” said the stranger, and he followed him in. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11745" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11752">“No need to trouble yourself anymore,” said Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11753" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11765">“But,” he added, “if you’d like to join me for a glass, it’d be my pleasure.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11766" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11799">“I accept your invitation,” the man answered. Since he was familiar with the establishment, he went in ahead of Renzo, passing through a small courtyard. He walked up to the door that led to the kitchen, lifted the latch, opened the door, and entered with his companion. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11800" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11817">A dim light shone from two hand lanterns hanging on poles attached to the ceiling beams. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11818" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11866">Several men were seated, though not idly, on benches to either side of a long narrow table that occupied almost one whole side of the room. Napkins and plates alternated with playing cards, faceup and facedown, dice tossed and picked up, bottles and glasses. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11867" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11917">A brisk trade was going on in coins of various denominations: berlinghe, reals, and parpagliole. If those coins could talk, they probably would have said, “This morning we were in the baker’s till, or in the pocket of a bystander so intent on watching the uprising that he forgot to mind his personal affairs.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11918" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11921">The noise was deafening. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11922" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11980">A scullery boy raced back and forth, waiting on the combined dining and gambling table. The innkeeper was sitting on a small bench by the hood of the fireplace, pretending to busy himself with the tongs, making and erasing figures in the ashes, while actually listening to everything going on around him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11981" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11990">At the clinking of the latch he stood up and went to meet the new arrivals. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_11991" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12080">Seeing the guide, he said to himself, “Damn him! Always showing up when he’s least wanted!” After a quick glance at Renzo, he said, to himself, “I don’t know you, but you’re either hare or hound if you’re in the company of a hunter like him. Let me hear a couple of words and I’ll know.” None of these thoughts were reflected in the innkeeper’s face, which was as still as a portrait: round and shiny with a thick red beard and two piercing blue eyes. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12081" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12088">“What might I get for you gentlemen?” he said aloud. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12089" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12103">“First, a good bottle of honest wine,” said Renzo, “and then a bite to eat.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12104" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12141">At that, he plopped down on a bench, near the head of the table, and let out a sonorous, “Ah!” as if to say, “After being on my feet all day, there’s nothing better than a nice bench.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12142" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12168">But he was immediately reminded of the bench and the table where he had sat down with Lucia and Agnese for the last time, and he sighed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12169" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12183">He shook his head as if to expel the thought, and saw the host arriving with the wine. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12184" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12193">His companion sat down across from him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12194" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12213">Renzo immediately poured him a glass, saying, “Just to wet your lips,” and, after filling the other glass, downed it in a single gulp. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12214" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12221">“What’ve you got to eat?” he asked the host. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12222" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12228">“I’ve got stew. Would you like some?” the man answered. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12229" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12232">“Good, yes, some stew.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12233" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12249">“Coming right up,” said the host to Renzo. To the boy he barked, “Take care of this stranger,” and he headed back to the fireplace. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12250" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12263">“But,” he stopped to say, “I’m afraid I don’t have any bread today.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12264" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12277">“Bread?” said Renzo in a loud voice, laughing. “Providence has taken care of that!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12278" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12303">He took out the third and last loaf of the bread he had found at the foot of the San Dionigi cross, held it up high, and shouted, “Here is the bread of Providence!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12304" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12321">Many heads turned at the sound of his exclamation. Seeing that trophy held aloft, one man shouted, “Hurrah for cheap bread!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12322" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12329">“Cheap?” said Renzo. “No, bread by the grace and love of God.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12330" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12331">“Better yet!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12332" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12343">“But,” Renzo added immediately, “I would not want you gentlemen to misunderstand. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12344" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12352">It’s not that I filched it, as they say. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12353" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12367">I found it on the ground. And if I could find its owner, I’d gladly pay him for it.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12368" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12389">“Bravo! Bravo!” his companions shouted, snickering even louder. The thought that he might be telling the truth did not occur to a single man. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12390" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12420">“You think I’m joking, but I’m not,” said Renzo to his guide. Turning the bread over in his hand, he added, “Look at how they treated it. Now it looks like flatbread! But there were so many people. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12421" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12435">If someone with tender bones had leaned down to grab it, he’d have been crushed.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12436" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12463">After biting off three or four mouthfuls, he chased it down with a second glass of wine, adding, “This bread won’t go down by itself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12464" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12471">My throat has never been so dry. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12472" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12476">All that shouting!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12477" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12493">“Prepare a good bed for this young man,” the guide said, “because he’d like to spend the night.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12494" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12503">Approaching his table, the host asked Renzo, “You want to sleep here?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12504" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12525">“I sure do,” replied Renzo, “any bed will do, as long as the sheets are freshly washed. I may be a poor boy, but I’m used to cleanliness.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12526" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12559">“Oh, that reminds me,” said the innkeeper. He went to the counter, in a corner of the kitchen, and came back with an inkpot and a blank sheet of paper in one hand and a pen in the other. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12560" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12589">“What’s this for?” exclaimed Renzo, swallowing a spoonful of the stew that the boy had set in front of him. Then, smiling in surprise, he added, “Is this what you call a clean sheet?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12590" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12637">The host, without answering, set the inkpot and the paper on the table. He propped his left arm and right elbow against the same table, and staring at Renzo with the pen in the air, he asked, “If you don’t mind, could I have your first name, last name, and place of birth?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12638" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12646">“What?” cried Renzo. “What’s all this got to do with a bed?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12647" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12703">“I’m doing my duty,” said the innkeeper, looking the guide right in the face. “We are required to account for everyone who comes to us for lodgings: first name, last name, place of birth, nature of their business here, whether or not they are bearing arms, length of stay: That’s what the decree says.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12704" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12726">Before answering, Renzo emptied another glass. It was his third, and from this point on I’m afraid we’ll lose count. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12727" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12733">Then he said, “Ah, of course, the decree! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12734" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12751">And I just so happen to be a doctor of law, so I know what they make of the decrees.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12752" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12789">“I’m telling you the truth,” said the host, still staring at Renzo’s mute companion. Going back to the counter, he removed from the drawer a large sheet of paper, an original printed copy of the decree, and came over to unfold it before Renzo’s eyes. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12790" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12823">“Ah, now I see,” the boy exclaimed, raising his refreshed glass and emptying it in one gulp. Extending his other hand, he pointed a finger at the decree. “Here’s the page from your missal. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12824" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12827">Oh joy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12828" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12842">I recognize that coat of arms. I know the meaning of that infidel’s face.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12843" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12879">(On the top of the decrees they would print the Governor’s coat of arms. Don Gonzalo Fernández de Córdoba’s bore a prominent figure of a Moorish king with a chain around his neck.) “What that face means is, ‘Command if you can; obey if you want.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12880" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12941">Once this face has sentenced to the galleys Don…never mind, I know who he is. I tell you what. When another sheet from the same missal allows an honest young man to marry an honest young woman who is happy to marry him, then I’ll tell my name to that face, and throw in a kiss, too. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12942" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12952">I might have good reasons for not giving my name. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_12953" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13000">And this scoundrel probably has a bunch of other scoundrels working for him, because if he were alone…” He ended his sentence with a gesture. “If a scoundrel wanted to know where I was, to play some dirty trick on me, I wonder whether that face would do anything to protect me. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13005">And now I’m supposed to tell you my business? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13006" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13009">That’s new. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13010" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13032">Let’s suppose I came to Milan to confess. In that case I’m going to confess to a Capuchin friar, not to an innkeeper.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13033" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13049">The man fell silent and continued to stare at the guide, whose face remained expressionless. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13050" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13071">Renzo, I am sad to report, downed yet another glass and kept on talking. “I’ll give you a good reason, my dear sir, that you can understand. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13072" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13092">If the decrees that say the right things, to help good Christians, don’t count, then the ones that say bad things shouldn’t count, either. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13093" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13107">Now will you get this rubbish out of my face and bring me another bottle of wine, since this one is empty?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13108" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13122">As he spoke, he tapped on it with his knuckles and added, “Can you hear that, sir? Can you hear that hollow sound?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13123" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13148">Renzo had once again managed to gradually attract the attention of the people around him, and once again his audience applauded him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13149" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13162">“What am I supposed to do?” asked the innkeeper, looking at the stranger, who was no stranger to him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13163" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13183">“Come on, come on,” shouted many of the tavern guests, “the boy is right. It’s all a nuisance, a trick, a pain! Every day a new law.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13184" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13210">In the midst of these cries, the stranger gave the innkeeper a disapproving look, for questioning him too directly, and remarked, “Leave him be. Don’t make a scene.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13211" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13249">“I did my duty,” said the innkeeper aloud. And then, to himself, “Now I’ve got my back against the wall,” and he took the paper, the pen, the ink, the decree, and the empty bottle, and gave them to the scullery boy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13250" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13290">“Bring me one more of the same,” said Renzo, “it’s a good honest wine. And we’ll down it just like we did the last one, without demanding its first and last name, place of birth, reason for coming here, and how long it intends to stay.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13291" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13326">“More of the same,” said the innkeeper to the boy, and went back to sit by the fireplace. “He’s a hare, all right,” he thought, sketching in the ashes again, “and look whose hands he’s fallen into. What a fool! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13327" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13347">If you want to drown yourself, go right ahead. But don’t go sticking me in the middle. The Luna Piena’s innkeeper wants no part of your madness!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13348" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13361">Renzo thanked the guide and all the others who had taken his side. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13362" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13377">“Good job, my friends!” he said. “Now I can really see that honest men help each other out.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13378" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13413">Then, extending his right hand over the table, and assuming the posture of a preacher once more, “How wonderful,” he exclaimed, “that all those who rule the world want to stick paper, pen, and inkpot into everything! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13414" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13418">Always with a pen in the air! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13419" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13427">What an obsession these great men have for using a pen!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13428" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13444">“My good friend from the country,” laughed one of the gamblers, who was winning, “do you want to know why?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13445" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13449">“Tell me,” answered Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13450" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13477">“I will,” the man said. “The ruling class eats a lot of goose, and ends up with so many quills, they’ve got to do something with them!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13478" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13488">Everyone burst out laughing, except for his opponent, who was losing. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13489" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13495">“Aha,” said Renzo, “a poet. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13496" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13506">So we’ve got poets here, too. Nowadays they’re born everywhere. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13507" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13523">I’ve got a poetic vein myself, and sometimes I come up with some very curious verses…but only when things are going well.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13524" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13587">To understand poor Renzo’s babbling, you need to know that among the common people of Milan, and even more among those in the countryside, poet does not mean, as all good men would have it, a sacred talent, a dweller of Mount Parnassus, a disciple of the Muses. It means a bizarre and somewhat eccentric soul whose speech and behavior are clever and odd, rather than sensible. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13588" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13611">Which shows you how intrepid common bunglers are at twisting words around to make them say the exact opposite of what they mean! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13612" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13624">For, I ask you, what’s the connection between being a poet and being eccentric? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13625" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13683">“I’ll tell you the real reason,” Renzo continued, “it’s because they hold the pen. So if they misspeak, the words are conveniently swept away by the wind. But if a poor kid says something, they pay close attention and skewer his words from the air with that pen and nail them to a sheet of paper, to use against him at the right time and place. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13684" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13751">They’ve got another trick, too. When they want to trick a poor kid who never went to school but who still has a good…what I’m trying to say is…” he trailed off, but he tapped, almost beat his index finger against his forehead to help them understand. “And if they realize that you’re catching on to them, in a heartbeat, they toss in a few words of Latin, to distract and confuse. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13752" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13757">Enough! This practice has to stop! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13758" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13797">Today, thank goodness, everything was done in the language of the people, and without pen, paper, or inkpot. And tomorrow, if people know how to behave, we’ll do even better, without harming a hair on anyone’s head. And in the name of justice.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13798" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13836">Meanwhile some of his listeners had gone back to gambling, others to eating, and many more to shouting. Some people left, others arrived, and the innkeeper kept an eye on everyone. All of which has nothing to do with our story. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13837" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13869">The mysterious guide couldn’t wait to slip away. He did not seem to have any business there, but he did not want to leave before chatting a little more with Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13870" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13900">He turned to him and started talking about bread again. After repeating some of the sentences that had been bantered about the room, he announced an idea of his own. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13901" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13915">“Well, if I were in charge,” he said, “I’d find a way to make things work better.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13916" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13939">“What would you do?” asked Renzo, looking at him with two eyes that were glassier than they should be, and twisting his mouth slightly, in an effort to pay closer attention. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13940" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13959">“What would I do?” he said. “I’d make sure there was bread for everyone. Enough for the poor and enough for the rich.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13960" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13965">“Ah, that’s the spirit,” said Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13966" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13968">“Here’s what I’d do. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13969" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13976">Set an honest price so that everyone can manage. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_13977" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14011">And then, distribute bread according to the number of mouths to feed: because there are greedy pigs, who want everything for themselves, and grab as much as their hands can carry. After which there’s not enough bread for the poor. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14012" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14015">So we need to divvy up the bread. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14016" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14019">How, you ask? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14020" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14039">Here’s how: Give a bakery voucher to each family, based on the number of mouths to feed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14040" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14077">To me, for example, they’d give a voucher that says, ‘Ambrogio Fusella, profession swordsmith, with wife and four children, all old enough to eat bread (pay attention now): You get X amount of bread for X amount of money.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14078" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14087">But fair, always based on the number of mouths to feed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14088" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14098">Take you, for example, they should make out a voucher to…what did you say your name was?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14099" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14136">“Lorenzo Tramaglino,” said the young man who, enthralled by the proposal, didn’t notice that it was all based on paper, pen, and ink, and that, for it to work, the first step would be to write down people’s names. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14137" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14145">“Very good,” said the stranger, “do you have a wife and children?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14146" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14161">“I ought to…no children…too soon…but my wife…if things had gone the way they’re supposed to…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14162" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14164">“You’re unmarried. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14165" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14172">So you’d have to be patient, only a small ration for you.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14173" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14184">“As it should be, but soon, as I hope…and with the help of God…Enough! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14185" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14189">And if I had a wife, too?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14190" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14199">“Then the voucher would be changed and the ration increased. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14200" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14211">Like I said, always on the basis of the number of mouths to feed,” said the stranger, standing up. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14212" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14233">“That’s what I like to hear!” shouted Renzo, and he went on, raising his voice and pounding his fists on the table. “So why don’t they make a law like that?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14234" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14238">“Don’t ask me. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14239" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14260">For now it’s good night and time for me to leave, since I think my wife and children have been waiting for me long enough.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14261" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14292">“One more drop, just another drop,” cried Renzo, quickly filling the man’s glass. Standing up immediately and grabbing him by the hem of his doublet, he gave a strong tug to make him sit down again. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14293" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14299">“One more drop, otherwise I’ll be offended.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14300" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14324">But his friend freed himself with a yank, and, leaving Renzo in his knot of pleas and reproaches, he repeated, “Good night,” and was out the door. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14325" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14340">Renzo continued to harangue him, but the man was already on the street. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14341" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14405">Renzo sank back down on the bench, stared at the glass that he’d filled, and seeing the boy pass by, gestured at him to come over, as if he had some business to discuss. Then he pointed to his glass, and in a slow, solemn voice, articulating his words in a very particular way, said, “See, I poured wine for that good man. Did you see? Right to the brim, like a friend, but he didn’t want it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14406" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14412">Sometimes people misunderstand a gesture like that. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n189" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14413" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14424">It’s not my fault. I did it out of the goodness of my heart. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n190" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14425" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14436">But now that I have, we can’t let it go to waste.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n191" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14437" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14446">At that, he took the glass and emptied it in one gulp. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n192" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14447" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14452">“I understand,” said the boy, walking away. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n193" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14453" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14462">“Ah! So you understand, too,” Renzo went on. “Then it’s true. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n194" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14463" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14467">When what’s right is right…!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n195" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14468" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14501">Here it will take all my love of the truth to make me faithfully continue a tale that does so little credit to such an important character: the hero of our story, you could almost say. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n196" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14502" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14542">But for the same love of impartiality, again, I should point out that this was the first time anything like this had happened to Renzo: And it was precisely his naïveté that made this first encounter with drunkenness so fatal. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n197" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14543" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14597">The first few glasses had gone straight to his head. He had tossed them back, one after the other—so unlike him—in part because he was so parched, in part because of a certain altered state, which allowed him to do nothing in moderation. For a more experienced drinker, this would have done little more than slake his thirst. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n198" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14598" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14614">Our anonymous source made an observation in this regard that I will repeat, for what it’s worth. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n199" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14615" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14661">One of the advantages of temperate and honest habits, he says, is that the more inveterate and rooted they are in a man, the more easily, the more immediately he suffers their loss the minute he veers away from them. So he remembers it for a long time after, and even a blunder teaches him a lesson. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n200" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14662" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14701">Whatever the case may be, when those first fumes rose to Renzo’s head, wine and words continued to flow, one down and the others up, without rhyme or reason. At the point where we left him, he was managing as best he could. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n201" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14702" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14743">He had a strong urge to speak, and there was no shortage of listeners, or at least of men present whom he could treat as listeners. For a while his words flowed unbidden, and allowed themselves to fall into some kind of order. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n202" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14744" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14759">Little by little, however, finishing sentences started to become monstrously difficult. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n203" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14760" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14792">The thought that appeared so vividly and resolutely in his mind would suddenly fog up and evaporate. And his words, after keeping him waiting for a bit, would turn out to be not quite right. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n204" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14793" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14813">Amid these tribulations, by one of those false instincts that can ruin a man, he reached for that damned bottle. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n205" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14814" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14833">Will someone with a lick of sense tell me what good a bottle does in such a circumstance? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n206" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14834" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14871">I am relating only some of the many words he spouted on that fateful evening. The many more that I am leaving out would be too unbecoming, for not only did they make no sense, they did not even try to, which is a prerequisite for a printed book. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n207" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14872" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14905">“Innkeeper? Mr. Innkeeper?” he started again, following him with his eye around the table or by the hood of the fireplace, sometimes staring at him when he wasn’t there, and always talking amid the uproar of the brigade. “What kind of an innkeeper are you? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n208" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14906" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14916">I can’t get over it…that stuff about my first name, last name, and trade. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n209" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14917" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14921">Asking a boy like me…! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n210" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14922" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14926">That wasn’t right. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n211" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14927" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14939">Where’s the satisfaction, the point, the pleasure…in writing up a poor kid on your papers? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n212" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14940" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14942">Am I right, men? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n213" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14943" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14951">Innkeepers should always take the side of poor boys…Listen, listen, sir. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n214" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14952" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14964">I want to make a comparison…because…They’re laughing, hey? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n215" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14965" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14976">Yes, I’m a little tipsy…but it doesn’t mean I’m wrong. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n216" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14977" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14987">Tell me, who do you get your business from? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n217" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14988" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14994">From poor boys, right? Am I right? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n218" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_14995" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15010">You tell me whether the men with the decrees ever come by here for a glass.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n219" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15011" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15020">“They only drink water,” said a man sitting near Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n220" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15021" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15034">“They want to keep their wits about them,” added another, “so they can tell their lies with a straight face.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n221" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15035" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15044">“Ah!” cried Renzo, “The poet has spoken. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n222" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15045" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15052">Then you understand my reasons, too. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n223" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15053" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15077">So answer me this, sir. Has Ferrer, who’s the best of the bunch, ever come here to lift a glass and to spread the wealth? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n224" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15078" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15091">And that murderous dog, Don…I’d better shut up now, because I’ve got too much on my mind. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n225" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15092" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15107">Ferrer and Padre Crrrrrr…now those are two good men, and there aren’t too many like them around. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n226" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15108" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15119">The old are worse than the young, and the young…even worse than the old! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n227" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15120" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15135">But I’m happy there was no bloodshed. That kind of barbarity is best left in the hands of the executioner. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n228" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15136" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15139">Bread? Oh, yes. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n229" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15140" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15149">I got pushed around…but I gave as good as I got. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n230" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15150" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15152">Make way! Times of plenty! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n231" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15153" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15164">Hurrah!…Yet, even Ferrer…a few little words in Latin…siés baraòs trapolorum…Damn bad habit!…Hurrah! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n232" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15165" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15191">Justice! Bread! Now those are words to live by!…Back home I could have used some honest men…when that damned dong, dong, dong started up, and then again, dong, dong, dong. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n233" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15192" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15197">Otherwise he wouldn’t have gotten away. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n234" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15198" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15207">And we’d have kept the priest there…I know who’s to blame!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n235" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15208" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15256">At these words he lowered his head and stayed that way for a while, as if lost in thought. Then he heaved a sigh, and looked up, with two damp, shiny eyes, and such a raw, maudlin look of distress that it’s a good thing the object of his affection could not see him in that moment. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n236" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15257" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15301">But the ruffians who were already making fun of Renzo’s passionate and muddled eloquence were even more amused by his air of contrition. The men sitting closest to him said to the others, “Look,” and everyone turned his way, making him the laughingstock of the room. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n237" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15302" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15337">Not that everyone else was in their right mind, or that their minds had ever been right in the first place, but the truth is that no one was more out of his mind than poor Renzo. Especially since he was a peasant. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n238" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15338" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15353">They all started, first one and then the other, to tease him with vulgar or silly questions. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n239" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15354" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15387">One minute Renzo seemed to take it badly, the next minute as a joke, and then, ignoring all those other voices, he would speak about something else. He would respond, then he would ask questions, always jumping around, always off topic. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap14-n240" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15388" targetEnd="quarantana/cap14.xml#c14_15453">Luckily, in the midst of his raving, he maintained an instinctive caution to avoid naming names, so that what must have been foremost on his mind did not slip out. For it would have been truly regrettable if her name, for which I, too, feel a little affection and respect, had been bandied about on those unsavory tongues like a plaything. </note>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>