<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>2022</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed: a novel</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
          <date>2022</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Michael Moore</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="english_2022_cap19">
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10047">Anyone who spotted a weed in a neglected field—a nice wild sorrel, say—and wanted to know whether it had come from a seed that had sprouted in the field, was blown in by the wind, or had been dropped there by a bird, would never, no matter how long they pondered it, reach a conclusion. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10048" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10082">Nor can we say whether it was from the natural depths of his brain or from Attilio’s insinuations that the Count Uncle decided to make use of the Father Provincial to untie Rodrigo’s tangled knot. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10083" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10130">Attilio had not chosen his words casually, and while he might have worried that such a bold suggestion would sting his uncle’s overweening but brittle pride, he still wanted to dangle it before him and thus set him on the path he hoped he would take. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10131" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10160">Yet that solution was so suited to his uncle’s temperament, so prescribed by the circumstances, that even without being prodded, you can bet he would have found it by himself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10161" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10193">Now that a war of sorts had been declared, the Count could not allow someone bearing his name, his own nephew, to wind up on the losing end, which could damage his reputation as a powerful man. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10194" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10223">The revenge that his nephew might seek on his own would be a cure worse than the disease, and spark greater problems. Rodrigo had to be stopped by every means possible, without a minute to spare. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10224" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10252">If he were ordered by the Count to leave his village immediately, he might refuse. Even if he did leave, it would be a retreat, the aristocracy surrendering the field to the clergy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10253" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10306">Rules, laws, and other such bogeymen were useless against such an adversary. The regular and lay clergy were immune from secular jurisdiction—as were their places of residence—as even someone who has read no other story than this one should know. Otherwise the friar would be easy game. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10307" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10338">The best tactic against such an adversary was to get him transferred, and the means by which this could be accomplished was through the Father Provincial, who had the power to decide whether the friar should be moved or kept in place. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10339" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10366">Now, the Father Provincial and the Count Uncle were old acquaintances. They saw each other rarely, but always with elaborate displays of friendship and extravagant offers of favors. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10367" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10436">Sometimes it is easier to deal with a leader of many individuals than a single individual, who sees only his own cause, feels only his own passion, and defends only his own concerns. A leader can see at a glance a hundred connections, a hundred consequences, a hundred interests, a hundred things to shun, and a hundred things to preserve. Which also means that he can be approached in a hundred different ways. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10437" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10582">After weighing the matter carefully, the Count invited the Father Provincial to dinner, along with other exquisitely selected guests: the most noble of his kinsmen, men of ancient noble lineage, who by their bearing, innate confidence, and aristocratic nonchalance—speaking of great things in familiar terms—managed, effortlessly, to constantly reinforce and renew an aura of superiority and power. There were also a few lackeys, bound to the family by hereditary employment, and to the Count by a lifetime of servitude. They said yes to everything, starting with the soup course. They said yes with their mouths, with their eyes, with their ears, and with their whole heads, whole bodies, and whole souls. By the time the fruit came round they were little more than men who no longer remembered how to say no. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10583" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10597">At the table, the host quickly steered the conversation to his favorite subject. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10598" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10610">Many roads lead to Rome, but for the Count they all led to Madrid. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10611" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10660">He spoke of the court, of the Count-Duke, of the ministers, the family of the Governor, the bullfights that he could describe in detail since he had enjoyed them from a privileged perch. He spoke of El Escorial, which he could describe in the most minute detail, since a protégé of the Count-Duke, a creado, had taken him on a tour of every nook and cranny. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10661" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10709">For a while the assembled guests, a captive audience, sat listening to him and him alone. Then they split off into private conversations, while the host continued to describe more of those fine things, as if in confidence, to the Father Provincial, who was seated next to him and allowed him to go on, and on, and on. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10710" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10749">But at a certain point, the priest steered the conversation away from Madrid, from one court to another, and from one dignitary to another, in the direction of Cardinal Barberini, a Capuchin friar, brother to none other than the current Pope, Urban VIII. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10750" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10779">At that point the Count had to allow someone else to speak for a while, and sat there listening, forced to remember that the world did not consist solely of people who did his bidding. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10780" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10795">When everyone got up from the table, he asked the Father Provincial to join him in the next room. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10796" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10806">Two authorities, two gray-haired men, two seasoned veterans, stood face-to-face. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10807" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10851">The Magnificent Lord invited the Most Reverend Father to have a seat, and then sat down himself. He began: “Considering the friendship between us, I thought I might have a word with Your Reverence about a matter of common concern, to be settled between the two of us, without resorting to other means. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10852" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10874">To put it plainly, with my heart in my hand, I’ll tell you what this is about. And in a nutshell, I’m sure you’ll agree. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10875" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10887">Tell me. At your order’s monastery in Pescarenico, do you know of a certain Padre Cristoforo from ***?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10888" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10893">The Provincial indicated that he did. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10894" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10934">“Tell me, Your Reverence, in all frankness, as a friend…this subject…this padre…I don’t know him personally, although I do know quite a few Capuchins: good men, zealous, prudent, humble. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10935" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10987">I’ve been a friend to the order since I was a boy…But in every big family…there is always one individual, one hothead…and this Padre Cristoforo, I know from certain information I have gathered that he’s a man…who’s always itching for a fight…who doesn’t exhibit all the prudence, all the deference…I’d be willing to bet he’s given you more than one headache.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_10988" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11071">“Ah,” said the Provincial to himself, “he wants a favor. My fault: I knew that blessed Cristoforo was a subject who had to be transferred from pulpit to pulpit, and not left for months in the same place, especially in a country monastery.” “Oh,” he said out loud, “I’m truly sorry to hear that Your Magnificence should have such an impression of Padre Cristoforo. To my knowledge, he’s a priest who’s…exemplary inside the monastery, and held in high regard outside of it, as well.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11072" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11076">“I understand perfectly. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11077" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11113">Your Reverence has to…But, but, as a sincere friend, I wish to advise you of an important matter. And even if you have already been informed, I can, out of a sense of duty, make you aware of potential…consequences. That’s all I’ll say for now. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11114" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11155">This Padre Cristoforo, we know that he was protecting a man from those parts, a man…Your Reverence will have heard him mentioned. The man who escaped from the hands of justice—what a scandal!—on that awful Saint Martin’s Day, after having done things…things…I am speaking of Lorenzo Tramaglino!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11156" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11188">“Aha,” thought the Provincial. Then he replied, “This circumstance comes as news to me. But Your Magnificence is well aware that it is our mission to seek out wayward souls, and set them on the path of…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11189" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11227">“Of course, but only certain wayward souls…These are thorny questions, delicate matters…” At this, rather than puffing up his cheeks and exhaling, he pursed his lips and took in as much air as he usually let out. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11228" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11258">Picking up where he left off, he added, “I thought I should apprise you of this circumstance, because if Your Reverence were ever to…Well, formal complaints might be lodged with Rome…it has nothing to do with me…but from Rome you might get…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11259" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11304">“I am grateful to Your Magnificence for this notification. But I am certain that, if inquiries are made into this allegation, it will be found that Padre Cristoforo has had no dealings with the man you’ve mentioned, other than to set him on the path of righteousness. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11305" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11309">Padre Cristoforo is someone I know.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11310" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11327">“Then you know better than I what kind of a man he was before taking his vows, the mischief he got into in his youth.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11328" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11353">“The glory of the habit, my dear Count, is that even a man with some notoriety in the secular life becomes another person once he wears it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11354" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11361">And ever since Padre Cristoforo donned the habit…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11362" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11381">“I’d like to believe you, I mean it, I’d really like to believe you. But sometimes, as the proverb says…the habit does not make the monk.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11382" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11415">That isn’t quite what the proverb says, but in his haste the Count had confused it with another that came to the tip of his tongue: Vulpem pilum mutare, non mores—the fox sheds its fur, not its habits. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11416" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11422">“I have received proof,” he continued, “confirmation.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11423" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11447">“If you know for certain,” the Father Provincial said, “that this priest has committed some wrong (we all have our failings), I would truly appreciate being informed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11448" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11458">I am his superior. Although I may not be worthy, it is my job to correct, to remediate.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11459" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11492">“Then I will tell you. Together with the unfortunate circumstance of this friar’s open protection of the person I mentioned, there is another unpleasant matter, which could…But, between the two of us, we can settle this matter today. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11493" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11510">It would seem that this same Padre Cristoforo has been picking fights with my nephew Don Rodrigo ***.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11511" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11519">“Oh, I’m so sorry to hear this. I’m sorry. Truly I am.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11520" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11535">“My nephew is young, brash, with a high opinion of himself. He’s not used to being provoked…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11536" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11545">“I will make it my duty to look into this matter. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11546" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11586">As I have already told Your Magnificence—and I am speaking with a gentleman who is as fair-minded as he is experienced—we are all made of flesh and blood, prone to error…in both the body, and the soul. And if Padre Cristoforo has failed to…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11587" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11611">“You see, Your Reverence, these are things that, as I was saying, should remain between us, things that we should settle here and now, because if we stir them up…matters will only get worse. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11612" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11645">And you know what will happen next. These skirmishes, these clashes, sometimes start over nothing, and then they go on and on…If you try to get to the bottom of it, there will either be no end, or a hundred other problems will arise. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11646" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11652">We need to nip it in the bud, Reverend Father, nip it in the bud. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11653" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11686">My nephew is young. The friar, from what I hear, still has all the energy and the…inclinations of a young man. And it’s up to us, with the weight of our years…sad but true, eh, Reverend Father?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11687" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11735">For anyone witnessing this exchange, it would be as if, while at the opera, the backdrop had been raised too early, by mistake, in the middle of the scene, revealing the singer—unaware that the audience is watching—chatting freely with a colleague. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11736" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11767">The face, the actions, and the voice of the Count, in uttering that “sad but true,” were completely natural. For once, there was no pretense. The weight of his years really did bother him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11768" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11781">Not that he missed the amusements, the brio, the beauty of youth: frivolous, foolish, miserable stuff! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11782" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11810">The reason for his unhappiness was more concrete and significant. He aspired to a higher post, once it became vacant, and feared that time was running out. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11811" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11850">If he got what he wanted, you can be sure that his age would no longer matter to him. He would want nothing more, and he would die happy, as everyone assures us they will the moment they attain something they have wanted badly. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11851" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11871">“It’s up to us,” he continued, “to show better judgment than our young people, and to sort out their misdeeds. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11872" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11893">Luckily we still have time. The matter hasn’t drawn a lot of attention, and can be nipped in the bud, principiis obsta. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11894" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11898">Keep the lit match away from the straw. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11899" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11923">Sometimes a subject who behaves badly or causes trouble in one place might succeed brilliantly in another. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11924" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11934">Your Reverence can surely find the right niche for this friar. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11935" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11979">And let’s not forget that other circumstance, which might raise the suspicions of someone who…who might wish for him to be removed. By assigning him someplace far away from here, we would be killing two birds with one stone. Everything would take care of itself. Or rather, no harm would be done.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_11980" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12041">This is the conclusion that the Father Provincial had been expecting since the beginning of their colloquy. “Of course!” he thought. “I can see where this is going. As always, whenever a poor friar starts to annoy the men of your circle, or even just one of you, and disturbs you in some way, then immediately, without finding out whether he is right or wrong, his superior is expected to get rid of him.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12042" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12077">When the Count had finished, and let out a long sigh that was the equivalent of a full stop, the Provincial replied. “I understand perfectly what the Count wishes to say. But before taking such a measure…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12078" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12112">“It both is and isn’t a measure, Reverend Father. Nothing could be more natural, more ordinary. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12113" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12168">And if you don’t take it, and immediately, I predict a mountain of troubles, an Iliad of disorder…A rash act…no, not by my nephew…I can rein him in…but at this point, if we don’t end it now, without wasting time, through a clean cut, we won’t be able to stop it, to keep it secret…and then it will involve more than just my nephew…It’ll stir up a hornet’s nest, Reverend Father. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12169" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12175">You see, we are a prominent family. We have friends…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12176" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12176">“In high places.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12177" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12208">“So you do understand. They are all people whose blood runs blue, which counts for something in our world…Our honor is at stake, this is a family matter. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12209" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12229">And then…even the most law-abiding…It would break my heart to have to…to be forced to…I who have always been so generous to the Capuchin order! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12230" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12282">To continue to do the good deeds you do, in edifying the common people, you priests need peace and quiet, not strife, you need to be in harmony with those who…not to mention priests who have family members outside the monastery…these squabbles over honor, over nothing, go on forever, spread, and before you know it…half the world is at war. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12283" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12318">I happen to be in a position that requires me to maintain a certain decorum…The Governor, my peers on the Council…they would all make common cause…especially considering that other matter…You know how these things go.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12319" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12333">“To be honest,” said the Father Provincial, “Padre Cristoforo is a gifted preacher. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12334" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12357">I was already thinking of…and I had been asked to do that very thing…but to do it now, at this moment, in these circumstances, might make it seem like a punishment, and a punishment before having clearly defined…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12358" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12377">“No, not a punishment: a precautionary measure, a mutually beneficial solution, to prevent the harm that might…have I made myself clear?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12378" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12390">“The Count and I might see the issue in these terms, of course. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12391" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12411">But given the facts reported to Your Magnificence, I think it impossible that word hasn’t gotten out in the village. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12412" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12441">Everywhere you look there are instigators, troublemakers, or at the very least malicious busybodies who get a kind of mad pleasure out of seeing the nobility and the clergy at one another’s throats. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12442" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12458">They smell something in the air, put two and two together, gossip…Everyone has his own decorum to maintain. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12459" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12497">And then I, as an (unworthy) superior, have an express duty…the honor of the habit…this is not a personal matter…it is a trust vested in me…Your nephew, since he is so angry, as Your Magnificence says, might interpret this measure as his personal revenge and start to…I’m not saying boast about it, or gloat, but rather…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12498" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12502">“Really, Most Reverend Father? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12503" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12539">My nephew is a gentleman, esteemed by society…in keeping with his rank and his duties. But in my presence he is a boy, and he will do neither more nor less than I tell him to do. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12540" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12549">What’s more, I’ll make sure my nephew knows nothing of this. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12550" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12556">Do we really need to account to anyone? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12557" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12573">These are matters that can be handled between us, as good friends, and between us they shall remain. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12574" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12579">Don’t give it a second thought. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12580" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12585">In a position like mine, one is used to keeping secrets.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12586" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12587">At this he heaved another sigh. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12588" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12596">“As for the busybodies,” he continued, “what’s the most they can say? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12597" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12610">A friar being sent to preach in another village: What could be more normal? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12611" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12628">And for those of us who see…those of us who prevent…those of us whose duty it is…we need not worry about gossip.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12629" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12657">“But, to prevent that from happening, it would be wise, on this one occasion, for your nephew to make some show of, some public display of friendship, of regard…not so much for us, but for the order…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12658" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12661">“Of course, of course. That would only be fair…But it’s hardly necessary. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12662" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12678">I know that the Capuchins always receive the proper recognition from my nephew. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12679" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12696">It is his natural inclination, and a family tradition. And he knows he’s doing something I appreciate. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12697" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12707">Nevertheless, in this particular case…something special…would be more than fair. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12708" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12735">Let me handle it, Most Reverend Father. I’ll instruct my nephew…what I mean is that the matter will have to be broached very carefully, so that he gets no inkling of what has passed between us. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12736" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12748">I would not want us to place a bandage where there’s no wound! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12749" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12759">As for our understanding, the sooner it’s taken care of, the better. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12760" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12773">And if you were to find the right niche for him at a good distance from here…to eliminate any opportunity…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12774" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12791">“It just so happens that I have, in fact, received a request from Rimini for a preacher. And I might have even, for no other reason, set my sights on…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12792" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12797">“That would be just the thing, just the thing. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12798" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12799">When would this be…?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12800" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12808">“Seeing as it has to be done, it will be done soon.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12809" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12817">“Sooner rather than later, Most Reverend Father. Better today than tomorrow. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12818" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12839">And,” he continued, as he stood up from his chair, “if there is anything I or my family can do for the good Capuchin brothers…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12840" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12861">“We know from experience the generosity of your house,” said the Father Provincial, also rising and following the victor to the door. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12862" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12878">“We have extinguished a spark,” said the Count, pausing for a moment, “a spark, Most Reverend Father, that could have started a conflagration. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12879" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12888">A couple of words between friends is all it takes to settle things.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12889" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12911">He opened the door and insisted absolutely that the Father Provincial go first. They entered the next room and rejoined the rest of the company. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12912" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12932">Great cunning, great skill, and great eloquence had been invested by the Count in managing the affair, but the result was equal to his efforts. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12933" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12955">In fact, through the conversation we have reported, he also succeeded in forcing Padre Cristoforo to go from Pescarenico to Rimini on foot, which is a very long walk indeed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12956" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12971">One night soon after, a Capuchin from Milan arrived in Pescarenico with an envelope for the Father Guardian. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12972" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12985">Inside was an order of transfer for Fra Cristoforo to go to Rimini, where he would deliver the Lenten sermons. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_12986" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13024">The cover letter to the Guardian instructed him to tell said friar to cease any and all thoughts of matters he might be attending to in the village he was leaving, and to discontinue all related correspondence. The bearer of the letter would be his travel companion. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13025" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13070">The Guardian said nothing that night. In the morning he summoned Fra Cristoforo, showed him the order, and told him to fetch his basket, his walking stick, his cloak, and his belt, and set out on the journey immediately with the messenger friar. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13071" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13083">Whether this came as a blow to our friend, I will leave to your imagination. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13084" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13131">His first thoughts were of Renzo, Lucia, and Agnese. And to himself he exclaimed, for lack of a better word, “Oh God! What will those poor souls do once I am gone?” But then he raised his eyes to heaven and repented for his lack of faith, for presuming he was indispensable. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13132" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13170">He crossed his arms over his chest in a gesture of obedience and bowed his head before the Father Guardian, who drew him aside and gave him the other warning, advising him to cease all communication with Lucia and Renzo, in the form of an order. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13171" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13230">Padre Cristoforo went to his cell, placed his breviary, his Lenten sermons, and the bread of forgiveness inside his basket, cinched his tunic with the leather belt, bid farewell to the brothers in the monastery, and lastly went to receive the blessing of the Guardian. Then, with his fellow traveler, he set out on the road that had been ordained. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13231" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13256">I mentioned a while back that Don Rodrigo, who was more intent than ever on fulfilling his long-dreamed-of design, had decided to seek the assistance of a fearsome man. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13257" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13298">I cannot give his first name, family name, title, or even guess as to what they might be: all the stranger, since we find records of him in more than one book (printed books, I mean) from that period. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13299" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13361">He is undoubtedly the same character, since all the facts match up, but everywhere great effort has been taken to avoid stating his name, as if it might scorch the pen and hand of the writer. Francesco Rivola, in his biography of Federigo Borromeo, called this character, “A lord as mighty in wealth as he was noble in birth,” and left it at that. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13362" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13462">Giuseppe Ripamonti, in the fifth book of the fifth decade of his Storia patria, mentions him at greater length, referring to him as “one,” “the former,” “the latter,” “this man,” and “that character.” “I will relate,” he writes in his elegant Latin, which I will translate as best I can, “the case of a certain man who, although one of the preeminent leaders of the city, had established his residence in the countryside, near the border. And there, securing his protection through crime, he ignored the judgments of the courts, judges, every prosecutor, and even the Crown. The life he led was wholly independent. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13463" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13488">He harbored fugitives, having once been a fugitive himself; after which he returned home as if nothing had happened…” From Ripamonti we shall borrow other passages that suit our purposes to confirm or elucidate the tale of the anonymous author of the manuscript, whom we shall continue to follow. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13489" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13538">To do whatever the law prohibited or any power opposed; to declare oneself the arbiter, the master, of other people’s affairs, for no good reason other than the thrill of command; to be feared by all, and deferred to by those more accustomed to receiving deference: These had always been his main passions. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13539" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13565">Ever since his youth, the roar and the spectacle of so much violence and so many duels, the sight of so many tyrants, had filled him with a mix of contempt and impatient envy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13566" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13603">As a young man living in the city, he never missed an opportunity, and indeed often went looking, to quarrel with the most notorious tyrants, to get in their way, to size them up, put them in their place, or force them to seek his friendship. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13604" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13659">Superior in wealth and retinue to most, and in audacity and determination to perhaps all, he bullied many men into submission, roughed up many, and made friends of many more. Not friends on an equal footing, to be sure, but lesser friends—the only kind he liked—who acknowledged themselves as his inferiors, and always granted him the right of way. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13660" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13700">In effect, however, he became the fixer, the instrument, for them all. They never failed to ask for the support of such a useful ally when it came to their dirty work. For him to refuse would have compromised his reputation. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13701" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13741">So whether on his own or on another’s behalf, he ended up breaking so many laws that neither his name, nor his family, nor his friends, nor his audacity could shield him from banishment. In the face of powerful opposition, he had to retreat and leave the state. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13742" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13803">I believe this is what Ripamonti was referring to in a remarkable passage: “When he was banished from the town, consider the discretion, respectfulness, and reserve with which he left: He crossed the city on horseback, accompanied by a pack of hounds, to the blaring of a horn; and as he passed before the court palace, he left the guards with an impertinent message to convey to the Governor.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13804" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13840">From his place of exile, he did not interrupt his affairs or neglect his correspondence with the friends who continued to associate with him, “in occult league with atrocious counsel and grievous deeds,” to translate Ripamonti literally. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13841" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13895">Indeed, in this period he seems to have contracted with influential persons to conduct some terrible new business, which the above-mentioned historian describes with mysterious brevity. “Even some foreign princes,” he writes, “availed themselves of his services more than once, for an important assassination, and they often sent him reinforcements of men from afar to serve under his command.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13896" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13989">Finally (after how long we do not know), either the banishment was lifted through the intercession of a powerful man, or his audacity was as good as immunity. He decided to return home, and return he did. Not to Milan, however, but to a castle bordering the territory of Bergamo, which at that time, as everyone knows, belonged to the Venetian Republic. “That house,” I again quote Ripamonti, “was like an assassin’s workshop: servants, on whose own heads there was a bounty, whose job it was to cut off the heads of other men. Neither cooks nor scullery boys were exempt from murderous duties; the boys’ hands were drenched in blood.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_13990" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14027">In addition to this lovely domestic family, he had, according to the same historian, another one consisting of similar subjects, scattered and garrisoned, so to speak, in various places throughout the two states on whose border he lived, always ready to carry out his orders. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14028" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14055">At one point or another, every petty tyrant for a wide swath of the surrounding countryside had been forced to choose between being friends or enemies with this much more powerful tyrant. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14056" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14080">Things had gone so badly for the first men who tried to resist him, however, that no one felt like following in their footsteps. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14081" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14099">Nor could they secure independence from him by minding their own business and keeping to themselves. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14100" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14125">He would send messages ordering them to abandon such and such an enterprise or stop bothering such and such a debtor, and the like. And they had to answer yes or no. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14126" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14174">When one party to a dispute requested his arbitration in a business matter, offering a vow of fealty, the other party had to make the difficult choice of either accepting his ruling or becoming his enemy—the equivalent, as has already been said, of the final stage of consumption. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14175" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14210">Many who were in the wrong went to him to be declared in the right. So did many who were in the right, to gain a powerful patron and preempt an adversary. Both types of men became his special employees. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14211" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14274">Occasionally a weak victim, tormented by a bully, would turn to him. Taking the underdog’s part, he would force the bully to stop, make amends for the damage he had done, and apologize. If the man resisted, he would go after him so aggressively that the bully would have to leave the places he had tyrannized, or pay a swifter and more terrible price. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14275" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14315">And in these cases, that dreaded and abhorred name would be momentarily blessed, because in those days, this kind of compensation, not exactly justice, but rather a remedy, was not forthcoming from any other authority, private or public. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14316" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14336">More often, as a general rule in fact, he administered to evil intentions, atrocious vengeance, and arrogant whims. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14337" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14383">No matter how he used his power, the effect it produced was always the same: to impress people with how much he could and would do with no regard for right and wrong: two things that obstruct men’s wishes in so many ways, and so often force them to reconsider. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14384" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14431">Each petty tyrant’s fame was limited mainly to the tiny part of the country that was richest and most powerful. Each district had its own despots, but they were all so alike that people had no reason to worry about anyone other than the despots on their doorstep. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14432" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14470">But the fame of our tyrant was spread throughout the Duchy of Milan: Everywhere his life was the subject of folklore, and his name conveyed something irresistible, strange, and fabled. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14471" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14494">The suspicion that he had allies and assassins everywhere also kept his reputation alive everywhere. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14495" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14534">But they were only suspicions, for who would openly admit to being in his employ? Any tyrant might be his accomplice, and every criminal one of his men. This uncertainty itself made his notoriety even greater, and the fear of it even more oppressive. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14535" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14594">Whenever a strange and particularly savage bravo appeared somewhere, or whenever a horrific crime was committed whose perpetrator could not immediately be named or guessed, people said or whispered the name of the man who we, thanks to our authors’ blessed (to avoid using another word) circumspection, are forced to call the Nameless One. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14595" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14643">The distance from his lair to the palace of Don Rodrigo was no more than seven miles. The moment Don Rodrigo became master and tyrant, he must have realized that he would be unable to exercise his own tyranny without confronting or forging an alliance with his neighbor. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14644" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14684">So he offered to be, and then became, a friend, like everyone else. Don Rodrigo had done his friend more than one favor (that’s all the manuscript says), and each time he received assurances that the favor would be returned at any time. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14685" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14706">But he was very careful to hide this friendship, or at least not to disclose its nature and just how close it was. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14707" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14805">Don Rodrigo did indeed aspire to be a tyrant, but not a brutal and solitary tyrant; for him this profession was a means, not an end. He wanted to live freely in the city, enjoy the comforts, entertainments, and honors of city life. This meant that he had to practice a certain restraint, consider his relatives, cultivate the friendship of important people, and keep a hand on the scales of justice, to make sure they would, as needed, tip in his favor, disappear, or, on occasion, land on someone’s head, which could be easier than meting out personal violence. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14806" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14838">Because of that, public knowledge of his closeness, or rather collusion, with a man of that ilk, a sworn enemy of law and order, would not have been very convenient, especially with his uncle the Count. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14839" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14912">But he was able to pass off that modicum of friendship as a necessary and therefore readily comprehensible association with a man whose enmity would be too dangerous. For if the man who is supposed to administer justice has neither the will nor the way, he ultimately allows others to take matters into their own hands, to an extent. And while he may not grant his express consent, he will turn a blind eye. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap19-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14913" targetEnd="quarantana/cap19.xml#c19_14945">One morning, Don Rodrigo went out on horseback, as if in a hunting party, with a small escort of bravi on foot. Griso walked by his side, and four others followed, as he set off for the castle of the Nameless One. </note>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>