<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>2022</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed: a novel</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
          <date>2022</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Michael Moore</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="english_2022_cap15">
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10040">The innkeeper, seeing no end in sight, approached Renzo while asking the others, politely, to leave him alone. He shook him by the arm, trying to persuade him that it was time to go to bed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10041" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10058">But Renzo kept ranting about first and last names, decrees, and good boys like himself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10059" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10093">After enough repetitions, however, those two words, bed and sleep, finally entered his head, making him feel the need for what they signified, and producing a brief moment of lucidity. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10094" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10127">That flicker of regained consciousness made him vaguely sense how little of it he had left, the way the last candle burning illuminates the others that are spent. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10128" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10152">He mustered his courage, stretched out his hands, and pressed them against the table. He tried once or twice to right himself, took a deep breath, staggered, and, on the third try, with the innkeeper’s help, managed to stand up straight. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10153" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10186">The innkeeper, continuing to prop him up, helped him to emerge from between the table and the bench. In one hand he held a lamp, and with the other he guided and dragged Renzo as best he could toward the staircase door. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10187" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10246">There Renzo, hearing the clamor of “Good night,” shouted after him, twisted around so abruptly that, if his supporter hadn’t so deftly grabbed his arm, that twist would have turned into a tumble. As I was saying, he twisted and with his one free arm he sliced and engraved his goodbyes in the air, in the shape of Solomon’s knot. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10247" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10278">“Off to bed with you,” said the innkeeper, dragging him along. He got him through the door and, with an even greater effort, pulled him up to the top of the stairs and into the room he had assigned to him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10279" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10328">At the sight of the bed awaiting him, Renzo’s mood lifted. He looked at the innkeeper affectionately, eyes like fireflies lighting up, then eclipsed by his exhaustion. He tried to steady himself and extend his hand to the innkeeper’s face to pinch his cheek in a sign of friendship and appreciation, but he couldn’t reach. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10329" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10367">“Good man!” he managed to say. “Now I can see that you are a gentleman: This is a good deed, giving a bed to an honest man. But making me look bad down there, with all that stuff about my first and last name, that wasn’t very nice. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10368" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10377">Lucky for me I’m no fool…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10378" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10420">The innkeeper, who didn’t believe that Renzo could still think straight, and knew from experience how men in that condition are more subject to mood swings, decided to take advantage of that moment of lucidity to give it another try. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10421" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10443">“Dear boy,” he said, with his kindest voice and manner, “I didn’t do it to annoy you, or to stick my nose into your business. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10444" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10459">What do you expect? It’s the law. We have to obey it, too, otherwise we’ll be the first to get hit with a fine. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10460" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10468">Better to do what they want and…is it such a big deal in the end? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10469" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10473">A couple of words? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10474" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10506">Not for their sake, but as a favor to me. Come on, just between the two of us, let’s take care of it. Tell me your name and…and then you can go to bed with a light heart.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10507" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10524">“You rascal!” Renzo exclaimed. “You trickster! There you go again! Bringing up this nonsense about first name, last name, and business in the city!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10525" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10532">“Oh, shut up, you fool. Go to bed,” said the innkeeper. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10533" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10544">But Renzo only got louder. “Now I get it. You’re in league with them, too. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10545" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10549">Wait and see. I’ll show you.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10550" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10566">Turning toward the stairs, he started to holler even louder. “Friends, listen up. The innkeeper is in—” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10567" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10590">“It was a joke!” the innkeeper shouted in Renzo’s face, pushing him toward the bed. “It was a joke, couldn’t you tell?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10591" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10596">“Oh, a joke? Well, that’s more like it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10597" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10610">When you say it was a joke…it really is a joke,” and he fell face-first on the bed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10611" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10624">“Come now. Off with those clothes. And be quick about it,” said the innkeeper, adding some necessary assistance to his advice. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10625" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10651">Once Renzo had removed his doublet (no easy matter), the innkeeper grabbed it immediately, rummaging through the pockets to look for coins, and found some. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10652" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10701">Thinking that, the next day, his guest would have more on his mind than paying him, and that the money would probably fall into hands from which he couldn’t extract it, he decided to see whether he couldn’t at least conclude this transaction. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10702" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10711">“You’re a good boy, an honest man, right?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10712" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10731">“Good boy, honest man,” Renzo mumbled, while his fingers struggled with the buttons of the clothes he still hadn’t removed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10732" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10749">“Excellent,” the innkeeper replied, “so let’s settle your little bill, because tomorrow I have to go out to take care of a few errands…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10750" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10760">“What’s fair is fair,” said Renzo, “I may be crafty but I’m an honest man…But the money? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10761" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10766">Do I have to go looking for my money at this hour of the night?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10767" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10797">“Here it is,” said the innkeeper, and by applying all his experience, all his patience, and all his skill, he managed to present his bill to Renzo and settle it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10798" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10808">“Give me a hand so I can get the rest of these things off,” said Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10809" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10818">“I’m dead tired.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10819" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10841">The innkeeper helped him with this request. He even put a blanket over him, and muttered a gruff “Good night,” since Renzo was already snoring. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10842" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10926">And then, by that strange spell that sometimes makes us look upon an object of vexation as if it were affectionate (stemming from little more, perhaps, than our desire to understand something that has a powerful effect on us), he stopped for a moment to contemplate his inconvenient guest, raising the lamp over his face, and reflecting the light onto it with his outstretched hand. In that pose, he resembled pictures of Psyche when she sneaks a furtive peek at her unknown consort. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10927" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10940">“You jackass,” he whispered to the poor slumberer. “You were asking for it! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10941" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10950">Tomorrow you can tell me if it was worth it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10951" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10971">You rednecks, you think you can travel the world without knowing where the sun rises. But all you do is get yourself and your neighbor in trouble.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10972" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10988">Having said or thought this, he drew away the lamp, stepped back, left the room, and locked the door. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_10989" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11016">From the landing, he called up to his wife and told her to have one of the servant girls mind the children, so she could go down to the kitchen to take over for him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11017" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11042">“I have to go out. Of all the bad luck, a foreigner ended up here, God knows how, I sure don’t,” and he briefly described the unfortunate set of circumstances. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11043" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11056">Then he added, “Keep an eye on everything. On a cursed day like today, the main thing is to be careful. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11057" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11079">We’ve got a handful of rabble-rousers downstairs who, between their drinking and being loudmouths already, God knows what they’ll say. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11080" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11083">All it would take is one hothead to…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11084" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11095">“Shush, I’m not a child! You’re not the only one who knows how to run this place. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11096" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11103">So far there’s been no complaints about me!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11104" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11177">“All right, all right. Just make sure they pay! And if they start up about the Commissioner of Provision and the Governor and Ferrer and the Decurioni and the aristocrats and Spain and France and all that rubbish, just pretend you don’t hear. Because if you disagree with them, things could get ugly very quickly. And if you agree, they could get ugly in the future. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11178" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11196">Anyway, if you hear certain remarks, turn around and say, ‘I’ll be right there,’ as if someone were calling you from another corner of the room. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11197" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11204">I’ll try to get back as soon as I can.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11205" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11250">At this, he went downstairs with her to the kitchen and looked around to see if anything new had happened. Then he took his hat and cloak off a peg, grabbed a cudgel from the corner, and, with another stern look, repeated to his wife the instructions he had given. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11251" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11276">Meanwhile, he thought back to the speech he had begun at poor Renzo’s bedside, and as he walked down the street, he picked up where he had left off. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11277" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11332">“Stubborn mountain boy!” No matter how hard Renzo had tried to conceal his identity, his origins were plain to see in his words, his tone, his appearance, and his movement. “On a day like today, by being politic, by keeping my head about me, I could have come out unscathed, but you had to come along and upset the apple cart. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11333" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11343">With all the taverns in Milan, why did you have to choose mine? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11344" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11362">If you’d at least come alone, I could have turned a blind eye. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11363" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11378">But no, you came with company. And what’s worse, in the company of a police agent!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11379" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11429">At every step of the way, the innkeeper ran into unaccompanied pedestrians, couples, or groups of people whispering as they went, and at this point in his silent allocution, he saw a patrol of soldiers coming toward him. Stepping aside to let them pass, he looked at them from the corner of his eyes and said to himself, “Here comes the crackdown. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11430" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11456">And you, you see a few people raising hell and what bright idea do you come up with, you jackass? That the world has to change! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11457" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11474">And with this bright idea you ruin yourself and try to ruin me while you’re at it. It’s not right! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11475" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11494">I did everything I could to save you, and you, you ignoramus, you repay me by raising a stink in my tavern! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11495" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11506">You’re going to have to get out of this mess by yourself! I’m going to do what’s best for me. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11507" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11518">As if I wanted to know your name out of curiosity! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11519" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11529">What do I care if your name is Thaddeus or Bartholomew? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11530" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11554">Do you think I like writing things down? You’re not the only one who wants to do things his own way! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11555" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11574">I know there are decrees that don’t count: what a discovery, and from the lips of a mountain boy! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11575" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11585">But what you don’t know is that for innkeepers the decrees do count! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11586" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11615">You think you can travel the world, running your mouth? If you want to do things your way, and pretend the decrees don’t exist, you’d better learn to watch your words. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11616" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11710">Do you know the reward awaiting the poor innkeeper who follows your example and doesn’t ask the names of the people who grace him with their presence, you idiot? A fine of three hundred scudi shall be levied, as mentioned above, on said host, innkeeper, and others—see, that’s where they stuck in the three hundred scudi fine, and do you know how they spend it?—two-thirds of which shall be paid to the Royal Treasury, and the rest to the accuser or informer: nice guy, your companion! And in the event of inability to pay, five years on the galleys and an additional monetary or corporal punishment at the discretion of His Excellency. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11711" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11715">Much obliged to Your Grace!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11716" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11726">With these words the innkeeper set foot on the threshold of the courthouse. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11727" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11775">Here, as in all government buildings, there was a whirlwind of activity. Everywhere people were rushing about, issuing the orders that seemed most effective for preventing disorder the next day and to reduce the opportunities and ardor of the people clamoring for more riots, while keeping power in the hands of those accustomed to wielding it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11776" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11793">Reinforcements were being added to the troops guarding the Commissioner’s house. Roads were being blocked with wooden beams and wagons. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11794" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11848">The bakers were all ordered to make bread around the clock. Couriers were dispatched to the surrounding towns, with orders to send grain to the city. A nobleman was assigned to each bakery, with orders to be there early in the morning, supervise distribution, and restrain the hotheads through the authority of his presence and the power of his words. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11849" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11925">But, as the saying goes, to strike one blow to the hoop and one to the cask, and reinforce their orders with an element of fear, the decision was also made to arrest a few of the rioters. This was where the police commissioner had to step in, and you can imagine how he felt about the riots and the rioters, with that bandage on the left side of his head. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11926" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11978">His spies had been in the field since the start of the uprising. And the so-called Ambrogio Fusella was, as the innkeeper had surmised, an undercover agent who had been sent out to nab red-handed anyone who could be identified, tailed, trapped, and arrested in the dead of night or sometime the next day. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_11979" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12004">After hearing a few words of Renzo’s soliloquy, he had immediately seen him as the perfect dupe, the very type of man he needed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12005" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12035">When he learned that the boy was a newcomer to the city, he attempted the master stroke of leading him straight to jail, as if it were the safest tavern in the city. But his plan fell through, as we have seen. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12036" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12072">He was able, however, to bring home a reliable report of his first name, last name, and hometown, in addition to one hundred and one other speculations. So when the innkeeper arrived at the courthouse to refer what he knew about Renzo, they already knew a lot more than he did. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12073" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12099">The innkeeper entered the customary room and gave his deposition: how a foreigner seeking lodging at his tavern had refused to give his name. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12100" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12142">“You have done your duty by informing the authorities,” said a criminal notary, laying his pen down, “but we already knew.” “Big secret,” thought the innkeeper, “that took real genius!” “And we also know,” the notary continued, “his precious name.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12143" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12154">“Damn! His name! How did they get that?” is what the innkeeper thought this time. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12155" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12166">“But you,” the man resumed with a stern expression, “are not telling the whole truth.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12167" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12171">“What more do you want me to say?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12172" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12198">“Ah! We are well aware that he brought into your tavern a quantity of stolen bread, stolen violently, through looting and rioting.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12199" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12211">“So a man comes in with bread in his pocket, I have no idea where he got it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12212" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12229">But I swear on my life, I only saw one loaf.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12230" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12240">“Of course. Excuses, excuses. You’d have us believe they’re all honest men. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12241" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12250">Can you prove that the bread was purchased legally?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12251" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12261">“I don’t have to prove anything! What’s it got to do with me? I’m just the innkeeper.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12262" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12293">“But do you deny that your customer had the impudence to offend the decrees, and to make insulting and irreverent remarks about His Excellency’s coat of arms?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12294" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12310">“Pardon me, sir. How can he be my customer if this was the first time I’d seen him? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12311" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12339">It was the devil, with all due respect, who sent him to my establishment. And if I did know him, I would hardly have needed to ask his name.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12340" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12359">“But at your tavern, and in your presence, inflammatory things were said. Rash words! Seditious ideas! Mutterings! Shouts! Protests!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12360" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12375">“How can your Lordship expect me to pay attention to the misbehavior of a bunch of loudmouths all talking at the same time? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12376" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12385">I have to tend to my business, since I’m a poor man. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12386" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12411">And your Lordship knows perfectly well that the loose-lipped can also get free with their fists, especially when there’s a lot of them, and…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12412" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12426">“Yes, let them do and say what they like. You’ll see whether they still feel like joking tomorrow morning. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12427" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12428">What are you thinking?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12429" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12432">“I’m not thinking anything.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12433" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12440">“You think the riffraff have taken over Milan?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12441" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12442">“Of course not.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12443" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12444">“You’ll see, you’ll see.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12445" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12470">“I understand exactly what you’re saying. The King will always be king. But anyone who played has got to pay. And a poor father doesn’t want to get caught in the middle. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12471" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12479">But you’re the ones with the power: You should take care of it.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12480" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12485">“Are there still many people at your establishment?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12486" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12487">“Quite a few.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12488" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12493">“And what is your customer doing? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12494" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12506">Is he still mouthing off? Getting people riled up? Plotting riots for tomorrow?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12507" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12515">“You mean the foreigner? He’s gone to bed.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12516" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12525">“So you still have a lot of guests on your hands…Well, make sure he doesn’t get away.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12526" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12542">“What, am I supposed to play the cop now?” said the innkeeper to himself, but he answered neither yes nor no. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12543" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12552">“You’re free to go. Don’t forget to use your head,” the notary continued. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12553" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12557">“I always use my head. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12558" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12568">Your Lordship knows I’ve never been on the wrong side of the law.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12569" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12579">“And don’t go thinking the law has lost its grip.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12580" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12590">“Me? Of course not. I don’t think anything of the sort. All I care about is running my tavern.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12591" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12599">“The usual story. You have nothing more to say?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12600" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12604">“What more do you want me to say? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12605" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12609">There’s only one truth.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12610" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12635">“Enough. We have your deposition. If anything comes up, you’ll have to give a more detailed report to the courts, based on the questions they ask.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12636" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12652">“What do I have to report? I don’t know anything. All I can do is tend to my establishment.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12653" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12657">“Make sure he doesn’t leave.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12658" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12672">“I hope the chief of police will be informed that I came to do my duty right away. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12673" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12677">I kiss your hands, my Lordship.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12678" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12712">At the break of day, Renzo had been snoring for about seven hours and he was still—poor thing!—fast asleep when he was startled by two strong shakes to his arms and a voice at the foot of the bed shouting, “Lorenzo Tramaglino!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12713" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12744">He woke, pulled away from those arms, struggled to open his eyes, and saw a man dressed in black standing at the foot of the bed and two armed men on either side of his pillow. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12745" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12782">Between his surprise at the rude awakening, and the hangover from the wine I’m sure you all remember, he was in a momentary daze. Thinking he was trapped in a dream he didn’t like, he tossed and turned as if to wake himself up. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12783" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12800">“So, you finally heard us, Lorenzo Tramaglino?” said the man in the black cape, the selfsame notary of the night before. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12801" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12807">“Get a move on it. Get up and come with us.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12808" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12816">“Lorenzo Tramaglino?” asked Renzo Tramaglino. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12817" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12826">“How do you know my name? What do you want from me?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12827" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12845">“Quit talking and start moving,” said one of the policemen, grabbing him by the arm again. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12846" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12855">“What’s the meaning of this outrage?” shouted Renzo, pulling his arm away. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12856" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12858">“Innkeeper! Oh, innkeeper! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12859" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12870">Where’d you disappear to?” “Shall we take him away in his shirtsleeves?” asked the first policeman, turning to the notary. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12871" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12889">“Do you understand what’ll happen to you if you don’t get up immediately and come with us?” the notary said to Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12890" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12893">“Why should I?” asked Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12894" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12902">“The police commissioner will tell you why.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12903" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12903">“Me? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12904" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12914">I’m an honest man. I didn’t do anything. And I can’t believe…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12915" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12933">“All the better, all the better. That way we can clear the whole matter up quickly, with a couple of words, and you’ll be free to go about your business.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12934" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12948">“So let me go now,” said Renzo, “I’ve got nothing to do with the law.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12949" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12953">“Get a move on!” said one policeman. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12954" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12959">“Are we really taking him away?” asked the other. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12960" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12964">“Lorenzo Tramaglino!” repeated the notary. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12965" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12970">“How do you know my name, sir?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12971" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12993">“Do your duty,” said the notary to the policemen, who immediately grabbed hold of Renzo to pull him out of bed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_12994" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13001">“Hey, don’t touch the body of an honest man. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13002" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13006">What is this?…I can dress myself.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13007" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13012">“Then get dressed immediately,” said the notary. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13013" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13036">“I will,” replied Renzo, and he started to pick up the clothes tossed here and there on the bed, like flotsam washed up on a beach. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13037" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13053">As he got dressed, he kept saying, “But I don’t want to go to the police commissioner. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13054" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13060">What does he want with me? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13061" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13071">Since you are mistreating me so unfairly, I want to be taken to Ferrer. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13072" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13082">Him I know. He’s a good man. And he owes me a debt of gratitude.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13083" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13092">“Yes, my boy, you’ll be taken to Ferrer,” replied the notary. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13093" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13109">In other circumstances he would have burst out laughing at such a request, but this was no time for laughter. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13110" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13151">On his way to the inn, he had already noticed a certain unrest in the streets. He couldn’t tell whether it was the dregs of a revolt that still hadn’t been completely suppressed, or the beginnings of a new one: people appearing, forming into an assembly, a crowd, an angry mob. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13152" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13173">And now, without appearing to listen, or at least trying not to, he could hear the noise from the street getting louder. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13174" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13209">He wanted to hurry, but he would also have preferred to lead Renzo away arm in arm, like an old friend, since, if they got into a struggle once they were on the street, they would still be three against one. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13210" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13232">So the notary cast a glance at the police officers as if to say: “Be patient and don’t get the boy any more agitated than he already is.” For his part, he tried to find the right words to calm him down. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13233" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13279">Renzo, meanwhile, was taking his sweet time getting dressed, trying to remember as best he could the events of the previous day, and guessing correctly, or almost, that the decrees and that stuff about first and last names must be at the bottom of everything. But how the devil did this man know his name? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13280" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13334">And what the devil had happened during the night to prompt the police to go out, unerringly, and arrest one of the good guys who, the day before, had played such an important role? And not all of those guys were still in bed, since Renzo had also noticed the noise from the street getting louder and louder. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13335" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13356">As he looked in the notary’s face, he could see the anxiety the man was struggling, in vain, to conceal. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13357" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13396">So to verify his hunches and sound out the situation, as well as to buy time and hatch a plan for himself, he said, “Now I see what’s at the bottom of all this: It’s because of that business about my first and last name. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13397" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13427">Last night I was a little tipsy. Sometimes these innkeepers serve a deceitful wine; and sometimes, like I say, once you’ve had a few, you know, it’s the wine that does the talking. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13428" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13440">But if that’s all there is, I’m ready to do whatever you want. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13441" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13449">Besides, you already know my name. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13450" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13454">Who the devil told you?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13455" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13480">“Good boy,” replied the notary with an affected kindness, “now you’re talking sense. And take it from someone in the business, me: You’re smarter than most. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13481" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13501">It’s the best way to get this taken care of quickly and efficiently. With this attitude, we’ll be done in two shakes of a lamb’s tail, and you’ll be free to go. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13502" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13515">But you see, my son, my hands are tied. I can’t release you here and now as I would like. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13516" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13536">Come along, be quick, nothing to be afraid of, because when they see who you are, I’ll put in a word…just leave it to me…Enough. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13537" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13539">Hurry up, my son.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13540" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13568">“Ah, so you’re not allowed to free me. I see,” said Renzo, and he continued to get dressed, resisting the police’s attempts to grab hold of him and make him hurry up. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13569" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13577">“Will we be passing by Piazza Duomo?” he asked the notary. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13578" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13696">“Wherever you like, whichever way is shortest, so that you can be released as quickly as possible,” he answered, annoyed that he had to ignore Renzo’s mysterious question, about which he would have liked to interrogate him a hundred times over. “Just my luck!” he thought. “Who should fall into my hands but a boy who, I can tell, wants nothing more than to spill his guts. And, if I had a little time, off the record, through a friendly chat, I could get him to confess to anything I wanted, without torture. This is a boy you could take to prison, once the interrogation was over, even before he realized he was under arrest. Just my luck that he would fall into my lap at a moment like this! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13697" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13751">But what other choice do I have?” he said to himself, while keeping his ears pricked and his head tilted back. “Nothing I can do about it. Plus, there’s a risk that today will be worse than yesterday.” These thoughts were further confirmed by a strange hubbub in the street. He couldn’t resist pulling the curtain back, to have a look through the window. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13752" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13796">Outside of the inn, he saw a cluster of citizens who, at the patrol’s order to disperse, had answered with insults; even after they were broken up, they continued to grumble. Still worse, in the notary’s eyes, the soldiers could not have been more cordial. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13797" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13854">He closed the curtain and stood still for a moment, uncertain of whether to complete the operation or to leave Renzo guarded by the two policemen and run to the police commissioner and report what was happening on the street. “Well,” he said to himself, “they’ll tell me I’m good-for-nothing, lily-livered, that I should just follow orders. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13855" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13859">Time to face the music. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13860" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13862">Damn these riots! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13863" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13866">Damn this job!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13867" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13876">Renzo was finally ready, the notary’s two minions by his side. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13877" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13896">The notary intimated to them not to be too aggressive, and said to Renzo, “Be a good boy. Now let’s get a move on.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13897" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13902">In the meantime Renzo, too, had been listening, seeing, and thinking. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n189" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13903" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13919">Now he was fully dressed, except for his doublet, which he was holding in one hand while rummaging through his pockets with the other. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n190" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13920" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13936">“Oh,” he said, looking at the notary with a shocked expression, “what happened to the money and the letter I had in there. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n191" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13937" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13938">My good sir!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n192" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13939" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13952">“You’ll get everything back in short order,” said the notary, “once we’ve taken care of a few formalities. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n193" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13953" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13954">Come now, let’s go.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n194" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13955" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13972">“No, no, no,” said Renzo, shaking his head. “I don’t like this. I want my things back, good sir. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n195" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13973" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13982">I will account for my actions, but I want what’s mine.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n196" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_13983" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14010">“Here, I’ll show you that I trust you. Take ’em, and be quick,” said the notary, removing the confiscated items from his breast pocket and handing them to Renzo with a sigh. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n197" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14011" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14031">Renzo, putting them back where they belonged, muttered between his teeth, “Keep your distance. You’ve been hanging around thieves so long that their habits have rubbed off on you.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n198" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14032" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14073">The policemen were eager to punch Renzo, but the notary held them in check with a look, all the while saying to himself, “If you cross the line, we’re going to make you pay, and with interest!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n199" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14074" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14109">As Renzo was putting on his doublet and getting his hat, the notary gestured to one of the policemen to lead the way downstairs. He sent the prisoner after him, then the other policeman, and then himself, too. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n200" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14110" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14159">Once they were in the kitchen—while Renzo was distracted, asking, “Where has he gone off to, that damn innkeeper?”—the notary gave another signal to the officers. They grabbed hold of the boy, one on the right and the other on the left, and quick as a flash bound his hands with devices that, by a hypocritical figure of speech, are called “handcuffs.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n201" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14160" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14204">They consisted (my apologies for descending into details unworthy of the gravity of our story, but they are required for the sake of clarity) of a piece of twine a little longer than the circumference of a normal wrist, fitted with two small pieces of wood at either end like pegs. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n202" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14205" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14261">The twine was wrapped around the prisoner’s wrist, while the pegs were passed between the middle and ring fingers of the captor’s hand, and held tight in his fist, so he could tighten the knot with a twist. This gave the police the means not only to secure the captive, but also to torture him if he resisted: This is why the twine was studded with knots. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n203" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14262" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14269">Renzo struggled to wriggle out of them, shouting, “What kind of a trick is this? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n204" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14270" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14272">To an honest man…!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n205" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14273" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14292">But the notary, who had just the right words for every painful event, urged, “Be patient! They’re just doing their duty. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n206" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14293" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14310">What do you expect? These are mere formalities. Even we can’t treat people the way we’d like to. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n207" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14311" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14326">And if we don’t follow orders, we’ll end up in even worse trouble than you! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n208" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14327" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14328">Be patient!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n209" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14329" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14342">As he was speaking, the two policemen gave the pegs another twist. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n210" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14343" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14360">Renzo quieted down, like a skittish horse that feels its lips being pinched by the bit, and exclaimed, “Patient?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n211" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14361" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14373">“Good boy,” said the notary, “that’s the right way to get yourself out of this. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n212" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14374" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14390">We’re just doing our job. It’s uncomfortable, I know. Just behave, and you’ll be out in a minute. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n213" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14391" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14413">And since I can see that you have the right attitude, and I feel inclined to help you, let me give you some free advice, for your own good. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n214" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14414" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14453">Listen carefully. I’ve got a lot of experience with these things. Walk straight ahead without looking around, without calling attention to yourself. That way no one will see—no one will notice what’s going on—and your honor will remain intact. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n215" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14454" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14476">In an hour you’ll be as free as a bird. There’s so much going on that they’ll want to handle your case quickly. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n216" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14477" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14492">I’ll put in a good word, too…Then you can go about your business and no one will know that you had a scrape with the law. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n217" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14493" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14547">And the two of you,” he continued, turning to the policemen with a stern look on his face, “be careful not to hurt him, since he’s under my protection. Do your duty, but remember that he’s an honest man, a fine upstanding man, who will be free very shortly, and he cares very much about his honor. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n218" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14548" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14564">Walk in a way that doesn’t attract attention, as if you were three gentlemen out for a stroll.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n219" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14565" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14575">And with a commanding tone and a menacing brow, he concluded, “Do you understand?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n220" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14576" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14620">Turning to Renzo, with his brow now unfurrowed and his face suddenly more cheerful, as if to say, “We really are your friends,” he whispered again, “Follow my lead. Walk with your head down, and quietly. Trust this man who cares about you. Let’s go.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n221" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14621" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14624">And the party set off. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n222" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14625" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14693">Renzo didn’t believe a word of it: not that the notary preferred him to the police; not that he cared about Renzo’s reputation; not that he intended to help him. He was well aware that the notary, fearing that an opportunity for his prisoner to escape would arise once they were on the street, was professing these fine sentiments to distract him from taking notice and taking advantage. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n223" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14694" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14716">So all the man’s precautions served only to confirm the plan Renzo already had in mind: to do the exact opposite. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n224" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14717" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14731">None of this should lead you to think that the notary was new or unpracticed in deception, because you’d be wrong. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n225" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14732" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14758">He was a seasoned master of the art, according to our historian, who seems to have been one of his friends. At that moment, however, the notary was very agitated. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n226" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14759" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14800">In a calmer state of mind, believe me, he would have laughed at anyone who thought they could trick a person into doing something suspect by coaxing, encouraging, or dispensing friendly, disinterested advice. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n227" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14801" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14850">But it is a general tendency of men, when they are agitated and distressed, and recognize that another person could get them out of a bind, to demand cooperation insistently, repeatedly, with all kinds of excuses. When swindlers are distressed and agitated, they, too, follow this same general rule. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n228" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14851" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14864">And in circumstances like these, they end up looking pathetic. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n229" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14865" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14937">The masterly tricks, the refined cunning by which they usually get their way, are almost second nature for them. Used at the right time, with the necessary composure, these expedients usually help them achieve their goal so surely and so covertly—and overtly, as well—that they are showered with universal praise when they succeed. But when these poor men are in dire straits, they use their ruses hastily, haphazardly, with neither manners nor grace. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n230" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14938" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14988">As a result, anyone who sees them scheming and striving is moved to both pity and laughter, and the man they hope to entrap, even if he is not so smart, can easily detect their ploy, and be inspired to turn their tricks against them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n231" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_14989" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15017">So you should never tire of urging professional swindlers to stay calm, or even better, to maintain the upper hand. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n232" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15018" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15047">The moment they were on the street, Renzo began to look near and far, side to side, make himself conspicuous, and listen carefully. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n233" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15048" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15085">People did not seem to be gathering in any unusual way, however. And although some faces suggested a hint of the rebel, everyone continued on his or her way, with no sense of rebellion. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n234" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15086" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15099">“Use your head, use your head!” the notary whispered behind his back. “Think of your honor, my son.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n235" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15100" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15142">But when Renzo, paying close attention to three men with angry faces coming his way, overheard them talking about a bakery, hidden flour, and justice, he tried to attract their attention by grimacing and coughing in a way that indicated anything but a cold. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n236" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15143" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15172">The men took a closer look at the convoy and stopped, as did others who were arriving. At the sound of murmuring, others who had passed by turned around and came back. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n237" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15173" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15194">“Watch yourself, boy, use your head. Don’t go ruining this. It’ll only make things worse for yourself. Think of your honor, your reputation,” the notary continued to whisper. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n238" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15195" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15197">But Renzo acted up even more. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n239" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15198" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15219">The police, after an exchange of glances, convinced they were doing the right thing (everyone makes mistakes), gave another twist to the handcuffs. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n240" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15220" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15242">“Ow! Ow! Ow!” cried their victim. At his cries, people came running from every corner of the street and crowded around, blocking the convoy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n241" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15243" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15261">“He’s a criminal,” snarled the notary to the people suddenly surrounding him. “He’s a thief who was caught red-handed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n242" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15262" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15267">Make way, in the name of the law!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n243" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15268" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15307">But Renzo saw his opportunity in the policemen’s white, or at least pale faces, and thought, “If I don’t make my move now, I’ll only have myself to blame.” He started to holler: “Boys, they’re dragging me off to prison for shouting ‘bread and justice’ yesterday. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n244" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15308" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15317">I didn’t do anything. I’m an honest man. Help me! Don’t abandon me, boys!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n245" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15318" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15354">The crowd murmured in his favor and calls arose to protect him. At first the policemen ordered, then they asked, then they begged the people nearby to get out of the way and leave. The crowd responded by pushing and shoving even more. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n246" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15355" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15377">Seeing the situation take a turn for the worse, the police let go of the handcuffs and focused only on getting lost in the crowd and sneaking away unobserved. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n247" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15378" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15394">The notary longed to do the same, but was prevented by his beloved black toga. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n248" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15395" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15424">The poor man, pale and alarmed, tried to make himself as small as possible, twisting and turning to wriggle his way through the crowd, but he couldn’t look up without seeing twenty other sets of eyes looking down on him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n249" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15425" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15482">He attempted to pass himself off as a foreigner who, happening upon the scene by chance, had gotten inadvertently caught in the crowd, frozen like a wisp of straw in ice. Finding himself in front of a man who was staring straight at him with a scowl even worse than all the others, the notary twisted his mouth into a smile and, playing the fool, asked, “What happened?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n250" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15483" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15486">“A black toga!” the man answered. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n251" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15487" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15490">“Black toga! Black toga!” echoed from every side. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap15-n252" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15491" targetEnd="quarantana/cap15.xml#c15_15526">The shouts were followed by shoves and, in no time, propelled in part by his own legs, in part by the elbows of others, he managed to attain what he wanted most in that moment: to be away from that stampede. </note>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>