<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>2022</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed: a novel</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
          <date>2022</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Michael Moore</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="english_2022_cap23">
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10036">While awaiting the hour to go to church and celebrate the Mass, Cardinal Federigo was reading a book—his usual habit in his spare time—when the chaplain came in with an odd look on his face. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10037" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10043">“A strange visitor, Your Grace, truly strange!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10044" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10048">“Who is it?” asked the Cardinal. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10049" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10075">“None other than ***,” answered the chaplain, emphasizing each syllable as he uttered the name (which I cannot share with my readers), adding, “He’s outside. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10076" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10091">In person. And he is requesting nothing less than an audience with Your Grace.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10092" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10109">“He is?” said the Cardinal, his face suddenly animated. He closed his book and stood up from his chair. “Show him in! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10110" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10126">Show him in at once!” “But,” replied the chaplain without moving, “Your Grace should know who he is: He’s a criminal, the notorious…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10127" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10147">“And should a bishop not feel blessed that a man like him suddenly wants an audience?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10148" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10177">“But,” insisted the chaplain, “we’re never allowed to talk about certain matters, because Your Grace says it’s nothing but gossip. But when the situation arises, I think it’s my duty. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10178" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10199">After all, zealousness will earn you enemies, Your Grace, and we know for a fact that more than one criminal has threatened that sooner or later—” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10200" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10206">“And have they?” interrupted the Cardinal. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10207" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10228">“I’m saying he’s a murderer, an outlaw, who’s in league with the meanest outlaws a man who might have been sent—” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10229" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10246">“This is a strange form of protocol,” Federigo interrupted again with a smile. “Are the soldiers urging their general to be afraid?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10247" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10272">Then, turning serious and pensive, he continued, “San Carlo would never have hesitated to receive such a man: He would have gone to him himself! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10273" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10279">Show him in at once; he’s waited too long as it is.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10280" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10296">The chaplain left, muttering, “It’s hopeless: These saints are all so stubborn!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10297" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10327">As he opened the door and returned to the room where the Nameless One and others were gathered, he saw the priests huddled to one side of the room, whispering and casting furtive glances at the visitor, who was standing alone on the other side of the room. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10328" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10365">The chaplain headed toward the man, sizing him up furtively, and wondering what kind of arsenal was concealed beneath his coat. And whether, before showing him in, he really should have asked…but he couldn’t bring himself to do it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10366" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10372">He went up to him and said, “His Grace awaits your Lordship. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10373" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10378">Please follow me.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10379" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10412">He led him through the small crowd, which immediately parted to let them pass, casting glances to the right and to the left as if to say, “What do you expect? Don’t you realize that Federigo always does everything his own way?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10413" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10446">The moment the Nameless One entered the room, Federigo went over to him with an eager and serene face, arms open wide, as he would for a welcome guest. He then gestured for the chamberlain to leave, which he did. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10447" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10456">The two men stood there for a few moments without speaking, each hesitating for different reasons. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10457" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10534">The Nameless One had been driven there by an inexplicable urge rather than a specific purpose. He was torn between two opposing passions: a vague longing to be relieved of his inner torment, and a feeling of shame and aggravation to have come before the Cardinal like a penitent, subdued and abject, to confess his guilt and beg forgiveness from another man. He couldn’t find or almost search for the right words to say. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10535" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10575">Still, as he raised his eyes to the man before him, he was pierced by a feeling of veneration both powerful and soothing that, while building his trust, lowered his contempt, and, without directly attacking his pride, still crushed it, and, I would say, forced him into silence. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10576" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10591">Federigo’s presence was, in fact, the kind that conveys superiority yet inspires love. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10592" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10692">He carried himself in a manner that was both natural and almost unconsciously majestic, neither stooped nor wasted by age. His eyes were grave and lively, his forehead serene and pensive. Despite his white hair and pallor—the marks of a life of abstinence, meditation, and toil—he had a kind of virginal glow. From his facial features one could see that, in his youth, he must have been what is properly considered handsome. But the habit of solemn and benevolent thought, the inner peace of a long life, the love of humanity, and the constant joy of an ineffable hope, had replaced it with what I would almost call the beauty of old age, highlighted by the magnificent simplicity of his purple cassock. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10693" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10769">For a few moments, the Cardinal trained on the Nameless One his penetrating gaze, long experienced in deciphering thoughts from appearances. He sensed that beneath the man’s dark and troubled face there was something close to the hope he himself had felt at the announcement of this visit. “Oh!” he said enthusiastically, “This is such a precious visit! And I am so grateful to you for the good decision to undertake it, although I am somewhat at fault.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10770" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10797">“At fault!” exclaimed the lord, amazed but also comforted by the Cardinal’s words and his manner, and relieved that the Cardinal had broken the ice. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10798" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10822">“Yes, of course I’m at fault,” continued the other, “for I made you come to me, when I should have been the one to come to you long ago.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10823" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10825">“You? To me? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10826" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10828">Don’t you know who I am? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10829" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10834">Are you sure you heard my name correctly?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10835" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10859">“My joy must be showing on my face! Do you think I would feel this way at the announcement—at the sight—of a stranger? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10860" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10910">You are the one who makes me feel this; you, as I said, whom I should have sought; you, whom I have so loved and grieved for, whom I have so prayed for; you, of my children, all of whom I dearly love, the one I should have most wanted to welcome and embrace, if I had believed I could hope for it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10911" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10928">But God alone can perform miracles. He alone can make up for the weakness and sloth of his poor servants.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10929" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10963">The Nameless One stood there in silence, dumbstruck and overcome with emotion. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10964" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10983">“What’s wrong?” Federigo continued, even more affectionately. “You are here to bring me good news. Why are you so reluctant to tell me?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10984" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10987">“Good news? Me? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10988" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10997">The fires of hell are burning in my heart! I should have good news for you? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_10998" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11013">Tell me, please, if you can, what good news you could expect from a man like me?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11014" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11027">“That God has touched your heart, and wants to make you one of His own,” replied the Cardinal calmly. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11028" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11028">“God! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11029" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11030">God! God! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11031" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11036">If only I could see him! If only I could hear him! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11037" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11039">Where is this God?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11040" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11044">“You are asking me? You? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11045" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11051">Who is closer to Him than you? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11052" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11094">Don’t you feel Him in your heart, weighing on you, disturbing you, never leaving you a moment’s peace? Don’t you feel Him drawing you in, holding before you the hope, in His tranquility and joy, for a joy that will be even more complete and immense the moment you recognize Him, confess your sins, and pray to Him?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11095" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11105">“Of course I do! Something is weighing on me, eating at me! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11106" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11107">But is it God? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11108" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11122">If this God exists, if He is who they say He is, what would God want with me?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11123" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11150">These words were uttered with a pang of despair, but Federigo replied in a voice that was solemn yet serene. “What would God want with you? With you? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11151" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11171">He can make you into an instrument of His power and goodness! He can attain a glory through you that no one else could give Him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11172" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11223">Although many in the world have long condemned you, and thousands upon thousands detest your actions”—for a moment the Nameless One was startled, astonished to hear himself criticized so openly, and even more astonished to feel relieved rather than indignant—“and what glory,” Federigo continued, “would they bring to God? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11224" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11260">Theirs are the voices of fear, voices of self-interest, calling out, perhaps, for justice, but a type of justice too easy, too obvious! And some of these voices, unfortunately, may envy your wretched power, your—until now—deplorable self-assurance. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11261" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11279">But if you yourself stand up to condemn the life you have led, to accuse yourself, well then, there will be glory to God! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11280" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11288">And you ask what use God may have for you? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11289" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11326">Who am I, a poor mortal, to tell you how you can benefit the Lord? What can He do with your impetuous will, your unshakable constancy, after He has reawakened your will and inflamed it with love, hope, and repentance? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11327" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11355">Who are you, poor mortal, to think the evil you plot and commit is greater than God’s ability to make you desire and strive for the good? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11356" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11361">You ask what God can do with you? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11362" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11373">He can forgive you! Save you! Redeem you! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11374" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11381">Are these things not magnificent and worthy of him? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11382" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11445">Just think! If I—weak, miserable, though proud man that I be—am so consumed by your health now that I would gladly sacrifice the few days I have left on this earth (as God is my witness), then imagine the greatness of His love, He who infuses my own imperfect but ardent love. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11446" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11458">Imagine how He loves and wants you, He who commands and inspires in me an all-consuming love for you.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11459" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11477">As these words left his lips, his face, his expression, and his every gesture radiated with their meaning. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11478" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11542">His listener’s face in turn changed from upset and agitated to stunned and intent, and then settled into a deeper calm. Eyes that had not shed a tear since childhood welled up. And when the Cardinal’s speech ended, the Nameless One gave his final and most unguarded response: He covered his face with his hands and began to sob uncontrollably. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11543" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11584">“God is good, God is great!” exclaimed Federigo, raising his eyes and his hands to the heavens, “What have I ever done, I, your worthless servant, your sleeping shepherd, to deserve an invitation to this banquet of grace, to witness this joyful miracle?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11585" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11593">As he spoke, he reached out for the hand of the Nameless One. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11594" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11609">“No!” cried the latter. “No! Away from me, away! Do not defile your innocent and generous hand. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11610" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11620">You do not know the things that my hand has done.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11621" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11653">“Allow me,” said Federigo, taking it firmly but affectionately, “allow me to grasp this hand that will right so many wrongs, spread so much good, soothe so many of the afflicted, and reach out—unarmed, peaceful, and humble—to so many enemies.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11654" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11658">“This is too much!” sobbed the Nameless One. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11659" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11663">“Leave me, Your Grace. Good Federigo, leave me be. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11664" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11686">A crowd of people is waiting for you. All good people, all innocent, many of whom have come from far away to see or hear you just this once. And yet you keep them waiting…to be with me!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11687" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11706">“Let us leave the ninety-nine sheep,” replied the Cardinal, “they are safe on the mountain. Now I wish to spend some time with the one that went astray. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11707" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11719">Those other souls may be even happier than if they had seen this poor bishop. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11720" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11742">Perhaps God, who has performed the miracle of mercy in you, is filling them at this very moment with a joy that they do not yet understand. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11743" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11780">They may already be with us without realizing it. Perhaps the Holy Spirit has instilled in their hearts a vague yearning to give love, a prayer for you, a prayer of thanksgiving of which you are the unknown recipient.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11781" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11822">As he spoke, he embraced the Nameless One, who, after trying to resist and pull away for a moment, surrendered, as if overcome by that impulse of love. He embraced the Cardinal in turn, and let his trembling, altered face fall to the other man’s shoulder. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11823" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11854">His burning tears landed on the untainted purple tunic of Federigo, whose guiltless hands affectionately clasped his fingers and patted a coat accustomed to bearing the weapons of violence and treachery. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11855" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11876">The Nameless One slipped out of the embrace, covered his eyes with one hand, and, turning his face upward, exclaimed, “God truly is great! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11877" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11918">God truly is good! Now I know myself; I understand who I am. My sins stand before me, and I am filled with self-loathing. And yet…and yet I feel refreshed by a joy…yes, a joy that I have never before felt in my whole horrible life!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11919" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11951">“God is giving you a taste of that joy to draw you into his service,” Federigo said, “to give you a new life that you will enter into resolutely, a new life in which you will have so much to undo, to repair, to regret!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11952" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11966">“I am such a wretch!” exclaimed the nobleman. “There are so many, so many things that I can only regret! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11967" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11990">But there is one deed, at least, that I have only just begun, that, if nothing else, I can interrupt, undo, and repair.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_11991" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12044">Federigo listened attentively. In even stronger words of loathing than I have used, the Nameless One briefly described the outrages Lucia had suffered, how the poor girl’s terrors, anguish, and pleas had sent him into a frenzy, and how she was still at the castle… </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12045" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12056">“We have no time to waste!” exclaimed Federigo, gasping with piety and concern. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12057" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12058">“You are blessed! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12059" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12078">This is a token of God’s forgiveness! He is allowing you to become an instrument of salvation for the very person you had sought to ruin. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12079" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12081">May God bless you! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12082" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12084">Indeed, He already has! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12085" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12092">Do you know where this poor tormented soul is from?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12093" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12099">He gave the name of Lucia’s village. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12100" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12122">“That’s not far from here,” said the Cardinal, “praise God; and perhaps…” As he spoke, he ran to a side table and shook a bell. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12123" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12197">In came the chaplain, with a worried look on his face. He cast a glance at the Nameless One and noticed his altered expression and reddened eyes. Then, he looked at the Cardinal, in whom he sensed a solemn happiness and impatient haste beneath his unflappable exterior. The chaplain stood there, slack-jawed and astonished, until the Cardinal brought him back to earth, asking whether the pastor of *** was present among the priests gathered outside. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12198" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12203">“He is, Your Grace,” replied the chaplain. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12204" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12215">“Send him in at once,” said Federigo, “together with the local priest.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12216" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12233">The chaplain left and returned to the room where the priests were assembled. All eyes turned to him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12234" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12261">With his mouth still agape, his face still painted with astonishment, he waved his hands in the air, calling, “Gentlemen! Gentlemen! Haec mutatio dexterae Excelsi—Here is the right hand of the Most High!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12262" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12268">And he stood there for a moment, saying nothing more. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12269" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12295">Then, resuming his official tone and voice, he added, “His Most Illustrious and Reverend Eminence wishes to see the local pastor as well as the parish priest of ***.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12296" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12317">The first man came forward at once; at the same time, a lone “Me?” mumbled and tinged with disbelief, emerged from the crowd. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12318" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12328">“Are you not the pastor of ***?” asked the chaplain. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12329" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12331">“One and the same, but…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12332" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12338">“His Most Illustrious and Reverend Archbishop wishes to see you.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12339" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12353">“Me?” that voice repeated, the monosyllable clearly asking, “What’s this got to do with me?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12354" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12380">But this time, emerged the man together with the voice: Don Abbondio in person, with a hesitant step and a face both stunned and disgruntled. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12381" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12408">The chaplain gestured to him, as if to say, “Come along, what’s taking you so long?” then, leading the way, he went to the door, opened it, and ushered in the two priests. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12409" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12437">The Cardinal let go of the Nameless One’s hand, having concluded their arrangements. He stepped away and gestured to the local priest to approach. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12438" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12516">He told him the story briefly, and asked the priest whether he couldn’t immediately find a good matron to travel in a sedan chair to the castle to fetch Lucia: a woman with a good heart and a good head, who would know how to behave on such an unusual mission—the most appropriate manners to adopt, and how to find the most suitable words, to hearten and calm the poor girl for whom, after so much distress and turmoil, being released might prove even more upsetting. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12517" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12530">After giving it a moment’s thought, the priest said he had just the right person, and left. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12531" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12555">With another gesture the Cardinal summoned the chaplain, whom he ordered to arrange immediately for the sedan chair and chairmen, and to have two mules saddled. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12556" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12564">Once the chaplain had left, the Cardinal turned to Don Abbondio. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12565" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12624">The priest was already standing near him, in order to keep his distance from the nobleman on the other side of the room. He cast a furtive glance at first one man, then the other, wondering what all the fuss was about. He then made a slight bow to the Cardinal, saying, “I have been informed that Your Grace wishes to see me, but I believe there has been a mistake.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12625" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12641">“No, there hasn’t,” replied Federigo. “I have some good news for you, as well as a gratifying and most pleasant errand. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12642" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12693">One of your parishioners, Lucia Mondella, whom you must have thought was lost for good, has been found. She’s near here, in the home of this dear friend of mine. I want you to go with him now; bring with you the woman that the local priest has gone to find. That is, you are to go to fetch your parishioner and accompany her back here.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12694" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12744">It was all Don Abbondio could do to hide how annoyed, irritated, and bitter this proposal—this order—had made him. With no time to compose his face or wipe away the frown that had already formed on it, he hid his feelings by bowing his head in a gesture of obedience. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12745" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12769">He then raised his head and made a deep bow to the Nameless One, with a pitiful look as if to say: “I am in your hands, have mercy on me: Parcere subjectis—spare the defeated!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12770" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12778">The Cardinal asked him whether Lucia had any relatives. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12779" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12794">“If you mean close relatives with whom she lives or has lived, she only has her mother,” replied Don Abbondio. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12795" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12801">“And is she home?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12802" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12803">“Yes, Your Grace.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12804" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12868">“Considering,” Federigo continued, “that the poor girl cannot go straight home, I’m sure she would be overjoyed to see her mother immediately. So, if the local priest is not back before I go to church, please tell him to order a cart or a saddle horse and send a sensible man to look for the mother and bring her here.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12869" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12875">“And if I were to go?” asked Don Abbondio. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12876" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12885">“No, no. Not you. I’ve already given you something else to do,” replied the Cardinal. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12886" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12894">“I meant,” pursued Don Abbondio, “to prepare her poor mother. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12895" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12922">She’s a very sensitive woman, and it would be best for her to be informed by someone who knows her, and knows how to handle her, in order to avoid doing more harm than good.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12923" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12946">“Which is why I’m asking you to tell the local priest who would be the right person for the job. You are needed elsewhere,” replied the Cardinal. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12947" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12979">And he wanted to add, “After what the poor girl has gone through, hours and hours of anguish in that castle, not knowing what further horrors lie before her, she needs to see a familiar face, someone she trusts.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12980" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12992">But he did not want to be so blunt in the presence of the Nameless One. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_12993" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13027">It did seem odd to the Cardinal, however, that Don Abbondio had not already come to the same conclusion as himself. His alternative proposal and insistence seemed so inappropriate that he suspected something behind them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13028" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13050">He studied the priest’s face and could easily perceive the man’s fear of traveling with someone as intimidating as the Nameless One and entering his castle even for a few minutes. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13051" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13118">Wanting to dispel that shadow of cowardice, but not wanting to pull the priest to one side and whisper to him in private while his new friend looked on, the Cardinal thought it best to do what he would have done anyway: speak directly to the Nameless One and hope that the man’s replies would make Don Abbondio realize that he was no longer to be feared. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13119" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13152">So, with that spontaneous familiarity that characterizes both a strong new friend and an old intimate, the Cardinal went over to the Nameless One and said, “Don’t go thinking that we’re done for today. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13153" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13162">You will come back, right? In the company of this good priest?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13163" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13178">“Will I be back?” replied the Nameless One. “Even if you rejected me, I would still remain stubbornly at your door, like a beggar. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13179" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13192">I need to speak with you! I need to hear you, to see you! I need you!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13193" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13209">Federigo took his hand, saying, “So you won’t mind staying for dinner with us. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13210" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13210">I’ll be waiting here for you. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13211" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13230">In the meantime, I am going to pray, and offer up thanks with my people, while you go to gather the first fruits of divine mercy.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13231" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13329">Hearing this exchange, Don Abbondio was like a scared child watching a man safely patting his big, growling hound and hearing him say that the animal, with its bloodshot eyes and reputation for biting and terror, is a nice doggy, good boy, good boy. The child looks at the master and neither agrees nor disagrees with him. But he looks at the dog, and doesn’t dare go near, for fear that the pooch will bare its teeth, maybe even take a bite out of him. At the same time, he doesn’t dare retreat, in case people notice. But in his heart, he says, “If only I were home!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13330" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13361">As the Cardinal prepared to leave, still holding the Nameless One’s hand, he noticed the look still on the face of the poor priest, who hung back, mortified, unhappy, and frowning despite himself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13362" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13429">Thinking that maybe he was unhappy because he felt left in a corner and ignored, especially compared to the warm welcome accorded to a violent criminal, the Cardinal stopped for a second, and, turning to him with a loving smile, said, “Reverend Father, you are always with me in the house of the Lord, but this man, ‘He was lost and now he is found.’ ” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13430" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13446">“I couldn’t be happier!” said Don Abbondio, bowing with equal reverence to both men. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13447" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13532">At that, the Archbishop pushed gently on the door. Two footmen manning the other side of the door immediately opened it, and the unusual pair appeared before the curious eyes of the assembled clergy, who witnessed two faces, each flush with different but equally profound emotions: a grateful tenderness and humble joy in the venerable Federigo, while in the Nameless One, a confusion tempered by relief, and a new shame, a compunction, which did not entirely conceal the vigor of his savage and wrathful nature. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13533" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13570">More than one observer would later remark how they were reminded of the verses from the book of Isaiah: “The wolf and the lamb shall feed together, and the lion shall eat straw like the ox” (65:25). </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13571" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13578">They were followed by Don Abbondio, whom no one even noticed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13579" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13624">When they had reached the middle of the room, the Cardinal’s chamberlain entered from the courtyard to report that he had carried out the chaplain’s instructions: The sedan chair and two mules were ready, waiting only for the woman who would comfort Lucia. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13625" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13662">The Cardinal told his chamberlain to instruct the local priest the moment he arrived with the woman, to speak with Don Abbondio, who was leading the expedition together with the Nameless One. Before bidding farewell, he clasped the nobleman’s hand one last time and repeated, “I’ll be waiting for you.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13663" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13676">He turned to salute Don Abbondio and headed toward the church. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13677" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13696">The clergy followed behind, half in a cluster and half in an orderly procession. The two traveling companions were left alone in the room. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13697" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13753">The Nameless One was absorbed in thought, impatient for the moment when he could free his Lucia from her pain and imprisonment. Now she was his, in a very different sense than the day before. His face expressed an intense agitation, which to Don Abbondio’s suspicious eyes could have easily appeared to be something worse. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13754" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13774">He looked at the nobleman out of the corner of his eye and would have liked to start up a friendly conversation, but, “What should I say to him?” he thought. “Should I repeat, ‘I couldn’t be happier’? Happy about what? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13775" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13795">That, after a lifetime of doing the devil’s work, you’ve finally decided to become an honest man like everyone else? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13796" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13814">Some compliment!…No matter how I put it, that’s all my congratulations will end up meaning. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13815" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13827">And how do I know he really has suddenly turned into an honest man, out of the blue! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13828" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13840">Plenty of people put on an act in this world, and for plenty of reasons! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13841" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13845">How am I supposed to know what’s true? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13846" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13856">Meanwhile, I have to accompany him! To that castle! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13857" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13863">What a mess! What a mess! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13864" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13868">If only someone had warned me this morning! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13869" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13924">If I do make it out of this alive, I’ll give an earful to that Perpetua, who forced me to travel so far from my parish for no good reason, saying that all the priests, near and far, were coming here, and I shouldn’t be left out. She went on and on, to get me to embark on this wretched business! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13925" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13927">Poor me! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13928" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13934">Well, I’d still better think of something to say to him.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13935" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13997">After turning it over in his mind again and again, he figured he could try saying, “I hardly expected the good fortune of finding myself in such distinguished company.” He was about to open his mouth when in came the chamberlain with the local priest, who informed them that the woman was waiting in the sedan chair, then turned to Don Abbondio to hear the Cardinal’s additional instructions. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_13998" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14029">Don Abbondio delivered them as best he could in his confused state of mind, after which he approached the chamberlain, saying, “At least give me a tame animal because I’m not much of a horseman, to tell you the truth.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14030" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14046">“You needn’t worry,” the man replied, suppressing a chuckle. “The mule belongs to the secretary, a man of letters.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14047" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14061">“That will have to do,” replied Don Abbondio, while thinking, “God help us.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14062" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14079">Hearing that everything was ready, the Nameless One headed for the door quickly, but then he remembered Don Abbondio, who was lagging behind. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14080" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14114">He stopped to wait for him, and when the priest arrived in a flurry, almost apologetically, he bowed with a courteous and humble gesture, allowing him to go first. This helped to calm the poor priest’s nerves. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14115" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14178">But what he saw the moment he stepped into the courtyard ruined that brief consolation. The Nameless One went to the corner where he had left his carbine, grabbed it by the barrel with one hand and by the strap with the other, and with a brisk, well-practiced motion, slung it over his shoulder. “Oh, no! Oh, no!” thought Don Abbondio. “What does he mean to do with that contraption? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14179" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14184">What kind of sacrifice, of self-mortification, is this for a recent convert? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14185" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14190">What if something makes him lose his temper? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14191" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14197">Oh, what manner of mission is this?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14198" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14252">If the nobleman had any inkling of what was going through his companion’s head, there’s no knowing what he would have done to reassure him. But he was thousands of miles away from suspecting anything, and Don Abbondio was careful to avoid any gesture that might have clearly signified, “I don’t trust you.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14253" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14273">When they got to the road, they found two mules saddled up. The Nameless One mounted the one presented to him by a groom. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14274" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14295">“You’re sure it’s not skittish?” Don Abbondio asked the chamberlain, as he set back on the ground the foot he had just lifted up to the stirrup of his mule. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14296" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14304">“Nothing to worry about; he’s a lamb.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14305" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14317">Don Abbondio tried to climb into the saddle, with the chamberlain’s support. Up, up, up—and he was astride. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14318" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14338">The sedan chair, borne by two more mules, was a few steps ahead of them. At the driver’s command it started to move, and the party was off. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14339" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14366">They had to pass in front of the crowded church, crossing a square that was packed with villagers and travelers who hadn’t been able to get in. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14367" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14411">The great news had already spread, and at the sight of the party, at the sight of that man, the object of hatred and terror only hours before, and now the object of joyful amazement, a murmur of approval arose from the crowd, which opened up before them and pushed forward at the same time to get a better look. The sedan chair passed by. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14412" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14449">The Nameless One passed by. Before the open doors of the church, the nobleman doffed his hat and lowered his feared head all the way down to the mane of the mule, while a hundred voices whispered: “May God bless him!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14450" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14490">Don Abbondio also doffed his hat, bowed, and commended himself to heaven. But when he heard the solemn harmony of his confreres singing in chorus, he felt an envy, a rueful tenderness, and a heartache so deep he struggled to hold back his tears. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14491" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14511">Once they were out of the village and into the open countryside, on winding and often deserted country roads, a darker veil settled over his thoughts. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14512" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14544">Looking about for something or someone to trust, his gaze could only land upon the driver who, as a member of the Cardinal’s household, must be a good man, while also looking well-equipped to defend himself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14545" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14581">Every so often, other travelers would appear, alone or in groups, hurrying to see the Cardinal. Those moments were a relief for Don Abbondio, though only fleeting, since he was headed for that dreaded valley, where the only people he would encounter were his friend’s vassals: and what vassals they were! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n189" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14582" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14610">Now more than ever, he would have preferred to start a conversation with his friend, to get a better sense of him and stay on his good side. But seeing the nobleman so preoccupied, he lost any desire to engage him, and thus was left to his own devices. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n190" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14611" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14640">I will only give you a short sample of what the poor man said to himself on that trip, since to transcribe it all would require a book: </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n191" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14641" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14712">“Both saints and sinners have quicksilver in their veins: Truer words were never said. But while they’re in constant motion themselves, why do they have to drag the rest of us along? And who should the biggest busybody of all set his eyes upon and drag into this but me. Me! A man who minds his own business. Me! When all I want is to be left alone! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n192" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14713" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14718">Then there’s that crazy troublemaker Don Rodrigo! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n193" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14719" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14737">He could be the happiest man in the world if he had a lick of sense. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n194" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14738" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14763">Rich, young, respected, courted: But no, the good life bores him, and he has to go digging up trouble for himself and everyone else. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n195" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14764" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14807">He could be living the high life: But no, he chooses the most insane, rotten, and infuriating profession in the world: harassing women! He could go to heaven in a coach and six: But no, he’d rather limp his way to hell. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n196" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14808" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14846">Not to mention that one…” And here he cast a sidelong glance at “that one,” as if suspecting the man could read his mind. “That one, after setting the world on fire with his crimes, is now setting it on fire with his conversion…If he really did convert! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n197" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14847" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14868">Meanwhile I’m the one who gets stuck testing whether or not it’s true!…Nothing you can do about it: When they’re born with that fire in the belly, all they ever do is raise hell. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n198" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14869" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14880">What’s so hard about living an honest life from childhood, like I have? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n199" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14881" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14900">No, sir: You’d rather maim, murder, maraud. Poor me! And then all that hubbub about repentance. Repentance! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n200" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14901" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14920">If you put your mind to it, you can repent in the peace and quiet of your own home, without fanfare, without bothering your neighbor. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n201" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14921" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14972">And then His Grace, standing there with open arms at the drop of a hat: ‘My dear friend, my dear friend.’ To hear him carrying on, you’d think he’d witnessed a miracle. And then jumping headfirst into a decision, quickly quickly. Well, haste makes waste is what they say where I come from. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n202" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14973" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14994">And then, to hand him over to a poor parish priest, with no precautions! Like flipping a coin to decide a man’s life. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n203" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_14995" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15010">A holy archbishop like him should be more protective of his priests, treat them like the apple of his eye. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n204" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15011" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15036">It wouldn’t hurt his saintliness to practice a little self-control, a little prudence, a little charity, if you ask me…And what if the whole thing is an act? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n205" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15037" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15050">Who knows what transpires in the hearts of men? Especially men like him! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n206" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15051" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15062">And I’m the one that gets stuck accompanying him to his home! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n207" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15063" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15076">Who knows what mischief is behind this: Poor me! Better not think about it! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n208" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15077" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15082">And how did Lucia get mixed up in this mess? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n209" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15083" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15097">Maybe there’s some kind of arrangement with Don Rodrigo. What terrible people! But at least it would explain things. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n210" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15098" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15103">But how did that one get hold of her? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n211" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15104" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15106">Who knows? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n212" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15107" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15126">Everything’s so hush-hush with His Grace. And me, the one they send trotting off—nobody tells me anything. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n213" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15127" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15150">I don’t want to know other people’s business—but if I’m risking my skin, I’ve got every right to know. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n214" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15151" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15161">If all we’re doing is fetching that poor creature, so be it! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n215" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15162" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15168">Although he could have brought her with him the first time. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n216" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15169" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15185">And then, if he has converted, if he has become a holy father, what do they need me for? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n217" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15186" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15188">What a mess! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n218" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15189" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15203">Enough: I pray to God it’s true. It will have been a great bother, but all right. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n219" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15204" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15241">I’ll be happy for poor Lucia’s sake: It must have been a narrow escape. God only knows what she went through. I feel sorry for her, but she’ll be the end of me…If I could only look into his heart and see what he’s thinking. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n220" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15242" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15257">One minute he’s looking like Saint Anthony of the Desert; the next he’s Holofernes in the flesh. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n221" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15258" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15262">Poor me! Poor me! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n222" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15263" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15279">Never mind. Heaven help me, since I didn’t come here just for the fun of it.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n223" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15280" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15313">From the Nameless One’s face, one could, in fact, almost see the thoughts running through his head, the way the clouds pass over the sun in a storm, constantly alternating between an angry light and a cold darkness. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n224" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15314" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15347">His spirit—still intoxicated by Federigo’s soothing words—felt remade and rejuvenated in this new life and ascended to thoughts of mercy, forgiveness, and love; then it fell back under the burden of his sinful past. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n225" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15348" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15385">He reflected anxiously on which of his evil deeds he could repair, and which he could stop short of completing, and which remedies were the quickest and surest, and how to disentangle many knots, and what to do about so many accomplices: The mere thought of it all was staggering. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n226" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15386" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15430">Even on the current expedition, which was the easiest and closest to completion, he proceeded with an impatient distress, worried about how much the poor girl was still suffering, and knowing that he, despite his eagerness to free her, was the cause of it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n227" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15431" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15454">When they came to a fork in the road, the driver turned around to ask directions: The Nameless One pointed the way with his hand, while at the same time gesturing him to hurry up. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n228" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15455" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15457">They entered the valley. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n229" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15458" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15464">Imagine how poor Don Abbondio felt in that moment! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n230" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15465" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15510">To be inside that notorious valley, about which he’d heard such horrible stories. To see the flower of Italian bravi in the flesh and blood: notorious men, fearless and ruthless. To run into one, two, or three at every turn of the road. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n231" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15511" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15538">They bowed submissively to the Nameless One, but what sunburnt faces! What thick mustaches! What nasty stares, which to Don Abbondio seemed to say, “Let’s rough up this priest.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n232" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15539" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15602">So great was his terror that, at its peak, he said to himself, “I wish I had married them! What could be worse than this!” All the while, they advanced along a rocky path beside the river: On the opposite side were harsh, dark, barren cliffs; on the near side, inhabitants that would make any wasteland preferable. He felt like Dante in the lower circles of hell! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n233" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15603" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15618">They passed the Malanotte. Bravi at the door, bows to the lord, curious glances at his fellow traveler and the driver. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n234" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15619" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15640">The men had no idea what to think. The Nameless One’s solitary departure that morning had already been extraordinary and his return now was no less so. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n235" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15641" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15645">Was he leading his prey into a trap? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n236" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15646" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15651">And how had he managed to snare them single-handedly? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n237" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15652" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15656">And why the foreign sedan chair? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n238" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15657" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15663">And whose livery was that? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n239" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15664" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15680">They stared and stared, but not one of them moved, held back by their master’s forbidding glare. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n240" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15681" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15686">They climb the slope. They’re at the top. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n241" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15687" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15771">The bravi guarding the terrace and the gates step back and to the side to let them through. The Nameless One signals to them to stand still. He spurs his mule and passes in front of the sedan chair, signaling to the driver and to Don Abbondio to follow. He enters a first courtyard, then a second. He goes toward a small doorway, gestures “stay back” to a bravo who has run up to hold the stirrup, and tells him, “Stay here, and don’t let anyone in.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n242" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15772" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15805">He dismounts, quickly ties the mule to a railing, goes up to the woman in the sedan chair, who has drawn back the curtain, and whispers, “Try to comfort her immediately. Let her know immediately that she is free and among friends. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n243" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15806" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15810">God will thank you for it!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n244" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15811" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15882">Then he gestures to the driver to open the sedan chair’s door. He turns to Don Abbondio and, with a more serene expression than the priest has ever seen or thought to see, flush with the joy of the good deed he is finally about to perform, whispers to him, “Father, I will not ask your forgiveness for the inconvenience to which I have subjected you. You are doing this for One who will repay you handsomely, and for this poor child of His.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n245" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15883" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15900">At this, he holds the bridle with one hand and the stirrup with the other, to help Don Abbondio dismount. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n246" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15901" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15910">That face, those words, that gesture, restored the priest to life. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n247" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15911" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15934">He let out a sigh of relief that had been building inside him for the last hour without finding a way out. He bowed toward the Nameless One and replied in a low, low voice, “Do you think so? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n248" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15935" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15945">But, but, but…!” and slid off his mount as best he could. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap23-n249" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15946" targetEnd="quarantana/cap23.xml#c23_15986">The Nameless One tethered his mule and told the driver to wait. He took a key from his pocket, unlocked the door, and entered. He ushered in the priest and the woman, leading the way to a staircase, which all three ascended in silence. </note>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>