<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>2022</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed: a novel</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
          <date>2022</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Michael Moore</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="english_2022_cap24">
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10038">Lucia had opened her eyes a short while before, but struggled to fully enter the waking world, to separate the murky visions of sleep from memories and images of a reality that felt like a dire vision of hell. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10039" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10057">The old woman had come over to her immediately to say, in a voice dripping with false humility, “Ah, so, you slept? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10058" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10070">You could’ve slept in the bed, like I told you many times last night.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10071" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10088">Getting no reply, she continued to plead in a tone that barely concealed her annoyance. “Now, come and eat; show some sense. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10089" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10092">You look awful! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10093" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10096">You need to eat something. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10097" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10105">Otherwise he’s going to blame me when he gets back!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10106" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10115">“No, no, I want to leave. I want to go to my mother. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10116" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10123">Your master promised me. He said, ‘tomorrow.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10124" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10126">Where is he now?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10127" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10140">“He’s gone out. He told me he’ll be back soon, and that he’ll do everything you want.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10141" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10146">“He did? He did? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10147" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10155">Good. I want to go to my mother. I want to go now!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10156" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10168">At that very moment, they heard footsteps in the next room, followed by a knock on the door. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10169" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10174">The old woman ran to it and asked, “Who’s there?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10175" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10180">“Open up!” replied a familiar, if more subdued, voice. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10181" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10210">The old woman slid the bolt across the door. The Nameless One pressed lightly upon it to open it just enough for the old woman to leave and Don Abbondio to squeeze in, together with the good matron. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10211" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10243">He then closed the door behind them, and ordered the old woman to a distant corner of the castle, where he had already directed the maid standing guard outside. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10244" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10280">That movement, the waiting, and the appearance of new people all made Lucia even more agitated. Although the present was unbearable, any change became a new source of fear and suspicion. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10281" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10298">She looked up and saw a priest and a woman, which made her feel a little better. She looked more closely—is it him or isn’t it? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10299" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10309">She recognized Don Abbondio and stared at him as if in a trance. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10310" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10340">The woman walked across the room and leaned over Lucia with a look of pity. Taking her hands, a gesture intended to both comfort her and pull her to her feet, she said, “You poor girl. Come, come with us.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10341" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10381">“Who are you?” Lucia asked, and without awaiting a reply, she turned back to Don Abbondio, who was standing a few steps back, he, too, wearing a look of compassion. She stared at him and exclaimed, “You! Is it you, Reverend Father? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10382" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10390">Where are we?…Oh, poor me! I don’t know what’s happening to me!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10391" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10400">“No, no!” replied Don Abbondio. “It really is me. Cheer up. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10401" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10406">Can’t you see? We’ve come to take you away from here. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10407" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10416">I really am your pastor, and I’ve come here for you, on muleback…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10417" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10448">As if all her strength had returned in an instant, Lucia jumped to her feet. Then she stared at those two faces again and said, “Our Blessed Virgin must have sent you.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10449" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10456">“I believe so,” said the good woman. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10457" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10476">“But can we leave here now, can we really leave?” Lucia asked, lowering her voice, with a fearful and suspicious look in her eyes. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10477" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10495">“All those people…?” she continued, her lips drawn, shivering with shock and horror. “And that nobleman! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10496" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10499">That man!…But it’s true, he had promised me…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10500" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10517">“He’s here, too. In person. And he’s come with us for this very purpose,” said Don Abbondio. “He’s waiting outside the door. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10518" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10526">Let’s go quickly and not keep a man like him waiting.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10527" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10589">Just then, the man of whom they were speaking opened the door and showed himself in. Mere minutes before, Lucia, having lost all hope, had wanted to see him and only him. But now, after seeing friendly faces and hearing friendly voices, she could not repress a sudden revulsion. She shuddered, held her breath, hugged the good woman, and buried her face in her bosom. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10590" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10657">When the Nameless One saw the girl whom he could barely look at the night before, the girl whom abstinence and prolonged suffering had made even more distraught, exhausted, and distressed, he stood back from the threshold. At the sight of her terrified gesture, he lowered his eyes and remained silent and motionless for a moment longer. Then, without moving from where he stood, he answered her unspoken question. “It’s true,” he exclaimed, “forgive me!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10658" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10679">“He’s come to free you. He’s no longer the man he used to be. Now he’s good: Don’t you hear him asking you for forgiveness?” the good woman whispered in Lucia’s ear. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10680" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10684">“What more do you want him to say? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10685" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10700">Come now, head up, stop acting like a baby so we can leave quickly,” added Don Abbondio. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10701" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10732">Lucia raised her face, stared at the Nameless One, and, seeing his head bent, his gaze mortified and confused, she was gripped by a mix of relief, gratitude, and pity, and exclaimed, “Oh, sir! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10733" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10739">May God bless you for the mercy you have shown me!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10740" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10752">“And to you, one hundred times over, for the good you are doing me through your words.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10753" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10763">At this, he turned, walked to the door, and was the first to leave. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10764" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10780">Lucia, now fully revived, followed him out with the woman holding her by the arm and Don Abbondio close behind. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10781" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10789">They descended the stairs and reached the door leading to the courtyard. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10790" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10822">The Nameless One held it open, then went to the sedan chair and opened its door; with an almost timid kindness (two qualities quite new to him), he held Lucia by her arm, and helped her and then the good woman to climb in. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10823" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10835">Finally, he untied Don Abbondio’s mule and helped him to remount. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10836" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10852">“Oh, what an honor!” the priest said, and was astride the animal much more quickly than the first time. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10853" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10863">Once the Nameless One was also in his saddle, the small party set out. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10864" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10876">The nobleman’s head was held high, and his gaze had regained its usual imperious expression. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10877" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10902">The bravi he encountered could clearly see signs of deep thought and unusual concern in his face, but they did not understand much more than that—nor was it possible for them to so much as guess. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10903" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10924">For at the castle, they still knew nothing of the great change he had undergone. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10925" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10954">The good woman immediately drew the curtains of the sedan chair. She took Lucia’s hands affectionately and started to comfort her with words of sympathy, tenderness, and congratulations. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_10955" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11006">Seeing how the poor girl had been unable to fully savor the joy of her liberation, due to the confusion and obscurity surrounding it—not to mention her exhaustion after the torments she had suffered—the woman gave the name of the village where they were going, which she thought would calm and settle the poor girl’s thoughts. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11007" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11017">“We are?” said Lucia, who knew how close it was to her home. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11018" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11022">“Oh Blessed Virgin Mary, I give you thanks! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11023" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11026">What about my mother? My mother?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11027" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11045">“We’ll send for her immediately,” said the good woman, not realizing it had already been done. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11046" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11057">“Yes, yes, may God bless you!…And you, who are you? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11058" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11060">How did you get here?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11061" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11141">“I was sent by my own pastor,” answered the good woman, “because this nobleman…God touched his heart (bless the Lord!), and he came to our village to speak with the Cardinal-Archbishop (that saintly man, who is here visiting!). He repented for his sins and said that he wanted to change his ways. He told the Cardinal that he had arranged for the kidnapping of a poor innocent girl—that would be you—in league with another godless man, whose name the priest didn’t disclose.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11142" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11147">Lucia raised her eyes to heaven. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11148" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11193">“Maybe you know who he is,” the good woman continued, “but let’s not think about that just now. The Cardinal felt that, since you are a girl, a female chaperone was needed, and he told the pastor to find someone. And the pastor, out of the goodness of his heart, came to me…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11194" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11201">“Oh! May God reward you for your charity!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11202" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11208">“Whatever do you mean, my poor girl? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11209" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11232">The Reverend Father told me to cheer you up, try to lift your spirits, and make you understand that God saved you through a miracle…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11233" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11240">“Oh, yes! It really was a miracle. Thanks to the intercession of the Blessed Virgin.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11241" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11277">“And he told me that you should rejoice, and forgive the man that harmed you, and be thankful that God worked His mercy on him. Indeed, you should pray for him, too, for that will not only be a credit to you, it will also fill your heart.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11278" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11305">Lucia answered with a gaze sweeter than words could express, a gaze that said yes, as clearly as if she had voiced it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11306" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11351">“Good girl!” continued the woman. “And since your own pastor was also there (priests had come from all over, enough of them to celebrate four high Masses at the same time), the Cardinal decided to send him along, too. But he hasn’t been much help. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11352" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11376">I’d heard he wasn’t much of a man, and now I can see with my own two eyes that he’s as tangled as a cat in a ball of yarn.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11377" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11387">“And that one…” asked Lucia, “that one who has become good…who is he?” “What? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11388" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11398">You don’t know?” said the good woman, and she spoke his name. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11399" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11402">“Lord have mercy!” exclaimed Lucia. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11403" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11425">That name: She’d heard it repeated so many times with horror, and in more than a few of these stories he was always the ogre! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11426" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11477">At the thought of being in his terrifying power before and now being under his merciful protection, at the thought of such a horrible plight and such a sudden redemption, to realize that the gruff, then emotional, then humbled face she had seen belonged to him—she was astonished, saying only, “Lord have mercy!” every now and then. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11478" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11493">“It truly is a great mercy!” said the good woman. “It must be a great relief for half the world. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11494" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11518">To think of how many people he tormented. And now, just like the Reverend Father told me…you can tell by the look on his face that he’s become a saint! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11519" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11525">Not to mention the things he immediately set out to do.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11526" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11554">It would be untrue to say that the good woman was not extremely curious to know every detail of the great adventure in which she was playing a part. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11555" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11609">But to her credit, I should say that, in addition to her respectful sympathy for Lucia, and her sense of the gravity and dignity of her assigned task, it never crossed her mind to ask an idle or indiscreet question; her every word on that trip was of comfort and concern for the poor girl. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11610" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11616">“God only knows the last time you ate!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11617" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11624">“I don’t remember…it’s been a while.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11625" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11625">“Poor thing! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11626" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11629">You need to get your strength back.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11630" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11635">“Yes,” replied Lucia in a faint voice. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11636" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11644">“We’ll find something ready at my house, thank goodness. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11645" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11650">Come now, we’re almost there.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11651" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11671">Lucia let herself collapse against the backrest of the sedan chair, as if to take a nap, and the good woman let her rest. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11672" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11695">For Don Abbondio, the return trip was not nearly as distressing as the way there had been, but it wasn’t exactly pleasant, either. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11696" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11735">His panic was replaced by relief, but a hundred other irritations soon began to crop up in his heart, not unlike the ground where a large tree has been uprooted: It remains bare for a period, but then fills up with weeds. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11736" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11759">He found himself growing more sensitive to everything else, and unfortunately, his thoughts of both the present and the future offered no lack of material with which to torment himself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11760" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11789">He felt the discomfort of traveling in this unaccustomed style more than before, especially during the initial descent from the castle into the valley. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11790" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11870">The sedan driver, urged on by gestures from the Nameless One, had made the animals move at a fast clip, and the two mules followed behind at the same pace. Wherever the incline became steeper, poor Don Abbondio was thrust forward, as if he were being hoisted from behind; he had to hold on to the pommel for dear life just to stay in the saddle. He didn’t dare ask to go slower, however, since he, too, wanted to get away from that area as quickly as possible. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11871" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11959">Whenever they came to an elevation in the road, or an embankment, the mule, true to its nature, would hew to the side, as if out of spite, and place its hooves right along the edge, so when Don Abbondio looked down, he saw a steep drop, or what looked to him like a precipice. “Ah, so you’ve got the same bad habits as your master,” he had a mind to tell the animal, “always looking for trouble rather than taking the easy way!” He yanked the bridle in the opposite direction, but to no avail. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11960" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11974">And so, grumbling with aggravation and fear, he let himself be led, as usual, by the pleasure of others. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_11975" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12021">Now that he had a better sense of their master’s intentions, he was no longer so intimidated by the bravi. “But,” he reflected, “if the news of his big conversion gets out while we’re still in the area, who knows how they might react! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12022" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12025">Anything could happen! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12026" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12037">What if they think I came here to play the missionary! Poor me! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12038" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12082">They’ll turn me into a martyr!” The scowl on the Nameless One’s face didn’t bother him. “That’s exactly what we need to keep these characters at a distance,” he thought. “Even I can see that. But what did I do to deserve such company!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12083" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12094">They reached the bottom of the hill, and at last they left the valley behind. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12095" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12152">The tension slowly drained from the Nameless One’s face, and Don Abbondio also came to wear a more natural expression. He pulled his head out from between his shoulders, stretched his arms and legs, and started to sit up straighter in the saddle, looking like a new man. With an easier spirit, he took deeper breaths and started to contemplate other, more distant dangers. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12153" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12159">“What will that brute Don Rodrigo have to say? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12160" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12180">With his nose out of joint, the damage to his reputation, and everyone jeering at him, I can imagine how badly he’s going to react to this news. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12181" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12187">I’ve no doubt he’ll get even worse. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12188" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12205">Just you wait, he’s going to take it out on me, since I got stuck in the middle of this pageant. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12206" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12231">And if he had the courage to send those two devils to accost me on the road before, who knows what he’s got in store for me now! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12232" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12253">He can’t take it out on your illustrious self, who’s a much bigger fish than he’ll ever be. No, he’ll have to hold his tongue. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12254" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12265">But the venom will be in his veins, and he’ll have to unleash it on someone! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12266" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12269">I know how these scores get settled. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12270" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12278">And it’s always the weak that have to pay the piper. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12279" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12310">His Grace is right to get Lucia out of harm’s way. And that other poor hapless soul is safe and sound and has already been punished enough. Which leaves me. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12311" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12329">Wouldn’t it be cruel, after all the trials and tribulations I’ve gone through—without getting any credit for them—if I had to pay the piper? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12330" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12342">What would His Grace do to defend me then, after dragging me into this? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12343" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12357">Can he guarantee that the hellion isn’t saving his worst for me? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12358" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12370">But he’s got so much on his mind, a finger in every pot! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12371" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12376">How can he keep an eye on everything? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12377" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12386">Sometimes those do-gooders leave things even more tangled up than before. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12387" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12443">They only see the big picture; once they feel a little satisfaction, they move on, and don’t want the trouble of dealing with the consequences. But the evildoers are much more diligent. They’re relentless; they follow everything to the bitter end, like they have a canker gnawing at them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12444" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12464">“Will I have to argue that I did not come here of my own free will but at the express command of his Illustrious Grace? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12465" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12471">Then it will look as if I was taking the side of evil. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12472" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12474">Heaven help me! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12475" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12478">Me, on the side of evil? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12479" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12485">For the sheer fun of it? Enough! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12486" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12523">I think it’d be best to tell Perpetua the whole story and let her spread it around. As long as it doesn’t strike His Grace’s fancy to publicize the event and make a useless scene by tossing my name in the mix! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12524" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12556">“For good measure, as soon as we arrive, if he’s already left the church, I’ll go find him to pay my respects very quickly. Or else I could convey my excuses and go straight home. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12557" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12576">Lucia is in good hands and doesn’t need me anymore. And after all this trouble, I’ve got a right to some rest, too. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12577" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12599">And then…I pray His Grace doesn’t suddenly get a hankering to hear the entire story and expect me to account for the business of that marriage! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12600" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12603">That’s the last thing we need! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12604" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12612">What if he pays a visit to my parish?…Oh! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12613" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12627">We’ll deal with that when the time comes. I don’t want to get myself all worked up before I have to. I’m in enough trouble as it is. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12628" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12634">For now, I’m going to shut myself up in my house. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12635" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12650">As long as His Grace is in these parts, Don Rodrigo won’t dare do anything crazy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12651" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12654">But after that?…After that? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12655" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12666">Ah! I can see that my final years are not going to be easy!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12667" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12694">In fact, the church services were not yet over when the party arrived. They passed back through the crowd, which was no less excited than before, and then they split up. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12695" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12722">The two men on mules turned in to a small piazza to the side, at the far end of which the pastor’s house was located. The sedan chair continued on to the home of the good woman. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12723" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12755">Don Abbondio followed through with his plan. As soon as he dismounted, he complimented the Nameless One lavishly and asked him to convey his apologies to the Cardinal, since he had to return to his parish on urgent business. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12756" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12777">He went looking for his “horse,” as he called it—the walking stick he had left in a corner of the room—and set off on foot. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12778" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12787">The Nameless One, for his part, waited for the Cardinal to return from church. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12788" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12821">The good woman, having seated Lucia in the best spot in her kitchen, was busy preparing something to restore her strength, shrugging off, with a certain rustic cordiality, the thanks and apologies that Lucia kept offering. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12822" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12854">Quickly quickly, she rekindled the fire beneath a kettle in which a nice capon was floating. She brought the stock to a boil and then poured some into a bowl filled with hunks of bread, which she at last presented to Lucia. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12855" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12890">As she watched the poor girl revive with each spoonful, she congratulated herself aloud that the event had taken place on a day when, in her words, there was something on the hearth besides the cat. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12891" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12924">“Today, everyone’s doing their best to scrounge up some food,” she said, and added, “except those who are so poor that they struggle even to put together a loaf of vetch bread and a bowl of millet polenta. But today everyone’s hoping to receive something from such a charitable nobleman. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12925" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12947">Thank heavens we’re not in that condition; between my husband’s trade and a little plot of land we have, we manage to get by. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12948" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12965">So go ahead and eat to your heart’s content, for soon the capon will be ready and you can have something a little more substantial.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12966" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12975">With that, the good woman went back to getting the meal ready and setting the table. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_12976" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13015">Lucia, her forces partially restored and her spirits settling, began fixing herself up out of a force of habit and a penchant for neatness and modesty: She combed and pinned back her loose, tangled hair and rearranged the kerchief over her breast and around her neck. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13016" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13065">As she did, her fingers brushed against the rosary she had placed around her neck the night before. She looked down at it, and in an instant, she was robbed of her composure. The memory of her vow, repressed and stifled by the many other sensations surrounding her, was suddenly resuscitated, appearing before her clearly and distinctly. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13066" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13108">All her newly revived mental faculties were once again overwhelmed. Were it not that a life of innocence, resignation, and faith had fortified her spirits, the remorse she felt in that moment would have given way to despair. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13109" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13135">After the rush of thoughts preceding language, the first words to form in her mind were, “Woe is me, what have I done!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13136" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13145">But that thought, too, renewed her feeling of shock. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13146" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13178">She recalled all the circumstances of the vow—the unbearable distress, the little hope she had of being rescued, the fervor of her prayers, and the depth of feeling with which she had made that promise. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13179" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13229">To regret that promise, after benefiting from its grace, seemed sacrilegious and ungrateful, a betrayal of both God and the Virgin Mary. Such an act of treachery would invite new and more terrifying misfortunes from which not even prayer could protect her. And so she hastened to take back that momentary regret. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13230" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13281">With a devout gesture, she removed the rosary from around her neck, and holding it in her trembling hand, confirmed and renewed her vow while asking, in a heartfelt entreaty, to be granted the strength to keep her promise, and be free of the thoughts and occasions that might overly agitate or shake her resolve. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13282" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13330">Her separation from Renzo (who had no likelihood of returning)—a separation that until this moment had been so bitter—now appeared to be an act of Providence, which had made the two circumstances coincide to serve a single purpose. So she tried to find in the first some reason to accept the second. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13331" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13374">This led her to imagine that Providence, to complete its work, would also find a way for Renzo to resign himself and stop thinking about her…But the moment this idea occurred to her, it threw into disarray the very mind that had sought it out. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13375" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13415">Poor Lucia, feeling that her heart was on the verge of regret, returned to her prayers, to the confirmations and the struggle, after which she stood up—if I may be allowed this expression—like a tired, wounded victor over a vanquished (but not killed) enemy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13416" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13428">Suddenly, there was a scampering of feet and a riot of happy voices. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13429" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13435">It was the good woman’s little family coming back from church. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13436" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13491">Two girls and a boy came bounding in. They stopped for a moment to take a curious look at Lucia, then ran to their mother and huddled around her. One of them asked the how and why of the strange guest and her name. Another wanted to talk about the amazing things she had seen. The good matron answered each and every child with “hush, hush.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13492" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13510">Then in came the master of the house, at a more serene pace, but with a face colored with polite concern. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13511" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13585">He was, if I have neglected to mention it, the tailor for the village and the surrounding areas, a man who knew how to read and had, in fact, read—and more than once—The Golden Legend, The Matter of France, and Wretched Guerrin and was reputed to be, in those parts, a man of talent and science. He rebuffed such praise modestly, saying only that he had picked the wrong vocation, and if he, rather than many others, had pursued his studies…! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13586" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13592">Still, he was a peach of a man. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13593" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13626">Having been present when the parish priest had asked his wife to go on the mission of mercy, he had not only given her his approval but also—as if it were necessary—his encouragement. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13627" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13674">Now that the Mass, the pomp, the crowds, and, especially, the Cardinal’s sermon had made him feel even more exuberant, he returned home with the anxious desire to know how the expedition had gone, and the expectation of finding the poor innocent victim safe and sound. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13675" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13700">“Look who’s here,” the good woman said to him as he entered, nodding toward Lucia. The girl blushed and stood up, starting to mumble her apologies. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13701" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13714">Crossing the room to her, the tailor interrupted Lucia with a warm greeting, exclaiming, “Welcome! Welcome! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13715" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13722">You bring the blessings of heaven into this house. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13723" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13728">I’m so happy to have you here! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13729" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13758">I already knew you would arrive safely, because I have never found anything in my books about God beginning a miracle without completing it. I’m so happy to see you here. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13759" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13760">Poor girl! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13761" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13770">But it is such a wonderful thing to have benefited from a miracle!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13771" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13809">Now don’t go thinking he was the only one describing what had happened as a miracle because he had read The Golden Legend. The whole town and district would go on to describe it in the same terms for as long as it was remembered. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13810" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13826">And, to be honest, there really was no better word for the yarns embroidered onto the story in the years to come. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13827" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13846">Going over to his wife, who was lifting the kettle off the chain, he whispered, “Did everything go well?” “Couldn’t have gone better. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13847" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13851">I’ll tell you about it later.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13852" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13855">“Yes, yes. As soon as you’re ready.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13856" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13899">After resting the kettle, she went to Lucia and accompanied her to the table, where she sat her down. Breaking off a wing of the capon, she placed it before her. She and her husband also sat down, and they both encouraged their shy and despondent guest to eat. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13900" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13936">From his first bites, the tailor started to hold forth in emphatic tones, amid the frequent interruptions of the children, who were also eating around the table and had, in truth, seen too many extraordinary things to be a captive audience for very long. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13937" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13947">He described the solemn ceremony, then skipped ahead to talk about the miraculous conversion. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13948" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13966">But the thing that had made the biggest impression on him was the Cardinal’s sermon, to which he kept referring. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13967" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13980">“To see him, a true aristocrat, before the altar, as if he were a simple parish priest…” he said. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13981" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13991">“And with that gold thing he wore on his head,” said one of the little girls. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13992" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13993">“Shush! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_13994" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14047">To think, I was saying, how a nobleman like that, and such a wise man, who, from what I hear, has read every book in creation, which no one else has ever done before, not even in Milan. To think that he can simplify things in a way that everyone can understand…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14048" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14053">“I understood, too,” said another little chatterbox. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14054" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14060">“Oh, you did? What did you understand, now? Shush!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n189" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14061" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14071">“I understood that he explained the Gospel rather than our pastor.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n190" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14072" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14073">“Shush! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n191" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14074" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14102">I’m not talking about people who know things: They’re supposed to understand! I’m saying that even the thickest—the most ignorant—could follow his sermon. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n192" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14103" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14125">If you asked them to repeat exactly what he said, they wouldn’t be able to fish out a word. But they have the feeling inside. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n193" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14126" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14139">And though he never mentioned that certain nobleman by name, he was obviously talking about him! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n194" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14140" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14152">All you had to do to understand was see the tears in his eyes. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n195" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14153" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14159">And then everyone started crying…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n196" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14160" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14175">“They really did,” the boy burst out. “But why were they all crying that way, like babies?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n197" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14176" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14177">“Shush! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n198" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14178" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14187">There sure are some hard hearts in this town. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n199" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14188" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14216">But he really showed us that, even if there is a famine, we still have to thank God and be happy. Do what we can, work hard, help one another, and then be happy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n200" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14217" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14233">Because it’s no disgrace to suffer or be poor. It’s a disgrace to do evil. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n201" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14234" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14268">And this is not just idle talk. Because we know that he himself lives like a poor man, and he’d take the bread from his own plate to feed the hungry. When he, more than anyone you can think of, could be living in the lap of luxury. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n202" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14269" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14290">Ah, and it is such a pleasure to hear him speak, not like so many others with their ‘Do what I say, not what I do.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n203" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14291" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14316">And then he made us see that, even those who aren’t aristocrats, if they have more than they require, then they should share with those in need.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n204" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14317" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14327">Here, he interrupted himself, as if struck by a thought. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n205" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14328" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14364">He sat still for a moment, then he put together a plate of the food that was on the table and, after adding a piece of bread, placed it on a napkin; taking it by its four corners, he said to the oldest girl, “Here, take this.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n206" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14365" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14393">In her other hand, he placed a flask of wine, and added, “Go to the widow Maria’s. Leave her this bundle and tell her it’s so she can enjoy some happiness with her children. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n207" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14394" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14406">But politely, mind you, so it doesn’t look like charity. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n208" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14407" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14418">And don’t say a word if you run into anyone. And watch that you don’t drop it.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n209" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14419" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14450">Tears came to Lucia’s eyes, and in her heart she felt a soothing tenderness, like the relief she had received from the spontaneous remarks earlier that a more deliberate speech would never have imparted. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n210" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14451" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14491">Her spirit was lifted by his descriptions of the visions of splendor and the surges of piety and wonder. She was captivated by the enthusiasm of the storyteller himself and forgot her own sad thoughts. Even when she returned to them, she felt stronger and better able to resist them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n211" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14492" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14519">The thought of her great sacrifice had not lost its bitter taste, but now it was associated with a vague feeling of solemn and austere joy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n212" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14520" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14556">Soon after, the village priest came by to say that the Cardinal had sent him to inquire after Lucia and inform her that His Grace wished to see her that very day, and to convey his thanks to the tailor and his wife. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n213" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14557" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14574">The two of them, excited and confused, could not find the words to reciprocate such pronouncements from such a personage. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n214" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14575" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14586">“Has your mother arrived yet?” the priest asked Lucia. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n215" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14587" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14590">“My mother!” she exclaimed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n216" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14591" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14624">When she heard that Agnese had been sent for, by order of the Archbishop, Lucia placed her apron over her eyes and burst into tears. She continued crying long after the priest had left. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n217" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14625" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14700">When the tumultuous feelings stirred in her by that announcement started to yield to more sedate thoughts, the poor girl remembered that the happiness of seeing again her mother, who was now so near—a happiness that had seemed impossible only a few hours earlier—is what she had expressly prayed for during those terrible hours, and made almost the condition of her vow. “Return me safely to my mother,” she had said; and now she remembered these words clearly. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n218" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14701" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14734">Her resolve to keep her promise was now even firmer, and she regretted once again, more bitterly this time, that “poor me!” which had initially escaped her lips. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n219" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14735" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14745">Agnese was, in fact, already nearby, even as they spoke of her. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n220" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14746" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14797">It is easy to imagine how the poor woman had felt upon receiving that unexpected invitation and learning the news—necessarily incomplete and confusing—of the danger her daughter had faced, now past but still horrifying. The messenger could neither describe in detail nor explain the whole terrible business. All Agnese could do was attempt to explain it to herself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n221" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14798" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14846">After running her hands through her hair, after shouting repeatedly, “Oh Lord! Oh Blessed Virgin!” after peppering the messenger with questions that he could not answer, she climbed into the cart in a fury, and continued to exclaim and ask questions without getting any answers for the entire ride. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n222" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14847" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14867">At one point, however, she ran into Don Abbondio, who was moving slowly slowly, setting his walking stick ahead of himself with each step. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n223" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14868" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14897">After an “oh!” from both parties, he stopped, she ordered the cart to stop, and she got out. They stepped into a chestnut grove alongside the road. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n224" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14898" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14910">Don Abbondio reported what he had been able to learn and was forced to witness. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n225" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14911" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14928">His story was unclear, but Agnese was at least reassured that Lucia was safe and sound. She breathed a sigh of relief. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n226" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14929" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14972">Don Abbondio wanted to bring up another subject and give her elaborate instructions on how to behave with the Archbishop, if, as was likely, he wished to speak with her and her daughter. The main thing was to avoid any mention of the marriage. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n227" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14973" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_14999">But Agnese, well aware that the good man was only pursuing his own interests, left him standing there without making any promises, and indeed without deciding anything, for she had more important matters on her mind. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n228" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15000" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15004">And she continued on her way. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n229" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15005" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15015">Finally, the cart reached its destination and stopped in front of the tailor’s house. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n230" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15016" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15029">Lucia jumped up from her chair. Agnese stepped down from the cart and raced inside. In a second, they were in each other’s arms. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n231" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15030" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15098">The tailor’s wife, the only other person there, comforted the two women, calmed them down, rejoiced with them, and then, discreet as ever, left them alone, saying she would prepare their bed, something she could easily manage by herself. Besides, both she and her husband would rather sleep on the floor than make their guests seek shelter elsewhere. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n232" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15099" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15120">After the first outpouring of hugs and tears, Agnese wanted to know everything that had happened to Lucia, who proceeded to tell her the painful story. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n233" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15121" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15143">As the reader knows all too well, it was a story that no one person knew in its entirety. Even for Lucia, there were obscure and altogether inexplicable parts. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n234" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15144" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15187">Chief among them, the fatal coincidence of that ominous carriage on the road at the very moment that she was passing by on a special errand. Mother and daughter ventured a hundred guesses without ever hitting the mark, or even getting close. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n235" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15188" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15209">As for the chief author of the plot, neither one of them could think of anyone except Don Rodrigo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n236" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15210" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15225">“That black soul! That outcast from hell!” exclaimed Agnese. “But his hour will soon be up. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n237" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15226" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15236">The Good Lord will make him pay for what he’s done, and then he’ll know what it’s like to…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n238" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15237" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15251">“No, Mother, no!” interrupted Lucia. “Don’t wish suffering on him, don’t wish it on anyone! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n239" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15252" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15256">If you knew what it means to suffer! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n240" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15257" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15259">If you had felt it! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n241" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15260" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15296">No, no! Let us instead pray to God and to the Blessed Virgin for him, so that God may touch his heart, as he did the heart of that other poor nobleman, who used to be even worse and is now a saint.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n242" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15297" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15338">More than once the revulsion Lucia felt in reviving such fresh and cruel memories made her hesitate. More than once, shedding tears, she struggled to find the strength and words to continue. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n243" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15339" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15355">But a different feeling restrained her at one point in her tale: the vow. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n244" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15356" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15461">She was afraid that her mother would accuse her of being rash and impulsive, and that, as in the attempted marriage, she would trot out one of her lax rules of conscience and demand that Lucia go along with it. Or that the poor woman would confide in someone, if only to solicit other ideas and advice, and in so doing make Lucia’s vow public; at the mere thought of this Lucia could feel her face turning red. She also sensed some embarrassment on her mother’s part, an inexplicable reluctance to bring up the subject. All of these things together made Lucia hide that important detail, and she resolved to confide first in Fra Cristoforo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n245" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15462" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15491">So imagine how she felt when, asking after him, she learned that he was gone, sent to a place far, far away, a town with a strange-sounding name! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n246" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15492" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15495">“Shall we talk about Renzo?” asked Agnese. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n247" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15496" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15503">“He’s safe, isn’t he?” replied Lucia anxiously. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n248" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15504" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15537">“That much is certain, since everyone says so. They’re all sure that he’s taken refuge near Bergamo, but exactly where, no one knows. And so far, he hasn’t sent word. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n249" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15538" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15544">Maybe he hasn’t found a way yet.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n250" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15545" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15574">“Ah, if he’s safe, thank God!” said Lucia. She was trying to change the subject when they were interrupted by a surprise: the appearance of the Cardinal-Archbishop. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n251" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15575" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15637">On his return from church, where we had left him, he heard from the Nameless One that Lucia had arrived, safe and sound. He had then invited the nobleman to join him at the table, and seated him to his right, in a circle of priests who couldn’t stop staring at him—his demeanor so tame yet strong, so humble yet domineering—and comparing him to the image long held in their minds. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n252" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15638" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15647">Once they had finished eating, the two men withdrew together. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n253" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15648" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15688">After a conversation that went on much longer than their earlier talk, the Nameless One departed for his castle on the same mule he had ridden that morning. And the Cardinal, summoning the local priest, told him that he wanted to be taken to the house where Lucia was staying. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n254" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15689" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15724">“Oh, Your Grace,” the priest replied. “No need to trouble yourself. I’ll immediately send word to the girl to come here with her mother, if she’s arrived, as well as her hosts, if Your Grace so wishes. Everyone whom Your Illustrious Grace wishes to see.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n255" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15725" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15732">“What I wish is to go and visit them myself,” Federigo replied. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n256" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15733" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15778">“No need for Your Illustrious Grace to trouble himself. I’ll send for them immediately, it will only take a moment,” insisted the meddling priest (an otherwise good man), not realizing that the purpose of the visit was for the Cardinal to pay homage, at the same time, to misfortune, innocence, hospitality, and his own ministry. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n257" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15779" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15793">But after his superior had repeated his wish once more, the subordinate bowed and led the way. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n258" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15794" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15831">When the two men appeared on the road, all the people gathered there stepped forward to meet them, and soon more people came running from every direction, getting as close as they could, right next to or right behind them, rough and tumble. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n259" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15832" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15841">The priest kept saying, “Get back! Make room! Enough now!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n260" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15842" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15868">“Let them be,” Federigo told him, and went forward, one moment raising his hand in blessing, and lowering it the next to pat the heads of the children underfoot. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n261" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15869" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15881">In this way, they reached the house and entered, while the crowd swelled outside. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n262" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15882" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15911">In their midst was the tailor, who had followed the crowd like the others, with his eyes peeled and his mouth agape, not knowing where everyone was headed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n263" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15912" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15935">When he saw that unexpected destination, he made his way—you can imagine how boisterously—shouting repeatedly, “Make way for a man who’s got to get through,” and in he went. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n264" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15936" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15958">Agnese and Lucia heard a rumble from the street getting louder. As they wondered what it could possibly be, the door opened and in walked the Cardinal and the local priest. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n265" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15959" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15989">“Is she the one?” the first asked the second, and at an affirmative nod, he went to Lucia, who was standing stock-still next to her mother. Both women were struck with surprise and embarrassment, unable to speak or move. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n266" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_15990" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16007">But Federigo’s soft voice, his appearance, demeanor, and especially his words immediately set them at ease. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n267" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16008" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16036">“Poor girl,” he began. “God has put you to a great test, but He has also shown that He has never stopped watching over you, and never forgotten you. He returned you to safety. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n268" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16037" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16062">And He has made you His instrument to perform a great deed, to foster a great act of mercy for one, while at the same time edifying the many.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n269" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16063" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16107">The mistress of the house appeared. At the sounds from the street, she, too, had looked out the window, and, seeing who was coming toward her house, had fixed herself up as best she could before running down the stairs. The tailor entered through the back door at almost the same time. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n270" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16108" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16122">Seeing the conversation well underway, the husband and wife withdrew to the corner at a respectful distance. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n271" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16123" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16155">After greeting them courteously, the Cardinal continued to speak with the mother and daughter, inserting an occasional question into his words of comfort, to see if their answers might give him an opportunity to perform an act of kindness for one who had suffered so much. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n272" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16156" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16233">“All priests should be like Your Grace, and take the side of the poor rather than getting them in trouble, and then leaving them to fend for themselves,” said Agnese, excited by the familiar and loving demeanor of Federigo, and vexed at the thought of Don Abbondio, who always sacrificed others, then tried to keep them from venting their feelings or taking their complaints to someone higher up, when, through a rare circumstance, the opportunity arose. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n273" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16234" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16244">“Please, speak your mind,” said the Cardinal. “Speak freely.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n274" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16245" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16263">“I mean to say that if our pastor had done his duty, none of this would ever have happened.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n275" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16264" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16301">At the Cardinal’s insistence that she explain herself, Agnese began to stumble over her words in the telling of a story in which she herself had played a part she would rather not disclose, especially to such a personage. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n276" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16302" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16348">Still, she managed to find a way, through a tiny omission. She talked about the planned marriage, the refusal of Don Abbondio—without leaving out the “my superiors won’t have it” excuse he had used (ah, Agnese!)—and then she skipped ahead to Don Rodrigo’s attempted kidnapping, and how, having been forewarned, they had managed to escape. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n277" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16349" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16358">“But then,” she added and concluded, “we escaped only to run into new troubles. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n278" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16359" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16397">If our pastor had told us the truth instead, and married my poor children, we would have left town immediately, all three of us, in secret, and gone far away, to a place that not even the winds would know. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n279" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16398" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16408">As it is, we wasted time, and what happened, happened.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n280" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16409" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16420">“Your priest will have to account to me for his behavior,” said the Cardinal. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n281" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16421" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16460">“No, Your Grace, please,” Agnese hastened to say. “That’s not the reason why I told you all this. Please don’t reprimand him. What’s done is done. Besides, what good would it do? If it happened again, he’d do the same thing.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n282" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16461" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16492">But Lucia, unhappy with her mother’s version of the story, added, “We were also partly to blame. It was clearly not God’s will that we should be married.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n283" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16493" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16502">“Poor child, how could you possibly be to blame?” asked Federigo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n284" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16503" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16536">Lucia, despite the warning looks her mother was secretly casting her way, told the story of their attempted marriage at Don Abbondio’s house, and she concluded by saying, “We were wrong, and God has punished us.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n285" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16537" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16572">“Accept from His hand the pains you have suffered, and go in peace,” said Federigo, “for no one has more reason to rejoice and to hope than those who have suffered and take the blame upon themselves.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n286" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16573" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16611">He then asked for the whereabouts of her fiancé, and on hearing from Agnese (Lucia remained silent, lowering her head and eyes) that he had fled the village, he was visibly surprised and saddened, and wanted to know why. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n287" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16612" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16624">Agnese told him what little she knew of Renzo’s story. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n288" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16625" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16656">“I have heard talk of him,” said the Cardinal. “But how could a boy who’s implicated in that sort of thing be engaged to a girl like her?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n289" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16657" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16670">“He was a good boy,” said Lucia, with a blushing face but a steady voice. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n290" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16671" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16691">“He was a quiet boy, almost too quiet,” added Agnese. “Ask anyone, including our priest. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n291" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16692" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16700">Who knows what kind of mischief, what kind of intrigues, they cooked up down there in Milan? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n292" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16701" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16709">It doesn’t take much to pass a poor man off as a criminal.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n293" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16710" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16737">“Unfortunately, you’re right,” said the Cardinal. “I’ll see what I can find out about him, I promise,” and he took down the boy’s first and last name in his notebook. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n294" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16738" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16780">He went on to say that he planned to visit her village in a few days, by which point Lucia should have no reason to fear returning there. In the meantime, he would make sure she had a safe place to stay until everything had been arranged. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n295" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16781" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16791">He then turned to the master and mistress of the house, who came forward immediately. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n296" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16792" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16819">He renewed the words of gratitude he had conveyed through the priest, and asked whether they wouldn’t mind providing shelter for a few days to the guests that God had sent them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n297" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16820" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16843">“Oh, yes, Your Grace,” answered the woman, with a voice and a face that expressed far more than that curt reply, choked as it was by her embarrassment. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n298" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16844" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16869">But her husband, dumbstruck by the presence of such a questioner, and the wish to distinguish himself on such an important occasion, struggled to formulate a memorable response. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n299" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16870" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16920">He furrowed his brow, squinted his eyes, pursed his lips, strained the arc of his intellect with all his might, and sought, rummaged, and groped his way through a clutter of half-baked ideas and broken words. But time was running out. The Cardinal indicated that he understood the silence. The poor man opened his mouth, and all that came out was, “Think nothing of it!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n300" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16921" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16925">Which is all he could think to say. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n301" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16926" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16947">As a result, not only was he mortified in the moment, but that awkward memory would return to spoil the pleasure of the great honor received for many years to come. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n302" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16948" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16991">And how many times, thinking back and reflecting on that circumstance, did he come up with, almost out of spite, any number of words that would have been superior to that inane “Think nothing of it!” But, as an old proverb says, you could fill the ditches with hindsight. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n303" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_16992" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17003">Then the Cardinal left, saying, “May the blessing of the Lord be upon this house.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n304" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17004" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17029">That evening, he asked the village priest the most appropriate way to compensate the tailor—who could not have been rich—for a hospitality that had to be costly, especially in times like these. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n305" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17030" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17111">The priest replied that neither the earnings from his trade nor the income from some plots of land that the good tailor owned would have allowed him to be generous with others after this year’s harvest. However, in truth, since he had set aside the surplus from the previous year, he was better off than most of his neighbors, and could easily handle some added expenses, and would certainly be happy to do so. Not to mention that he would never accept any payment for the favor. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n306" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17112" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17123">“In all likelihood,” said the Cardinal, “he has some people in his debt who can’t afford to pay?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n307" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17124" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17149">“These poor people usually pay with their surpluses from the harvest, Your Grace. But last year nothing was left over, so everyone has far less than what they need.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n308" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17150" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17176">“Well, then,” said Federigo, “I will take care of those debts myself. And you will do me the favor of getting the promissory notes from him and settling the unpaid accounts.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n309" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17177" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17180">“It will be a considerable sum.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n310" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17181" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17199">“All the better. Unfortunately, you will also find some people who are too poor to have debts since they have no credit.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n311" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17200" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17202">“Unfortunately is right! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n312" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17203" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17218">One does what one can: But how can we take care of everything in times like these?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n313" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17219" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17229">“Draw the amount from my account and reimburse the tailor well. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n314" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17230" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17248">In a year like this, anything that’s not spent on food must seem excessive. But this is a special case.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n315" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17249" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17264">I would not want to conclude the story of that day without giving you a brief account of how the Nameless One ended his own. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n316" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17265" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17291">Word of his conversion had preceded his return to the valley. The news had traveled fast indeed, spreading shock, apprehension, torment, and grumbling. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n317" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17292" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17310">He indicated to the first bravi or servants (one and the same) he encountered that they should follow him home, and he repeated this order every step of the way. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n318" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17311" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17331">The bravi followed behind, with the usual deference and a new uncertainty. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n319" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17332" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17378">When the Nameless One and his ever-growing entourage reached the castle, he signaled to the men at the gate to fall in behind the others. He entered the first courtyard, went to its center, and there, astride his mule, let out a thunderous shout. It was the customary signal for everyone within earshot to come running. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n320" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17379" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17400">Those who had been scattered throughout the castle obeyed instantly, joining the others who were already gathered; all gazed up at the master. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n321" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17401" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17418">“Meet me in the reception hall,” he told everyone and watched them disperse from the height of his steed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n322" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17419" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17431">Then he dismounted, led his mule into the stall by himself, and went to where he was awaited. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n323" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17432" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17460">The hubbub filling the hall died down the moment he appeared. Everyone moved to the side—they numbered about thirty in all—clearing a large space for him in the middle of the room. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n324" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17461" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17490">The Nameless One raised his hand, as if to hold that sudden silence. He lifted his head, which towered above all the others, and spoke: “Everyone, listen, and let no one speak unless called upon! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n325" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17491" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17503">My children! The road on which we have journeyed so far will lead to the depths of hell. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n326" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17504" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17527">It is not my wish to criticize you, I, who am the prime, the worst offender. But hear what I have to say. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n327" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17528" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17546">God in His mercy has called upon me to change my ways. I shall, and I already have: May He do the same for all of you. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n328" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17547" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17567">Know, then, and hold it for certain that I have decided I would rather die than disobey His holy law. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n329" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17568" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17593">I release each one of you from the criminal commissions you have received from me. Do you understand me? Indeed, I order you not to carry them out. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n330" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17594" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17614">And make no mistake: From now on, no one will be allowed to do wrong under my protection and in my service. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n331" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17615" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17653">Whoever wishes to remain with me under these conditions will be like a son to me. And at the end of the day, I would be happy to know that even the least of you has had his fill, down to the last crust of bread in the house, before I myself have eaten. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n332" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17654" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17694">For those of you who do not want this, you will receive all the wages owed you, and also a gift. You are free to leave, but you can no longer set foot in this house unless it is to change your ways, in which case I will welcome you back with open arms. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n333" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17695" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17714">You have tonight to think this over. Tomorrow morning, I shall summon you, one by one, to hear your answer. And then I will give new orders. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n334" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17715" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17721">For now, retire, each man to his station. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n335" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17722" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17735">And may God, who has shown me such mercy, guide your thoughts.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n336" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17736" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17762">At this he stopped, and everyone remained in silence, giving no outward appearance of the turbulent thoughts that might have been seething in their criminal minds. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n337" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17763" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17799">They were used to hearing their master’s voice as the expression of a will that was not to be questioned. And that voice, announcing his change of heart, gave no indication of weakness. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n338" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17800" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17823">It did not occur to anyone to take advantage of his conversion and answer him as they would an ordinary man. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n339" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17824" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17846">In him, they saw a saint, but one of those saints depicted with their heads held high and a sword in their fist. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n340" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17847" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17905">Apart from their fear, they were, as his lieges, fond of him (especially those—the majority—who had been born on his estate). Their admiration filled them with goodwill, and in his presence, they felt what I would call the deference that even the most loutish and petulant feel before a man they recognize as their superior. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n341" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17906" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17960">So although the words they had just heard from his mouth were hostile to their ears, they did not ring false or strange. While in the past his men might have made fun of such ideas a thousand times, it was not from disbelief but rather to deflect through humor the fear that would have gripped them if they had taken them seriously. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n342" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17961" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17994">And now, seeing the effect of that same fear in a man like their master, there was not a single person unaffected, some more, some less, at least for a good while. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n343" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_17995" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18045">The men who had found themselves outside of the valley that morning were the first to hear the great news. Together they had witnessed, and then reported, the joy and the fresh confidence of the people, the love and the veneration for the Nameless One that had penetrated what had once been a place of old hatred and old fear. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n344" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18046" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18099">To their amazement, they now saw the man whom they alone had always looked up to as the idol of the multitude. They still saw him as superior to others, but in a very different—though no lesser—degree than before; still towering over the common horde, still a leader among men. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n345" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18100" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18109">So there they all stood, dumbfounded, each uncertain of the other, and each uncertain of himself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n346" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18110" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18177">Some grumbled, some started to plan where they would seek shelter and employment. Some thought about whether they were capable of adapting to life as honest men. But there were also some who, touched by his words, felt a certain inclination. And some, without coming to a decision, planned to promise him anything, just to be on the safe side, all while devouring the bread offered so wholeheartedly—which was so scarce in those days. And to buy time no one breathed a word. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n347" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18178" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18208">When the Nameless One, at the end of his speech, once again raised his imperious hand to signal that they should leave the room, they all filed out together, quietly quietly, like a herd of sheep. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n348" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18209" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18235">He, too, left the room, following behind them. Pausing in the middle of the courtyard, he observed how they scattered in the twilight, each returning to his station. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n349" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18236" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18264">Going upstairs to get a lantern, he circled the courtyards, the corridors, and the rooms once more. He inspected every entrance, and when he saw that all was quiet, he finally went to sleep. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n350" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18265" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18270">Yes, to sleep, because he was tired. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n351" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18271" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18298">Although he had always gone in search of affairs that were complicated and urgent, never before, at any juncture, had he found himself with so many matters to handle. Yet he was tired. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n352" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18299" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18323">The remorse that had robbed him of sleep the night before, rather than settling down, was now calling out more loudly, more sternly, more absolutely. Yet he was tired. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n353" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18324" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18408">The order, the system of rule he had established so carefully within his realm for many years, through a unique combination of audacity and perseverance, he himself had now undermined with just a few words. The limitless service of his men, their willingness to do anything, that loyalty of thieves on which he had long relied, had been shattered by none other than himself. He had transformed his resources into a mountain of troubles, and sown confusion and doubt in his own home. Yet he was tired. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n354" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18409" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18433">So he went to his room, approached the side of the bed where he had found so many thorns the night before, and knelt down with the intention of saying his prayers. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n355" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18434" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18471">In a deep recess of his mind, he rediscovered the prayers that he had learned as a child. He started to say them, and those words, which had remained tangled in a ball for so long, started to come one after the other, as if they were unraveling. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n356" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18472" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18550">He was filled with a combination of undefinable sentiments: a certain tenderness in the physical return to the habits of innocence, sharper pangs at the thought of the abyss he had placed between that time and this, a yearning to attain, through acts of atonement, a clearer conscience, a state closer to the innocence to which he could not return, and a gratitude toward and trust in the mercy that could lead him to that condition, and that had already given him so many signs of willingness. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n357" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18551" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18558">He then got up off his knees, went to bed, and fell asleep immediately. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n358" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18559" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18614">And so ended that day, a day celebrated in the period when our anonymous scribe was writing. Nowadays, were it not for him, we would know nothing about this story—or at least none of the details—since Ripamonti and Rivola, whom I have quoted above, limit themselves to saying only that the notorious tyrant, after a meeting with Federigo, changed his life admirably and permanently. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n359" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18615" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18626">But how many people have read their books? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n360" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18627" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18634">Even fewer than those who will read my own. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n361" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18635" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18659">And who knows whether, in the valley itself, among those still interested in seeking it, and capable of finding it, some faded, confused tradition of that event has survived. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap24-n362" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18660" targetEnd="quarantana/cap24.xml#c24_18668">For so many things have happened between then and now! </note>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>