<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>2022</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed: a novel</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
          <date>2022</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Michael Moore</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="english_2022_cap27">
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10048">More than once, I have had occasion to mention the war for succession that was then raging in the states of the late Duke Vincenzo Gonzaga, the second to bear that name, but I have always done so very hastily, in passing reference. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10049" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10062">Now, however, we are in need of more detailed information to understand our story. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10063" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10108">Anyone who knows their history will be familiar with these events. However, since my intuition tells me that this book will only be read by the ignorant, it might not be a bad idea for me to give a smattering of background information to those who need it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10109" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10162">I have already noted that, upon the death of the Duke, the first in the line of succession was Charles Gonzaga, head of a cadet branch of the family transplanted to France, where it held the Duchies of Nevers and Rethel. As first in line, he was enlisted to come into possession of Mantua, and of Montferrat, as well, a fact I omitted out of haste. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10163" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10231">The Court of Madrid wanted to keep the new prince out of these two fiefs at all cost (this I have mentioned), and needed a reason to do so (since it would be unjust to wage a war for no reason). Thus, the court declared that it would uphold the claim on Mantua of another Gonzaga, namely Ferrante, the Prince of Guastalla; and the claim on Montferrat of Charles Emmanuel I, the Duke of Savoy, and Margherita Gonzaga, Dowager Duchess of Lorraine. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10232" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10325">Don Gonzalo—a descendant and namesake of El Gran Capitan, the great Spanish general Gonzalo Fernández de Córdoba (1453–1515)—probably agitated for a declaration of war more than anyone. He had already fought in Flanders and was all too eager to do battle in Italy. But before the Court of Madrid had reached a decision, he interpreted its intentions and anticipated its orders by signing a treaty with the Duke of Savoy for the invasion and partition of Montferrat. After that it was easy to get the Prime Minister of Spain, the Count-Duke of Olivares, to ratify the treaty. He persuaded him that there would be no difficulty in taking Casale—the best-defended citadel in the section of Montferrat allotted to the King of Spain! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10326" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10390">In the name of the King, however, he declared that he had no intention of occupying the town except as a depository, while awaiting the Emperor’s ruling. The Emperor, in the meantime—interceding in part on behalf of others, in part for reasons of his own—refused to allow Charles Gonzaga to take possession of Mantua, ordering the Duke to forfeit the disputed states to him. He would then consult the parties and decide who the rightful heir was. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10391" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10399">But the Duke would not agree. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10400" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10420">You see, Nevers had influential friends of his own: Cardinal Richelieu, the Venetian senators, and the Pope (Urban VIII, as I have mentioned). </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10421" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10458">But the Cardinal—busy with both the Siege of La Rochelle and a war with England, and opposed by the party of the Queen Mother, Marie de’ Medici—had his own reasons for not favoring the House of Nevers. The most he could offer was hope. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10459" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10506">The Venetians did not want to make a move, or even take sides, until a French army had descended into Italy. Doing their best to help the Duke surreptitiously with the Court of Madrid and the Governor of Milan, they limited themselves to declarations, proposals, and exhortations (calm or menacing, depending on the circumstances). </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10507" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10533">And while the Pope endorsed Nevers to his friends, interceded on his behalf with enemies, and came up with proposals for a settlement, he refused to hear any talk of sending men into battle. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10534" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10546">The two allies for the offense were thus able to undertake the concerted operation even more confidently. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10547" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10585">The Duke of Savoy, for his part, entered Montferrat. Don Gonzalo laid siege to Casale enthusiastically, but things didn’t go as well as he’d imagined. Don’t go thinking that everything is roses in war. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10586" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10622">Madrid did not give him the help he had wanted: In fact, it failed to provide him with the most basic needs. His ally was a little too helpful, by which I mean that, after taking his own share of Montferrat, the Duke of Savoy started helping himself to the area allotted to the King of Spain. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10623" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10669">Don Gonzalo was frustrated beyond compare, but he feared that if he protested, the Duke—who was as crafty and changeable in negotiations as he was valiant on the battlefield—might look to the French. So Don Gonzalo was forced to turn a blind eye, put up with him, and keep his mouth shut. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10670" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10705">In addition, the siege was going badly, dragging on and sometimes losing ground because of the solid, vigilant, and determined resistance of the besieged; Don Gonzalo’s lack of men; and, according to some historians, his many blunders. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10706" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10754">I won’t argue with them, and should this be true, I am even willing to find it beautiful if, for that reason, one fewer man was left dead, wounded, or maimed, and ceteris paribus—all things being equal—the roof tiles of Casale were to suffer a little less damage. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10755" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10769">It was at this juncture that Don Gonzalo received news of the riots in Milan and rushed off to be there in person. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10770" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10813">There, among the things reported to him, was the rebellious and clamorous escape of Renzo, and the events—both true and alleged—that led to his arrest. He was also told that the youth had taken refuge in the territory of Bergamo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10814" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10820">This circumstance caught the attention of Don Gonzalo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10821" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10884">From another source, he was informed that in Venice they were overjoyed by the Milan uprising; that, at first, they had believed Don Gonzalo would be forced to lift the siege of Casale; and that, regardless, they thought he himself was in a state of shock and deeply troubled, especially since the news of the surrender of La Rochelle—longed for by the Venetians and dreaded by him—came immediately after the riots. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10885" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10930">Offended—as a man and as a politician—that these gentlemen should entertain such a notion, he sought every opportunity to prove that he had lost none of his former confidence (since to openly say, “I’m not afraid,” is as good as saying nothing at all). </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_10931" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11016">One good strategy is to feign outrage, pick a quarrel, or protest. So when the Venetian Resident came by to pay his respects—and at the same time to investigate how Don Gonzalo was feeling, from the expression on his face and from his manner (take note of everything: Such is the subtle old art of diplomacy)—Don Gonzalo, after skimming over the subject of the riots as if he had already put the whole matter behind him, then made the commotion about Renzo that you’ve heard about, just as you’ve heard, too, all that happened as a result. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11017" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11106">After that, he no longer concerned himself with such a trivial and, to his mind, concluded business. And later—which was quite a while later—when the reply reached the camp above Casale, where he had returned, and where he had other things on his mind, he looked up and shook his head, like a silkworm searching for a mulberry leaf. He stood there for a moment, trying to get a vivid picture of an event that was buried in shadows. Then he remembered the character in question, recalled Renzo vaguely and fleetingly, moved on to another matter, and didn’t give the boy a second thought. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11107" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11143">From the little that Renzo had been able to infer, however, he must have assumed anything other than benign neglect. For several months, he had no other thought, or rather, no other concern, than to live in hiding. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11144" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11163">Of course he longed to send his news to the women and to hear theirs. But there were two major difficulties. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11164" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11234">First, that he would have to confide in a scribe, since the poor boy did not know how to write, or even read, in the broad sense of the word. And if, when asked, he claimed that he did, as he did, you might recall, with Professor Argle-Bargle, it wasn’t a boast or bluster. He could indeed read printed pages if he took his time, but handwriting was another kettle of fish. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11235" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11286">So he would be forced to share his business and his jealously guarded secret with a third person, and in those days, it wasn’t easy to find someone who could both wield a pen and be trusted, especially in a village where he had no old acquaintances. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11287" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11324">The second difficulty was to find a messenger, a man who was traveling to the same area and would be willing to take the letter and make sure that it reached its destination. All qualities that are likewise difficult to find in a single person. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11325" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11333">Finally, after looking long and hard, he found someone to write for him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11334" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11360">But not knowing whether the women were still in Monza, or where they might be, he thought it best to enclose the letter for Agnese inside one addressed to Fra Cristoforo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11361" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11414">The scribe also agreed to find someone to deliver the envelope. He gave it to a man who was supposed to be passing not far from Pescarenico. The man left it at a roadside inn near the final destination, with careful instructions. Since the envelope was addressed to a monastery, it arrived, but what happened to it next no one would ever know. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11415" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11444">Receiving no reply, Renzo had another letter written, more or less like the first, and enclosed it with another missive, addressed, perhaps, to a friend or relative in Lecco. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11445" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11460">He looked for and found another carrier. This time, the letter reached the person for whom it was meant. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11461" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11508">Agnese ran to Maggianico, where her cousin Alessio read and explained it to her. Together, they agreed on a response, which he put down on paper. She found a way to send it to Antonio Rivolta at his place of residence. The whole process took much longer than I make it sound, however. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11509" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11515">Renzo received her reply and had another letter written back. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11516" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11536">In short, a correspondence began between the two that was neither quick nor regular, but that, amid fits and starts, was ongoing. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11537" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11568">To get a sense of their exchange, you should know a little about how the system functioned, or rather how it still does, because in this particular matter, I believe that little to nothing has changed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11569" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11627">The peasant who cannot write, and needs something written, goes looking for a person who knows the art, and chooses someone, as best he can, from among members of his own class, since he is intimidated by others or doesn’t trust them. He explains the background, with some degree of order and clarity, and in the same fashion, he dictates what needs to be put down on paper. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11628" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11708">The writer, in equal parts understanding and misunderstanding, offers some advice, proposes a few changes, and says, “Leave it to me.” He picks up his pen, puts down the other person’s thoughts in written form as best he can, corrects them, improves them, emphasizes some parts, and softens or leaves out others, depending on what he thinks sounds best; because—there’s no escaping it—a man who knows more than others does not want to be a tool in their hands. When he delves into their business, he wants to do things slightly in his own way. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11709" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11741">Still, the writer does not always manage to say everything he means. Sometimes he even ends up saying the opposite; the same thing also happens to me when I write for the press. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11742" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11774">When a letter composed in such a manner reaches the addressee, who, like the sender, is also unschooled in the ABC’s, he or she must turn to another learned man of similar status to read and explain the message. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11775" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11811">Questions over interpretation arise since the recipient, who is familiar with the background, claims that certain words mean one thing, while the reader, based on his experience with composition, claims that they mean something else. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11812" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11844">In the end, the one who cannot write must submit to the one who can and entrust him with the reply; a reply that, following the pattern of the previous letter, is subject to the same style of interpretation. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11845" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11934">And if, moreover, the subject of the correspondence is a little delicate, and involves secret matters that should be indecipherable to a third person if the letter happens to go astray; and if, in this regard, there is also a deliberate intention not to say things clearly, then, no matter how brief the correspondence, the two parties will end up understanding each other as well as two medieval scholars might have, in the olden days, after debating the meaning of Aristotle’s entelechy for four hours (I have shied away from using a more modern example to avoid getting my ears boxed!). </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11935" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11947">This is exactly what happened to our two correspondents. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11948" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11958">The first letter written for Renzo covered many subjects. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_11959" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12030">It began with both the story of his escape (told more concisely, but also more chaotically, than the tale you’ve read) and a report on his current situation. Neither Agnese nor her dragoman could get a clear or complete idea of what he was talking about. Secret warnings, a new name, being safe but forced to hide: Such things were unfamiliar to them, and they were described cryptically in the letter. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12031" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12055">This section was followed by anxious, passionate questions about Lucia’s situation, with obscure and pained allusions to the rumors that had reached him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12056" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12085">The letter ended with uncertain and distant hopes, plans projected into the future, and, until such time, promises and prayers to keep their engagement, not to lose patience or courage, and to wait for better days. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12086" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12110">Some time later, Agnese found a trusted means of getting a letter, together with fifty scudi provided by Lucia, into Renzo’s hands. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12111" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12154">At the sight of so much gold, Renzo had no idea what to think. His mind troubled by dismay as well as an apprehension that left no room for contentment, he ran to his scribe to ask him to interpret the letter and find the key to this strange mystery. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12155" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12223">In the letter, Agnese’s scribe, after complaining about how unclear the previous message was, went on to describe, in an almost equally clear manner, what he called the tremendous story of that person. At this point, he explained the reason for the fifty scudi. Then, in a roundabout way, he came to the story of the vow, and added the more direct and explicit advice that Renzo set his heart at peace and think no more about it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12224" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12250">It was all Renzo could do to keep from taking out his frustration on the reader-interpreter: He shook with rage, horrified at what he could and could not understand. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12251" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12274">He had that terrible script read back to him three or four times, sometimes thinking he understood it better, sometimes finding that what had initially seemed clear had become more obscure. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12275" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12291">And in his passionate fervor, he wanted the scribe to immediately pick up his pen and reply. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12292" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12438">After the strongest imaginable expressions of pity and fear over Lucia’s situation—“write!” he continued to dictate: “I have no intention of setting my heart at peace, and I never will. And that such advice should not be given to a boy like me; and that I won’t touch the money; that I’ll give it back, and I’ll keep it in safekeeping, for the girl’s dowry. But that the girl must be mine; that I don’t know about any vows; and that I have always heard that the Madonna intercedes to help the troubled, to bestow grace, but I’ve never heard a word about her being spiteful and short of words; and that this cannot be; and that, with this money, we have enough to set up house here; and that, if I’m in a bit of trouble now, it’s just a storm that’ll pass quickly”; and other things of this sort. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12439" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12455">Agnese received the letter some time later and dictated back. And their exchange continued as I have described. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12456" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12507">Lucia felt greatly relieved when her mother managed—who knows how—to convey that the boy was safe and had been informed of the vow. She wanted nothing more than for him to forget her or, to be more precise, for him to try to forget her. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12508" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12530">For her part, she made a similar resolution regarding him a hundred times a day, and she used every means to put it into effect. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12531" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12556">She kept busy and tried to bury herself in her work. Whenever Renzo’s image appeared before her, she would say or sing a silent prayer. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12557" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12594">But that image, almost mischievously, did not tend to announce its appearance; it would sneak up behind other images, so that her mind wouldn’t even realize it was there until some minutes had passed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12595" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12626">Lucia’s thoughts were often on her mother; how could they not be? But the imaginary Renzo gradually receded into third place, like the real Renzo had done so many times in the past. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12627" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12646">Every time her thoughts turned to the people, places, and memories of her past, his image squeezed in. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12647" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12676">And if the poor girl sometimes let herself fantasize about the future, he would appear there, too, if for no other reason than to say, “Anyway, I won’t be there.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12677" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12740">So, while it was a hopeless endeavor not to think about him, her ability to think less intensely of him than her heart desired was constrained. She would have managed better if she alone had desired it, but Donna Prassede, for her part, was wholly devoted to expelling Renzo from Lucia’s thoughts, and she had found no better expedient than to bring him up constantly. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12741" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12749">“Well?” she would say. “Have we stopped thinking of him?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12750" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12756">“I’m not thinking of anybody,” Lucia would answer. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12757" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12799">Such a reply was not satisfactory to Donna Prassede. She would counter that actions spoke louder than words. From there, she would expound on the behavior of young people. In her words, “Once they’ve got their heart set on a troublemaker (always their inclination), they never let go. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12800" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12824">Give them an honest suitor, a gentleman, reasonable, settled, with whom, by some accident, things don’t work out, and they’re immediately resigned. But a ne’er-do-well? They’ll never get over him.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12825" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12859">And then would begin the panegyric for the poor absent boy, the rascal who had gone to Milan to rob and murder. She wanted Lucia to confess the mischief he had supposedly gotten into in his own village. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12860" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12918">Lucia, her voice trembling with all the shame, sadness, and indignation she could find in her kind soul and humble condition, swore up and down that, in her village, people had only ever had good things to say about the poor boy. She wished, she added, that someone from her village could be there to attest to the fact. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12919" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12945">She even defended his exploits in Milan—of which she was not well informed—precisely because of her knowledge of him and his behavior ever since childhood. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12946" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12979">She defended him and intended to keep defending him, because of her duties toward charity, her love of the truth, and—to say the word she herself used to explain her feelings—her love for her fellow man. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_12980" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13001">But in these apologies, Donna Prassede found ammunition to convince Lucia that her heart was still lost to him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13002" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13015">And to be honest, in moments like these, I myself couldn’t tell you what the truth was. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13016" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13112">The ignoble portrait that the old woman painted of the poor boy reawakened in the girl’s mind, more vividly and distinctly than before, the opposite image, which had been shaped by their long acquaintance; and the forcibly repressed memories came flooding back. The older woman’s aversion and scorn reminded Lucia of her many former reasons for respect. Donna Prassede’s blind, violent hatred only strengthened Lucia’s compassion. With affections such as these, who knows how much there might or might not be of the sentiment hidden behind them, which is so easily introduced into minds. Imagine how it will affect those who are being forced to drive it away. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13113" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13137">Whatever the case may be, the discussion, on Lucia’s part, could never continue for long, since the words quickly ended in tears. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13138" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13192">If Donna Prassede had been driven to treat Lucia this way by some inveterate hatred of her, maybe those tears would have moved her and made her stop. Since she was speaking with the best intentions, however, she forged ahead, undeterred; sobbing and pleading may restrain the weapons of an enemy, but not the scalpel of a surgeon. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13193" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13231">And then, having fulfilled her duty, she would pass from jabs and rebuffs to exhortations and advice, seasoned with words of praise to temper the bitter with the sweet and better achieve her purpose by working on the girl’s mind from different angles. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13232" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13277">After these quarrels (which always had more or less the same beginning, middle, and end), the good-hearted Lucia, of course, felt no grudge toward the harsh preacher, who otherwise treated her with great kindness; even here, you could still see the woman’s good intentions. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13278" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13305">But they left her with such reawakened and resurgent thoughts and affections that it required much time and effort to regain her former calm. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13306" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13330">Luckily for her, Lucia was not the only target of Donna Prassede’s beneficence, so these quarrels were infrequent. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13331" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13395">In addition to the rest of the servants, whose thoughts, to varying degrees, all required correction and guidance, in addition to all the other opportunities to lend these same services, out of the goodness of her heart, to the many toward whom she had no obligations—opportunities that she sought out if they did not volunteer themselves—she also had five daughters. None of them lived at home, but for all the worries they gave her, they might as well have. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13396" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13450">Three were nuns, and the other two were married. So of course Donna Prassede found herself with three convents and two households to supervise: a vast and complicated enterprise made even more arduous by the fact that the two husbands, with the backing of fathers, mothers, and siblings, and the three Mothers Superior, supported by other dignitaries and many nuns, refused to accept her oversight. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13451" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13503">It was war, or rather five separate wars: covert and courteous, to an extent, but still intense and without respite. On all five fronts, it took constant vigilance to evade her attentions, shut out her opinions, ignore her demands, and keep her in the dark about everything as much as possible. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13504" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13532">Not to mention the resistance and difficulties she encountered in managing the affairs of others with whom she had even less business. For everyone knows that people usually don’t know what’s good for them and have to be forced to accept it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13533" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13568">But her zeal did have free rein at home, where each person was subject, everywhere and in everything, to her authority. With the exception of Don Ferrante, for whom things proceeded in their own peculiar way. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13569" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13579">A man of learning, he was one to neither command nor obey. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13580" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13598">So much the better that, in all household matters, her Ladyship should be the boss. But that did not make him a servant! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13599" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13635">And if, when asked, he occasionally lent her the service of his pen, it was because it struck his fancy. Otherwise, he knew how to say no when he wasn’t convinced of what she wanted him to write. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13636" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13651">“Figure out a way,” he would tell her in such cases. “Do it yourself, since it seems so clear to you.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13652" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13701">Donna Prassede, after years of trying, fruitlessly, to push him from doing nothing to doing something, had limited herself to frequent grumbling, calling him a lazybones, a man set in his ways, a man of letters—a title she invested with both irritation and satisfaction. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13702" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13741">Don Ferrante spent long hours in his study, where he had a considerable collection of books—just under three hundred volumes: These were very select works, all the most reputable texts, on various subjects in which he could boast some knowledge. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13742" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13810">In astrology, he was regarded as more than a dilettante, and rightly so, because he had mastered not only the general notions and common vocabulary of influences, aspects, and conjunctions, but he also knew how to speak authoritatively, almost ex cathedra, of the twelve houses into which the heavens are divided, the great circles, the degrees of shadow and light, ascendants and descendants, transits and revolutions; in short, the most certain and recondite principles of the science. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13811" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13869">For about twenty years, he had supported Gerolamo Cardano’s division of the zodiac into twelve houses, in long and frequent disputes with another scholar who was fiercely attached to the system of Alcabitius (out of sheer obstinacy, according to Don Ferrante). Although Don Ferrante readily acknowledged the superiority of the ancients, he could not abide any refusal to side with the moderns when they were clearly right. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13870" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13917">He also had a better than average familiarity with the history of the science, and in a pinch, could quote the most famous predictions that had come true, and argue with subtlety and erudition about the ones that had not, to prove that the fault lay not with astrology, but with those who had not known how to apply it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13918" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13938">As for ancient philosophy, he had learned quite enough, and kept learning more, through his reading of Diogenes Laërtius. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13939" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13981">But no matter how nice the old systems are, one cannot adopt them all. If you wish to be a philosopher, you have to choose one, and Don Ferrante had chosen Aristotle, who, he used to say, was neither ancient nor modern. He was simply the philosopher. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_13982" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14020">He also had various texts by the wisest and most sophisticated of Aristotle’s followers among the moderns. He never wanted to read the works of Aristotle’s critics (so as not to waste time, he said), or buy them (so as not to waste money). </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14021" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14109">As an exception, however, he made room in his library for the celebrated twenty-two books of De subtilitate by Girolamo Cardano, and a few of his other anti-Aristotelian works, because of his primacy in astrology, saying that anyone who could write a treatise like De restitutione temporum et motuum coelestium, and a book like Duodecim geniturarum, deserved an audience, even when he was wrong; and that his biggest flaw was an excess of genius; and who knows what he could have achieved, also in philosophy, if he had only stuck to the right path. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14110" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14161">Otherwise, Don Ferrante passed for a consummate Aristotelian in the estimate of the learned, although he felt like he did not know enough, and said more than once, in all modesty, that the essence, the universals, the soul of the world, and the nature of things were not as clear as one might believe. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14162" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14344">Natural philosophy was for him not so much a study as a hobby. On this subject, he had read rather than studied the works of Aristotle and Pliny; nevertheless, thanks to these readings, and the information he had gleaned incidentally from treatises on general philosophy, and by leafing through the Magia naturalis of Giovanni Battista della Porta, as well as the three histories of Cardano (Lapidum, plantarum, animalium), the treatise on herbs, plants, and animals of Albertus Magnus, and other less important works, he could converse intelligently on the remarkable virtues and singular curiosities of many medicinal herbs; precisely describe the forms and habits of mermaids and the solitary phoenix; explain how the salamander can pass through fire without burning; how the remora, that tiny fish, has the strength and ability to bring to a halt even the largest ships on the high seas; how dewdrops turn into pearls inside an oyster shell; how the chameleon feeds on air; how crystal is formed from ice that has slowly hardened over the centuries; and other wondrous secrets of nature. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14345" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14386">He had delved more deeply into magic and witchcraft since, according to our anonymous writer, these sciences were far more popular and necessary, and their effects were more important and easier to verify. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14387" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14419">Needless to say, Don Ferrante’s only purpose in such a study was to learn the sinister arts of sorcery in depth, so he could guard and defend himself against them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14420" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14473">And, with the support primarily of the great Martin Delrio (the master of that science), he was able to discourse expertly on love spells, sleeping spells, curses, and the infinite varieties of these three main types that, unfortunately—our anonymous author goes on to say—were still practiced in his day, and with such unfortunate effects. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14474" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14511">Equally broad and solid was Don Ferrante’s knowledge of history, especially universal history. His authors in this field were the most reputable, in fact: Tarcagnota, Dolce, Bugatti, Campana, and Guazzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14512" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14523">But what is history, Don Ferrante would often ask, without politics? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14524" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14555">A guide who walks and walks and walks with no one following him to learn the way, is wasting his steps. Just as politics without history is a man walking without a guide. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14556" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14586">So on his bookshelves, there was a place reserved for the political writers, which featured prominently—among minor, and less famous volumes—the works of Bodin, Cavalcanti, Sansovino, Paruta, and Boccalini. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14587" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14664">But there were two books in this field that Don Ferrante placed over and above all the others. Two that, for a time, he used to call the best, without ever being able to decide which of the two was singularly deserving of the title. The first, Il principe and discorsi by the celebrated Florentine Secretary: quite the scoundrel, Don Ferrante used to say, but profound. The second was the Ragion di stato, by the no less celebrated Giovanni Botero: a decent man, he used to say, but a sharp one. But shortly before the period within which our story takes place, a book appeared that put an end to the question of primacy, surpassing even the works of those two matadors, as Don Ferrante used to call them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14665" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14883">A book that contained and identified all the tricks, for the sake of knowing them, and all the virtues, for the sake of practicing them. A tiny book, but pure gold. In a word, the Statista regnante, by Don Valeriano Castiglione, that most famous man whom the greatest scholars vied to praise, and for whose services the greatest personages competed. The same man, it is well known, upon whom Pope Urban VIII lavished the most extraordinary praise. The man whom Cardinal Borghese and the Viceroy of Naples, Don Pietro of Toledo, implored, respectively, to write about the deeds of Pope Paul V, and the wars of the Catholic King in Italy, both to no avail. The man whom King Louis XIII of France appointed as his historian, at the suggestion of Cardinal Richelieu, and upon whom Duke Charles Emmanuel of Savoy conferred the same honor. The man who was praised by Duchess Cristina, Christine, daughter of the most Christian King Henry IV, in a diploma that enumerated, along with his many other qualities, “The certain glory of the fame he has won in Italy as the foremost writer of our day.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14884" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14910">But while Don Ferrante could say he was versed in all these sciences, there was one in which he deserved and enjoyed the title of master: the chivalric sciences. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14911" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14928">Not only could he argue about the subject with true mastery, but he was also frequently asked to intervene in matters of honor, and he never failed to render a verdict. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_14929" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_15012">In his library and, one could say, in his head, were the works of the most renowned writers in the field: Paride del Pozzo, Fausto da Longiano, Urrea, Muzio, Romei, Albergato, and the first and second Forno of Torquato Tasso, whose Gerusalemme liberata and the Gerusalemme conquistata he always had close at hand, and whose passages on chivalry he could quote from memory. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_15013" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_15055">But the supreme author, to his mind, was our own celebrated Francesco Birago, with whom he had, on more than one occasion, been called upon to judge a matter of honor; and a man who, for his part, spoke of Don Ferrante with particular esteem. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_15056" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_15106">From the moment that renowned gentleman’s Discorsi cavallereschi appeared, Don Ferrante predicted, without hesitation, that this work would make Olevano’s work obsolete, and remain, together with its other noble sisters, as the code of supreme authority for posterity; a prediction, according to our anonymous author, whose veracity we can all judge for ourselves. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_15107" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_15191">He then moved on to some readings for pleasure, but I am starting to wonder whether the reader really wants to hear any more of this catalogue, and to fear that you may have begun to consider me a servile copyist, and as much of a bore as the anonymous writer, for having so naïvely followed Don Ferrante far afield of the main story, down this tangent in which he has been so long-winded probably only to boast of his learning and show that he wasn’t behind the times. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_15192" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_15254">But what’s written is written, and I’ll have to keep it, so as not to waste my efforts, but I’ll skip the remaining books so we can get back on the main road; especially since we have a long way to go before we will encounter any of our characters, and an even longer way still before we find the ones at the center of the events that most interest the reader, if indeed the reader finds anything interesting in all this. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_15255" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_15294">Until autumn of the following year, 1629, everyone remained—some by choice, others by force—almost in the same condition in which we left them, without anything happening, nor anyone doing anything worth reporting. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_15295" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_15326">Autumn came, and although Agnese and Lucia had planned on getting together, a major public event scattered their plans to the wind—which was certainly one of the least of its effects. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_15327" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_15343">Other major events later followed that did not, however, lead to any notable change in the destinies of our characters. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_15344" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_15423">But in the end, they would be swept up by new, more widespread, powerful, and extreme circumstances, affecting even the least of them, according to the scale of the world. Like a giant whirlwind that pursues, wanders, splits, and uproots, ripping up roofs, stripping the stucco off bell towers, tearing down walls, and casting debris everywhere, even blowing away the twigs hidden in the grass, seeking out the dried rotting leaves in the corners where a breeze had borne them, and then carrying them around in the grips of its plunder. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap27-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_15424" targetEnd="quarantana/cap27.xml#c27_15451">Now, in order to better understand the private events that remain for me to relate, we must absolutely take a step back and pause for a rough account of the public events. </note>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>