<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>2022</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed: a novel</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
          <date>2022</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Michael Moore</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="english_2022_cap29">
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10010">Here, among the poor terrified people, we find a few individuals of our acquaintance. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10011" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10045">News of the army’s descent, approach, and actions spread like wildfire, and anyone who didn’t see Don Abbondio during that period doesn’t know the meaning of terror and distress. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10046" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10116">“They’re coming: thirty, forty, fifty thousand. They’re devils, heretics, antichrists. They sacked Cortenuova, set fire to Primaluna, and are now laying waste to Introibo, Pasturo, and Barzio. They’ve reached Ballabio. Tomorrow they’ll be here!” These were the rumors passing from mouth to mouth. The people scurried about, stopping one another in agitated consultation, debating whether to flee or stay. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n4" type="comm" status="insertion">Women huddled together, tearing at their hair. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10117" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10146">But Don Abbondio—more determined to flee than anyone else, and to beat the crowd, as well—saw insurmountable obstacles and terrifying dangers on every road and at every possible refuge. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10147" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10151">“What can we do?” he exclaimed. “Where can we go?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10152" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10182">The mountains, apart from the arduous hike, were not safe: Everyone knew that the Landsknechts would clamber up them like cats if they had any inkling or hope of plunder. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10183" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10236">And the lake was rough, with a high wind blowing. Not to mention that most of the boatmen had taken refuge with their vessels on the opposite shore, fearing they’d be forced to ferry soldiers or cargo. The remaining boats had already departed, overloaded with people, buffeted about by the weight and the storm, and reportedly in danger of capsizing any moment. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10237" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10278">Not a cart, horse, or other means of transportation could be found to escape the army’s path. Don Abbondio wouldn’t have been able to travel very far on foot, and he feared being overtaken on the road. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10279" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10345">The Bergamo territory was close enough that his legs could have gotten him there in a single stretch. But everyone knew that a contingent of cappelletti, mercenaries in the employ of Venice, had been quickly dispatched to Bergamo to guard the border and keep the Landsknechts out, though the cappelletti themselves were nearly as diabolical as the intruders. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10346" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10418">The poor man rushed about the house, in a panic and at wit’s end. He followed Perpetua around so they could agree on a course of action. But she was busy gathering up the house’s valuables and hiding them in the attic or a cubbyhole, and rushed past him, out of breath and worried, with her hands and arms full. “Right now, I’m going to finish putting these things in a safe place. Then we’ll do what everyone else is doing,” she replied. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10419" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10467">Don Abbondio kept trying to detain her to discuss their various alternatives. But between the hustle and bustle, the panic that she, too, could feel in her bones, and her irritation at her master’s fears, her patience had run thin. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10468" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10473">“Everyone else is doing their best. So will we. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10474" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10481">Excuse me, but don’t you have something else to do besides getting in my way? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10482" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10493">Don’t you realize that we are all trying to save our skin? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10494" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10503">Do you think the soldiers are coming only for you? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10504" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10522">You might give me a hand at a time like this instead of getting in my way with your whining and fretting.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10523" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10557">With this and other such retorts, she dismissed him, having already decided, once she had finished her hasty operation as best she could, to take him by the arm like a child, and drag him up a mountain. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10558" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10597">Left to his own devices, Don Abbondio went to the window, looked out, and listened carefully. Seeing someone pass by, he called out in a voice both plaintive and reproachful: “An act of charity for your poor priest! Please find him a horse, a mule, a donkey. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10598" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10603">How is it that no one wants to help me? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10604" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10606">What kind of people are you? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10607" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10627">At least wait for me so that I can come with you. Wait until there’s at least fifteen or twenty of us, then lead me away in company, so I won’t be left here alone. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10628" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10633">Do you want to leave me in the hands of dogs? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10634" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10649">Don’t you realize that most of them are Lutherans, and they think that murdering a priest would be a good deed? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10650" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10656">Do you want to leave me here to be martyred? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10657" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10659">What kind of people are you? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10660" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10662">What kind of people?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10663" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10668">But to whom was he speaking? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10669" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10710">To men walking past, stooped over from the weight of their humble possessions, thinking of what they had left behind, driving their cows before them, pulling behind them their children—who were also carrying as much as they could—and the women holding the little ones who couldn’t walk. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10711" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10740">Some trudged forward, without replying or looking up. Some said, “Ah, Reverend! Do what you can. At least you don’t have a family to worry about. You’ve got to fend for yourself. Do your best.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10741" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10751">“Woe is me!” exclaimed Don Abbondio. “What kind of people are these! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10752" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10764">Don’t they have hearts! Is there no charity left in the world! Everyone is thinking only about themselves, and no one is thinking about me.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10765" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10770">And he turned around to look for Perpetua. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10771" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10778">“There you are,” she said. “And the money?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10779" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10780">“What should we do with it?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10781" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10796">“Give it to me, and I’ll go bury it in the garden, together with the silverware.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10797" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10797">“But…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10798" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10815">“No buts about it. Give it here. Keep the little that we might need. I’ll take care of the rest.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10816" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10842">Don Abbondio obeyed: He went to his desk, took out his savings, and handed them over to Perpetua. “I’m going to bury this in the garden, at the foot of the fig tree,” she said, and went out. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10843" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10885">She reappeared a little later, with one basket holding the food supplies and another small empty pack basket. She quickly started placing a few of her and her master’s linens in the bottom, saying, “You could at least carry your breviary.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10886" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10888">“Where are we going?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10889" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10893">“Where do you think? Where everyone else is headed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10894" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10908">Let’s get on the road first, then we can listen and decide the best thing to do.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10909" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10929">In that moment, Agnese arrived at the door with a pack basket strapped to her back and the air of someone with an important proposal to make. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10930" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10962">She had decided not to wait for the unwelcome guests—alone as she was, and still having a little of the Nameless One’s money—and had spent a while debating where to seek refuge. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_10963" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11017">The remainder of those scudi, which had come in so handy during the famine months, was the main reason for her anxiety and indecisiveness. She had heard that people with money had fared the worst in towns already invaded, exposed to both the violence of the foreigners and the treachery of their neighbors. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11018" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11061">It was true that she had not breathed a word of the fortune that had rained down on her from heaven, as they say, to anyone except Don Abbondio. Every now and then, she would come by and ask him to change a scudo, always leaving a little something extra for him to give to people less fortunate than herself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11062" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11083">But hidden money, especially for someone not used to handling large amounts, keeps the owner in constant suspicion of others’ suspicions. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11084" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11164">Now, as she, too, stashed away whatever she couldn’t take with her, she remembered that the Nameless One had offered her the most generous favors when he sent her the money. She remembered the stories she had heard of his castle being situated in such a secure spot that the only ones who could reach it, in defiance of the master, were the birds. So she decided to go up there and ask him for shelter, but she needed someone to introduce her. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11165" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11235">Don Abbondio immediately came to mind. He had been making such a fuss over her ever since his conversation with the Archbishop, especially now that he no longer had to worry about his safety: The two young people were distant, so there was only a distant possibility that he might receive requests that would try his benevolence. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11236" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11269">She imagined that, with all the commotion, the poor man must be even more distressed and shocked than she was, and that her idea might appeal to him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11270" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11278">Finding him with Perpetua, she explained her proposal to both of them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11279" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11285">“What do you think, Perpetua?” Don Abbondio asked. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11286" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11304">“I think it’s a godsend. Let’s stop wasting time and start moving.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11305" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11306">“And then?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11307" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11317">“And then? And then, we’ll be fine once we get there. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11318" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11339">That man—everyone knows he wants nothing more now than to help his neighbor, so he’ll be more than happy to welcome us in. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11340" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11351">And there, on the border, and so high up, we won’t need to worry about the soldiers coming. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11352" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11386">And then, we’ll find something to eat, too. Because, up in the mountains, once we’ve finished these gifts from God”—as she spoke, she placed some food inside the basket, on top of the linens—“we’ll be in quite a predicament.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11387" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11391">“Converted? But is he truly converted?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11392" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11409">“How could anyone doubt it now, after everything we know, and after what you yourself have seen?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11410" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11416">“What if we’re headed for a trap?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11417" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11418">“A trap? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11419" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11432">Excuse me, but with all your dithering, we would have never reached a decision. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11433" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11440">Well done, Agnese! Good idea!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11441" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11457">Setting the pack basket on a small table, she slipped her arms through the straps and pulled it over her shoulders. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11458" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11477">“Couldn’t we find,” Don Abbondio interjected, “some man to come with us, willing to escort his parish priest? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11478" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11496">If we run into a scoundrel—and unfortunately there’s more than a few of them around—what help would the two of you be?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11497" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11502">“More excuses, just to waste time!” exclaimed Perpetua. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11503" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11515">“Do you really think we should go looking for someone? It’s every man for himself now. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11516" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11526">Chin up. Go fetch your breviary and hat, and we’ll be on our way.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11527" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11561">Don Abbondio left and came back a moment later with the breviary under his arm, his hat on his head, and his walking stick in hand. All three of them went out by a small door that opened onto the piazza. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11562" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11587">Perpetua locked it behind her—more as a formality than out of any faith in that lock or those shutters—and put the keys in her pocket. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11588" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11609">As they passed the church, Don Abbondio cast a glance at it, muttering to himself, “The people’ll have to look after it, since it’s there to serve them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11610" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11630">If they have some feeling for their church, they will. If not, so much the worse for them.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11631" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11655">They went through the fields, quietly quietly, each one contemplating his or her own situation, and glancing around—especially Don Abbondio—to see if any suspicious or unusual characters were lurking. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11656" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11679">They didn’t run into anyone. Everyone was either indoors—guarding their house, packing up, or hiding their belongings—or on the trails leading up the mountain. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11680" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11698">After huffing, puffing, and occasionally bursting out with some interjection, Don Abbondio started to grumble even more. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11699" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11761">He complained about the Duke of Nevers, who could have stayed in France and amused himself by playing the Prince, but no, he wanted to be the Duke of Mantua, the world be damned. As for the Emperor, he should have shown more sense than the others, let the river run its course, and not taken offense at every little thing. After all, he’s still the Emperor in the end, no matter who becomes Duke of Mantua. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11762" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11795">The person who irked him the most, however, was the Governor, who should have done everything in his power to keep scourges away from the country, but was too busy attracting them, all for the fun of waging war. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11796" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11809">“Those gentlemen should be here,” he said, “to see for themselves how much fun this is. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11810" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11815">They have a lot to answer for! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11816" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11826">In the meantime, the innocent always get caught in the middle.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11827" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11844">“Forget about them. They’re not coming to save us,” Perpetua said. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11845" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11857">“Forgive me, but this is just your usual chatter, going around and around in circles. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11858" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11863">But do you know what’s worrying me?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11864" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11865">“What?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11866" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11907">Perpetua, who, on that stretch of the road, had found plenty of time to ponder her mad dash to hide things, started to complain that she’d forgotten this, misplaced that, here left footprints that could guide the thieves, there… </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11908" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11926">“Good work!” exclaimed Don Abbondio, convinced by now that he was safe enough to fret about his possessions. “Good work! What did you do? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11927" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11930">What were you thinking?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11931" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11976">“I beg your pardon?” replied Perpetua, squaring up for a moment on her two feet and placing her hands on her hips as best she could manage with the pack basket on her back. “I beg your pardon? Now you turn around and scold me when you’re the one who made me lose my mind rather than helping me out and encouraging me! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_11977" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12019">I was more worried about the household things than my own. I had to be both Martha and Magdalene, with no one to give me a hand. If anything goes wrong, I’m not the one to blame. I went above and beyond the call of duty!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12020" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12096">Agnese interrupted this spat by bringing up her own troubles. Rather than complain about discomfort and damage, she was despairing over when she could embrace her Lucia again. Because, if you recall, they had arranged to meet that fall. But given the circumstances, no one could presume that Donna Prassede had any intention of taking her holiday in these parts. In fact, if she had already been staying there, she would have left, like all the other vacationers. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12097" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12113">The sight of these familiar places made her thoughts more vivid, her sorrow more piercing. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12114" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12148">From the footpath, they entered the main road: the same one the poor woman had traveled to bring her daughter back home, for such a brief moment, after their stay at the tailor’s house. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12149" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12154">And now the village was already coming into view. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12155" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12163">“We should stop to say hello to those good people,” said Agnese. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12164" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12186">“And also to rest for a bit and a bite to eat. I’m getting tired of carrying this basket,” added Perpetua. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12187" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12202">“As long as we don’t waste time,” proclaimed Don Abbondio. “We’re not here for pleasure.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12203" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12216">They were welcomed with open arms and great joy, for their arrival was a reminder of a good deed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12217" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12241">Do good to as many people as you can—our author writes at this point—and you will be rewarded many times over with faces that lift your spirits. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12242" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12272">Agnese broke down in tears when she embraced the good woman, which came as a great relief. Between sobs, she replied to the woman’s and her husband’s inquiries about Lucia. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12273" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12289">“She’s better off than us,” interjected Don Abbondio. “She’s in Milan, far away from danger, and far away from all this devilry.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12290" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12300">“You two are also fleeing?” the tailor asked the priest and his companion. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12301" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12310">“Of course,” the master and the servant replied as one. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12311" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12312">“My sympathies.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12313" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12321">“We’re headed for the castle of ***,” added Don Abbondio. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12322" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12328">“Good thinking: You’ll be as safe up there as in church.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12329" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12336">“But aren’t you afraid to stay here?” asked Don Abbondio. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12337" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12365">“Let me tell you, Reverend. I don’t imagine the soldiers will be coming to this village for lodgment—the correct term, I’m sure you know—since, thank goodness, we’re too far off their path. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12366" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12394">Maybe a raid, at most, God forbid. But in any case, we’ve still got time. We’re waiting first to hear more about how the poor villages fared where the soldiers do end up stopping.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12395" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12429">The little group decided to stay for a bit to catch their breath. And since it was mealtime: “Good people,” proposed the tailor, “you must honor my poor table. Just potluck. Something simple.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12430" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12439">Perpetua mentioned that she also had a little something to break the fast. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12440" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12464">After polite refusals from one side and the other, they agreed to pool their resources, as they say, and dine together. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12465" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12477">The children gathered joyfully around their old friend Agnese. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12478" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12518">Quickly quickly, the tailor ordered one girl (the daughter who had brought the bundle of food to the widow Maria: Do you remember her?) to shell a few of the early chestnuts stored in a corner, and set them by the fire to roast. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12519" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12541">“And you,” he said to a boy, “go to the orchard and shake the peach tree, just enough for a few to drop, and bring them here: all of them!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12542" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12556">“And you,” he said to another, “go to the fig tree and pick the ripest fruit. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12557" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12563">You know how to do it!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12564" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12607">He himself went to tap some wine from a barrel. His wife got out the table linen, Perpetua dug out their provisions, and the table was set: a napkin and a majolica dish at the place of honor, for Don Abbondio, along with silverware that Perpetua had brought in her basket. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12608" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12632">They sat down and ate, if not so cheerfully, then at least with greater happiness than any of them had expected to feel on that day. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12633" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12655">“What do you think of all this turmoil, Reverend?” asked the tailor. “It’s like a story you’d read about the Moors in France!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12656" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12658">“What can I say? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12659" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12664">Why did this, too, have to happen to me!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12665" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12680">“Well, you’ve chosen a good refuge,” the tailor continued. “Who the devil would go all the way up there? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12681" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12698">And you’ll be in good company. I hear that many people have taken shelter there, and more still are arriving.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12699" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12707">“I only hope,” said Don Abbondio, “that we will be welcome. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12708" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12726">I know that good man. And when I had the honor to meet him on another occasion, he was such a gentleman!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12727" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12749">“As for me,” said Agnese, “he told His Eminence the Cardinal that if I ever needed anything, all I had to do was go to him.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12750" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12762">“His conversion was so wonderful!” Don Abbondio continued. “And he’s kept it up, hasn’t he? He’s kept it up.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12763" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12787">The tailor started to describe in minute detail the holy life of the Nameless One and how he had gone from being the scourge of the area to its model citizen and benefactor. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12788" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12815">“What about the people who surrounded him?…All those attendants?” asked Don Abbondio, who had heard talk of his bravi more than once, but never stayed quiet long enough to listen. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12816" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12832">“He dismissed most of them,” the tailor replied. “And the ones that remained have changed their ways, they really have. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12833" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12845">The castle has become a kind of hermitage: But you, of course, know all about such places.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12846" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12855">He then started to reminisce about the Cardinal’s visit with Agnese. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12856" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12858">“What a great man!” he said. “A great man! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12859" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12877">A shame that he visited you for such a short time, and I didn’t even have the chance to pay him some honor. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12878" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12890">I would be so happy to speak with him again, with a little more leisure.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12891" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12943">When they got up from the table, he showed her a print of the Cardinal that he had attached to one side of the door, in homage to the man, but also so he could tell anyone who came by, from one who knows, that it didn’t look anything like the man. Because he’d had a chance to see the Cardinal in person, up close and at length, in this very room. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12944" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12953">“Is that supposed to be him? That thing there?” asked Agnese. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12954" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12958">“Maybe the habit, but the rest…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12959" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12986">“It’s not much of a resemblance, you’re right,” said the tailor. “I always say the same thing myself. They can’t fool us, can they? But at least his name is underneath: I keep it as a souvenir.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_12987" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13015">Don Abbondio wanted to get moving. The tailor promised to find a cart that would take them to the foot of the hill, and he went looking for one immediately. A little later, he came back to tell them that one was on its way. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13016" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13049">He then turned to Don Abbondio, saying, “Reverend, should you ever want me to bring you a book up there, to pass the time, I offer my humble services. Since I also like to read a little myself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13050" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13059">Nothing like yourself, of course, only books in Italian, not Latin. But…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13060" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13078">“Thank you, thank you,” replied Don Abbondio. “In times like these, the required readings are just about all a person can manage.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13079" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13107">As they were saying their “thank-yous” and “think nothing of its,” exchanging farewells and best wishes, invitations and promises to visit on their trip home, the cart arrived at the front door. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13108" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13128">They strapped on their pack baskets, climbed on, and began the second half of their trip less worried and with a little more peace of mind. — </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13129" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13139">The tailor was right about the Nameless One. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13140" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13168">From the day we left him, he continued to fulfill his promises, make reparations for his wrongs, plead for peace, and help the poor—in short, always doing good whenever the occasion arose. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13169" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13190">The same courage he had once demonstrated in attacking and defending, he now demonstrated by doing neither one nor the other. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13191" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13260">He always went out alone, unarmed, ready for any repercussions he might face for all the violent deeds he had committed, and convinced it would be yet another such deed if he used force to defend someone—himself—who was responsible for so much violence to so many; and convinced that any wrong done to him would be an offense to God, yes, but also just retribution toward himself; and that he had no right to punish such an offense. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13261" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13281">Nevertheless, he was just as inviolate now as he had been when he used to arm himself and many others for his own security. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13282" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13321">The memory of his past aggressions, which should have incited many to revenge, and the sight of his present meekness, which would have made it even easier, conspired instead to earn him admiration, and to keep it, as his main protection. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13322" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13334">He was the man whom no one could humble, yet had now humbled himself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13335" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13395">The grudges, which had once been aggravated by his contempt for others and their fear of him, disappeared in the face of his newfound humility. Against all expectations, and without danger, his victims had received a satisfaction that even the most successful revenge could never have attained: the satisfaction of seeing him atone for his crimes, and share, so to speak, in their own indignation. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13396" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13449">There were many who, for years, had been intensely, bitterly frustrated at never being in a position to get the better of him, or to be redeemed for some great wrong he had done them. Now, when they encountered him alone, unarmed, acting like he would put up no resistance, their only impulse was to commend him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13450" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13489">Through that voluntary humiliation, his presence and bearing had acquired, without his realizing it, something loftier and more noble, since even more than before, one could see the absence of all fear in him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13490" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13513">Even the most raw and passionate hatred seemed to be restrained and held in check by the public veneration of this penitent and charitable man. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13514" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13558">So great was this veneration that he was often embarrassed by the accolades bestowed on him. To avoid being overly glorified, he had to be careful not to allow his face or his actions to show too much of his inner compunction, and not to overly humble himself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13559" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13579">As his place in church he chose the last pew, and there was no danger that anyone would take it away from him, for to do so would have been to usurp a place of honor. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13580" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13619">To insult this man, or treat him with disrespect, would seem not so much an act of insolence or cowardice as a sacrilege. And the people who might have been restrained by such feelings also shared them to some extent. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13620" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13648">These and other reasons also shielded him from the vengeance of the law, and procured for him the security that he himself scorned. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13649" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13688">His rank and relations, which had always protected him, served him even more since his illustrious though infamous name was now complemented by praise for his exemplary conduct and the glory of his conversion. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13689" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13714">The judges and grandees, like the people, openly rejoiced in this. And it would have been strange to go after so highly praised a man. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13715" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13766">Not to mention that a government engaged in an ongoing and often unsuccessful battle against active and recurrent uprisings must have been happy not to have to worry any longer about one of the most indomitable and vexing rebels, especially since the Nameless One’s conversion had freely offered such unexpected and beneficial reparations. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13767" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13811">Harassing a saint did not seem like a good way to undo their embarrassment at having failed to bring a criminal to heel. Punishing him would only serve to dissuade others of his kind from ceasing their criminal activities. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13812" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13839">The role that Cardinal Federigo had played in his conversion, and the association of their two names, might also have given him a sacred shield. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13840" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13928">In those days, there was a peculiar relationship between Church and State. The two were often in conflict, though they never tried to destroy each other, and often lessened their hostilities toward one another through acts of appreciation and deference, sometimes working together to pursue a common goal without ever making peace. This situation might make it seem as if reconciliation with spiritual authority had encouraged, if not the absolution, then at least the forgetfulness of the secular authorities, when in fact the Church had always worked to deliver the result that both parties desired. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13929" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13956">If the Nameless One had been toppled, his enemies great and small would have competed to trample on him; since he prostrated himself voluntarily, he was spared by all, and revered by many. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_13957" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14017">However, not everyone was pleased with his amazing transformation: Many hired killers and fellows in crime lost a powerful leader on whom they had depended. Plots organized long before were suddenly called off, just moments before they were supposed to be executed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14018" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14056">But we already know how the thugs in his service reacted when they heard him announce his conversion: with dismay, sorrow, dejection, aggravation—a little of everything, except for contempt or hatred. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14057" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14087">His men who were stationed elsewhere as well as his accomplices in high places all felt the same way when they heard the terrible news, and all of them for the same reasons. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14088" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14103">According to Ripamonti, these men reserved their hatred, instead, for Cardinal Federigo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14104" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14126">They believed that he had meddled in their affairs expressly to ruin their livelihoods. The Nameless One had only wanted to save his soul; no one could begrudge him that. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14127" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14154">Little by little, most of the household thugs had left, unable to adjust to the new order, and seeing no probability of change. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14155" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14215">Some might have gone looking for another master, perhaps among the old friends of the man they had left. Some might have enlisted in a regiment—a tercio as it was then called—of Spain, Mantua, or another party to a conflict. Some might have gone on the road, to become highwaymen, responsible only to themselves. Still others might even have been happy with a life of random crime. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14216" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14231">The men who used to be under his command in scattered towns probably followed the same pattern. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14232" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14305">As for those who adapted to the new regime, or willingly embraced it, most had returned to farming, since they were natives of the valley, or to trades they had learned in their early years but later abandoned. The foreigners remained in the castle as servants. Both groups, rebaptized at nearly the same time as their master, lived like he did, unharmed and respected, without giving or receiving offense. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14306" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14408">When the German marauders descended, and refugees from the invaded or threatened towns arrived at the castle seeking shelter, the Nameless One was pleased that the vulnerable now saw his walls as a sanctuary rather than as a dark specter in the distance. He welcomed them with expressions of gratitude rather than courtesy. He let it be known that his home was open to anyone who needed shelter, and he immediately thought to fortify both his castle and the valley against invasion from the Landsknechts or cappelletti. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14409" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14493">He gathered together the remaining servants, few and valiant (as in the verses of Giovanni Torti), and gave them a speech on the wonderful opportunity that God had given all of them to help the neighbors they had once oppressed and terrorized. Then, with that natural tone of command which knows it will be obeyed, he announced his general plan. First and foremost, he issued guidelines on how to behave so the new arrivals would see them as friends and defenders. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14494" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14600">He then instructed them to bring the firearms, swords, and pikes down from an attic room where they had long been stored and to distribute them. He sent word to his peasants and tenants in the valley that anyone who wished could come to the castle with their weapons. Anyone who didn’t have a weapon would be provided with one. He appointed a few men as officers, and placed others under their command. He established pickets at the entrances to the valley and other places, as well as on the hill and at the gates of the castle. He scheduled rounds and rotations, like in a military camp, as had been the custom at the castle during his dissolute past life. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14601" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14633">In one corner of that attic room, separate from all the rest, were the weapons that he alone had carried: his notorious carbine, his muskets, swords, cutlasses, pistols, knives, and daggers, now lying on the floor or leaning against the wall. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14634" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14650">None of the servants dared to touch them, but they agreed to ask their master which ones he wanted. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14651" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14667">“None,” he replied. Whether it was a vow or a resolution, he would always remain unarmed, at the head of this makeshift garrison. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14668" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14708">At the same time, he mobilized other servants, or his employees, to prepare accommodations in the castle for as many people as possible, to set up beds and arrange pallets stuffed with straw or wool in rooms large and small, which then became dormitories. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14709" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14735">And he ordered ample provisions to feed however many guests God would send him, whose numbers, in fact, grew by the day. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14736" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14785">In the meantime, he was never still. Inside and outside the castle, up and down the hill, moving about the valley, to establish, reinforce, and visit posts, to see and be seen, to create and maintain order, through his words, his eyes, and his presence. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap29-n189" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14786" targetEnd="quarantana/cap29.xml#c29_14840">And everyone, whether they had seen him before or were seeing him now for the first time, stared in astonishment, forgetting for a moment the troubles and fears that had driven them there. And they turned around to stare again when, taking his leave, he continued on his way. </note>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>