<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>2022</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed: a novel</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
          <date>2022</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Michael Moore</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="english_2022_cap22">
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10058">A few minutes later, the bravo returned and reported that Cardinal Federigo Borromeo, the Archbishop of Milan, had arrived in *** yesterday and would be spending the day. When the people of the surrounding villages heard the news on the eve of his arrival, they were all inspired to come and see him. The bells were ringing, not to inform the people but to celebrate. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10059" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10074">Left alone, the Nameless One continued to look out at the valley, more pensive than ever. “For one man! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10075" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10082">Everyone in a rush, everyone joyful, all to see one man! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10083" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10094">Each of them must be tormented by some demon. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10095" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10110">But none of them, not one, suffers from a demon like mine! No one has been through a night like mine! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10111" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10117">What is it about that man that brings so many people such joy? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10118" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10131">A few coins to hand out here and there?…But they can’t all be there for charity. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10132" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10153">What then, a few gestures in the air, a few words…Oh, if only he has a few words of consolation for me! If only…! But why shouldn’t I go? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10154" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10155">Why not?…I’ll go, I will. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10156" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10166">And I want to speak with him. I want to speak with him in private. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10167" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10169">What should I say to him? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10170" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10181">Well, I’ll tell him, I’ll tell him…I’ll hear what this man has to say!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10182" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10269">Once he fumbled his way to this decision, he dressed quickly, throwing on a military-style coat. He took the pistol that was still lying on the bed and tucked it into his belt on one side, and on the other, he holstered another gun that had been hanging on a nail in the wall. He stuck his dagger in the same belt, then took down from the wall a carbine, whose notoriety rivaled his own, and slung it around his shoulder. He picked up his hat, left his chamber, and went straight to the room where he had left Lucia. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10270" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10286">He set the rifle down in a corner near the door and knocked, calling out at the same time. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10287" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10298">The old woman leapt out of bed and ran to open the door. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10299" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10315">The master entered, looked around the room, and spotted Lucia huddled in the corner, motionless. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10316" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10329">“Is she asleep?” he asked the old woman in a low voice. “Asleep over there? Were those my orders, you wretch?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10330" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10347">“I did my best,” she replied, “but she wouldn’t eat, and wouldn’t come…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10348" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10360">“Let her sleep in peace. Make sure you don’t disturb her. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10361" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10377">And when she wakes up…Marta will be in the next room. Send her to get anything the girl requests. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10378" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10401">When she wakes up…tell her that I…that the master has gone out for a little while, that he’ll be back, and that…he’ll do whatever she wants.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10402" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10416">The old woman couldn’t believe her ears, thinking, “What is she, some kind of a princess?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10417" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10458">The master left, picked up his rifle, told Marta to wait in the next room, and sent the first bravo he encountered to stand guard, so that no one except her would set foot inside the room. Then he left the castle and headed down the hill at a run. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10459" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10489">The manuscript does not mention the distance between the castle and the village where the Cardinal was staying, but judging from the events I am about to relate, it could not have been more than a long walk. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10490" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10528">We know this not only from the influx of people from the valley and even farther away, but also because the memoirs of that period record that crowds used to come from twenty miles away or more to see Federigo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10529" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10575">The bravi who encountered him on their way up the hill stopped respectfully to let their master pass, waiting to see if he had any orders or if he wanted them to accompany him on some expedition. They didn’t know what to make of his manner, or his glaring in response to their bows. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10576" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10591">When he got to the main road, the passersby were amazed to see him without his customary escort. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10592" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10611">Nevertheless, each of them stepped to the side, leaving enough space for one, and doffed their hats in deference. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10612" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10632">In the village, he encountered a large crowd, but as his name traveled from mouth to mouth, the crowd opened up to let him pass. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10633" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10642">He approached one man and asked where the Cardinal might be. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10643" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10652">“At the parish priest’s,” the man replied with a bow, pointing out its location. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10653" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10673">The Nameless One headed in that direction and entered a small courtyard filled with priests, all of whom eyed him with surprise and suspicion. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10674" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10689">Directly across the yard, he saw an open door that led to a sitting room where many other priests had congregated. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10690" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10714">He slipped off his rifle, leaned it against the wall in a corner, and entered the room. There, too, he was greeted by stares, whispers of his name, then silence. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10715" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10730">Turning to one of the priests, he asked where the Cardinal was, saying he wished to speak with him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10731" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10769">“I’m not from around here,” the priest answered. He looked around the room and called out to the Cardinal’s chaplain and crossbearer, who was sitting in a corner and whispering to a colleague, “Him? The notorious one? What’s he doing here? Keep your distance!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10770" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10826">But when the chaplain heard his name echoing in the silent room he had to come forward. He bowed to the Nameless One, listened to his request, glanced quickly at his face with an uneasy curiosity before looking down again, then stood still for a moment and said, or rather stammered, “I wouldn’t know whether His Grace…at this moment…is…maybe…could…Anyway, I’ll go see.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10827" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10841">And reluctantly, he went to convey the message to the Cardinal in the next room. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10842" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10892">At this point in our story, I cannot resist lingering for a moment, like a sad and weary wayfarer who has traveled through an arid and wild landscape, and stops to kill a little time lying in the grassy shade of a nice tree near a freshwater spring. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10893" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10942">Because here we meet a character whose name and memory has the capacity to revive our spirits with peaceful reverence and joyful affection, particularly now, after we have witnessed so much pain and contemplated such manifold and appalling depravity. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10943" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10972">I absolutely must say a few words about this character, but if any of you would rather not hear them, and instead prefer to continue on with the story, you are welcome to skip to the next chapter. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_10973" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11010">Born in 1564, Federigo Borromeo was one of those rare men of any era who dedicated great intellect, the resources of his vast wealth, all the advantages of a privileged status, and an unwavering sense of purpose in seeking out and practicing good. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11011" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11040">His life was like a clean brook that springs from a cliff, running along a path through various landscapes and then emptying, still clear, into the river, without ever becoming stagnant or muddy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11041" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11092">Though he grew up surrounded by luxury and splendor, he also learned about sacrifice and humility, the vanity of earthly pleasure, the injustice of pride, and the true dignity and riches that, heartfelt or not, are passed down from one generation to the next through the most basic teachings of religion. He heeded those words and lessons. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11093" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11154">He took them seriously, tested them, and found them to be true. Though other words and lessons that opposed his beliefs were also passed from generation to generation, with the same certainty and often from the same lips, he realized that they could not be true. So he resolved to let the truth be the guide of all his thoughts and deeds. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11155" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11196">Convinced that life was not predestined to be a burden for the many and a feast for the few, but rather a task for all, for which all must answer, he sought ways to make his own life more purposeful and saintly from an early age. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11197" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11228">In 1580, he made public his decision to dedicate himself to the priesthood, and was ordained by his cousin Carlo, who by long and universal acclaim was already considered destined for sainthood. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11229" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11284">Soon after, Federigo enrolled in the college his cousin had founded in Pavia, which still bears the family name. He applied himself assiduously to his prescribed duties, and also took on two more responsibilities: teaching Christian doctrine to the poor and forsaken, and visiting, serving, consoling, and caring for the sick. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11285" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11335">He used his conferred authority to persuade his colleagues to join him in his work. He led by example with honesty and generosity, as if destined to become a leader, regardless of the nobility of his birth. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11336" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11358">In fact, he did not seek and even studiously avoided any of the advantages his status could have granted him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11359" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11384">He kept a table that was poor, not frugal, and clothing that was poor, not plain, in keeping with his general tenor and behavior. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11385" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11405">Though some of his relatives felt his behavior was debasing the family name, he never considered changing. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11406" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11504">When tutors attempted to sneak little luxuries to him, treating him like a prince, he resisted, and even waged war on them. Perhaps they thought they could win him over with time; or they believed that their sycophancy would be rewarded through reflected splendor; or they were those prudent souls that recoil equally from virtue and vice, always preaching that perfection lies in the middle, where they themselves felt most comfortable. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11505" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11525">But these attempts did not fool Federigo, and though he was still between boyhood and adolescence, he reprimanded all who attempted such gestures. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11526" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11629">It is no surprise, then, that Federigo modeled his own behavior after that of his superior, Cardinal Carlo, his senior by twenty-six years, whose grave, solemn presence was living proof of his saintliness, a constant reminder of his works, a man whose authority was increased, as if it were needed, by the open, spontaneous praise of those who surrounded him, whoever and however many they were. What is surprising, however, is that when Federigo was only twenty years old, and Carlo died, no one noticed that he had lost his guide and conscience. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11630" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11691">His intellect, piety, relationships with other powerful cardinals, and his family’s status (now also considered the epitome of saintly leadership, thanks to Carlo) made Federigo a likely candidate for promotion to a high office in the Church. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11692" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11762">But he was deeply convinced of something that no one who professes Christianity can legitimately deny. The Church teaches that no man is superior to other men, except in serving them. He feared higher office, not because he spurned serving others—few lives have been as dedicated to others as his—but because he considered himself unworthy and incapable of such high and perilous service. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11763" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11780">So when in 1595 Clement VIII offered him the archbishopric of Milan, he was taken aback, and refused without hesitation. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11781" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11787">At the express order of the Pope, however, he accepted. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11788" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11823">As we all know, such demonstrations of humility are neither difficult nor rare. Besides, hypocrisy requires no more ingenuity to profess such demonstrations than mockery does to deride them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11824" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11836">But does this mean they cannot be the natural expression of a wise and virtuous sentiment? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11837" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11880">The way one lives is the proof of principles professed in words. Even if the words that express these sentiments come from the lips of all the impostors and all the jesters in the world, they will always be beautiful when they are preceded or followed by a life of selflessness and sacrifice. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11881" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11913">Archbishop Federigo engaged in a constant, singular effort to use for his own person only the finances, time, and care that were strictly necessary. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11914" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11936">He would repeat the age-old saying that the Church’s revenues are the patrimony of the poor. The following examples show how he lived by this creed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_11937" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12004">He commissioned an estimate of his personal and household expenses. When he discovered that they amounted to six hundred scudi (scudo is the gold coin of the same weight and value as what would later be called the zecchino), he ordered that all household expenses should henceforth be paid from his personal assets, for he felt it was wrong for a wealthy man like himself to live off the Church. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12005" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12053">He was such a frugal and parsimonious administrator of his own needs that he never threw away an article of clothing until it was completely threadbare. As his contemporaries noted, he combined a taste for simplicity with exquisite cleanliness: two remarkable habits in such a dirty and gaudy era. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12054" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12091">Likewise, he ensured that no leftovers from his frugal meals would go to waste and donated them to the hospice for the poor; by his order, a resident came to his dining room every day to collect whatever remained. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12092" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12190">These concerns might lead you to imagine a stingy, miserly, petty virtue, a mind fixated on minutia and incapable of higher projects. But then, there is the existence of the Biblioteca Ambrosiana. Federigo conceived and built it from the ground up, energetically and with courageous munificence. He stocked it with books and manuscripts. In addition to donating his own collection, which he had assembled with great trouble and expense, he sent eight of the most cultivated experts he could find to purchase books throughout Italy, France, Spain, Germany, Flanders, Greece, Lebanon, and Jerusalem. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12191" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12201">In this way he managed to gather approximately three thousand printed volumes and fourteen thousand manuscripts. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12202" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12317">He added a college of scholars to the library. (Nine at first, whose salaries he paid while he was alive. After he died, they were reduced to two, since the ordinary revenues could not cover the cost.) They were tasked with cultivating various studies—theology, history, literature, the ancient Church, and Oriental languages—with the requirement that each of them publish works on their assigned subject matter. He also added what he called the trilingual college, for the study of Greek, Latin, and Italian, and a secondary school where students were instructed in these subjects and languages, so that one day they could teach them themselves. He also added a printing press for Oriental languages, namely Hebrew, Chaldean, Arabic, Persian, and Armenian; a painting gallery, a sculpture gallery, and a school for the three main design arts. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12318" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12369">For these fields he was able to find trained professors. For the others, we have seen the lengths to which he had gone to collect books and manuscripts; it must have been much harder to find the typefaces for those languages, which at the time were less cultivated in Europe than they are today. It was even harder to find the men. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12370" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12424">Eight of the nine scholars he hired were young seminarians, which indicates Federigo’s opinion of the scholarship and the reputations made during that period. Posterity seems to have confirmed his judgment, by consigning the work and reputations of those scholars to the trash heap of history. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12425" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12465">The regulations that he established for the use and administration of the library demonstrate his hope that it would remain in use for years to come, which is not only a beautiful aspiration, but in many respects ahead of its time in wisdom and nobility. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12466" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12533">He instructed the librarian to correspond with the most learned men in Europe, gather news from them of the latest science as well as advice on the best books coming out in every field, and acquire them. Then, he was to inform scholars about useful books they might not know about, and provide each person—citizens and foreigners alike—with the opportunity and time to use the library according to their needs. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12534" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12554">Nowadays, that might seem obvious and innate to the function of a library, but during that time, it was not. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12555" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12680">In a history of the Ambrosiana, Pierpaolo Bosco, the librarian after Federigo’s death, wrote (using the syntax and elegance common to that century) how unique it was that a library built by a private individual, and almost entirely at his own expense, would allow the public to browse and borrow from its collection. Visitors were also offered a place to sit, as well as paper, pen, and inkpot, so they could take any notes they needed. In contrast, other renowned public libraries of Italy locked their books in cabinets rather than put them on display; librarians only removed them as a favor afforded to a precious few. No one ever thought that scholars might want the opportunity to study them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12681" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12706">If one was to endow such a library, it meant that you were essentially removing books from circulation, a style of cultivation that leaves a field barren, and unfortunately continues to happen all too often. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12707" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12764">Do not ask the effects of Borromeo’s foundation on public culture: In two sentences you could show whether they were miraculous or nonexistent. But it would be laborious, useless, and inappropriate to try to explain them here. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12765" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12849">Just consider what a generous, judicious, benevolent, persevering lover of human improvement he must have been to create such opportunities, despite the ignorance, inertia, and general antipathy toward scholarly pursuits that were common at the time. The protests of “What does it matter?” “This is how he spends his money?” “What an idea!” and “That’s all we needed,” probably far surpassed the expenses of his undertakings: approximately one hundred and five thousand scudi, almost all of which came from his own pocket. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12850" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12906">But to simply call him supremely charitable and generous does not even scrape the surface of how much he spent in emergency relief to the needy. There may still be some who think that such expenditures—I was about to say all expenditures, really—are the best and most useful form of charity. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12907" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12927">But Federigo considered true charity his primary duty, and here, as in all else, his actions were consistent with these convictions. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12928" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12975">He gave generously to the poor throughout his life, but particularly during the famine that our story has already described. From this period, I have the opportunity to report some episodes that illustrate the wisdom and kindness that characterized his charitable giving. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12976" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12994">His biographers have noted many unique examples of his virtues, but here I will mention only one. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_12995" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13053">When he learned that a nobleman had used tricks and coercion to force his daughter to become a nun, despite her wish to get married, he summoned the father. And when he got him to admit that the true reason for that persecution was that he did not have the four thousand scudi needed to arrange a suitable (in his opinion) marriage for his daughter, Federigo provided her with the money. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13054" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13082">Some may consider this to be overly generous, ill-considered, and too indulgent of the foolish whims of an arrogant man; there must be a hundred better ways to spend four thousand scudi. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13083" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13137">I have no reply except to say that I wish there were more instances of philanthropy so unrestrained by public opinion (every era has its own), so independent of general trends, as in this case of a man inspired to give four thousand scudi to prevent a young girl from becoming a nun against her will. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13138" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13153">His tireless charity stood out not only in his generosity, but also in his manner. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13154" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13184">He was welcoming to all, and believed everyone deserved a friendly face and loving kindness, especially those considered to be of low birth, particularly since they received so little human warmth. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13185" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13212">Here, too, he had to contend with the gentlemen who believed in ne quid nimis—“nothing in excess”—who preferred to keep him within limits, that is to say, within their own limits in all things. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13213" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13286">Once, during a visit to a remote mountain village, Federigo was teaching a group of poor children and he would lovingly pat them on the head between his questions and instructions. One such gentleman advised him to keep his distance from these “dirty and disgusting” children: as if the good man supposed that Federigo did not have the foresight or sense to come to such a refined realization himself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13287" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13328">In certain times and matters, men holding higher offices have a singular misfortune: While they will rarely find someone who will advise them of their faults, there is no shortage of brave men ready to criticize their good deeds. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13329" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13356">Not without some animus, the good Bishop replied, “Their souls are in my care, and they may never see my face again. Don’t you think they deserve my tenderness?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13357" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13396">These moments of irritation were rare, however, and he was widely admired for his gentle manners and imperturbable calm, which many attributed to his extraordinarily happy temperament. This was the result of the constant governing of a sharp and temperamental disposition. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13397" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13427">The only times he was severe or indeed harsh was when the priests working under him were guilty of greed, negligence, or other sins contrary to their noble calling. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13428" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13469">In matters of his own interests or earthly glory, he never expressed any indication of joy, regret, enthusiasm, or agitation: which was admirable if he did not feel these impulses in his heart, and even more so if in fact he did. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13470" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13540">At the many papal conclaves he attended, he developed the reputation of never aspiring to that post so coveted by the ambitious and so dreaded by the pious. Once, however, when a very influential colleague came to offer him his vote and that of his faction (an ugly word, but that’s the term they used), Federigo rejected the proposal so vehemently that the colleague dropped all thought of it and turned elsewhere. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13541" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13553">This same modesty and aversion to power was equally apparent in the everyday moments of his life. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13554" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13599">When his duties forced him to organize and govern, he was cautious and tireless, always avoiding meddling in the affairs of others. Even when others requested his involvement, he used discretion and restraint, which was uncommon among men like Federigo, who zealously pursue the good. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13600" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13630">If I were to indulge in summarizing the remarkable features of his character, I would almost certainly describe a unique combination of seemingly opposite and irreconcilable qualities. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13631" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13678">But allow me to note another unique aspect of his beautiful life. Although most of it was filled with activity, administration, functions, teaching, audiences, diocesan visits, travels, and controversies, his studies occupied no small part of his time: as much, in fact, as a professional man of letters. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13679" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13697">And among his many different claims to fame, his contemporaries also considered him a scholar. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13698" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13738">We should not overlook, however, his strong conviction and long practice of ideas that many would find rather strange and baseless nowadays. I say this even to those who are eager to justify them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13739" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13795">Anyone who wishes to defend him tends to argue, most commonly, that these beliefs were errors of his time rather than his own. This argument might be valid, in some cases, after a detailed examination of the facts, but it is meaningless if people adopt it randomly and out of context, as they usually do. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13796" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13844">And since I do not wish to solve complicated questions with simple answers, or prolong a single episode, I will forgo explaining it. All I will say is that we cannot expect perfection, even in the most admirable of men; if we do, we might as well write a eulogy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13845" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13872">Some of my readers might be wondering—and not be insulted by my assumption—whether this man of such intellect and learning bequeathed some monument to posterity. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13873" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13875">Indeed he did! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13876" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13919">He left behind about one hundred volumes, both long and short, Latin and Italian, printed and in manuscript. All of his moral treatises and sermons, as well as dissertations on history, sacred and profane antiquity, literature, the arts, and other subjects, are stored in the library he founded. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13920" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13938">“And how come,” my readers might ask, “so many works are forgotten, little known, or so seldom studied? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_13939" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_14015">How can a man of such intellect, learning, experience of men and the world, introspection, passion for beauty and the good, candor, and so many other qualities of a great writer not have left—among these hundred volumes—a single one considered praiseworthy, even by people who might disapprove of his other works, a single title that is known, even by people who might not read the book? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_14016" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_14037">How could all the writing he produced not be enough, collectively, to earn him literary fame among posterity?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_14038" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_14071">This is undoubtedly a reasonable question, and raises a very interesting issue. The observation of some general facts would yield the reasons for this phenomenon and help to explain other similar occurrences. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_14072" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_14089">But those reasons would be many and long-winded. And what if they were not to your liking? Or they made you turn up your nose? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap22-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_14090" targetEnd="quarantana/cap22.xml#c22_14121">So rather than gossiping about this man, let us pick up our story where we left off, so we can see him in action, following the guidance of our author. </note>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>