<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>2022</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed: a novel</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
          <date>2022</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Michael Moore</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="english_2022_cap28">
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10037">After the Saint Martin’s Day riots, times of plenty seemed to have miraculously returned to Milan: Bread piled high in every bakery; prices as low as they’d been in better years, for flour, too. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10038" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10078">The people who had taken to the streets on those two days to protest, or worse, had something to celebrate now (except for the few who had been arrested). And don’t go thinking they settled down once the shock of the arrests had worn off. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10079" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10104">In every square, corner, and tavern, there was public jubilation, rounds of congratulations, and boastful whispers that they had figured out how to bring down the price of bread. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10105" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10129">Amid all the celebrations and bravado, however, there was (and how could there not be?) an apprehension, a foreboding, that the good times would not last. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10130" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10175">The bakers and flour sellers continued to be attacked, as they had been during the previous period of artificial abundance produced, temporarily, by Antonio Ferrer’s first tariff. Everyone consumed without restraint. Anyone with some money set aside invested it in bread and flour, storing them in bins, small casks, and kettles. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10176" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10207">This competition to take advantage of the low prices made it not only impossible for the situation to last (which it was inherently), but harder to sustain for even a short time. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10208" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10323">And then, on the fifteenth of November, Ferrer, De orden de Su Excelencia, issued a decree that anyone who had grain or flour at home was prohibited from buying any more, and everyone was prohibited from buying more than a two-day supply of bread, on pain of pecuniary or bodily punishment, at the discretion of His Excellency. Every official and every individual was commanded to report transgressors. Judges were ordered to search specific houses. At the same time, bakers received a new order to keep their shops well stocked with bread, on pain, in the event of failure, of five years or more on the galleys, at the discretion of H.E. To imagine that any such decree could be executed would take quite an imagination indeed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10324" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10367">And if every decree issued in those days had been executed, the Duchy of Milan would have had to send as many men out to sea as the British fleet does today. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10368" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10391">Be that as it may, if the bakers were to obey these orders and bake that much bread, they needed a sufficient supply of ingredients. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10392" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10430">There were thoughts (since during a famine there are always renewed attempts to make bread from products normally consumed in another form), there were thoughts, I was saying, of adding rice to the ingredients for multigrain bread. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10431" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10486">So on the twenty-third of November, the Commissioner and Tribunal of Provision issued a decree to confiscate half of all rough rice (risone, as they used to call it, and still do) in everyone’s possession. The penalty for having it without the permission of the gentlemen of the Tribunal was forfeiture of the rice and a fine of three scudi per bushel. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10487" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10493">The most honest of decrees, as everyone can see. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10494" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10507">But this rice had to be paid for, and at a price vastly disproportionate to the cost of bread. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10508" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10545">The task of making up for the huge gap was imposed on the city, but the Council of the Decurioni, which had assumed responsibility for the city, resolved on that same day to communicate to the Governor that this policy was not sustainable. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10546" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10608">In his decree of the seventh of December, the Governor set the price of rice at twelve liras per bushel; anyone who sold it at a higher rate, or refused to sell, was threatened with confiscation of the rice and a fine equivalent to its value, and greater pecuniary and bodily punishment, including the galleys, at the discretion of H.E, in accordance with the quality of the cases and the persons. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10609" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10654">The price of white rice had already been set prior to the uprising. And the rate, or—to use the most celebrated term in modern annals—the maximum of wheat and other more ordinary grains, was probably established by other decrees that I have not had the opportunity to see. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10655" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10679">As a result of the price of bread and flour being kept so low in Milan, a parade of people rushed in from the countryside to buy it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10680" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10763">To remedy what Don Gonzalo called this “inconvenience,” he prohibited, by another decree on the fifteenth of December, the exportation of bread worth more than twenty soldi from the city, on pain of forfeiture of the bread and a twenty-five scudi fine, and, in the event of inability to pay, two jerks of the strappado in public, and an even greater punishment, as always, at the discretion of H.E. On the twenty-second of the same month (it is unclear why so late), he issued a similar order for flour and grain. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10764" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10786">The masses had wanted to bring back the days of plenty through looting and arson. The government wanted to maintain them through the galleys and the strappado. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10787" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10813">These methods were complementary, but did they help achieve the goal? The reader will see in a moment. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10814" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10869">After all, it’s easy to see and worthwhile to observe the logical connection between these strange measures. Each was the inevitable consequence of its predecessor, and all of them stemmed from the initial decision to set the price of bread far below its real price: that is to say, rather than leave things to the natural law of supply and demand. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10870" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10912">To the masses, such an expedient has always appeared, and could only ever appear, to be as fair as it is easy to execute. So it is only natural that, amid the suffering and hardship of the famine, they would want, implore, and, if possible, impose set prices. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10913" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10950">But as the consequences of the decrees began to be felt, the authorities had to remedy each one, with a law that prohibited people from doing exactly what the previous law had encouraged. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10951" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10960">Allow me to observe in passing a singular coincidence. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_10961" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11065">In a country and period closer to our own, during the most clamorous and remarkable period in modern history, recourse was made in similar circumstances to similar expedients (substantially the same, you might say—varying only by degree—and in almost the same order), despite it being a different era, with a growth of learning in Europe, and especially in that country. This was mainly because the mob, which had not received the benefit of that learning, was able to impose its judgment for so long and forcer la main, force the hand—as they say in that country—of the lawmakers. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11066" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11114">Getting back to our story, in the end, the two main effects of the uprising were the immediate loss and destruction of food, and widespread, reckless, and excessive food consumption for as long as the low prices held, at the expense of the small amount of grain that was supposed to last until the new harvest. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11115" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11144">In addition to these general effects, let us not forget the four poor devils who were hanged as leaders of the riot: two in front of the Forno delle Grucce, two at one end of the street of the Commissioner of Provision. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11145" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11174">The historical accounts from those days were written so haphazard that I have been unable to find out how and when the brutal rates were ended. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11175" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11207">If, given the lack of concrete facts, I may venture a guess, I’d be inclined to believe that they were abolished shortly before or after the twenty-fourth of December, the day of the executions. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11208" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11264">As for the decrees, after the last one I mentioned, on the twenty-second of the same month, I have found none that deal with the food supply. Maybe the documents were destroyed or eluded my research, or maybe in the end the government, discouraged if not chastened by the ineffectiveness of its remedies, and overwhelmed by events, abandoned them to their fate. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11265" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11391">What I have found in the accounts of more than one historian (inclined, as they were, to describe great events rather than to identify their causes and development) is a portrait of the country, and mainly of the city, in the late winter and spring, when the cause of the ills—the imbalance between the supply of food and the demand for it—was aggravated rather than eliminated by remedies that temporarily suspended its effects. Little was to be gained even by sufficient imports of foreign wheat. Such a measure was obstructed by the lack of public and private funds, food shortages in the surrounding villages, the scarcity, slowness, and restrictions of commerce, and the laws themselves, which tended to create low prices and keep them low, when, as I said before, the true cause of the famine, or rather the famine itself, continued unchecked and in full force. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11392" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11399">Here is my copy of that heartbreaking portrait. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11400" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11425">Stores were boarded up as far as the eye could see; workshops were mostly abandoned; and the streets were an appalling spectacle, an endless parade of misery, a perpetual abode of suffering. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11426" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11586">The beggars by trade were now the minority, lost and confused among the multitude of new arrivals, and reduced to competing for charity with people from whom they might have once received it: shop boys and apprentices who, dismissed by workshop owners, had lost their daily wages, and scraped by on their reserves and capital; the owners themselves, who had been bankrupted and ruined by the shutdown of business; and workers and master craftsmen of every trade and art, from the most ordinary to the most refined, the most basic to the most luxurious. They wandered from door to door, street to street, leaning against corner walls, crouching on the sidewalks in front of houses and churches, begging piteously for charity, or wavering between need and a still ungoverned shame, emaciated, weary, shivering from the cold and hunger in ragged, threadbare clothing that still bore the signs, in many, of the comfortable life they used to lead, while their apathy and despair offered vague clues of earlier habits of honest hard work. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11587" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11625">Servants formed no small part of the pitiable horde, dismissed by masters who had themselves fallen on hard times, or who, despite their wealth, were unable, in such a year, to maintain the customary luxury of a household staff. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11626" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11658">And attached to these various indigents were a number of others who were used to living, in part, on their earnings: children, women, and the elderly, clinging to their former supporters or begging in other areas of the city. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11659" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11721">Easily distinguished by their matted forelocks and tattered splendor, as well as something in their attitude, their behavior, and the marks imprinted on a face by the habits of a lifetime (the stranger the life, the sharper and clearer the marks), were many bravi who, having lost the bread of their criminal livelihood due to the common condition, were reduced to begging for the bread of charity. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11722" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11785">Subdued by hunger, competing for charity with their former victims, they shuffled, frightened and dazed, down streets they had long ruled with heads held high, and fierce and threatening looks, wearing rich, gaudy livery, long feathers in their caps, armed with expensive weapons, dressed sharply, and perfumed. Now they humbly extended the same hand for charity that they had once raised brazenly, to threaten, or treacherously, to wound. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11786" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11824">Perhaps the most appalling, and at the same time, most heartbreaking sight was that of the peasants: individuals, couples, entire families—husbands and wives carrying babies in their arms or bound to their backs, holding children by the hand, and trailed by their elderly. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11825" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11885">Some had seen their houses broken into and looted by soldiers (billeted or passing through) and fled in desperation. To arouse more sympathy, and as a badge of their misery, some of them exhibited the bruises and scars from beatings received while defending their last few supplies or escaping a blind and brutal violence. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11886" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11943">Others were spared that particular scourge but had been driven from their homes by two afflictions from which no corner was immune—barren land and heavy taxation (more exorbitant than ever to satisfy the so-called wartime needs)—and had come to the city, and continued to come, as if expecting the ancient seat to be a last refuge of wealth and pious munificence. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11944" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11994">The newly arrived could be identified not so much by their uncertain gait and air of freshness as by their dismay and irritation at finding such total competition for their misery, in a place where they had thought they would be singular objects of compassion and thus attract attention and relief. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_11995" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12042">Their rivals, who had been wandering and living on the city streets for longer, surviving on help they obtained or received seemingly at random amid the vast imbalance between supply and demand, had a more grim and weary consternation etched on their faces and gestures. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12043" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12127">Their clothing was different (on those who could still be considered clothed), as was their appearance: pale faces from the lowland, tanned ones from the higher plains and the hills, ruddy ones from the mountains. But they were all gaunt and distraught, with sunken eyes, blank stares that were glowering or numb, matted hair, and long unkempt beards. Bodies that hard work had developed and toughened were now worn down by poverty. Through their tattered clothes you could see wrinkled skin on bony arms and emaciated shins and chests. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12128" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12158">And different, but no less painful, than the sight of this defeated vigor, was the sight of the weakest, women and children, succumbing more quickly to languor and exhaustion. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12159" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12179">Here and there along the streets were piles of straw leaning against the houses, trampled and mixed with foul trash. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12180" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12206">But this filth was both a gift and an example of charity. For these were beds lent to some of the poor wretches on which to lay their heads at night. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12207" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12256">Every now and then—even during the day—you could see one of them lying down or stretching out, strength sapped and legs buckling from hunger and exhaustion. Sometimes the grim bed held a dead body. Sometimes a person would suddenly collapse, like a rag, and fall to the cobblestones, lifeless. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12257" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12275">You might also see the occasional neighbor or passerby leaning over certain of these beds, moved by a sudden pang of compassion. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12276" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12306">In some places, there were signs of a more orderly and lasting relief, delivered by a wealthy hand that was used to doing good on a large scale: This was the hand of the good Federigo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12307" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12358">He had selected six priests in whom deep and tireless charity was accompanied and served by a robust constitution. He divided them into pairs, each of which was assigned to patrol a third of the city, followed by porters carrying various foods, subtler and more rapid restoratives, and clothing. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12359" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12386">Every morning, the three pairs would set out for different neighborhoods, go up to the people lying abandoned on the ground, and minister to each according to his or her need. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12387" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12406">Those who were already at death’s door and no longer able to ingest food would be given the last rites and the consolations of religion. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12407" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12435">Soup, eggs, bread, and wine were dispensed to the hungry. Others, exhausted by a more prolonged hunger, were offered broth, a restorative tonic, and stronger wine, after first being revived, if necessary, by spirits. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12436" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12445">At the same time, they distributed clothing to those more indecently and woefully exposed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12446" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12468">Nor did their assistance end there. The good shepherd wanted, at least wherever possible, to provide more effective and lasting relief. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12469" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12519">The poor who, thanks to that first restorative, found the strength to get back on their feet and walk, were given a little money so that the recurrence of need and the lack of other support would not cause a swift relapse to their former plight. For others, room and board were sought in a nearby house. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12520" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12565">At the homes of the well-to-do, they were usually welcomed out of charity, as the Cardinal had recommended. At the homes of others, whose means fell short of their goodwill, the priests asked that the poor soul be given room and board; they set a price, and immediately paid a deposit. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12566" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12583">They would then notify the local parish priests, so that they might visit the indigent, in addition to going back themselves. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12584" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12605">Needless to say, Federigo did not limit his cares to the most extreme cases, nor did he wait for them to be reached before taking action. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12606" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12633">So ardent and varied was his charity that it heeded every call and responded to every need, rushing in to aid suffering it had not foreseen, and taking as many forms, so to speak, as the variety of needs. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12634" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12671">In fact, by gathering all of his resources, saving even more rigorously, drawing on reserves meant for other types of largesse that were now secondary, he looked for every possible way to raise money and used all of it to feed the hungry. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12672" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12730">He made large purchases of grain and sent much of it to the parts of the diocese with the greatest shortages. And since the food relief fell far short of the need, he also sent salt, which—according to Ripamonti (Historiae patriae, decadis V, book VI, 386)—“converted the grass of the fields and the bark of the trees into food.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12731" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12813">He also distributed wheat and money to the parishes of the city, which he himself visited, neighborhood by neighborhood, to distribute charity. He helped many poor families anonymously. At the Archbishop’s palace, as attested by a contemporary writer, the physician Alessandro Tadino (in the Raguaglio we will often have occasion to cite below), two thousand bowls of rice soup were distributed every morning. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12814" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12889">But even these acts of charity—which we can certainly call heroic, since they came from only one man and from only his resources (Federigo declined, as a rule, to administer the generosity of others)—together with the generosity of other private hands, who though not so rich, were still quite numerous, and the subsidies decreed by the Council of the Decurioni, and distributed by the Tribunal of Provision, still fell far short of the need. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12890" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12948">While some people from the mountains, on the verge of starvation, had their lives prolonged by the Cardinal’s charity, others reached that extreme anyway, while still others relapsed once that measured ration was depleted. Other areas that charity deemed less afflicted found their aid not forgotten, but rather postponed, until the affliction became fatal. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_12949" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13002">Death was everywhere, and people flocked to the city from every part, where a couple thousand of the hungry—the healthiest and the most experienced at elbowing their way through a crowd—would acquire a soup, enough to stave off death for another day. But thousands more were left behind, envying those whom we might call the lucky ones, although the left behind often included their wives, children, and parents. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13003" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13041">And while in some parts of the city, the most forlorn and abject were picked up off the ground, revived, cared and temporarily provided for, in a hundred other parts they collapsed, languished, and even died without help or comfort. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13042" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13082">All day long, you could hear the muddled droning of voices begging on the streets. All night, a murmur of groans, broken occasionally by sudden loud laments, howling, and solemn invocations that ended in piercing screams. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13083" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13119">Amid such dire straits, with so many different grievances, there was remarkably no attempt at nor even a call for an uprising; at least there is no record of one. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13120" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13156">And yet, among those living and dying in that manner, there were many who had not attended the school of resignation. There were hundreds of the very same men who, on Saint Martin’s Day, had made their voices heard. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13157" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13213">Nor should we think that all had been restrained by the example of those four poor wretches who had paid the price for everyone. For what effect could the mere memory of that torture have on the multitude of refugees, knowing that they, too, had been sentenced to a slow torture which they were already undergoing? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13214" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13253">But this is how we men are made: Indignant and furious, we rebel against moderate ills, but bow in silence before the extremes. We bear the worst of what we once considered unbearable, stupefied but not resigned. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13254" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13294">The constant decline in population of that pitiable throng were replenished many times over every day. People kept pouring into the city, first from the neighboring villages, then from the wider countryside, then from the other cities in the state, and finally even from cities outside the state. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13295" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13352">And in the meantime, the longtime inhabitants of Milan were leaving every day, some to avoid the sight of so much affliction, others, seeing themselves replaced, as it were, by new competitors in begging, left in a last desperate attempt to find help anywhere—anywhere it might exist, anywhere they would not have to vie with such a massive and insistent crowd. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13353" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13382">As they left, they ran into pilgrims coming from the opposite direction, a sight repulsive to both sides, and a grim sample, a sinister omen, of the destination toward which each was headed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13383" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13414">But each continued on their way, if no longer with the hope of changing their fate, then at least so as not to return beneath a sky turned hateful, and to never again see the places where they had lost all hope. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13415" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13447">Except that some, their forces failing them altogether, collapsed in the road, lifeless, where their bodies remained: an even more woeful sight to their fellows in misery, an object of horror, and perhaps a reproach to the other travelers. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13448" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13522">“I myself saw,” wrote Ripamonti, “on the road that circles the walls, the body of a woman…half-chewed grass sticking out of her mouth, and her lips frozen in a wrathful, convulsive effort…she had a bundle on her back, and swathed in the rags around her breast was an infant, wailing for the pap…some good souls arrived who, picking the poor creature up off the ground, took it away, thus fulfilling the first duties of a mother.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13523" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13543">That contrast between splendor and rags, excess and misery—an ordinary sight in ordinary times—had by then ceased entirely. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13544" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13564">Rags and misery were almost everywhere, and what could be distinguished was the bare semblance of frugal sobriety. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13565" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13623">The nobility could be seen walking in clothing that was plain and modest, or even threadbare and cheap. Some, because the common causes of the misery had so reduced their fortunes or given the final blow to already shaky patrimonies; others, because they feared that ostentation would provoke public desperation, or were embarrassed to insult the public calamity. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13624" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13653">The hated but respected tyrants, who used to go about with an entourage of bravi, now traveled alone for the most part, with their heads lowered and faces that seemed to both offer and plead for peace. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13654" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13696">Others, who in times of prosperity had already been of a more humane disposition and more modest bearing, now seemed confused, dismayed, and almost overwhelmed by the constant sight of a misery that surpassed not only the possibility of relief but I would almost say the limits of compassion. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13697" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13718">Those with the means to offer charity had to make a grim choice between hunger and hunger, urgency and urgency. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13719" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13783">And no sooner was a sympathetic hand seen extended toward the hand of some unfortunate, then other unfortunates would enter into the fray. Those with the most remaining strength pushed their way to the front to beg more insistently. The exhausted, the elderly, and the children raised their bony hands. Mothers lifted and displayed from afar their crying infants, swaddled in rags, and doubled over in their hands from hunger. — </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13784" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13831">And so the winter and spring passed. For months, the Tribunal of Health had been warning the Tribunal of Provision of the danger of contagion looming over the city because of the misery growing in every part of it. It proposed that the vagrants be housed in various shelters. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13832" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13869">As this proposal was being discussed, as it was being approved, as consideration was being given to the means, methods, and places to enact it, more and more bodies piled up on the streets every day, and, in direct proportion, so did misery. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13870" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13935">At the Tribunal of Provision, another proposal was made—considered the easiest and most expeditious—to gather all the vagrants, healthy and sick alike, in a single place, the lazaretto, where they would be fed and cared for at public expense. And so it was decided, against the recommendations of the health authorities, who argued that such a large gathering would increase the very dangers being guarded against. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13936" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13994">— The lazaretto of Milan (if this story should, by chance, fall into the hands of someone who has neither seen nor heard of it) is a four-sided, almost square enclosure, outside the city, to the left of the Porta Orientale, separated from the city walls by a moat, the road circling the walls, and a ditch that surrounds the enclosure itself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_13995" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14043">The two longer sides measure about five hundred yards; the other two are maybe fifteen yards shorter; all four are subdivided into small one-story rooms on the outermost side. On the inside, a vaulted portico, supported by small slender columns, runs along three of the walls. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14044" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14082">There were two hundred and eighty-eight rooms, more or less. In our own time, a large opening made in the middle, and a smaller one in a corner of the side wall facing the main road, removed a number of them, I don’t know how many. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14083" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14107">At the time of our story, there were only two entrances: one in the middle of the side facing the city walls, and the other on the opposite side. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14108" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14120">In the center of the enclosure there was, and still is, a small octagonal church. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14121" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14208">The original purpose of the complex, begun in the year 1489 with money from a private bequest and continued later with funds from both the government and other testators and donors, was, as the name implied, to shelter, when necessary, victims of the plague. The plague had already broken out on an average of two, four, six, or eight times in a century—long before this period and for a long time after—striking first one, then another European country, sometimes impacting a large part of it or even sweeping throughout the entire territory. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14209" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14225">At the time of which we are speaking, the lazaretto was being used only to store merchandise subject to quarantine. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14226" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14258">Now, to empty it, the authorities dispensed with strict adherence to health regulations. After the prescribed disinfections and inspections had been completed, quickly quickly, all the merchandise was released in a single go. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14259" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14291">Straw was put down in all the rooms, and food supplies were provisioned in the available quality and quantity. Then by public decree, all vagrants were invited to report there for shelter. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14292" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14334">Many came in willingly; all those who were lying sick in the streets and public piazzas were transported there. In a few days, between one group and the other, more than three thousand people were housed, but far more were left outside. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14335" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14443">Maybe each of them was hoping to be one of the few left to enjoy the city’s charity. Maybe it was a natural aversion to being confined. Or the poor’s distrust of anything proposed by the rich and powerful (a distrust that is always proportionate to the mutual ignorance between those who feel it and those who inspire it, to the number of the poor, and to the inanity of the laws). Or maybe they knew what was actually being offered. Or maybe it was all of these things combined, or some other reason. The fact remains that most of them, ignoring the decree, continued to shuffle down the streets, barely lifting their feet. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14444" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14453">Therefore, it was thought best to shift from invitation to coercion. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14454" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14501">The police went on patrols to force the vagrants into the lazaretto. Anyone who resisted was taken there in restraints. For each person brought in, the police received a bounty of ten soldi, which goes to show how, even in times of great scarcity, there is always room for the misuse of public money. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14502" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14550">And although the assumption—indeed the express intention of the Tribunal of Provision—had been to evict a certain number of vagrants from the city and let them live and die in freedom elsewhere, they were now pursued so relentlessly that, in no time at all, the lazaretto’s population, between guests and prisoners, was approaching ten thousand. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14551" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14574">Women and children were presumably lodged in separate quarters, but the contemporary memoirs don’t specify. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14575" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14665">There must have been no lack of rules and regulations to maintain order, but I’m sure you can all imagine the type of order that could be established and maintained in times like those and especially in circumstances like those, with such a vast and varied assembly, in which the unwilling were tossed in with the willing; the professional beggars with those for whom begging was a shameful, humiliating necessity; the many schooled in sloth, cheating, scorn, and violence in the squares, taverns, and palaces of tyrants with the many others raised to do the honest labor of the fields and the workshops. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14666" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14686">How the lot of them shared food and lodgings would be hard to imagine did we not have reliable information, but we do. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14687" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14740">They slept piled on top of one another, twenty or thirty to a cell, or lying beneath the porticos on smatterings of putrid, fetid straw or the bare ground; for although instructions had been given for a sufficient supply of fresh straw, to be frequently changed, the truth is that there was not enough, it was rotten, and it was never changed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14741" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14789">Instructions had also been given for the bread to be of good quality; now, what administrator would ever admit to the preparation and distribution of bad food? But how could something unavailable under normal circumstances, even for limited service, be obtained in this case, and for that multitude? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14790" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14823">At the time, it was said, as we see in the memoirs, that the bread in the lazaretto had been adulterated with heavy and non-nutritious ingredients. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14824" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14866">There was even a shortage of water, by which I mean fresh and healthy water. The community well must have been the ditch surrounding the walls, which was shallow, slow-moving, and sometimes muddy, made worse by the use and vicinity of such a large and varied multitude. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14867" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14905">In addition to these aggressive causes of mortality, which attacked bodies that were sick or feeling poorly, the season was extremely perverse: persistent rains, followed by an even more persistent drought, bringing with it an early and violent heat wave. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14906" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14973">In addition to sickness, there was the sickly feeling: the boredom and the mania of captivity, the memory of former habits, the grief over the dearly departed, the concern over the dearly absent, the torment and disgust toward one another, and so many other explosions of depression and rage, either brought in or born there; not to mention the fear and constant sight of death, which so many causes has made common, and which itself became a new and potent cause. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_14974" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15202">No one should be surprised by the spike and predominance of the death rate in that enclosure, which took on the appearance and, for many, the name of plague. Whether the combination and increase of all these causes served only to increase the activity of a simple influenza epidemic; whether (as seems to happen in even less severe and prolonged famines) it was a certain type of contagion that found fertile soil, so to speak, in bodies predisposed and prepared by hardship and malnutrition, bad weather, filth, exhaustion, and depression: that found, in short, the right season and the necessary conditions to be born, nourished, and multiply (if a layman may be allowed to use these words, based on the hypothesis proposed by several scientists and recently reproposed, with many arguments and much reserve, by a man as diligent as he was ingenious). Perhaps the contagion first broke out in the lazaretto, as the physicians of the Tribunal of Health seem to have believed, according to an obscure and inexact report; perhaps it had already been alive and festering before (the most likely possibility, considering how advanced and widespread the hardship was, and how high the death rate), and, once introduced into that throng of inmates, spread with a new and terrifying rapidity. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15203" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15222">Regardless of which hypothesis is true, the daily death toll in the lazaretto quickly surpassed one hundred. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15223" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15241">While in that place all was languor, anguish, fear, sorrow, and trembling, at the Tribunal of Provision all was shame, shock, and uncertainty. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15242" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15269">There were debates and consultations with the Tribunal of Health, but the only conclusion reached was to undo everything that had been done with so much fanfare, and at great expense and vexation. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15270" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15290">The lazaretto was opened; all the paupers with any strength left were released, and they fled with a furious joy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15291" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15323">Once again, the city echoed with its former laments, though now more feeble and wavering; again, it saw a smaller and more pitiable throng, writes Ripamonti, when he thought of how the crowd had thinned. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15324" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15340">The sick were transported to Santa Maria della Stella, which in those days was a shelter for the poor, where most of them died. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15341" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15348">In the meantime, however, the blessed fields started to turn golden. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15349" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15364">The vagrants who had arrived from the countryside left the city, each headed toward his or her hometown, to the long-awaited harvest. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15365" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15396">The good Federigo bade farewell with a final effort and a new example of charity: Each peasant who appeared at the Archbishop’s palace was given one giulio and a scythe for reaping the crops. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15397" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15425">With the harvest, the famine finally came to an end. The death rate, whether caused by an epidemic or a contagion, went down by the day, but still persisted until the fall, and was about to end when suddenly a new scourge broke out. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15426" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15444">Many important events—of the kind given the special title of history—had taken place in the meantime. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15445" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15499">Cardinal Richelieu—after taking La Rochelle and patching together an agreement with the King of England—had, through the power of his words, proposed to and persuaded the Royal Council of the need for prompt support for the Duke of Nevers. At the same time, he convinced the King to lead the expedition in person. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15500" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15531">While the preparations were being made, the Count of Nassau, Imperial Commissioner, ordered the new Duke in Mantua to hand over the states to Emperor Ferdinand; if not, the Emperor would send an occupying army. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15532" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15585">The Duke, who in more desperate circumstances had managed to hold off accepting such a harsh and suspect condition, was now encouraged by the approaching support of France. So he held off a little longer, couching his “No” in language as convoluted and verbose as possible, and proposing terms of surrender that were more ostentatious but less costly. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15586" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15596">The Commissioner left, declaring that they would settle the matter through force. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15597" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15670">In March, Cardinal Richelieu descended into Italy with the French King at the head of an army. He had requested passage from the Duke of Savoy. There were talks: inconclusive. After a skirmish, won by the French, talks were renewed. A settlement was reached whereby the Duke, among other things, agreed that Don Gonzalo would lift the siege of Casale; if he refused, the Duke of Savoy would join with the French in an invasion of the state of Milan. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15671" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15693">Don Gonzalo, thinking he had gotten off easy, lifted the siege of Casale, which a French battalion immediately entered to reinforce the garrison. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15694" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15728">It was on this occasion that Achillini addressed his famous sonnet to King Louis: “Sweat, oh ye Fires, in forging metal!” He wrote another poem urging the King to embark immediately on the liberation of the Holy Land. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15729" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15759">But destiny decrees that the opinions of poets shall not be heeded; and if you ever find historical events that suggest otherwise, be honest and admit that you had predetermined them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15760" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15779">Cardinal Richelieu had decided, instead, to return to France, where he believed more urgent business awaited him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15780" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15831">Girolamo Soranzo, the Venetian envoy, gave, in vain, a host of reasons why that was the wrong decision. But the King and the Cardinal paid as little heed to his prose as they had to Achillini’s poetry, and withdrew most of the army, leaving only six thousand men in Susa to keep the pass open and enforce the treaty. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15832" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15858">While that army was marching in one direction, the army of Ferdinand was marching from the other. It invaded the Grisons and the Valtellina and was preparing to descend into Milanese territory. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15859" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15910">Apart from all the damage to be feared from the army’s passage, dispatches had been sent to the Tribunal of Health, warning that the army harbored the plague, elements of which the German troops always carried in those days, as Benedetto Varchi mentions in describing the pestilence they had brought to Florence a century earlier. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15911" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15971">Alessandro Tadino, one of the commissioners on the Tribunal of Health (there were six, in addition to the president: four magistrates and two physicians), was—as he relates in the Raguaglio (p. 16) that I have already mentioned—assigned to represent to the Governor the terrible danger looming over the territory if that army were to pass through on its way to besiege Mantua, as was rumored. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_15972" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16027">From Don Gonzalo’s overall behavior, he seems to have been obsessed with gaining a place in history, which would not, in fact, ignore him. But (as often occurs), history either did not know or bother to record his most memorable contribution: his response to Tadino on that occasion. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16028" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16067">He replied that he didn’t know what should be done; that the army had been set into motion by questions of interests and glory which outweighed the danger that it posed; all things considered, they should take the best precautions they could, and place their trust in Providence. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16068" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16152">In order to take the best precautions possible, the two physicians on the tribunal (the aforementioned Tadino and Senatore Settala, son of the celebrated Lodovico) proposed a ban, with harsh penalties, on the purchase of items of any sort from the soldiers passing through. But it was impossible to make the president of the tribunal understand the need for such an order. “He was a good-hearted man,” wrote Tadino, “who could not believe that so many thousands of people would meet their deaths through commerce with these people and their goods.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16153" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16192">I cite this as one of the most remarkable passages of that time. As long as there have been commissions of health, there has never been a president who has made a similar argument, if indeed we can call it an argument. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16193" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16217">Shortly after uttering that reply, Don Gonzalo left Milan. His departure was as dismal as its cause. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16218" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16246">He was removed because of the failure of the war he had championed and led. The people blamed him for the famine they had suffered under his administration. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16247" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16276">(No one either knew or was bothered by his response to the plague—as we shall see—except the Tribunal of Health, especially the two physicians.) </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16277" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16328">As he left the governor’s palace in a traveling coach, guarded by halberdiers on either side, with two mounted trumpeters in front, and other coaches carrying nobles behind, he was greeted by the loud jeering of children who had gathered in Piazza del Duomo and chased after him pell-mell. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16329" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16380">The moment the procession entered the road leading to Porta Ticinese, by which they were supposed to leave, it was surrounded by a mob of people, some of whom had been waiting while others came running. Especially since the trumpeters, creatures of protocol, did not stop playing their horns all the way from the palace to the gates of the city. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16381" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16429">When an investigation into this riot was later held, one of the men, in response to criticism that his trumpeting had made the situation worse, said, “My dear sir, this is our profession. And if His Excellency had preferred that we not play, he should have given us orders to be silent.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16430" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16464">But Don Gonzalo, either from reluctance to do something that might show fear, or fear of doing something that might inflame the mob, or because he was simply stunned, gave no such order. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16465" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16494">While the guards struggled in vain to hold them back, the mob surrounded the carriage on all sides, shouting, “Down with the famine, down with bleeding the poor,” and worse. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16495" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16532">As the carriage approached the gate, they started to pelt it with rocks, bricks, and garbage of all kinds: the usual ammunition in such a skirmish. Some scrambled up the walls, from which they launched a final volley at the carriages as they left. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16533" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16536">And immediately after, they disbanded. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16537" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16564">The Marquis Ambrogio Spinola, a man whose name had already acquired, in the wars in Flanders, the military renown it still enjoys today, was sent to replace Don Gonzalo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16565" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16604">In the meantime, the German army, under the supreme command of Count Rambaldo di Collalto—another Italian condottiere of lesser but not insignificant fame—had received the final order to proceed with the siege of Mantua, and in the month of September, it entered the state of Milan. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16605" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16646">Armies, in those days, still consisted, for the most part, of soldiers of fortune enlisted by a professional condottiere, who had been commissioned by one prince or another, and sometimes on his own account, to sell the services of himself and his men. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16647" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16668">The men were attracted to that profession not so much by the pay as by the hope of looting and all the other enticements afforded by such license. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16669" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16689">Regular, overall discipline, there was none. Nor would it have concorded very well with the largely independent authority of the various condottieri. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16690" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16748">They were not particularly fussy about such matters. Even if they had wanted to, it is hard to see how they could have established and maintained discipline, since soldiers of that species would either mutiny against an innovative commander who got it into his head to abolish looting, or at least desert him, leaving him to guard his standard by himself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16749" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16816">Moreover, since the princes who hired these so-called bands were more concerned with mustering large numbers, to ensure military success, than in having a militia proportionate to their usually very limited ability to pay, the soldiers were generally paid late, on credit, and piecemeal. So the spoils of the places that had fallen became a kind of tacitly accepted supplement. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16817" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16842">Almost as famous as Wallenstein himself is his dictum: It is easier to maintain an army of one hundred thousand men than one of twelve thousand. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16843" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16893">And the army of which we are speaking consisted largely of men under his command who had laid waste to Germany in the course of the war so celebrated for itself and for its effects, later known, for its duration, as the Thirty Years’ War, which was then in its eleventh year. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16894" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16937">There was also Wallenstein’s own regiment, led by one of his lieutenants. Most of the other condottieri had served under his command, including more than one who, four years later, would contribute to his meeting the sorry end that everyone knows. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16938" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16996">The infantry numbered twenty-eight thousand, and the cavalry seven thousand. Descending from the Valtellina to reach the area of Mantua, they had to follow the full length of the Adda, past two branches of the lake, and then when it became a river again, until it emptied into the Po, which still left them with a good stretch to cover. In all, they spent eight days in the Duchy of Milan. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_16997" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_17052">Most of the residents had taken refuge in the mountains, carrying their most valuable possessions, and driving their livestock before them. Others stayed behind, so as not to abandon someone sick, or to save the house from fire, or to keep an eye on their valuables, hidden or buried. Others because they had nothing to lose or were counting on gaining something. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_17053" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_17108">When the first contingent reached the village selected as a stopping place, it immediately spread out into the village and the surrounding areas and proceeded to sack them. Anything that could be used or taken disappeared. All the rest was destroyed or ruined: Furniture was turned into firewood, houses into stables. Not to mention the beatings, injuries, and rapes. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_17109" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_17127">Every ruse, every trick to save things proved useless, for the most part, and sometimes led to greater damage. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_17128" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_17206">The soldiers were much more experienced in the stratagems of this aspect of the campaign, and they dug through every nook and cranny, tore down and demolished walls. They easily recognized the loose soil in the garden and went up into the mountains to steal the livestock. They entered the caves, guided by some local scoundrel, in search of any rich man who might be hiding, dragged him to his house and, by torturing him with threats and beatings, forced him to tell them where his treasure was hidden. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_17207" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_17246">Finally, they would start to leave, and be gone. In the distance, you could hear the sound of the trumpet and drums dying down, followed by hours of terrified silence. And then, an accursed new beating of drums, a new blaring of trumpets, would announce the arrival of another contingent. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_17247" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_17306">Finding nothing more to plunder, the newcomers laid waste to whatever remained with even greater fury, burning the empty casks and doorways to rooms where nothing was left, then setting fire to houses themselves. And with even greater rage, of course, they mistreated the people, and so from bad to worse, for twenty days, as many days as there were contingents in the army. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap28-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_17307" targetEnd="quarantana/cap28.xml#c28_17337">Colico was the first town in the Duchy invaded by those demons. Then they raided Bellano. From there they entered and spread out into the Valsassina, which poured them into the territory of Lecco. </note>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>