<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>2022</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed: a novel</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
          <date>2022</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Michael Moore</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="english_2022_cap20">
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10093">The castle of the Nameless One loomed over a narrow, damp valley, atop a bluff that jutted out from the rugged mountain chain to which it was either connected or separated—it was hard to tell—by a massif of crags and boulders, and a maze of caves and cliffs that extended in both directions. The side facing the valley was the only accessible one; although it was at a steep incline, it was smooth and unbroken, with meadows at the summit, cultivated plots on the slopes, and cottages scattered here and there. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10094" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10116">At the base was a bed of pebbles over which, depending on the season, ran a rivulet or a mighty stream, which in those days served as a border between the two states, the Duchy of Milan and the Republic of Venice. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10117" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10155">The opposite end of the valley was demarcated by another wall of mountains, which also had some farmland on the slopes, though most of it was shattered rock and boulder, and sheer rock faces, pathless and barren, except for an occasional shrub poking out of a crevice or along a ledge. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10156" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10191">From the heights of his horrid castle, like the eagle in its gory nest, the savage lord dominated every inch of the area where a man might set foot. He never saw anyone above him, or even higher up. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10192" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10208">Looking around, he could survey his enclave: the hills, the floor of the valley, and the roads traveled within it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10209" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10253">There was one path that twisted and turned its way up to his ghastly domicile, unfurling like a ribbon before the man who was gazing down on it. Through the castle windows and embrasures, the lord could easily count the footsteps of anyone who approached, and aim his weapons a hundred times over. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10254" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10285">With the garrison of bravi he kept up there, he could flatten or send tumbling down the hill many members of even a large company before a single one managed to reach the top. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10286" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10312">All of which is to say that no one would dare set foot up there or in the valley, or even just pass through, who wasn’t in the good graces of the lord of the castle. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10313" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10334">If a law officer were detected, he would be treated like a captured enemy spy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10335" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10369">Tragic stories were told of those who had attempted such an enterprise, but the stories were already old, and none of the younger generation remembered ever having seen a man of that type in the valley, dead or alive. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10370" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10413">This is how the anonymous author describes the place, but he never mentions its name. Indeed, to keep us from finding out its specific whereabouts, he says nothing about Don Rodrigo’s trip, and sets him immediately in the valley, at the foot of the bluff, and the start of that steep and winding path. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10414" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10427">Here there was a tavern that might as well have been called a guardhouse. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10428" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10473">Over the door hung an old sign with a radiant sun painted on both sides. For the common people, who sometimes repeat names handed down to them, and sometimes invent their own, it was simply the “Malanotte,” the “evil night.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10474" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10509">At the sound of a horse approaching, a tough-looking youth appeared at the door, armed like a Saracen. After a quick look around, he went back inside to inform three thugs who were playing a game with greasy old cards bent like roof tiles. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10510" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10527">The one who seemed to be in charge stood up, went to the door, and, recognizing one of his master’s friends, greeted him with respect. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10528" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10565">Don Rodrigo returned the greeting politely, and asked if the lord was up at the castle. When the man replied that he thought so, Don Rodrigo dismounted and tossed the horse’s reins to Tiradritto, one of his own bodyguards. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10566" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10600">He removed his musket and handed it to Montanarolo, as if to relieve himself of a useless burden so he could climb the hill more easily. In reality, he was well aware that he wouldn’t be allowed up with a weapon. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10601" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10628">He dug a few berlingas out of his pocket and handed them to Tanabuso, saying, “You can all wait here, and have some fun with these good people.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10629" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10652">Then he took out a few gold scudi and placed them in the leader’s hand, half for him, the other half to be divided up among his men. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10653" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10667">Finally, together with Griso, who had also set his musket aside, he began the ascent on foot. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10668" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10711">The three bravi, plus Squinternotto, making it four (do you notice these names? Remember them with care), stayed behind with the Nameless One’s own three bravi, and the lookout boy, to play cards, imbibe, and boast of their exploits. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10712" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10756">Another of the Nameless One’s foul bravi, also on his way to the castle, caught up with Don Rodrigo a few minutes later. He recognized him at a glance, and accompanied him the rest of the way. This spared Don Rodrigo the annoyance of having to say his name and explain who he was to anyone he might run into who didn’t know him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10757" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10811">Once he’d reached the castle and gone in (leaving Griso at the door), he had to pass through a maze of dark corridors and across a series of rooms whose walls were hung with muskets, sabers, and polearms, in each of which a bravo or two stood guard. After waiting for quite a while, he was admitted into the presence of the Nameless One. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10812" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10848">The latter came up to him, returned his greeting, and at the same time inspected his face and hands, an old habit that he had come to apply almost unconsciously to anyone who approached him, even his most trusted friends. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10849" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10905">He was tall, swarthy, and almost completely bald. The few remaining hairs on his head were white. His face was lined. At first sight, he looked older than his sixty years, although his demeanor and movements, his harsh features, and the sinister but lively gleam in his eyes indicated a strength of body and mind that would have been extraordinary in a much younger man. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10906" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10953">Don Rodrigo said that he had come for advice and for help; that finding himself engaged in a difficult enterprise, which he could not renounce, for the sake of his honor, he remembered the promises of a man whose promises were never exaggerated or empty. He started to describe his wicked imbroglio. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_10954" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11002">The Nameless One, who had already heard vague reports of Don Rodrigo’s troubles, listened carefully, out of a curiosity for such stories, and since this one involved a name he knew and detested: Fra Cristoforo, a sworn enemy of tyrants, in word and, where possible, in deeds. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11003" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11047">Don Rodrigo, knowing with whom he spoke, started to dramatize the difficulties of his enterprise, the distance of the place, a convent, the Signora!…At this, the Nameless One suddenly interrupted him, as if commanded by a demon lurking in his heart, to say that he would take the matter in hand. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11048" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11071">As he made a note of our poor Lucia’s name, he dismissed Don Rodrigo, adding, “You will receive instructions from me shortly on what you have to do.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11072" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11120">The reader may remember that reprobate Egidio, who lived next to the convent where poor Lucia had taken refuge. You should know that he was one of the closest and most intimate partners in crime of the Nameless One, which is why the latter had given Don Rodrigo his word so quickly and readily. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11121" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11133">As soon as he was alone, however, he did not so much regret, I would say, as resent that he had given it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11134" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11149">For some time now, he had been feeling, if not remorse, then a certain disquiet over his evil ways. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11150" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11189">A lifetime of crime had amassed in his memory, if not in his conscience, which was reawakened with each new act, pressing down on him in all its ugliness and multitude, an already uncomfortable burden growing heavier and heavier. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11190" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11208">The revulsion he had experienced at his first crimes, which he had later overcome and almost completely repressed, had now returned to make itself felt. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11209" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11247">In his early years, the prospect of a long, indefinite future and the sense of a vigorous vitality had filled him with an easy confidence. Nowadays, though, his thoughts of the future made the past even more unbearable. “To grow old—to die. And then?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11248" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11293">Remarkably, the image of death that, when danger was near, or he found himself face-to-face with an enemy, used to fire his spirits and instill in him a courageous rage, now gripped him with panic when it appeared to him in the still of night, in the safety of his castle. It was not the threat of death at the hands of a mortal enemy like himself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11294" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11345">Nor could it be repelled by superior weapons or a quicker hand. This death came alone, and from deep within. It might still have been distant, but it was creeping up on him steadily. And even as his mind painfully struggled to banish the thought, it came closer and closer. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11346" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11414">In the early days, the almost constant spectacle of violence, revenge, and murder had instilled in him a ferocious desire for more, and given him an authority that overruled his conscience. Now, his mind was revisited every now and then by the vague but terrifying idea of being judged before God, of an accounting that would not ignore his crimes. Now, having outmatched the vulgar ranks of the wicked to stand above them, he was sometimes filled with an overwhelming sense of loneliness. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11415" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11464">He had heard God mentioned, but long refused to acknowledge or deny Him, since his only concern had been to live as if there were no God. Now, in moments of inexplicable despondency and unfounded terror, he imagined hearing His voice crying out from within: “YET I AM!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11465" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11509">In the heat of youthful passion, the law he had heard proclaimed in God’s name (but not heeded) had seemed hateful, nothing more. Now, when that same law suddenly sprang to mind, despite his best efforts, he saw it as inescapable. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11510" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11547">Rather than admit his new anxieties to another person, however, he buried them deep inside, and concealed them beneath a mask of even greater brutality. He also tried to hide them from himself and stifle them, in the same way. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11548" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11592">Ruing the days (since he could neither erase nor forget them) when he used to commit outrage without remorse, with no other thought than to succeed, he made every effort to bring that time back, and hold on to or regain his former willpower—ready, proud, unperturbed—in order to convince himself that he was still that same man. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11593" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11610">So on this occasion, he had immediately given his word to Don Rodrigo in order to stave off any hesitation. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11611" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11688">As soon as the latter had left, however, he started to feel a wavering in the resolve he had just mustered. He started to feel the slow encroachment of temptations to go back on his promise, which would have made him lose face with a friend, a minor accomplice. To put an immediate end to that agonizing conflict, he summoned Nibbio, one of the most skillful and daring ministers of his iniquity, to whom he usually assigned all correspondence with Egidio. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11689" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11714">With a resolute air, he ordered him to mount a horse at once and go straight to Monza, inform Egidio of the commitment he had made, and request his assistance in fulfilling it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11715" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11763">The fiendish messenger came back with Egidio’s reply sooner than his master had expected: The deed would be easily done. A coach should be provided, along with two or three well-disguised bravi; he would handle everything else, and take charge of the matter. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11764" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11794">At this news, the Nameless One, despite his misgivings, quickly ordered Nibbio to provide for everything Egidio had requested, and to set out on the expedition with two others that he named. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11795" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11824">If Egidio had been forced to rely only on his usual resources to perform the dreadful task requested of him, he would never have agreed so quickly and decisively. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11825" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11859">But inside that sanctuary, where everything seemed to be an obstacle, the heinous youth had a secret weapon; the very thing that would have posed the greatest difficulty for others was an advantage for him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11860" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11898">We have already described how the wretched Signora had succumbed to his words. The reader might have realized that this would be her first step—but not her last—down the road to abomination and bloodshed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11899" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11921">The same voice that had become stronger and, I would almost say, more authoritative because of her crime, now demanded that she sacrifice the innocent girl she was supposed to protect. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11922" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11927">The proposal left Gertrude in shock. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11928" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11962">To lose Lucia through no fault of her own, through an unforeseen accident, would have already felt like a misfortune, a bitter punishment. But now she was being ordered to deprive herself of the girl through treachery, to convert a means of atonement into a source of remorse. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11963" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11986">The hapless woman tried every possible way to avoid carrying out the abominable order; everything, that is, except the way of righteousness, which had always been open to her. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_11987" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12014">Crime is a rigid and unyielding taskmaster that can only be overcome through total rebellion, which Gertrude could not bring herself to do, so she obeyed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12015" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12087">The day had come and the appointed hour was near. Gertrude, alone with Lucia in her private parlor, showed more tenderness than usual, and Lucia accepted and returned her affection with growing fondness. Like the lamb that trembles fearlessly under the shepherd’s hand as he softly pets her and pulls her along, she turns to lick his hand, not realizing that waiting outside the pen is the butcher to whom she has just been sold. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12088" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12097">“I have an important errand, and only you can do it for me. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12098" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12109">There are many people in my service, but not a single one I can trust. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12110" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12153">It’s a sensitive matter that I will explain to you later. I need to speak right away with the Father Guardian of the Capuchins who brought you to me, my poor Lucia. But no one can know that I sent for him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12154" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12161">You are the only person who can deliver this secret message for me.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12162" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12269">Lucia was terrified by this request. Submissively, but without hiding her dismay, she tried to excuse herself for reasons that the Signora surely understood and should have foreseen. She shouldn’t be going alone, without her mother, without anyone, down an isolated road, in a strange town…But Gertrude, educated in the ways of evil, made a show of dismissing her excuses, acting so surprised and so displeased to encounter such reluctance in the one person whom she thought she could trust. But it would be in broad daylight! Just a short walk! On a road that Lucia had traveled a few days before! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12270" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12290">And, even if she had never seen the monastery, it was impossible to miss if she followed directions!…She made such a fuss that the poor girl, her gratitude evoked and her feelings hurt, relented and said, “All right, then. What exactly do I have to do?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12291" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12332">“Go to the Capuchin monastery,” and the Signora described the road again, “ask for the Father Guardian. Tell him, in private, to come to me right away, but not to tell a soul that I am the one who sent for him.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12333" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12348">“But what should I tell the stewardess, who has never seen me leave and is sure to ask where I’m going?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12349" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12370">“Try to slip past her without being seen. And if you can’t, tell her that you’re going to a church, where you’d promised to say a prayer.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12371" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12418">Here was a new difficulty for the poor girl: to tell a lie. But once again the Signora acted so offended by her reluctance and made her feel so wrong to place vain scruples before gratitude, that Lucia, bewildered rather than convinced, and more emotional than ever, replied, “All right, I’ll go. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12419" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12420">May God help me!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12421" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12423">And she started to leave. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12424" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12454">When Gertrude, who from behind the grating was following her with a steady but tortured gaze, saw Lucia set foot on the threshold, she opened her mouth, overcome by an irresistible impulse, and said, “Wait, Lucia!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12455" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12462">The girl stopped and turned toward the grating. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12463" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12481">By then, however, another thought, which was accustomed to prevailing, had already taken hold of Gertrude’s twisted mind. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12482" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12514">Pretending to be dissatisfied with her earlier instructions, she explained to Lucia once more the road she had to take, and dismissed her, saying, “Do everything exactly as I said, and come back quickly.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12515" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12516">Lucia left. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12517" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12570">She passed the cloister doors unnoticed and entered the street, her eyes lowered, keeping close to the wall. The Signora’s directions and her own recollections helped her find the town gate. She passed through and continued down the main road, focused but trembling slightly, until a few minutes later she recognized the path leading to the monastery. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12571" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12598">That road used to be, and still is, sunken like a riverbed between two high banks with hedges on either side forming a sort of canopy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12599" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12646">As she turned onto it, Lucia saw how isolated it was and felt a growing sense of fear. She started to walk more quickly and was relieved a moment later to see a coach stopped, and next to it, by an open door, two travelers looking around, as if uncertain of the road. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12647" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12663">When she drew near, she overheard one of them say, “Here is a nice young lady who’ll give us directions.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12664" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12693">In fact, when she reached the carriage, the same man, with a manner more noble than his appearance, turned and asked, “Could the young lady tell us the way to Monza?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12694" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12727">“That way, you’d be going in the wrong direction,” replied the poor girl. “Monza is this way…” and as she turned to point with her finger, the other man (Nibbio) suddenly grabbed her around the waist and lifted her off the ground. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12728" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12781">Lucia twisted her head back, terrified, and let out a scream. The scoundrel forced her into the coach. A third man, sitting in the front, took her and, no matter how much she struggled and screamed, forced her into the seat facing him. Another trapped her cries in her throat by placing a handkerchief over her mouth. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12782" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12802">Meanwhile, Nibbio jumped into the coach, too: The door slammed shut and they were off at a gallop. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12803" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12845">The man who had asked the perfidious question remained behind. He looked up and down the road, to see if anyone had noticed Lucia’s shouts: There was no one. He jumped off to the side, grabbed hold of a tree in the underbrush, and disappeared. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12846" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12883">He was one of Egidio’s henchmen. Feigning disinterest, he had stood at his master’s door to see when Lucia left the convent. He had observed her carefully, so he would recognize her, then took a shortcut to wait for her at the appointed spot. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12884" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12899">Who could describe her terror, her distress? Who could express what was going through her mind? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12900" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12965">She opened her frightened eyes wide, anxious to see her awful plight, then closed them immediately, disgusted and terrified by those ghastly faces. She twisted and turned, but was held tight on every side. She gathered all her forces and lunged toward the door repeatedly, but two muscular arms kept her trapped in the back of the carriage, while four other gnarled hands held her in place. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12966" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12982">Every time she opened her mouth to let loose a scream, it was stifled in her throat by the handkerchief. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_12983" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13005">In the meantime, the three foulmouthed heathens kept repeating, in the most humane voices they could muster, “Quiet, quiet. Don’t be afraid, we don’t want to hurt you.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13006" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13063">After a few minutes of anguished struggle, she seemed to calm down. Her arms went slack, her head fell back, and her gaze remained frozen through her barely opened eyes. The horrid faces staring back at her seemed to blur and waver in a horrible mix. The color drained from her cheeks. She broke out in a cold sweat, collapsed, and fainted. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13064" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13069">“Come now, be brave,” said Nibbio. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13070" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13094">“Be brave, be brave,” repeated the other two rogues, but senselessness had spared Lucia the comfort of hearing those horrid voices. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13095" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13105">“What the devil? She looks dead,” said one of them. “What if she really is?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13106" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13118">“She’s not dead!” said the other. “It’s one of those fainting spells that women get. Believe me. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13119" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13136">Every time I’ve had to send someone, man or woman, to meet their maker, it took a hell of a lot more than that.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13137" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13150">“Enough!” said Nibbio. “Stick to your job and don’t go looking for trouble. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13151" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13171">Get your guns out from under the seat and have them ready. The forest we’re going through is always crawling with outlaws…Not like that, damn it! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13172" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13194">Hide them behind your backs, pointing up. Can’t you see that she’s a scared mouse, one of those that faints over nothing? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13195" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13202">If she sees guns, she really could die on us. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13203" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13224">And when she comes to, make sure not to scare her! Don’t touch her unless I tell you to. In fact, I can handle her by myself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13225" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13230">Keep your traps shut: Let me do the talking.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13231" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13241">Meanwhile the carriage, still racing ahead, had entered the forest. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13242" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13261">After a while, poor Lucia started to regain consciousness, as if waking up from a deep, troubled sleep, and she opened her eyes. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13262" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13284">She struggled to make out the terrifying figures that surrounded her, and to gather her thoughts. Finally she remembered her awful plight. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13285" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13321">With the little strength she had left, she immediately threw herself at the door again, hoping to jump out. But she was held back, and was only able to glimpse the wild solitude of the place they were passing through. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13322" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13361">She let loose another cry, but Nibbio, raising the cruel hand that held the handkerchief, said, “Come now,” as gently as he could, “keep quiet, now, and it’ll go better for you. We don’t want to hurt you. But if you won’t shut up, we’ll have to make you shut up.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13362" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13363">“Let me go! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13364" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13366">Who are you? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13367" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13369">Where are you taking me? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13370" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13372">Why have you kidnapped me? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13373" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13376">Let me go, let me go!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13377" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13395">“I’m telling you there’s nothing to be afraid of. You’re not a child. You should know that we don’t want to hurt you. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13396" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13407">Can’t you see that we could have killed you a hundred times over if we had wanted to? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13408" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13410">So be quiet.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13411" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13422">“No, no, let me go on my way. I don’t know you.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13423" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13425">“But we know you.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13426" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13431">“Blessed Virgin Mary! What do you mean you know me? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13432" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13435">Let me go, for heaven’s sake. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13436" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13438">Who are you? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13439" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13441">Why have you kidnapped me?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13442" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13445">“Because we were ordered to.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13446" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13453">“Who. Who ordered you to?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13454" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13469">“Shut up!” said Nibbio with a scowl. “Enough of your questions!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13470" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13522">Lucia made another sudden lunge for the door. Failing again, she resorted to imploring them, with her head lowered, her voice choking on her tears, and her hands clasped before her lips: “For the love of God, of the Holy Virgin, let me go. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13523" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13528">What did I ever do to you? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13529" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13537">I’m a poor creature who’s never hurt you. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13538" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13552">What you’ve done to me I will forgive from my heart, and I will pray to God for you. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13553" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13571">But if you have a daughter, a wife, a mother, think of what they would suffer if they were in my situation. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13572" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13586">Remember that we all have to die, and that one day you will want God to be merciful to you. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13587" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13598">Let me go. Let me get out of here: The Good Lord will help me to find my way.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13599" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13600">“We can’t.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13601" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13602">“You can’t? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13603" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13607">Oh Lord, what do you mean you can’t? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13608" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13610">Where are you taking me? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13611" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13611">Why?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13612" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13629">“We can’t, don’t waste your breath. Don’t be afraid, we don’t want to hurt you. Stay calm and no one will touch you.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13630" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13665">Becoming more distressed, more devastated, and more terrified by the minute, Lucia turned to He who holds the hearts of men in His hand, and, if He so desires, can soften even the hardest of them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13666" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13714">She huddled in the corner of the carriage, crossed her arms over her breast, and prayed to herself. Then, taking out her rosary beads, she began to say the rosary more fervently and emotionally than ever before. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13715" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13731">Every so often, hoping to be granted the mercy she had implored, she would turn to them to beg again, but always in vain. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13732" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13746">Then she would faint once more and come to once more, only to relive new torments. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13747" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13784">My heart cannot bear to describe her ordeal any longer: An overwhelming sorrow makes me skip to the end of that journey, which lasted for more than four hours, after which we will still have some more agonizing hours to endure. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13785" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13791">Let us go now to the castle where the unhappy girl was being taken. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13792" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13801">The Nameless One waited with an unusual agitation and ambivalence. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13802" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13862">How strange! The same man who had disposed of so many lives in cold blood, who in the midst of so many vile deeds had never stopped to consider the suffering he caused, thinking only of his own savage desire for revenge. Now, in having successfully laid claim to this stranger, this poor peasant girl, he felt a kind of revulsion, almost a terror, I would say. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13863" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13902">He had been staring for some time at the road that led into the valley from a window high up in his castle. Suddenly, he saw the coach appear, advancing slowly, since its earlier speed had exhausted the horses’ energy and depleted their strength. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13903" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13937">Although from his vantage point it looked like little more than a toy buggy one gives to a child, he recognized it immediately and felt his heart beat faster. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13938" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13953">“Will she be in it?” was his first thought. And then, “She’s such a nuisance! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13954" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13955">Let’s get rid of her.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13956" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13982">He was tempted to summon one of his henchmen to intercept the coach, with orders for Nibbio to turn around and take the girl to the palace of Don Rodrigo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13983" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13995">But an imperious “No” that echoed in his mind put an end to that thought. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_13996" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14031">Still tormented by the need to boss someone around, and finding it intolerable to wait idly for the coach that was making its way to him too slowly, treacherously, almost punitively, he sent for an old servant woman. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14032" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14052">She had been born in that same castle, the child of a former guard, and had spent her whole life there. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14053" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14104">Everything she had seen and heard from the time she was in swaddling clothes had impressed on her mind a grand and terrifying idea of the power wielded by her masters. The main lesson she had learned from her instructions and her experience was to obey them in all things, since they were capable of doing both great harm and great good. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14105" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14136">The idea of duty, which is deposited like a seed in the hearts of all men, had in her become associated with feelings of deference, terror, and an overweening desire to serve. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14137" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14164">When the Nameless One became master, and started to make such horrifying use of his power, she had initially felt a certain revulsion as well as an even deeper sense of submission. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14165" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14199">As time went by, however, she grew accustomed to the constant evidence of her eyes and her ears, and came to see in the strong, unbridled will of such a great lord a kind of fatal justice. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14200" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14228">At an early age, she married one of his men who, soon after, during a risky expedition, left his life by the side of the road and left her a widow in the castle. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14229" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14251">The immediate revenge that the master took gave her a fierce consolation, and increased her pride at being under such protection. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14252" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14286">Since then, she only rarely set foot outside the castle, and gradually, the only notion of human life that remained in her was the little she had received within its precincts. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14287" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14313">She was not assigned any particular duties in that den of thieves, merely given the occasional odd job, which gnawed away at her. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14314" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14335">One time it would be rags to patch, another time a meal to prepare quickly for a man returning from an expedition, and yet another some wounds to dress. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14336" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14371">The men’s orders, reproaches, and even their thanks were peppered with ridicule and obscenities: the usual epithet was “old lady,” to which someone always added other adjectives that varied according to status and mood. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14372" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14407">Prodded from her laziness and provoked into anger—her two dueling passions—she would sometimes return the compliment with words that Satan himself would have liked. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14408" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14416">“You see that coach down there,” the master said to her. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14417" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14440">“Yes, I see it,” the old woman responded, jutting out her pointed chin and squinting with her sunken eyes as if she were trying to force them from their sockets. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14441" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14451">“Have a sedan chair prepared at once, get in, and have them carry you down to the Malanotte. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14452" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14469">Quick, quick, so you get there before the coach. It is moving at a funereal pace. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14470" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14477">In that coach there is…there’s supposed to be…a girl. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14478" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14497">If there is, give Nibbio my orders for her to be put in the sedan chair and for him to come up here at once. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14498" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14513">You stay in the sedan chair with that…girl. And when you get back to the castle, take her to your room. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14514" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14527">If she asks where you’re taking her, and whose castle it is, be careful not to…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14528" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14531">“I see,” said the old woman. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14532" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14536">“But,” the Nameless One continued, “try to cheer her up.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14537" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14540">“What am I supposed to say?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14541" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14544">“What are you supposed to say? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14545" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14548">Cheer her up, I said. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14549" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14566">Do you mean to tell me you’ve reached this ripe old age without knowing how to cheer up a child when needed? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14567" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14573">Haven’t you ever heard of heartache? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14574" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14578">Haven’t you ever been afraid? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14579" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14588">Don’t you know the words that are soothing at times like that? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14589" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14595">Say those kinds of words to her, figure something out, damn it! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14596" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14596">Go!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14597" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14652">Once she had left, he stood at the window for a while, staring down at the coach, which was already looking much bigger. Then he looked up at the sun, which, at that moment, was sinking behind the mountain. Then he gazed at the clouds scattered above, which in an instant had turned from brown to the color of fire. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap20-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14653" targetEnd="quarantana/cap20.xml#c20_14674">He stepped back from the window, closed it, and started pacing up and down the room, as hastily as an impatient traveler. </note>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>