<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>2022</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed: a novel</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
          <date>2022</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Michael Moore</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="english_2022_cap25">
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10051">The next day, in Lucia’s little village and throughout the Lecco territory, all the talk was of her, of the Nameless One, of the Archbishop, and of another fellow who, as much as he enjoyed having his name on everyone’s lips, would, under the circumstances, have gladly dispensed with it: by which I mean his Lordship, Don Rodrigo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10052" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10083">Not that there hadn’t been talk of his deeds before—but only secretly, in bits and pieces. Two people had to know each other quite well before they would broach the subject. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10084" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10128">Even then, they didn’t fully express what they felt. Because, generally speaking, when people cannot give vent to indignation without grave danger, they not only express it less (if at all), they actually feel it less. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10129" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10200">But who could resist asking and conversing about such a sensational event, in which the hand of God had been witnessed, and two such remarkable characters had made such a remarkable impression? One man who combined a zeal for justice with great authority, the other, in whom violence personified seemed to have been brought to its knees, as criminality laid down its weapons, so to speak, and sued for peace. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10201" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10211">Don Rodrigo, by comparison, was insignificant. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10212" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10236">Now everyone could see clearly how he had harassed innocence in order to dishonor and persecute it with such brazen insistence, such atrocious violence, and such abominable treachery. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10237" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10263">Now his many other feats were criticized, and in their regard, encouraged by the general consensus, people said what they felt. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10264" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10282">But in a whisper, with a shudder, and from a distance, since he was still surrounded by bravi. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10283" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10295">Much of the public censure also fell on his friends and toadies. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10296" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10326">The Mayor—who had always been deaf, dumb, and blind to the tyrant’s deeds—was derided, but out of earshot, for while he had no bravi, he did have the police. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10327" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10371">Similar regard was not accorded to Professor Argle-Bargle—whose only armor was empty talk and deception—and other lackeys of his ilk; they were subjected to finger-pointing and accusing stares, till they concluded that it would be best not to show their faces in public for a while. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10372" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10411">Don Rodrigo, stunned by this unthinkable development, so different from the news he had been expecting just one day ago, just one moment ago, remained holed up in his palace, seething for two days, alone but for his bravi. On the third day, he left for Milan. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10412" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10465">Matters had gotten too out of hand. He wanted to confront the local gossip, and even find an opportunity to make an example of someone, especially the most brazen offenders. But when he learned that the Cardinal was also paying a visit to his territory, he was forced to leave. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10466" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10515">The Count Uncle, who knew only as much about the affair as Attilio had told him, would certainly expect Don Rodrigo to cut a prominent figure at such an occasion and be accorded the most distinguished public reception from the Cardinal. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10516" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10543">That’s what his uncle would expect, together with a full report, since this was an important opportunity to show the esteem in which a leading authority held the family. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10544" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10625">But now everyone could see the direction things had taken. To escape such a thorny predicament, Don Rodrigo got up one morning before dawn and climbed into a carriage, which was guarded on every side by Griso and other bravi. He left orders for the rest of his household to follow, and departed like a fugitive, like Catiline from Rome (if I may be permitted to elevate our characters through an illustrious comparison), fuming and swearing that he would soon be back, in a different guise, to take revenge. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10626" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10640">As this unfolded, the Cardinal was visiting a different parish every day in the Lecco territory. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10641" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10662">On the date he was due to arrive in Lucia’s village, most of the townsfolk gathered in the street to meet him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10663" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10749">At the entrance to the village, right next to the cottage of Agnese and Lucia, a triumphal arch was built of upright stakes, with poles laid across the top, covered with straw and moss, and festooned with green boughs of butcher’s broom and holly speckled with scarlet berries. The church façade was adorned with tapestries. Blankets and bed linens were hung from every window, while babies’ swaddling clothes were arranged like banners: For better or worse, this is all that they had available to create a sense of abundance, and the little needed to create, for better or for worse, the impression of excess. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10750" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10836">At around three in the afternoon, the hour at which the Cardinal was expected, those who had stayed at home—primarily the elderly, women, and children—also set out to meet him, some in an orderly procession, others in little clusters. At the head of the assembly was Don Abbondio, grumpy in the midst of so much festivity because of the confounding racket, the masses of people whose teeming, as he kept repeating, made his head spin, and the inner dread that Agnese and Lucia had spilled the beans, and he would have to account for the unperformed marriage. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10837" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10892">All of a sudden, the Cardinal, or rather, the crowd surrounding his sedan chair as well as his entourage, appeared. The only visible indication of his presence was in the air above everyone’s heads: the tip of the cross borne by the chaplain who was astride a mule. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10893" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10943">The people walking alongside Don Abbondio raced ahead to reach the larger crowd. After repeating three or four times, “Slowly now. Single file. What are you doing?” he turned around irritably, continuing to grumble, “What a ruckus. What a ruckus,” and entered the still-empty church to wait there. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10944" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10972">The Cardinal came forward, blessing the people with his hand, while the people blessed him with their words. It was all his entourage could do to hold back the crowd. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_10973" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11005">Since this was Lucia’s village, the people wanted to do something extraordinary for the Archbishop—no easy task, since everywhere he went, the people strove to outdo themselves. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11006" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11054">From the very start of his appointment, upon his first solemn entrance into the Duomo, the crowd had rushed toward him so forcefully as to raise fears for his life. The gentlemen closest to him had to unsheathe their swords to frighten and drive back the swarm of people. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11055" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11084">This was an era of so much unruliness and violence that even a demonstration of goodwill to a bishop in a church—and the attempts to control it—could come close to killing him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11085" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11127">And even that defense would not have sufficed if two young priests robust in body and spirit—Clerici and Picozzi, the Master and Deputy Master of Ceremonies—had not lifted him up on their arms and carried him bodily from the door of the cathedral to the high altar. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11128" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11161">Ever since then, during his many episcopal visits, his first entry into any church was likely to be—and I’m not exaggerating—one of his most fatiguing, and sometimes most dangerous pastoral duties. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11162" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11206">He entered the church as best he could. He went up to the altar, and after standing in prayer for a few minutes, he made his customary remarks to the people about his love for them, his desire for their salvation, and his instructions on the services for the next day. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11207" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11221">Then he retired to the pastor’s house, where he inquired, among other things, about Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11222" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11236">Don Abbondio replied that the youth was a little rambunctious, a little headstrong, a little quick-tempered. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11237" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11267">But in response to more detailed and precise questions, he had to admit that Renzo was an honest lad, and that he, too, could not understand how he could have gotten into all the mischief he was accused of in Milan. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11268" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11288">“And the girl,” the Cardinal continued, “do you think it would be safe for her to come and stay in her house again?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11289" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11318">“For the moment, she can come and stay, if she prefers,” replied Don Abbondio. “For the moment,” he repeated with a sigh. “But Your Grace would always need to be here, or at least nearby.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11319" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11334">“The Lord is always near,” said the Cardinal. “Nevertheless, I’ll arrange for her to stay someplace safe.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11335" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11356">And he immediately gave instructions for a sedan chair with an escort to be sent early the next day to fetch Agnese and Lucia from the tailor’s house. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11357" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11395">Don Abbondio left the room feeling pleased that the Cardinal had spoken to him about the two young people without demanding an account of his own refusal to marry them. “So he knows nothing,” he said to himself. “Agnese must have kept her mouth shut. What a miracle! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11396" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11449">They are supposed to be seeing each other again, it’s true, but I’ll remind her of what I said, I will.” What he didn’t know, poor man, is that Federigo had not brought up the subject precisely because he intended to speak with him at greater length when he had a moment. The Cardinal wanted to hear the priest’s explanations before coming to any conclusion. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11450" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11474">But the good prelate’s plans of getting Lucia to safety were to become superfluous. After he left her, certain developments arose that I should relate. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11475" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11502">During the few days the two women had spent at the tailor’s hospitable cottage, they had each resumed their former lifestyle as best they could. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11503" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11525">Lucia had immediately asked for some work to do, and, as in the convent, she sewed and sewed, secluded in a little room far from the eyes of others. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11526" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11537">Sometimes Agnese would go out, sometimes she would join in her daughter’s work. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11538" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11577">Their conversations were becoming more somber but also more affectionate. They were each preparing for their separation, since the lamb could not return to living so close to the den of the wolf. When and how would this separation end? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11578" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11586">For one of them in particular, the future was unclear, complicated. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11587" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11640">Agnese, meanwhile, kept spinning her optimistic conjectures: If nothing bad had happened to him, Renzo would eventually send news of how he was doing, if he had found work and a place to settle. And if (who could doubt?) he had kept his vow, then why couldn’t they go live with him? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11641" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11667">Again and again, she shared these hopes with her daughter, for whom I couldn’t say whether it was harder to listen or to reply. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11668" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11717">Lucia had kept her great secret to herself, and although it was uncomfortable to deceive her good mother—and not for the only time—she was held back, almost invincibly, by shame and the various fears I have mentioned, so she lived day in and day out without saying a word. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11718" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11737">Her plans were quite different from her mother’s, or rather, she had no plans at all. She had placed herself in the hands of Providence. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11738" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11783">So she tried to ignore her mother’s musings or change the subject. Or she would say, vaguely, that she no longer had any hope or desire for the things of this world, only to soon be reunited again with her mother. Most of the time, her tears arrived at just the right moment to keep her from speaking any further. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11784" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11805">“Do you know why you think that way?” Agnese would say. “It’s because you’ve suffered so much, and you can’t believe that things might turn out right in the end. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11806" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11834">Let’s leave it in God’s hands, and if…Allow yourself to see a glimmer, just a glimmer, of hope, and then you can tell me if you’ve stopped thinking about him.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11835" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11840">Lucia kissed her mother and wept. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11841" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11871">In the meantime, a close friendship had blossomed between the two women and their hosts. And why would it not between the benefited and benefactors, when all are good people? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11872" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11880">Agnese especially enjoyed long chats with the mistress of the house. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11881" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11916">For his part, the tailor entertained them with stories or moral tales, especially at the table, where he always had an interesting excerpt to relate from Bevis of Hampton or the Desert Fathers. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11917" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11938">Not far from the village, a well-heeled couple, Don Ferrante and Donna Prassede, were taking their vacation (our anonymous author, as usual, has left out their family name). </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11939" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11970">Donna Prassede was an elderly noblewoman with a strong propensity for good deeds, certainly the worthiest profession a person can exercise, but which can unfortunately—like all the others—also make matters worse. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_11971" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12007">To do good, you have to be able to recognize it, and as in anything, the only way we can recognize it is through our personal passions, judgments, and ideas, which are often limited. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12008" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12050">There is a saying that, when it comes to friends, you should have very few, but to those few be very close. Donna Prassede applied the same rule to ideas: including, unfortunately, many that were bad, which were not the ones she cherished the least. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12051" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12159">Thus, she would submit as “good” causes that were not, or adopt methods that might instead cause harm, or believe to be legitimate things that were nothing of the sort, because of a confused assumption that someone who goes beyond the call of duty is entitled to go beyond what is right. She would not see the truth of a matter, or she would see things that just weren’t there, and make many similar misjudgments, which can and does happen to everyone, even the best of us. But to Donna Prassede they happened far too often, and not infrequently, all together. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12160" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12197">When she heard the big story about Lucia, and everything being said about her, Donna Prassede was gripped by a curiosity to see the girl for herself. She sent a carriage with an elderly squire to fetch mother and daughter. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12198" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12217">Lucia shrugged her shoulders and asked the tailor, who was acting as their emissary, to find a way to excuse them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12218" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12253">As long as he was dealing with ordinary people who wanted to meet the miracle girl, the tailor was happy to comply. But in this case, refusal sounded more like rebellion to him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12254" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12320">He made a big fuss, exclaiming any number of things aloud: This was no way to behave; it was an important family; one doesn’t say no to aristocrats; this could make their fortune; not to mention that Donna Prassede, in addition to everything else, was a saint. So many things, in short, that Lucia had to give in, especially since Agnese backed up all his arguments with her own iterations of, “Well, he’s right.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12321" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12384">When mother and daughter arrived before the lady, she made a great show of welcoming and congratulating them. She asked questions and dispensed advice, all with a certain air of innate superiority, but corrected by expressions of humility, tempered by shows of concern, and seasoned with so much spirituality that Agnese, almost immediately, and Lucia, soon after, started to feel a lifting of the oppressive deference they had initially felt in the presence of nobility. Indeed, they now found her appealing. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12385" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12441">To make a long story short, Donna Prassede, hearing that the Cardinal had taken it upon himself to find shelter for Lucia, and struck by the desire to second and, at the same time, precede his good intentions, offered to take the girl into her own household where, without being assigned any particular task, she could help the other girls with their work at her pleasure. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12442" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12451">She added that she would handle informing His Grace. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12452" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12491">In addition to the obvious and immediate good of this gesture, Donna Prassede saw and settled on another, which, in her opinion, was more worthy of consideration: to correct a wayward mind, to place on the path of righteousness someone who greatly needed it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12492" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12551">From the moment she had first heard talk of Lucia, she was convinced that a young girl who could become engaged to a ne’er-do-well, a troublemaker—a jailbird in short—must have some hidden flaw or vice, since birds of a feather…Lucia’s visit had confirmed this conviction. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12552" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12569">Not that she didn’t look like what passes for a good girl. Still, there was much to find fault with. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12570" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12610">That lowered head, that chin nailed to the hollow of her throat, that reluctance to answer questions, or barely answering them, as if she were forced, might indicate modesty, but they were also a clear sign of obstinacy: It was not hard to imagine that her little head had ideas of its own. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12611" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12629">And that constant blushing, those repressed sighs…and those two big eyes, which Donna Prassede did not like at all. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12630" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12682">She was certain, as if she had received it on good authority, that Lucia’s troubles were a punishment from heaven for her friendship with that ne’er-do-well, and a warning that she should break it off. She therefore channeled her efforts toward just such a happy goal. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12683" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12717">Since, as she often told others and herself, her purpose in life was to second the will of heaven (but she often made the mistake of confusing the will of heaven with her own). </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12718" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12732">She was careful, however, to not even hint at this second intention. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12733" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12763">For it was another one of her maxims that, in order to do what’s good for a person, the first rule, in most cases, is not to tell them what you have planned. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12764" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12772">Mother and daughter looked each other in the face. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12773" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12811">Given the painful need to separate, the offer seemed acceptable to both, if only because Donna Prassede’s villa was so close to their little village. In the worst of cases, they would still be near each other and able to spend the next holiday together. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12812" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12830">Seeing the consent in each other’s eyes, they turned to Donna Prassede with the appreciation that signifies acceptance. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12831" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12848">The noblewoman renewed her kindness and promises, and said that she would immediately prepare a letter for them to show the Cardinal. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12849" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12876">After the two women left, Donna Prassede had Don Ferrante write a draft. Since he was an educated man (as I will describe in more detail), she used him as her secretary for important occasions. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12877" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12920">This being just such an occasion, Don Ferrante invested it with all of his learning and, as he handed his spouse the draft for her to copy, he emphasized the orthography, one of the many subjects he had studied, and one of the few over which he held the upper hand in that house. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12921" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12932">Donna Prassede copied it diligently, and had the letter forwarded to the tailor. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12933" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12952">This all occurred two or three days before the Cardinal sent the sedan chair to bring the women back to their home village. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12953" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12962">Upon their arrival, Agnese and Lucia got off at the parish house, where the Cardinal was waiting. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_12963" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13013">Instructions had been given to show them in immediately. The first person to see them was the chaplain, who, while carrying out the orders, detained them just long enough to hastily advise them on the protocols to be observed with His Grace and the correct forms of address, as he tended to do whenever the Cardinal wasn’t looking. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13014" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13051">It was a constant source of frustration for the poor man to see the scant attention paid to such details in the Cardinal’s orbit. “All because that blessed soul is too kind,” he told other members of the household. “Too familiar.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13052" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13068">And he would relate how, with his own ears, he had heard people responding to the Cardinal with a “yes, sir, no, sir.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13069" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13099">At that moment, Federigo was discussing parish affairs with Don Abbondio, leaving the priest no room to issue his own private instructions to the women, as he would have preferred. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13100" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13129">The only thing he did manage to do was to give them a look as he passed by them on his way out and their way in, to hint that he was pleased with them, and that they should continue, like good girls, to say nothing. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13130" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13178">After the first welcomes from one side, and the first curtsies from the other, Agnese removed the letter from beneath her blouse and presented it to the Cardinal, saying, “This is from Donna Prassede, who says that she knows Your Grace well, since, of course, among nobles, I guess you all know one another. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13179" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13181">When you’ve read it, you’ll see.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13182" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13198">“That will be fine,” said Federigo, after he had read it and managed to extract its meaning from the flowery rhetoric of Don Ferrante. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13199" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13225">He knew that family well enough to be sure that Lucia had been invited with the best intentions, and that there she would be safe from the intrigues and violence of her tormentor. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13226" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13237">As for his opinion of Donna Prassede, we do not know. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13238" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13274">In all likelihood, she is not the person he would have chosen for this task, but it was not his habit, as I have said or implied elsewhere, to undo the arrangements made by others in order to redo them better. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13275" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13327">“Accept in peace this new separation, and the uncertainty in which you find yourselves.” He added, “Have faith that this will soon be over, and that the Lord will guide things to the end for which He seems to have destined them. But of one thing you may be sure: He only wishes what is best for you.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13328" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13348">He gave Lucia in particular some loving advice, and to both women some words of comfort. Then he blessed them and sent them on their way. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13349" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13375">The minute they stepped outside, they were greeted by a swarm of friends. The whole village seemed to be waiting for them, and they were led home in triumph. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13376" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13401">The women vied with one another in congratulations, sympathy, and questions; they exclaimed their sadness at hearing that Lucia would be leaving the next day. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13402" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13417">The men competed with one another in volunteering services: Each one wanted to stand guard over their cottage that night. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13418" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13439">This fact inspired our anonymous author to formulate a proverb: If you don’t want too many helpers, then try not to need them! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13440" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13451">This warm welcome left Lucia flustered and dismayed; Agnese was not so easily perturbed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13452" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13486">Ultimately, it was also good for Lucia, taking her mind off the thoughts and memories that were sadly reawakened on that doorstep, in those rooms, and at the sight of every object, even in the midst of compliments. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13487" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13512">When the bell struck announcing the start of Mass, everyone headed to the church, and the walk there became yet another triumphal procession for the two women. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13513" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13535">After the Mass ended, Don Abbondio, who had rushed home to make sure that Perpetua had everything prepared for the meal, was summoned by the Cardinal. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13536" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13580">He went immediately to his distinguished guest who, as he approached, intoned, “Reverend Father.” These words were uttered in a manner that left no doubt that they were the start of a long and serious conversation. “Reverend Father, tell me, why did you not join in marriage that poor girl Lucia with her fiancé?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13581" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13651">“They must have spilled the beans this morning,” Don Abbondio said to himself. By way of a reply, he mumbled, “Your Grace will have heard talk of the commotion caused by that affair. It was so confusing that, even today, it’s hard to get a clear picture. As Your Grace himself can see, the girl is here, after many misfortunes, almost by miracle. As for the young man, after misfortunes of his own, no one knows where he is.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13652" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13679">“What I am asking,” the Cardinal continued, “is whether it is true that, before all these things happened, you refused to celebrate their marriage when they asked you to, on the scheduled day, and, if so, why.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13680" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13714">“The truth is…if Your Grace only knew…the threats…the terrible orders I was given not to talk…” At this, he stopped without completing his sentence, intimating respectfully that it would be indiscreet to question him any further. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13715" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13758">“But!” said the Cardinal, in a voice and with a solemn air that was not his custom. “This is your Bishop who, to perform his duty and to justify your behavior, is asking you why you did not do what the rules required you to do.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13759" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13800">“Your Grace,” said Don Abbondio, shrinking into himself, “I didn’t mean to say…It’s just that I thought, it being so messy, an old story for which there was no remedy, that there was no point bringing it up…But, but, I can say…I know that Your Grace would not want to betray his poor pastor. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13801" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13825">Because, you see, in these parts, Your Grace cannot be everywhere, and I am stuck here, defenseless…But if you order me to, I’ll tell you, I’ll tell you everything.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13826" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13834">“Then tell me. I would like nothing better than to find you blameless.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13835" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13869">Don Abbondio therefore proceeded to tell the sad story, leaving out the most important name, however, and replacing it with “a powerful lord,” thus giving to prudence what little he could in such a bind. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13870" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13883">“And you had no other reason?” asked the Cardinal after Don Abbondio had finished. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13884" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13903">“Perhaps I did not make myself clear,” the priest answered. “At pain of death, I was ordered not to celebrate that marriage.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13904" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13916">“And did you think that was a good enough reason for you to fail to perform a specific duty?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13917" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13936">“I have always tried to do my duty, no matter how much it inconvenienced me, but when it is a question of life…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13937" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13960">“And when you were ordained into the Church,” Federigo said, in an even more solemn tone, “to assume the burden of the priesthood, did the Church safeguard your life? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13961" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13977">Did it tell you that the duties of the priesthood are free from every obstacle, immune from all danger? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13978" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13990">Did it perhaps tell you that your duties ended where danger began? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13991" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13997">Did it not tell you the opposite instead? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_13998" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14009">Did it not warn you that you were being sent forth as a lamb among wolves? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14010" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14026">Did you not know there were violent men who might not be happy with the instructions you would be given? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14027" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14059">He who gave us His teachings and example—which we imitate in being called and in calling ourselves shepherds—when He descended to earth in fulfillment of the prophecy, did He make it a condition that His life be saved? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14060" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14089">Did He need the sacrament of Holy Orders to save His life, to preserve it for a few more days on earth, at the expense of charity and duty? Did He need the laying on of hands, the holy chrism? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14090" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14100">Let the world profess this virtue and teach this doctrine. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14101" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14151">What am I saying? Oh, for shame! Because the world rejects this virtue, and makes its own laws prescribing evil and good. The world has its own gospel—a gospel of pride and hatred—which does not accept love for life as a reason to disobey its commandments. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14152" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14157">It will not have this: It will be obeyed! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14158" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14165">And us? We children and preachers of the promise? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14166" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14180">What would become of the Church if all of your brothers used similar language? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14181" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14190">What would become of the Church if She had come into the world with such doctrines?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14191" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14226">Don Abbondio hung his head. In the middle of these arguments, his spirit was like a chick between the talons of a hawk, dangling above an unknown region, high up in an air which he had never breathed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14227" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14241">Realizing that he had to answer in some way, he said, with a certain forced humility, “Your Grace, I may be wrong. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14242" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14253">If a man’s life counts for nothing, then I don’t know what to say. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14254" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14286">But when you have to deal with certain people, powerful men, who will not listen to reason, even if I wanted to be brave, I don’t know what could be gained by it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14287" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14299">He’s a man, the one I’m talking about, who you can’t defeat or even appease.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14300" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14313">“Do you not know that suffering for the sake of justice is our victory? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14314" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14334">And if not, what do you preach? What do you have to teach? What good tidings do you have to bring the poor? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14335" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14345">Does anyone expect you to defeat force through force? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14346" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14372">One question you will never be asked, on that day, is whether you succeeded in making the powerful do their duty; you have been given neither the mission nor the means to do so. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14373" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14399">But you will certainly be asked whether you have used all the means in your power to do what you were ordained to do, even when the powerful had the temerity to forbid you from doing so.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14400" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14469">“These saints are odd,” Don Abbondio thought. “The gist of what he is saying is that he cares more about the love of two young people than the life of a poor priest.” He would have been happy for their conversation to end there. But he could see that at every pause, the Cardinal seemed to be expecting a reply: a confession, an excuse, anything. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14470" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14487">“I can only repeat,” he then said, “that I might be wrong, Your Grace…But it’s hard to be brave when you’re not.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14488" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14510">“So then why, may I ask, did you take a vow to enter a ministry that requires you to do battle with the passions of this world? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14511" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14546">How did you not realize that, in this ministry, regardless of conditions, courage would be required to fulfill your obligations, and that there was Someone who would give it to you, unfailingly, if you asked Him? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14547" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14588">Do you believe those millions of martyrs were innately courageous? That they thought, innately, that their lives didn’t count? The many young people who had just started to enjoy life; the many old people used to complaining that their lives would be over too soon; the many maidens, wives, and mothers? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14589" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14600">They all found courage, because courage was required, and they had faith. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14601" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14627">Knowing your own weakness and duties, did you not think to prepare yourself for the difficult moments in which you might find yourself, in which you did, in effect, find yourself? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14628" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14666">Ah, if during your many years of pastoral responsibilities, you had loved your flock (and how could you not?), if you had invested all of your heart, your cares, and your pleasures in them, then you wouldn’t have been lacking courage when you needed it: For love is intrepid. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14667" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14713">If you had loved those entrusted to your spiritual care, those whom you call your children, then—of course!—when you saw two of them being threatened alongside yourself, just as the weakness of the flesh made you fear for yourself, love would have made you fear for them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14714" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14779">You would have been humbled by your initial fear, because it stemmed from your weakness. You would have prayed to God for the strength to overcome that fear, to drive it away, as a temptation. But the holy and noble fear for others, for your own children, that you would have heeded. It would have given you no peace, aroused you to action, forced you to think, to do everything in your power to protect them from the danger looming over them…What did this fear inspire in you? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14780" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14785">Love? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14786" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14790">What did you do for them? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14791" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14793">What did you think of doing?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap25-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14794" targetEnd="quarantana/cap25.xml#c25_14800">Federigo fell silent, as if awaiting a reply. </note>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>