<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>2022</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed: a novel</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
          <date>2022</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Michael Moore</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="english_2022_cap36">
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10035">Who would have told Renzo, a few hours earlier, as his search neared its end and his moments of greatest doubt and decision began, that his heart would be torn between Lucia and Don Rodrigo? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10036" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10110">And yet, so it was. On that short walk, the figure of Don Rodrigo blended in with all the cherished or terrifying images that hope or fear had set before him. The words he had heard by that dismal bed were caught between the yeses and noes at war within his mind. As he prayed for a happy end to his great ordeal, he also added the prayers he had recited over the dying man before the tolling of the bell had cut them short. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10111" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10205">The octagonal chapel stood in the middle of the lazaretto, elevated by a short set of steps. Originally, it was open on all sides, with no walls or support other than pillars and columns: a perforated structure, in other words. On every side there was an arch between two columns. On the inside, the church proper was surrounded by a gallery of eight arches, one for each side, and topped by a cupola, making the central altar visible from every window of the surrounding buildings and almost every point in the yard. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10206" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10230">Today, the building has been converted for other uses and the once-open façades have been walled in, but the original framework has remained intact, clearly indicating its former appearance and purpose. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10231" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10280">Renzo had just started walking in that direction when he saw Padre Felice appear in the portico of the chapel and stand beneath the middle arch of the side that faced the city. A group had congregated before him in the central pathway, at the foot of the steps. From the friar’s posture Renzo could already see that the sermon had begun. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10281" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10294">Renzo made his way through the pathways to the back of the crowd, as he had been instructed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10295" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10320">There he stopped, quiet as a mouse, and surveyed the assembly. All he could see from that point, however, was an expanse of heads, pressed together like cobblestones. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10321" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10360">Some in the middle were covered with kerchiefs or veils: This is where he stared most intently. Unable to discover anything in the crowd, he looked up to where everyone was staring. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10361" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10388">The venerable figure of the preacher humbled and moved him, and, with all the attention he could spare at a moment of such great expectation, Renzo began to listen to his sermon: </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10389" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10458">“Let us pause to consider the thousands upon thousands who departed in that direction.” The preacher pointed over his shoulder to the gate leading to the San Gregorio cemetery, which had been turned into a vast common grave in those days. “Let us look around at the thousands upon thousands who remain here, still uncertain of how they will leave. Let us look at ourselves, the few of us who are departing from here alive. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10459" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10461">Blessed be the Lord! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10462" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10483">Blessed in justice, and blessed in mercy! Blessed in death, and blessed in health! Blessed in His having chosen us! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10484" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10554">Oh, why did He choose us, my children, if not to set aside a small population for Himself, redeemed through affliction and inspired by gratitude? If not so that we would feel more profoundly that life is a gift from Him, and that we should cherish it as we should all things that He has given, and express our gratitude through good deeds that we can offer up to Him? If not so that the memory of our hardships would make us more compassionate and helpful to our fellow man? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10555" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10610">Those who have suffered, hoped, and feared alongside us, whom we leave behind as friends and relations, brothers and sisters. For those who watch us leave this place, may they be edified by our composure, while taking solace in the thought that some of us have departed from here alive. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10611" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10635">God does not want them to see us erupt in a loud, worldly joy at our escape from the death with which they still wrestle. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10636" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10663">Let them see us leave filled with gratitude for ourselves and prayers for them, so that they may know we shall continue to pray for their pour souls once we are outside. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10664" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10679">As we take our first steps in this journey, may we begin a life filled with charity. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10680" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10713">May those who have regained their former strength lend a fraternal arm to the weak. May the young support the old. May those of you who have lost your own children see the children all around you who have lost their parents. Become parents to them! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10714" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10725">And this charity, by redeeming your sins, will also ease your pain.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10726" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10767">A dull murmur of groans and sobs that had been swelling within the assembly suddenly fell silent when the preacher placed a rope around his neck and dropped to his knees. The crowd waited quietly to hear what he was about to say. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10768" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10805">“For myself,” he began, “and for all my brothers, who, through no merit of our own were chosen for the great privilege of serving Christ by serving you, I humbly beg for your forgiveness if we have proven unworthy of this great mission. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10806" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10887">If sloth, the rebellion of the flesh, has made us less attentive, less responsive to your needs; if an unjust impatience, a sinful weariness, has made us appear before you looking irritated or severe; if the desperation of your need kept us from treating you with the proper humility at times; if our frailty has led us to do things that upset you, please forgive us. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10888" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10898">By the same token shall God forgive your trespasses, and bless you.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10899" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10907">Making the sign of the cross over the congregation, he then stood up. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10908" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10939">I have been able to report if not the exact words that he spoke, then at the least their sense and theme, although I cannot describe the manner in which he said them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10940" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10979">It was the manner of a man who said it was a privilege to serve the plague victims, because that is what he believed it to be; who confessed that he was unworthy, because he truly felt he was; and who begged for forgiveness, because he was convinced that he needed it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_10980" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11034">But what about the people who had seen the Capuchins dedicate themselves wholly to serving others and seen so many die; who had watched this man who spoke on their behalf, always the first in his labors and first in authority, until he himself was at death’s door? Can you imagine the sobs, the tears, with which they responded to his words? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11035" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11077">The admirable friar then took a large cross that was leaning against a pillar and raised it high. Leaving his sandals on the edge of the outer gallery, he descended the steps and began to make his way through the crowd, which parted respectfully to allow him to lead the procession. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11078" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11160">Renzo’s eyes filled with tears, as if he himself had been asked to bestow that singular forgiveness. He stepped to one side along with the others and hid by a hut, waiting, with his body in the shadows and his head sticking out, his eyes wide open and his heart racing, but also with a special newfound confidence born, I believe, from the tenderness inspired in him by that sermon, and the sight of tenderness all around. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11161" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11236">Now came Padre Felice, barefoot, with the rope around his neck and bearing the large heavy cross. His face was gaunt and pale, radiating both contrition and courage. He walked slowly but resolutely, like a man whose only thought was to help the weak, and who had found the strength, through hard work and discomfort, to shoulder the rigors required by and inseparable from his job. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11237" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11256">Immediately after him came the older children: Many had no shoes, while most were not fully clothed, some in only a shirt. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11257" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11306">Then came the women, almost all of whom were holding a girl by the hand and singing the Miserere in rounds. The feeble sound of their voices, the pallor and languor of their faces, inspired compassion in anyone who found themselves there as a simple spectator. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11307" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11332">Renzo looked closely from row to row, face to face, skipping none. The procession was moving slowly, so he had ample time to examine every woman who passed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11333" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11363">They kept coming and coming. He kept looking and looking, but always in vain. He gave a rapid glance at the remaining rows: By now very few are left. Here comes the last row. All the women have passed by. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11364" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11387">All had the faces of strangers. His arms hanging and his head leaning to one side, he followed with his eyes the last row of women before the men’s group began to pass by. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11388" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11415">At the appearance of a few carts trailing behind, bearing convalescents still too frail to walk, his attention and his hopes revived. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11416" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11437">The women were in the last carts of the procession, which was moving so slowly that Renzo was able to examine every single face. To no avail. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11438" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11482">He examined the first cart, then the second, and the third, always with the same result, until the last passed him, followed only by another stern-looking Capuchin holding a stick, the group supervisor. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11483" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11499">It was Padre Michele who, as I have mentioned, shared the leadership of the lazaretto with Padre Felice. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11500" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11529">With that, Renzo’s cherished hope vanished, taking with it not only the comfort it had afforded but, as is generally the case, leaving him in worse shape than before. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11530" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11542">The best he could hope for now was to find Lucia in a sickbed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11543" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11580">Yet as the ardor of his hope succumbed to growing fear, the poor boy clung with all his strength to that sad and feeble thread. He fell into line and walked toward the place where the procession had begun. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11581" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11645">At the foot of the chapel, he knelt on the bottom step, where he said a prayer to God, or rather a jumble of muddled words, broken sentences, exclamations, questions, complaints, and promises. It was one of those speeches not meant for the ears of men, since they have neither the insight to understand nor the patience to listen to them. They are not big enough to feel compassion for such words without contempt. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11646" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11703">He stood up, revived. He walked around the chapel, and found himself on a path he hadn’t noticed before that led to the other gate. A few steps away, he saw the fence the friar had mentioned, and its large gaps exactly as had been described. He passed through one of them and found himself in the women’s quarter. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11704" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11753">Almost immediately, he spotted a small bell on the ground, the kind the monatti wore on their feet, and realized it could serve as his passport inside this area. He picked it up, making sure no one was looking, and tied it to his ankle the way that they did. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11754" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11839">Then he set out on his search, a search that would have already been arduous because of the sheer number of objects, even if they had been another type of object altogether. He began to survey or rather contemplate new miseries, similar to yet so unlike the ones he had already witnessed. Although everyone was suffering from the same calamity, here there was a different suffering, a different languishing, and a different moaning, as well as a different form of mutual support, pity and assistance. And the observer felt a different sympathy and revulsion. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11840" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11866">He had already been walking for quite a while without incident or results, when he heard someone behind him say, “You, over there!” apparently directed at him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11867" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11899">He turned and saw a commissioner in the distance raise a hand, point straight at him, and shout, “They need help over there, in the rooms. We’re done cleaning.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11900" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11948">Renzo immediately realized for whom he’d been mistaken, and that the bell was the reason for the confusion. He cursed himself for thinking only about how this identifier would prevent problems, and not how it could invite them. But how could he handle this man? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11949" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11980">He nodded quickly at the commissioner, as if to indicate that he’d understood and would obey the order, and then disappeared from his sight, slipping off between the huts to one side. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_11981" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12018">When he felt far enough away, he decided to get rid of the source of attention. To avoid being noticed, he squeezed into a narrow space between two huts standing back-to-back. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12019" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12044">He crouched down to untie the bell, his head leaning against the straw wall of one hut, when he heard a soft voice coming from within. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12045" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12048">Good Lord! Could it be? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12049" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12059">He held his breath, and listened as if his life depended on it…Yes! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12060" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12078">Yes! It was her voice!…“Afraid of what?” she said softly. “We’ve been through something much worse than a storm. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12079" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12087">The people who have taken care of us so far will continue to do so.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12088" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12106">Renzo didn’t let out a shout, but not because he feared discovery. He couldn’t breathe. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12107" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12149">His knees buckled and his eyesight clouded over, but only for a moment. In the next, he was back on his feet and fully alert, more vigorous than before. In a hop, skip, and a jump, he circled the hut and stood at the door. He peered at the woman who had been speaking as she leaned over a cot. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12150" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12168">She turned around at the sound of someone at the door. She looked and couldn’t believe her eyes. Was she dreaming? She looked more closely. “Oh my Lord!” she cried. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12169" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12183">“Lucia, I’ve found you! You’re here! It really is you! You’re alive!” exclaimed Renzo as he stepped forward, trembling all over. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12184" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12200">“Oh my Lord,” replied Lucia, trembling even more. “Renzo? What is this? How? Why? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12201" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12202">But the plague!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12203" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12204">“I’ve had it already. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12205" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12206">And you…?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12207" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12208">“Ah…me, too. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12209" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12212">And my mother?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12213" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12224">“I haven’t seen her since she moved to Pasturo, but I hear she’s well. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12225" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12233">But you…you’re so pale! You look so weak! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12234" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12237">Are you really better?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12238" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12244">“The Lord has decided to keep me here on earth a little while longer. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12245" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12250">Oh, Renzo! Why did you come here?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12251" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12263">“Why did I come here?” said Renzo, approaching even closer. “You’re asking why I came? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12264" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12269">Do I have to tell you? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12276" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12281">Am I not Renzo? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12282" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12286">Are you not Lucia?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12287" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12291">“What are you saying? What are you saying? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12292" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12298">Didn’t my mother get someone to write to you?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12299" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12304">“Yes, unfortunately she did. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12305" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12326">What kind of thing was that to write to someone down on his luck, a boy in trouble, driven from his home, a boy who at the very least has always respected you.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12327" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12328">“But, Renzo! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12329" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12334">Renzo! Since you already knew…why did you come? Why?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12335" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12336">“Why did I come? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12337" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12342">Oh, Lucia, how can you even ask why I came? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12343" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12345">After all our promises? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12346" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12349">Are we no longer ourselves? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12350" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12357">Do you no longer remember what we were denied?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12358" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12381">“Oh Lord!” exclaimed Lucia in anguish, clasping her hands together and looking up at the sky. “Why did you not grant me the grace of taking me to heaven…? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12382" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12386">Oh, Renzo! What have you done? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12387" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12396">Just when I was starting to hope that…with time…I would forget…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12397" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12405">“You call that hope? And you say it to my face?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12406" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12408">“Ah, what have you done? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12409" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12428">And in this place! Surrounded by this misery! By these sights! Here, where people come to die! How could you?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12429" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12460">“The dying? All we can do is pray to God for them, and hope they’ll go to a better place. But that’s no reason, no, not even that, for the living to lead lives of despair…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12461" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12462">“But, Renzo, Renzo! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12463" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12470">Think of what you’re saying. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12471" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12476">I made a vow to the Blessed Virgin!…A vow!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12477" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12487">“And I’m telling you that some vows don’t count.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12488" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12489">“Oh Lord! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12490" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12491">What are you saying? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12492" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12497">Where have you been? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12498" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12501">Who has filled your head with these thoughts? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12502" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12503">Why are you speaking this way?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12504" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12525">“I’m speaking like a good Christian! As for the Blessed Virgin, I think I know her better than you do. Because I think she has no desire for vows that hurt your fellow man. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12526" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12532">If the Virgin had actually spoken, that would have been a different matter. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12533" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12538">But it’s all in your imagination. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12539" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12544">Let me tell you the vow you should make to Her. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12545" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12585">Vow that you will name our first daughter after her, Maria. I can make that vow, too. That’s how you’re supposed to honor the Virgin. Devotions like that make more sense, and they don’t hurt anyone.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12586" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12616">“How can you say that? You don’t know what you’re saying! You don’t know what it means to make a vow, Renzo. You weren’t the one in that situation. You don’t know what it was like, Renzo! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12617" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12622">Go. Go now, for the love of heaven.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12623" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12632">She broke away from him in a fury, returning to her cot. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12633" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12650">“Lucia!” said Renzo, without moving. “At least tell me, tell me, if it weren’t for that vow…would you still be mine?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12651" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12683">“You have no heart!” replied Lucia, turning away from him and struggling to hold back the tears. “You’d force me to say words that won’t do any good? Words that might be sinful and could put me in harm’s way? Would that make you happy? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12684" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12695">Go now, please go! Forget me. You can see that we are not destined to be together. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12696" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12708">We shall meet again in heaven, for our time on earth is so short. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12709" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12775">Go. Try to let my mother know that I’ve recovered. God has always helped me, even here, and I have found a good soul here, this kind woman, who is like a mother to me. Tell her that I hope she will be spared from this disease, and that we will see each other again when and where God wishes…Go now, for the love of heaven, and don’t think about me…except when you are praying to God.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12776" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12809">She drew even closer to the woman’s bed, as if shielding herself from danger, like someone with nothing left to say and nothing more she wanted to hear. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12810" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12819">“Listen to me, Lucia, listen to me!” cried Renzo, but did not move any closer. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12820" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12824">“No, go now, for mercy’s sake!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12825" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12828">“Listen to me. Padre Cristoforo…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12829" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12829">“What?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12830" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12831">“He’s here.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12832" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12833">“Here? Where? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12834" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12836">How do you know?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12837" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12855">“I spoke with him a little while ago. I spent some time with him. And a priest of his quality, I think…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12856" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12863">“He’s here? To help the poor plague victims, I’m sure. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12864" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12869">But what about him? Has he had the plague?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12870" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12913">“Ah, Lucia! I’m afraid, I’m afraid that, unfortunately…” As Renzo hesitated to deliver the news that pained him, and would pain Lucia even more, she stepped away from the cot and came closer to him. “I’m afraid that he has it now!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12914" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12916">“That poor saint of a man! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12917" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12920">But not just the poor man. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12921" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12922">Poor us! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12923" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12928">How is he? Is he in bed? Is someone taking care of him?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12929" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12945">“He’s up and about, helping others. But if you saw him, how pale he is, how he struggles to stay on his feet! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12946" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12957">There have been so many who look that way, so many, unfortunately…there’s no mistaking it!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12958" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12960">“Oh, poor us! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12961" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12964">To think that he’s right here!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12965" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12980">“Only a few feet away. Almost the same distance as from your house to mine…if you remember!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12981" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12983">“Oh Blessed Virgin!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12984" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12986">“Not much farther than that. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12987" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12993">And to think that we talked about you! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_12994" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13004">He told me some things…if you only knew what he showed me! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13005" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13022">You will hear. But now I want to tell you what he said earlier, his exact words. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13023" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13061">He told me that I was right to come looking for you, and that it pleases God for a young man to act this way, so God would help me find you. And he was right. He truly is a saint. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13062" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13063">Don’t you see?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13064" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13073">“But if he said that it’s only because he doesn’t know…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13074" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13095">“How can you expect him to know the things you did on your own, without following any rules or anyone’s advice? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13096" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13112">A good, sensible man like him would never have expected that. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13113" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13118">But you should have seen what he showed me!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13119" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13153">Then he told her about their visit to that hut. In the time she had spent at the lazaretto, Lucia’s heart and senses had hardened, and grown used to the most ghastly sights. Still she was filled with horror and compassion by the story he told her. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13154" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13201">“And there, too,” continued Renzo, “he spoke like a saint. He said that maybe God wished to deliver grace to that poor wretch (what else could I call him now?), that He is waiting to take him at the right moment. But he wants us to pray for him together…Together! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13202" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13204">Do you understand?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13205" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13221">“Yes, yes, we’ll pray for him, each of us where God has placed us. For He will know how to unite our prayers.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13222" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13228">“But I’m telling you his exact words…!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13229" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13233">“But, Renzo, he doesn’t know…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13234" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13262">“Don’t you understand that when a saint speaks, God speaks through him? That Padre Cristoforo would never have said that if it wasn’t so? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13263" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13267">And what about that poor man’s soul? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13268" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13288">I really did pray for him, and I will keep praying. I prayed from my heart, as if he were my brother. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13289" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13316">But how do you think he will fare up there in heaven, poor man, if you and I don’t repair things between us, and right the wrong that he committed? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13317" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13341">If you listen to reason, then everything will go back to the way it was supposed to be. What’s past is past. He has paid his debt down here…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13342" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13356">“No, Renzo, no. God does not want us to do wrong for the sake of His mercy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13357" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13369">Let us leave this matter in His hands: Our only duty is to pray. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13370" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13380">If I had died that night, does that mean that Don Rodrigo might never have been forgiven? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13381" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13389">And since I did not die, and I was released…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13390" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13421">“And your mother? Poor Agnese, who has always loved me, and who suffered so much to see us become husband and wife, didn’t she also tell you that you were wrong? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13422" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13440">She’s made you listen to reason other times, too, because, sometimes, she has more sense than you.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13441" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13455">“My mother? You want my mother to advise me to break a vow? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13456" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13461">Renzo, you’re not yourself!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13462" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13467">“Do you really want to know? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13468" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13476">The two of you, you don’t know everything! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13477" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13490">Fra Cristoforo told me I should go back to him and let him know whether I’d found you. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n171" type="comm" status="insertion">I’ll go now. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13491" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13497">Let’s hear what he has to say. I think he’s going to say…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13498" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13518">“Yes, go to that holy man. Tell him that I pray for him, and that he should pray for me. I need his prayers. I need them so much! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13519" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13539">But for the love of heaven, for the sake of your soul, of my soul, don’t come back here again to hurt me, to…tempt me. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13540" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13560">Fra Cristoforo will explain it to you, and make you come to your senses. He’ll set your heart at peace.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13561" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13564">“My heart at peace? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13565" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13569">Well, you can forget about that! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13570" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13592">First you had that awful letter sent to me. Do you have any idea how much that hurt me? And now you have the heart to say the same thing in person? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13593" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13610">Let me tell you loud and clear that I will never set my heart at peace. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13611" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13622">Maybe you want to forget me. But I don’t want to forget you. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13623" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13637">And I promise that if you make me lose my senses, I’ll never get them back. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13638" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13646">To hell with my job, to hell with good behavior! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13647" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13662">You want to condemn me to a lifetime of anger? Very well, then. I’ll live as an angry man…And that scoundrel! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13663" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13687">God knows I forgave him from my heart, but you…Do you really want me to spend the rest of my life believing that if it hadn’t been for him…? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13688" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13696">Lucia! You told me to forget you. Forget you! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13697" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13699">How am I supposed to do that? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13700" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13708">Who do you think I’ve been thinking of this whole time? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13709" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13715">And after all that’s happened! After all our promises! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n189" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13716" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13724">Is there something I did to you after we said goodbye? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n190" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13725" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13765">Are you treating me this way because I suffered? Because I got into trouble? Because I was a wanted man? Because I’ve been homeless and sad and far away from you for so long? Because I came back to look for you as soon as I could?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n191" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13766" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13794">When Lucia was finally able to speak through her tears, she clasped her hands, raised her reddened eyes to the heavens, and exclaimed, “Oh Blessed Virgin, help me! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n192" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13795" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13808">You know that ever since that night, I have never lived through another moment like this. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n193" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13809" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13814">You helped me then. Help me now!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n194" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13815" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13857">“Yes, Lucia, go ahead and invoke the Madonna. But how can you believe that the mother of mercy, a person so good, would want us, or at least me, to suffer…all because of a word you let slip at a moment when you didn’t know what you were saying? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n195" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13858" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13867">Do you really believe that she helped you then only to leave us in this tangled mess now? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n196" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13868" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13884">Or is this just an excuse, and you’ve come to hate me? Tell me. Tell me the truth.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n197" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13885" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13900">“Please, Renzo, please, for the love of your dearly departed, stop. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n198" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13901" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13905">You’re killing me…This is not my time. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n199" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13906" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13920">Go to Padre Cristoforo. Give him my regards, and don’t come back here ever again.” “I’m leaving. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n200" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13921" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13927">But don’t think I won’t be back. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n201" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13928" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13935">I’d come back here if this were the ends of the earth.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n202" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13936" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13937">With that he left. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n203" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13938" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13961">Lucia sat or rather sank to the floor next to the cot. Leaning her head against it, she continued to sob uncontrollably. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n204" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13962" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13983">Her companion, who until that moment had been holding her breath, but watching and listening intently, wondered at the meaning of that apparition, that quarrel, that weeping. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n205" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_13984" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14005">The reader must be wondering who she might be. Once again, it will only take a few words to satisfy your curiosity. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n206" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14006" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14011">She was the wealthy widow of a merchant, perhaps in her thirties. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n207" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14012" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14092">In the space of a few days, she had watched her husband and all of her children die at home. It was not long before she came down with the plague herself. She was taken to the lazaretto and placed in the same hut as Lucia, who was just starting to regain her strength and consciousness after surviving the worst of the disease, unaware of the series of roommates who had come through her quarters. She had become ill when she was still at the house of Don Ferrante and had been unconscious ever since. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n208" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14093" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14126">The hut was only big enough for two, and they struck up an intimacy, and bonded in their sickness, abandonment, and isolation among the multitudes; very soon, it was as if they had been living together for years. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n209" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14127" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14142">Lucia was soon able to help her companion, who was extremely ill. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n210" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14143" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14179">Now that she, too, was out of danger, they kept each other company and kept up each other’s spirits. They had promised not to leave the lazaretto unless they could go together, and remain together afterward. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n211" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14180" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14232">The widow had left her home, shop, and coffers—all well-stocked—in the care of her brother, a commissioner on the Tribunal of Health. She was about to become the sad and lonely mistress of far more wealth than she needed to live comfortably, and she wanted to keep Lucia by her side, as a daughter or sister. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n212" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14233" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14263">Lucia had agreed, grateful to her and to Providence, but not until she received news from her mother, and learned, she hoped, of her approval. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n213" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14264" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14283">Since Lucia was reserved by nature, she had never uttered a word about her engagement or any of her extraordinary adventures. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n214" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14284" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14302">But now, with such a great reawakening of emotions, her desire to pour out her heart matched her companion’s desire to listen. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n215" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14303" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14329">Holding the widow’s right hand, Lucia immediately set about answering her questions, with no restraint other than her sobs. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n216" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14330" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14338">Meanwhile Renzo was hurrying off to the good friar’s quarters. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n217" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14339" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14356">After some difficulty and retracing his steps a few times over, he finally managed to make it back. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n218" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14357" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14386">He found the hut but not the man. After circling and searching the area, he saw him in a shack, leaning almost prone over the ground to comfort a dying man. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n219" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14387" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14392">Renzo stood there, waiting in silence. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n220" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14393" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14412">Soon after, he saw the friar close the poor man’s eyes, get down on his knees, and say a short prayer. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n221" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14413" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14419">When he stood back up, Renzo went up to him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n222" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14420" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14426">“Oh,” Fra Cristoforo said, seeing him come, “well?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n223" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14427" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14430">“She’s here! I found her!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n224" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14431" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14433">“In what condition?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n225" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14434" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14437">“She’s recovered, or at least she’s on her feet.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n226" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14438" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14441">“Praise God!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n227" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14442" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14456">“But,” said Renzo, when he was close enough to whisper, “there’s another complication.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n228" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14457" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14458">“Tell me.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n229" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14459" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14481">“What I mean to say is…You know how good she is, but sometimes Lucia can be a little stubborn. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n230" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14482" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14520">After all our promises, after all that we’ve been through—which you know about—now she says she can’t marry me. She says—what do I know?—that on that awful night, she lost her mind and—how can I put this—made a vow to the Virgin. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n231" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14521" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14525">It makes no sense! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n232" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14526" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14557">It would be a good thing for someone who knows these things, and understands when to make a vow, but for us common people, who don’t know how to go about it…Can that vow really be valid?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n233" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14558" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14563">“Tell me, is she far from here?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n234" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14564" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14571">“No, a short ways from the other side of the church.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n235" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14572" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14583">“Give me a minute,” said the friar, “and we’ll go there together.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n236" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14584" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14590">“Do you mean that you’ll make her understand…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n237" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14591" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14598">“I don’t know, my son. I have to hear from her first.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n238" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14599" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14623">“I see,” said Renzo. He stood there, staring at the ground with his arms folded over his chest, still ruminating over the same uncertainties. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n239" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14624" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14672">The friar went in search of Padre Vittore, and asked him to cover for him one more time. He went into his hut, came out with his bag on his arm, and returning to Renzo, said, “Let’s go.” Fra Cristoforo went first, heading toward the same hut that they had entered together a little while earlier. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n240" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14673" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14686">This time he entered alone. A moment later he reappeared, saying, “All we can do is pray.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n241" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14687" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14691">And then, “Now lead the way.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n242" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14692" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14696">Without another word, they set out. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n243" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14697" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14712">The sky was growing darker, heralding the imminent storm. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n244" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14713" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14754">Sharp bolts of lightning pierced the spreading darkness, casting a harsh bright light on the long roofs and arches of the galleries, the cupola of the chapel, and the squat chimneys of the huts. Peals of thunder broke with a loud boom, echoing from one region of the sky to the next. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n245" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14755" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14803">The young man pressed on, impatient to get there, paying close attention to the path. He walked slowly, however, so that his companion could keep up with him. Exhausted by his labors, aggravated by illness, and oppressed by the muggy air, Padre Cristoforo was struggling to walk, and kept raising his gaunt face to the sky as if to catch his breath. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n246" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14804" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14819">When Renzo saw the hut, he stopped, turned around, and in a trembling voice said, “We’re here.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n247" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14820" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14820">They went in. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n248" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14821" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14826">“They’ve come!” cried the woman from the cot. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n249" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14827" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14839">Lucia turned, leapt to her feet, and went toward the old man crying, “I can’t believe my eyes! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n250" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14840" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14842">Oh, Padre Cristoforo!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n251" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14843" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14851">“Ah, Lucia. The Lord has delivered you from so much torment! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n252" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14852" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14860">How glad you must be to have always placed your hopes in Him.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n253" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14861" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14862">“Oh, yes. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n254" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14863" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14865">But you, Padre? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n255" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14866" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14870">Goodness gracious, how you’ve changed! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n256" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14871" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14875">How are you feeling? Tell me: How are you?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n257" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14876" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14891">“As God wishes, and as, by His grace, I wish to be, too,” replied the friar serenely. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n258" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14892" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14906">Drawing her to the side, he added, “Listen. I only have a few minutes. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n259" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14907" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14916">Are you ready to confide in me, as you have other times?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n260" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14917" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14924">“You are still my father confessor, aren’t you?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n261" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14925" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14933">“So, my daughter, what is this Renzo tells me about a vow?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n262" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14934" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14949">“At a moment of great tribulation, I made a vow to the Virgin…to never marry.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n263" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14950" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14950">“Poor girl! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n264" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14951" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14959">But did you not remember that you were already bound by another vow?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n265" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14960" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14969">“No, I didn’t…but this was a vow to Our Lord, to the Blessed Virgin.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n266" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14970" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14981">“The Lord, my daughter, appreciates sacrifices, offerings, when they affect us alone. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n267" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_14982" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15003">When we make them from the heart, of our own free will. But you cannot offer up the free will of another, to whom you were already bound.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n268" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15004" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15006">“Was I wrong?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n269" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15007" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15033">“No, poor girl, that’s not what I’m saying. On the contrary, I am sure that the Blessed Virgin appreciated your tormented heart’s intention, and offered it to God on your behalf. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n270" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15034" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15045">But tell me, did you ever seek anyone’s advice on this matter?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n271" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15046" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15068">“I didn’t think I had done something wrong or that I needed to confess. And aren’t we supposed to keep quiet about the few good deeds we are able to do?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n272" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15069" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15085">“So there is nothing else preventing you from keeping your promise to Renzo?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n273" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15086" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15093">“I don’t know…something preventing me…? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n274" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15094" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15124">I couldn’t really say…” Lucia replied with a hesitation that indicated anything but uncertainty. Though her face was still pale from the illness, she suddenly turned bright red. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n275" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15125" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15164">“Do you believe,” the old man continued, lowering his eyes, “that God gave the Church the authority to remit or to retain the debts and obligations that people might have contracted with Him, depending on the greater good?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n276" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15165" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15168">“Yes, I do.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n277" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15169" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15216">“Then you should know that those of us entrusted with the care of the soul have the broadest powers of the Church for all who come to us. Therefore, should you request it, I can release you from any obligation, whatever it might be, that you might have contracted through your vow.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n278" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15217" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15228">“But isn’t it a sin to go back on, to repent a vow made to the Virgin? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n279" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15229" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15267">At the time I made it with all my heart…” said Lucia, shaken violently by the power of an unexpected feeling that I can only call hope, and by the opposing force of terror strengthened by all the thoughts over which she had for so long obsessed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n280" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15268" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15298">“A sin, my daughter?” said the friar. “A sin to turn to the Church, to ask its minister to use the authority the Church has given him, and that the Church has received from God? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n281" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15299" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15336">I have seen how the two of you were united. And if ever two people were united by God, it seemed to me that it was you. I do not see why God would want to keep you apart now. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n282" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15337" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15358">And I bless whoever it is that bestowed upon me the authority to speak on His behalf, however unworthy I may be, and allow you to take back your word. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n283" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15359" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15382">And if you ask me to release you from your vow, I will not hesitate to do so. And indeed I wish you would ask me.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n284" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15383" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15397">“Then…then…I’m asking you,” said Lucia, with a face now colored only by modesty. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n285" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15398" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15471">The friar gestured to the young man, who was in the far corner, observing intently (since that’s all he could do) a dialogue that would have a profound effect on him. When Renzo came closer, Padre Cristoforo said to Lucia in a loud voice, “With the authority granted to me by the Church, I hereby release you from your vow of chastity, annulling that which might have been unadvised in it, and freeing you of any obligation you may have contracted thereby.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n286" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15472" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15482">The reader can imagine how those words sounded to Renzo’s ears. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n287" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15483" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15500">His eyes shone with gratitude for the man who had uttered them, and he instantly tried, and failed, to catch the eyes of Lucia. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n288" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15501" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15541">“Return now, with peace and security, to your former concerns,” the Capuchin went on to say. “Ask the Lord once again for the grace to be a good wife. And trust that he will grant you that grace in even greater abundance, after all that you have suffered. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n289" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15542" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15604">And you,” he said, turning to Renzo, “remember, my son, that if the Church is offering you this companion, it is not to give you a temporal, earthly pleasure, which even if it could be whole and free of unhappiness, would still end in great sorrow the moment you leave each other. No, it is that the Church wishes to set you both on the road to eternal joy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n290" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15605" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15623">Love each other as fellow travelers, with the thought that one day you will have to leave each other, and the hope that you will meet again in eternity. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n291" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15624" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15654">Thank the heavens for leading you to this condition, not through turbulent and fleeting joy, but through troubles and miseries, to prepare you for a serene and peaceful joy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n292" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15655" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15684">If God should bless you with children, then try to raise them in His light, and instill in them the love of Him and of all humanity. And then guide them well in all else. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n293" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15685" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15694">Lucia, did he tell you”—and he pointed to Renzo—“who he saw here?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n294" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15695" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15699">“Oh, Padre, yes he did!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n295" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15700" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15703">“Pray for him! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n296" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15704" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15707">Never grow tired of doing so. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n297" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15708" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15712">And pray for me, too! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n298" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15713" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15721">My children! I want you to have something by which to remember this poor friar.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n299" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15722" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15764">At this he removed from his basket a box of ordinary wood, sanded and polished with Capuchin refinement. “This holds the remains of a crust of bread, the first piece of charity that I ever received. That bread you have heard me speak of before. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n300" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15765" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15775">I leave it with you. Conserve it. Show it to your children. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n301" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15776" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15808">They will grow up in a sad world and in sad times, surrounded by the proud and the irate. Tell them they must always forgive, and forgive everything. And that they, too, should pray for this poor friar.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n302" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15809" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15824">He handed the box to Lucia, who accepted it respectfully, as if it were a relic. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n303" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15825" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15838">Then, in a calmer voice, he asked, “Now tell me, who do you know in Milan? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n304" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15839" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15847">When you leave here, where will you stay? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n305" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15848" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15861">And who will take you to your mother, God bless and preserve her?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n306" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15862" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15882">“This good woman has been like a mother to me. The two of us will leave here together, and then she will take care of everything.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n307" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15883" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15891">“God bless her,” said the friar, coming next to the cot. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n308" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15892" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15919">“I wish to thank you, too,” said the widow, “for the joy you have brought to these poor children, although I had hoped to keep my dear Lucia with me always. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n309" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15920" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15942">But in the meantime, I will take care of her. I’ll accompany her to her village and bring her to her mother.” Then she added, in a whisper, “I want to provide for her trousseau. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n310" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15943" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15958">I have far too many things myself. And I don’t have anyone else to enjoy them with anymore.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n311" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15959" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15975">“In so doing,” replied the friar, “you will make a great sacrifice to the Lord, and for the good of your fellow man. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n312" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_15976" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16017">I have no need to recommend this girl to you. I already see that you treat her as if she were your own daughter. I can only praise the Lord, who is our father even in the midst of afflictions. By reuniting them, He has given a clear sign that He loves them both. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n313" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16018" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16043">Come now,” he then said, turning to Renzo and taking him by the hand, “there’s nothing left for the two of us to do here. We have already stayed too long. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n314" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16044" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16044">It’s time for us to go.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n315" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16045" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16051">“Oh, Padre!” said Lucia. “Will I see you again? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n316" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16052" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16066">I am better now, I, who has never done good in this world, while you…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n317" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16067" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16096">“For many years now,” replied the old man in a solemn and gentle voice, “I have been asking the Lord for a favor, and for one great favor: to end my days in service to my fellow man. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n318" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16097" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16115">If he wishes to grant it to me now, then everyone who bears some love for me must help me to thank him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n319" type="comm" status="insertion">It is time for us to go. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n320" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16116" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16125">Now give Renzo any messages you may have for your mother.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n321" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16126" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16156">“Tell her what you have seen,” said Lucia to her fiancé, “that I have found a second mother here, that I will come to her as soon as I can, and that I hope, I pray, to find her healthy.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n322" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16157" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16171">“If you need money,” said Renzo, “I have everything that you sent me, and…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n323" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16172" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16181">“No, no,” interrupted the widow, “I have more than enough.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n324" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16182" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16185">“Time for us to go,” repeated the friar. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n325" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16186" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16205">“Goodbye, Lucia…! And goodbye to you, too, kind woman,” said Renzo, unable to find the words to express his feelings. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n326" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16206" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16220">“Who knows whether the Lord will grant us the grace for us all to meet again!” exclaimed Lucia. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n327" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16221" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16240">“May He always be with you, and bless you,” Padre Cristoforo said to the two women, and he left the hut with Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n328" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16241" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16253">Night was falling and the storm was about to break. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n329" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16254" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16268">The Capuchin renewed his invitation to the young man to spend the night in his hut. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n330" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16269" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16281">“I may not be able to keep you company,” he added, “but at least you’ll have a roof over your head.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n331" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16282" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16319">Renzo was impatient to leave, however, and had no interest in staying there any longer if he could neither see Lucia nor pass some time with the good friar. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n332" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16320" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16345">The hour and weather did not matter to him; night and day, sun and rain, dawn and dusk, were all the same to him in that moment. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n333" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16346" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16361">So he thanked the friar, but said that he wanted to leave as soon as possible to go look for Agnese. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n334" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16362" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16409">When they reached the middle path, the friar shook his hand and said, “If—by the will of God—you do find the good Agnese, please send her my respects. And tell her, and all those who are still in Pescarenico, to remember Fra Cristoforo. Tell them to pray for him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n335" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16410" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16416">May God remain by your side, and always bless you!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n336" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16417" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16423">“Oh, dear Padre…! Will we meet again? Will we?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n337" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16424" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16425">“Up in heaven, I hope.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n338" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16426" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16467">With these words, he took his leave of Renzo. The young man stood there watching him until he disappeared from sight, then he walked quickly to the gate, and cast a last compassionate glance around that place of sorrow. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap36-n339" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16468" targetEnd="quarantana/cap36.xml#c36_16499">There was more movement than usual: monatti running, objects being carried, the entrances to huts being pulled shut, and convalescents shuffling to the huts and galleries, in search of shelter from the approaching storm. </note>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>