<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>2022</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed: a novel</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
          <date>2022</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Michael Moore</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="english_2022_cap35">
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10085">Reader, picture, if you will, the lazaretto: a cramped space populated by sixteen thousand plague victims, with huts and sheds here, carts there, and people everywhere; two endless fugues of porticos, to the right and the left, teeming, overflowing, with the dead and dying, all jumbled together, on pallets or straw, while a buzzing hovered over this seemingly endless shantytown. Here and there was a coming and going, a running and stopping, a bowing and standing up of the convalescent, the delirious, and the attendants. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10086" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10105">This was the sight that instantly greeted Renzo’s eyes and held them, transfixed and overwhelmed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10106" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10159">I will not attempt to describe this scene in detail, nor would the reader want me to. Following our young man on his woeful journey, we will stop where he stops, and describe enough of what he witnessed to relate what he did, and what followed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10160" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10224">A pathway cleared of huts and other constructions ran from where Renzo stood at the back entrance to the chapel in the middle, and from there, to the front entrance. Upon closer inspection, Renzo noticed carts moving along it, and things being removed to make space. He saw Capuchin friars and laymen directing the operation, while sending away anyone who didn’t belong there. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10225" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10250">Fearing that he, too, would be expelled, he slipped between the huts on the right, the direction in which he happened to turn. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10251" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10303">He continued his search from hut to hut, wherever he could set his foot, poking his head inside each one, peering at beds set up outside, studying the faces wracked with pain, contracting in spasms, or motionless in death, hoping to find the very thing he was afraid to find. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10304" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10335">He had already walked for a while, repeating his painful examination again and again, but without finding a single woman; so he wondered if they might be in a separate area. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10336" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10346">And he was right. But he had no idea where that area might be or how to find it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10347" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10392">Every now and then he ran into attendants, who were as different in appearance and dress as they were different if not opposite in the principle that gave both one and the other equal strength to perform their duties: the extinction of all compassion in one; superhuman compassion in the other. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10393" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10421">He did not feel comfortable asking questions of either, however, to avoid running into obstacles. So he decided to continue on and try to find the women himself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10422" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10446">As he walked, he often had to glance away from what he saw around him, nearly blinded by the sight of so much suffering. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10447" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10455">But where could he look, where could he rest his eyes, if not on more suffering? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10456" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10470">The very air and sky compounded the horror of those sights, if anything indeed could. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10471" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10531">A dense, dark fog had rolled in, making the day feel more like a stormy night. But in the center of the low, gloomy sky, the sphere of the sun broke through faintly, as if piercing a heavy veil, flickering as it radiated its heavy dead heat. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10532" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10575">Every now and then, amid the steady drone of the jumbled multitude, a deep rumbling of thunder could be heard that seemed interrupted, hesitant. Even if you listened carefully, you could not tell where it was coming from; you might have thought it was the distant sound of carts that had screeched to a sudden halt. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10576" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10626">In the surrounding countryside not a branch moved, not a bird alit or took flight: Only the swallow, appearing suddenly on the roof of the lazaretto, swooped down with its wings outstretched, as if to rake the yard. Alarmed by the commotion, however, it quickly soared back up and away. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10627" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10704">This was the type of weather when, among a company of travelers, no one breaks the silence; the hunter stares at the ground as he walks, lost in thought; the peasant woman tilling the soil stops singing, unawares; the type of weather portending a storm, when nature—as if outwardly still while agitated by an inner distress—seems to oppress every living thing and bear down on every action, on leisure, on life itself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10705" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10766">But in that place designed for suffering and death, men who were already in the grips of disease could be seen succumbing to this new oppression. In the final throes of the disease, the pain became more excruciating, the moans grew more strangled, as hundreds and hundreds suddenly got worse. A crueler hour, perhaps, had not yet visited this place of misery. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10767" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10819">The young man had already been walking for a while through that labyrinth of huts, in vain, when he began to discern a singular mix of wailing and bleating among the various laments, until he reached a splintered, rickety stockade from where that peculiar sound seemed to be coming. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10820" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10899">He placed his eye against a wide crack between two boards and spotted a fenced-off area with a smattering of huts. There he saw an infirmary, or rather babies lying on little mattresses, pillows, unfolded sheets, or quilts, while wet nurses and other women fussed over them. What most drew and held his gaze were the goats that mingled about, acting as the nurses’ helpers: a hospital for the innocents, as best could be afforded by that time and place. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10900" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10955">It was, I was saying, quite a sight to see these animals stand calmly over one baby and then another, offering their udders, or trot over to the sound of wailing, with an almost maternal instinct, and stop next to and try to position themselves above the little nursling, bleating and wagging their tails as if calling for someone to help the two of them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10956" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_10999">Wet nurses were sitting here and there with babies held against their breasts, some so lovingly as to make the observer wonder whether they had been drawn there by the pay or by the charity that spontaneously seeks out the needy and the afflicted. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11000" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11024">One woman, crestfallen, removed a crying infant from her weary breast and went sadly in search of an animal to take her place. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11025" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11050">Another gazed tenderly at the little one who had fallen asleep on her breast, and, kissing it gently, went into a hut to lay it down on a little mattress. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11051" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11104">But a third, surrendering her breast to a little stranger, stared at the sky not with an air of indifference but of distraction. What was she thinking, through that gesture, through that expression on her face, if not of a child of her own womb who had perhaps suckled on her breast not very long ago, and perhaps died upon it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11105" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11112">Older women attended to other chores. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11113" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11151">One ran to pick up a crying baby and carry it to a goat that was grazing on a pile of fresh grass. She placed the baby on the udder, scolding and patting the inexperienced animal until it meekly acquiesced to the task. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11152" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11198">One woman ran to rescue a poor infant that had been trampled by a goat that was busy nursing another baby. A third woman rocked a child back and forth in her arms, singing a lullaby, trying to coo it to sleep with songs and soft words, calling it by a name she had given the baby herself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11199" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11245">A Capuchin with a snow-white beard arrived carrying two shrieking babies, one in each arm, whom he had found lying next to their deceased mothers. A woman ran to take them and immediately looked around the group of women and animals to see who could take their mothers’ places. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11246" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11280">Renzo tried to look away more than once, driven by his primary, predominant concern, only to go back and peer through the opening for a little while longer. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11281" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11300">Finally, he pulled himself away and walked along the fence until he came upon a cluster of huts that blocked his path and forced him to turn around. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11301" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11321">He went between the huts to try to find the fence again, so that he could follow it to the end and discover a new country. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11322" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11342">While he was looking ahead, trying to figure out a path, a sudden, fleeting, momentary apparition caught his eye and made his heart stop. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11343" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11381">A hundred yards ahead, he saw a Capuchin friar pass by and immediately disappear between the huts: a Capuchin who, even from this distance and at a glance, had the same gait, demeanor, and shape as Fra Cristoforo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11382" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11463">With all the agitation you can imagine, Renzo ran in the man’s direction. He searched the labyrinth of huts, up and down, inside and out, until, with a joy that matched his agitation, he spotted again that same form, that same friar, just ahead of him, stepping away from a kettle and walking toward a hut with a bowl in his hand. Renzo saw him sit down in the doorway and make the sign of the cross over the bowl. Then, after casting his gaze around like a man who is always alert, he started to eat. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11464" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11468">It was indeed Padre Cristoforo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11469" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11487">To tell his story from the moment we lost sight of him until this encounter will only take a couple of words. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11488" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11524">He did not leave Rimini, nor had he considered doing so, until the breakout of the plague in Milan gave him the opportunity to do something he had always wanted to do: sacrifice his life for his fellow man. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11525" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11535">He pleaded insistently to be recalled from his current posting so he could attend to and serve the plague-stricken. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11536" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11555">Since the man who had forced his transfer, the Count Uncle, was dead, not to mention the greater need for nurses than politicians, his request was granted without objection. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11556" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11568">He came to Milan immediately, entered the lazaretto, and had already been there for about three months. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11569" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11594">Renzo’s relief at finding the good friar did not last long, however, for in the very moment that he verified it was him, he could not help but notice how much he had changed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11595" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11628">His posture was stooped and stiff, his face gaunt and pale. He seemed utterly exhausted, his flesh broken and failing, as if the only thing holding him up was sheer willpower. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11629" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11656">He stared at the young man who was coming toward him, who was using gestures to stand out and be recognized, since he dared not speak. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11657" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11673">“Oh, Padre Cristoforo!” Renzo said, when he was close enough to be heard without raising his voice. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11674" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11687">“You? Here?” asked the friar, placing his bowl on the ground and standing up. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11688" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11692">“How are you, Padre? How are you feeling?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11693" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11715">“Better than many of the poor souls you see here,” answered the friar. His voice was faint, somber, altered like every other aspect of him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11716" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11765">Only his eyes were the same as before, if not even brighter and livelier. It was as if charity, sublimated by this extreme sacrifice, and rejoicing to feel so close to its maker, had given him a purer and more ardent flame than the one that his illness was slowly extinguishing. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11766" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11778">“But you,” he continued, “how is it that you’re here? Why have you come to face the plague like this?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11779" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11783">“I’ve already had it, thank heavens. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11784" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11788">I’ve come looking for…Lucia.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11789" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11792">“Lucia? Is Lucia here?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11793" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11802">“She is. At least I hope to God that she still is.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11803" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11805">“Is she your wife now?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11806" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11814">“Oh, dear Padre! No, she’s not my wife. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11815" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11823">You know nothing about what happened to us?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11824" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11853">“No, my son. Ever since God separated me from you, I haven’t heard anything. But now that He has sent you to me, I really would like to know. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11854" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11857">But…I thought you’d been banished?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11858" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11865">“So, you do know the things they did to me.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11866" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11870">“But you, what did you do?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11871" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11891">“Well, if I said that I showed good judgment that day in Milan, I would be lying, but I did not do anything wrong.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11892" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11899">“I believe you now, and I did before.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11900" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11905">“Then I can tell you everything.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11906" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11919">“Wait,” said the friar, and taking a few steps outside the hut, he called, “Padre Vittore!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11920" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11956">A few seconds later a young Capuchin appeared, whom he asked, “Can you do me a favor, Padre, and keep an eye on these poor children while I step out for a second? If anyone asks for me, please let me know. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11957" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11974">Especially that one over there! If he shows even the smallest sign of reviving, come fetch me immediately, please.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11975" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11989">“Don’t worry, I will,” replied the young man. And the older man, turning to Renzo, said, “let’s go in here. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_11990" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12003">But,” he added immediately, stopping, “you look tired to me: I’m sure you need something to eat.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12004" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12020">“You’re right,” said Renzo, “now that you mention it, I realize I haven’t eaten all day.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12021" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12090">“Just a minute,” said the friar. He fetched another bowl and went to the kettle to fill it. He came back and handed it to Renzo together with a spoon. He invited the boy to sit down on the pallet that served as his bed. Then he went to a cask in the corner, drew a glass of wine, and placed it on the little table in front of his guest. Finally, he picked up his own bowl and sat down next to him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12091" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12102">“Oh, Padre Cristoforo!” Renzo said, “You didn’t have to go to such trouble. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12103" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12109">You are still the same kind man. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12110" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12114">I thank you with all my heart.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12115" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12133">“Don’t thank me,” said the friar, “this is food for the poor. But today you are one of them, too. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12134" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12159">Now tell me everything I don’t know. Tell me about our poor little girl, and try to be quick about it. We haven’t got much time, and we have a lot to do, as you can see.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12160" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12228">Between one spoonful and the next, Renzo started to tell the story of Lucia, how she had taken refuge at the convent in Monza, and how she had been abducted…At the picture of such suffering and such danger, at the thought that he had been the one to direct the poor innocent creature to that place, the good friar gasped. But he started to breathe easier as he listened to the amazing story of how she had been freed and returned to her mother, who had found her a situation with Donna Prassede. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12229" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12278">“Now I’ll tell you about me,” continued Renzo. And he spoke very briefly about that day in Milan, the escape, and how he had been forced to live far from Pescarenico, and then how, with the world turned upside down, he decided to take the risk and come back home. How Agnese had not been there, and how in Milan he had learned that Lucia was at the lazaretto. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12279" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12299">“And here I am,” he concluded, “I’m here to look for her, to see if she’s alive, and if…she still wants me…because…sometimes…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12300" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12314">“But do you have any clue where they’ve put her?” asked the friar, “Or when she arrived?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12315" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12330">“No, Padre. I know nothing except that she’s here, if she is still here, I pray to God!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12331" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12340">“You poor boy! Where have you looked so far?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12341" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12356">“I’ve gone around and around, but so far, I’ve only seen men. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12357" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12383">I figured the women must be in a separate area, but I’ve never managed to get there. If that’s true, can you show me where it is?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12384" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12398">“Don’t you know, my child, that men aren’t allowed in unless they have a job there?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12399" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12403">“Well, what would happen to me if I went there anyway?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12404" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12440">“The rules are fair and sacrosanct, my son. And even though the number and gravity of the problems make it difficult to observe them strictly, it still doesn’t mean that an honest man should disobey them.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12441" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12478">“But, Padre Cristoforo,” said Renzo, “Lucia should have been my wife. You know how we were separated. For twenty months now I’ve suffered, and I’m a patient man. I’ve come this far, taking many risks, each one worse than the last, and now…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12479" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12523">“I don’t know what to say,” continued the friar, responding more to his own thoughts than to Renzo’s words. “You clearly have the best intentions, and God would be pleased if everyone who enters that area behaved as I trust you will. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12524" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12570">That same God certainly blesses you for how you have persevered in your love, and how faithful you have been in your desire and search for the woman whom He has destined for you. God is stricter than any man, but also more indulgent, and I believe He will forgive you for the unusual methods you have to use to find her. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12571" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12594">Just remember that both you and I will have to answer for how you behave once you get there: answer not so much to men, but certainly to God. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12595" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12596">Come.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12597" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12648">At this he stood, and so did Renzo. The boy heeded his words, but he had also decided, in the meantime, to abandon his earlier plan to bring up Lucia’s vow. “If he hears that, too,” he thought, “he’ll definitely make things harder for me. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12649" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12663">Either I find her, and we’ll have time to talk about it later. Or…and in that case, what will it matter?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12664" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12698">As they walked to the door of the hut, which faced north, the friar continued, “Listen carefully. Padre Felice, the president of the lazaretto, is taking the few people who have recovered to finish their quarantine somewhere else. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12699" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12748">Do you see the church there in the middle…?” Raising his shaky, bony hand, he pointed left, through the murky air, at the dome of the chapel, which towered over the miserable tents. “They will be assembling there now, and then leaving in a procession by the same gate through which you must have entered.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12749" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12759">“Ah! So that’s why they were clearing the path.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12760" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12772">“Yes. And you must have also heard the bell ring?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12773" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12775">“I heard it ring once.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12776" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12796">“That was the second bell. By the time the third bell rings, everyone will have gathered. Padre Felice will make a short speech, and then they will head out with him. At the third bell, join them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12797" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12830">Try to slip behind the crowd and stand to one side of the path where you can watch them pass without disturbing anyone or being noticed. And you can see…you can see…if she is among them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12831" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12871">If God did not wish for her to be among them, then”—and he raised his hand again, pointing to the side of the building opposite them—“over there, that part of the building and some of the yard in front is assigned to women. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12872" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12894">You’ll see a fence dividing this section from that, but in some places there are gaps or openings, so it won’t be hard for you to slip through. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12895" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12912">Once you’re inside, if you don’t do anything to arouse suspicion, it’s likely no one will speak to you. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12913" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12933">But if you do run into any obstacle, just say that Padre Cristoforo from *** knows you and will answer for you. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12934" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12941">Look for her there. Look for her with faith and…resignation. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12942" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12962">Because, remember, you have come here searching for no small thing: You are looking for a living person in the lazaretto! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12963" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12983">Do you know how often I’ve seen my poor charges replaced by newcomers? How many I’ve seen carried away? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12984" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12989">How few have walked away on their own two feet?…Prepare yourself to make a sacrifice…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_12990" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13003">“Yes, I understand,” Renzo interrupted, his eyes clouding over and his expression changing. “I understand! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13004" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13027">I’m going: I’ll look, I’ll search in one place, then another, through the whole lazaretto, high and low…and if I don’t find her…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13028" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13046">“If you don’t find her?” asked the friar with a solemn, expectant air, and a look of warning. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13047" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13076">That suggestion of doubt rekindled Renzo’s anger and extinguished the light in his eyes. “If I don’t find her, then there’s someone else I will try to find. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13077" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13126">Whether in Milan, in his evil palace, at the ends of the earth, or in the devil’s lair, I’ll find the rat who tore us apart! If it hadn’t been for that scoundrel, then Lucia would have been my wife these twenty months. And if it had been our destiny to die, then at least we would have died together. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13127" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13132">If he’s still alive, I’ll find him…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13133" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13145">“Renzo!” said the friar, grabbing him by the arm and giving him a severe look. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13146" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13201">“And if I find him,” Renzo went on, blinded by rage, “if the plague hasn’t already brought him to justice…The days are long past when a ne’er-do-well, guarded by his bravi, can drive people to despair and laugh it off. The time has come for men to meet face-to-face. And…I’ll take justice into my own hands!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13202" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13245">“Shame on you!” thundered Padre Cristoforo, his voice regaining all its former power and sound. “Shame on you!” His head rose up from his chest and his cheeks colored with their former vitality. The fire in his eyes was terrifying. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13246" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13247">“Look around you!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13248" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13273">With one hand, he grabbed Renzo’s arm and forcefully shook it, while sweeping the other over the vast scene of pain and suffering before them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13274" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13279">“Look around you! It is He who castigates! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13280" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13286">He who judges but shall not be judged! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13287" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13292">Who punishes and forgives! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13293" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13301">But you, you worm crawling on the earth, you would take justice into your own hands? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13302" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13309">Do you even know what justice is? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13310" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13312">Go, you disgrace, leave this place! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13313" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13355">I had hoped…yes, I had hoped that before I die, God would have given me the consolation of hearing that my poor Lucia was alive. To perhaps see her, and hear her promise that she would say a prayer for me, over there, by the common grave where I will soon be buried. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13356" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13362">But now you have robbed me of that hope. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13363" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13384">God did not leave her on this earth for you. And clearly you do not have the audacity to think yourself worthy of God’s consolation. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13385" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13401">But He will have thought of her, because she is one of those souls for whom eternal consolation is reserved. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13402" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13409">Go now, I have no more time to waste on you.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13410" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13426">At this he pushed Renzo’s arm away and started to head toward one of the huts of the sick. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13427" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13442">“Padre!” Renzo said, chasing after him with an imploring gesture. “Would you send me away like this?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13443" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13451">“What!” the Capuchin replied in an equally stern voice. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13452" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13484">“Do you dare expect me to take time away from the afflicted, who are waiting for me to speak to them of God’s forgiveness, to listen to your words of rage, your plans for revenge? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13485" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13513">I listened to you when you asked for consolation and help, and for the sake of charity I interrupted my charitable work. But now you are set on revenge, so what do you want from me? Go. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13514" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13548">I have seen victims die here with words of forgiveness on their lips. And I have seen persecutors who grieved that they could not beg their victims for forgiveness. I have wept with both. But what shall I do with you?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13549" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13561">“I forgive him! I really do forgive him! I forgive him for all time!” exclaimed the youth. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13562" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13580">“Renzo,” the friar said in a grave but calmer voice, “think for a minute, and tell me how many times you have forgiven him.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13581" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13605">Minutes went by without an answer. Padre Cristoforo suddenly lowered his head, and in a slow somber voice, continued what he had been saying, “You know the reason I donned this habit.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13606" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13607">Renzo hesitated. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13608" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13613">“You know!” the old man repeated. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13614" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13617">“I know,” replied Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13618" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13642">“I, too, have hated. I, who reprimanded you for a thought, for a word, when the man whom I hated with all my heart, whom I hated for so long, is a man whom I murdered.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13643" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13649">“Yes, but he was a bully, one of those…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13650" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13668">“Silence!” the friar interrupted him. “If there had been a good reason, do you really think I would have spent thirty years trying to find it? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13669" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13690">Ah, if I could only make you feel in your heart what I have felt ever since that day, and still feel today, for the man whom I hated! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13691" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13700">If only I could! Perhaps I cannot, but God can: I pray that He will do it!…Listen, Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13701" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13741">He loves you better than you love yourself. You might have plotted your revenge, but He has the strength and the mercy to prevent you from carrying it out. He is granting you the grace that someone else did not deserve. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13742" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13764">You know, and you have said many times, that He can stay the hand of a bully. But He can also stay the hand of an avenger. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13765" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13788">Do you think that because you are poor, because you are offended, He cannot defend you from a man created in His own image? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13789" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13798">Do you really think He will allow you to do whatever you want? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13799" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13805">No! But do you know what you can do? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13806" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13819">You can hate, and be lost. You can, by embracing one feeling, cast yourself beyond the blessing of God. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13820" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13853">Because no matter what happens, no matter what fortune may hold for you, you can be sure that punishment certainly lies ahead, until your forgiveness is so true that you will never again have to say, ‘I forgive him.’ ” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13854" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13893">“Yes, yes,” said Renzo, overcome by emotion, by confusion. “I know now that I never really have forgiven him. I know now that I have spoken like an animal and not a Christian. And now, by the grace of our Lord, yes, I forgive him with all my heart.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13894" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13898">“And if you were to see him?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13899" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13913">“I would pray to God to give me patience and to touch his heart.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13914" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13931">“Would you remember that God did not tell us to forgive our enemies, but to love them? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13932" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13943">Would you remember that He loved him so much that He died for him?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13944" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13947">“Yes, with your help I would.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13948" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13951">“Good, then come with me. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13952" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13957">You said, ‘I’ll find him,’ and you will. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13958" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13982">Come, and you’ll see the man you so hated, whom you could and would have harmed, whose life you wanted to take.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13983" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_13999">Taking Renzo’s hand, and gripping it as firmly as a healthy young man, he started on his way. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14000" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14008">And Renzo followed, afraid to ask anything more. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14009" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14038">After a few steps, the friar stopped near the opening of a hut, stared at Renzo with a mix of gravity and tenderness, and led him inside. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14039" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14091">The first thing Renzo saw as he entered was a sick man sitting on a pile of straw; a man who was not gravely ill, and who indeed appeared to be on the verge of recovery. When the man saw Padre Cristoforo, he shook his head, as if to say no. The friar lowered his head with sadness and resignation. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14092" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14171">Renzo, in the meantime, was looking around with restless curiosity, when he noticed three or four sick men, one of whom was on a mattress off to the side, wrapped in a bedsheet, and using a nobleman’s cloak as a blanket. He stared at him more closely. It was Don Rodrigo. Renzo took a step back, but with a firm grip the friar drew him to the edge of that dirty heap and, with his other hand, pointed at the man lying on top of it. There lay the unhappy man, unresponsive. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14172" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14210">His eyes were wide open but vacant, his face pale and covered with black lesions, his lips black and swollen. You would have thought it was the face of a corpse, but every so often, his body would convulse violently, revealing the stubborn life still inside. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14211" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14244">His chest lifted every so often in labored breathing. His right hand, uncovered, was pressed to his heart; his fingers, covered with lesions and black at the tips, curled inward like a claw. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14245" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14254">“Do you see!” said the friar in a soft and solemn voice. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14255" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14260">“It may be punishment, or it may be mercy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14261" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14288">What you feel now for this man who offended you is the same feeling that God—whom you, too, have offended—will have for you on the day of judgment. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14289" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14292">Bless him, and you shall be blessed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14293" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14306">He has been like this for four days, showing no signs of life. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14307" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14347">Perhaps God is ready to grant him his hour of absolution, but He wanted to hear you pray for it. Perhaps He wants both you and that innocent girl to pray for it. Or perhaps He is withholding grace until He hears your prayer, the prayer of a heart that is afflicted and resigned. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14348" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14368">Perhaps both this man’s salvation and your own depend on your capacity for forgiveness, for compassion…for love!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14369" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14385">He fell silent and, joining his hands together, bowed his head and prayed. Renzo did the same. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14386" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14396">They had been in this posture for a few moments when the bell started tolling. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14397" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14405">Both friar and youth moved, as if in concert, and went out. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14406" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14416">One of them asked no questions. The other made no protests. Their faces spoke for them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14417" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14442">“Go now,” said the friar, “go prepared to receive grace or to make a sacrifice. To praise God whatever the outcome of your search may be. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14443" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14453">And whatever it may be, come to inform me, and we will praise him together.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap35-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14454" targetEnd="quarantana/cap35.xml#c35_14475">Without another word, they separated. One went back inside. The other headed to the chapel, which was no more than a hundred yards away. </note>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>