<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>2022</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed: a novel</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
          <date>2022</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Michael Moore</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="english_2022_cap38">
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10021">One evening Agnese heard a carriage stop outside the door. “It must be her!” And yes, it was, together with the good widow. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10022" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10028">Can you imagine their joyful embraces? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10029" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10054">Early the next morning, Renzo stopped by, unaware of her arrival. He was making his usual visit to complain to Agnese about Lucia’s long delay. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10055" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10073">The things he did and the things he said when he found her right before his eyes I will also leave to your imagination. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10074" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10088">Lucia’s expressions, however, require no such effort. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10089" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10099">“Good morning. How are you?” she said, eyes lowered, without losing her composure. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10100" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10114">And don’t go thinking that Renzo found her manner too distant, or that he took it badly. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10115" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10151">He took it in the spirit with which it was offered. Just as polite people know the value of understatement, he could see clearly that those words did not express everything that was in Lucia’s heart. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10152" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10174">Besides, it was easy to see that she had two ways of saying them: one for Renzo, and another for all the people she might know. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10175" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10194">“I’m fine every time I see you,” the young man replied with an old expression that he could have invented in that moment. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10195" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10219">“Poor Padre Cristoforo!” said Lucia. “We must pray for his soul, although we can be almost sure that he is praying for us in heaven.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10220" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10225">“I was expecting it, unfortunately,” Renzo replied. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10226" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10239">And this was not the only sad note that was sounded in that conversation. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10253" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10318">Renzo was like a skittish horse that digs in its heels and rears first one hoof and then the other, always planting them back in the same place, and goes through a thousand motions before taking a step and then suddenly takes off at a gallop, as if driven by the wind: This is what time had become for Renzo. First the minutes seemed like hours, and then the hours seemed like minutes. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10319" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10353">Not only did the widow not spoil the company: She fit in quite nicely. And certainly Renzo, when he saw her lying on that cot, could never have imagined that she would have such a sociable and jovial disposition. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10354" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10367">But the lazaretto and the countryside, death and marriage, are not one and the same. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10368" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10409">With Agnese she had already formed a friendship. With Lucia there was the pleasure of seeing her, both tender and playful, and how she gently teased her, never too much, just enough to make the girl show all the joy she had in her heart. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10410" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10424">Finally, Renzo decided he would go to see Don Abbondio to make arrangements for the wedding. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10425" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10455">When he arrived, he joked, but in a deferential manner. “Father,” he said, “have you recovered from the headache that kept you from marrying us back then? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10456" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10481">The time is right. The bride is here. And I’ve come by to find out when you would be available. But this time around, I’m asking you to make it quick.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10482" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10526">Don Abbondio did not say no, but he started to hem and haw, making excuses and imagining other scenarios. Should he really call out Renzo’s name in a public square, with that warrant out for his arrest? Why not do the wedding someplace else? And so on and so forth. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10527" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10540">“I see,” said Renzo. “It seems you still have that headache. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10541" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10543">But hear me out.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10544" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10565">And he started to describe the state in which he had seen poor Don Rodrigo, who had surely departed the world by then. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10566" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10574">“Let’s hope,” he concluded, “that God has been merciful to him.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10575" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10588">“He’s got nothing to do with it,” said Don Abbondio, “did you hear me say no? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10589" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10599">I’m not saying no. I’m saying…I’ve got my reasons, good reasons. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10600" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10606">But if there’s a chance he’s still breathing…Look at me: a shell of a man. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10607" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10640">I had one foot in the grave. But I’m still here. And if trouble steers clear of me…Well, I hope to be around for a little while longer. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10641" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10654">But with a temper like his…Well, anyway, as I was saying, he’s got nothing to do with it.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10655" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10703">After a little more back and forth, equally inconclusive, Renzo performed a deep bow, returned to his group, delivered his report, and concluded, “I came back here since it was all I could do to keep from blowing my top and saying something I might regret. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10704" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10734">There were moments when he acted just like the last time: the same scowl, the same arguments. If we’d gone on any longer, I’m sure he would have trotted out a few words in Latin, too. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10735" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10754">I can tell he’s still dragging his feet. Maybe we should just do what he suggests, and get married where we’re going to live.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10755" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10776">“Do you know what we’re going to do?” piped up the widow. “I think just us women should give it a try, to see if we can do any better. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10777" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10789">That way I, too, will have the pleasure of meeting this man, if he is indeed as you say. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10790" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10801">We should wait until after lunch, so we don’t go back on the attack so soon. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10802" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10856">Now, Mr. Bridegroom, take the two of us for a walk, while Agnese is busy with lunch. I’ll play the part of Lucia’s mother. I want to get a good look at these mountains and the lake, which I’ve heard so much about. From the little I’ve seen, they seem quite magnificent.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10857" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10891">Renzo took them to his friend’s house, where another joyful welcome awaited. They made him promise he would come and have supper with him, not just that day, but every day, if he was able. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10892" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10899">After the walk and lunch, Renzo left without saying where he was going. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10900" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10918">The three women lingered for a bit, trying to decide how they would handle Don Abbondio, and finally they came up with a plan of attack. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10919" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10941">“Here they are,” the priest said to himself, but he put on a happy face. He relayed his congratulations to Lucia, his regards to Agnese, and his compliments to the foreigner. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10942" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10998">He invited them to have a seat and then immediately launched into a disquisition on the plague. He wanted to hear from Lucia how she had managed to survive the troubles. When she mentioned the lazaretto, her companion also took the opportunity to speak. Then Don Abbondio spoke about his own tribulations, as was only fair. He then congratulated Agnese for making it through unscathed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_10999" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11031">The conversation went on like this for a while. The women waited for an opening to get to the heart of the matter. Finally, one of the two—I don’t know which—broke the ice and brought up the marriage once again. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11032" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11034">Well, what were you expecting? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11035" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11040">Don Abbondio was deaf in that ear. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11041" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11060">It’s not that he said no. But he continued to hem and haw, jumping from one topic to another. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11061" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11067">“What we need to do,” he said, “is get that warrant for his arrest lifted. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11068" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11097">You, Signora, you’re from Milan: You must know how to pull strings. I’m sure you have some connections, maybe a nobleman with a little clout? Friends like that can heal every wound. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11098" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11150">And then there’s a shortcut you can take, which doesn’t require as much trouble. Since these two young people, and our Agnese here, already intend to move to another state (home is where the heart is, after all), they could just get married there, where the warrant isn’t valid. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11151" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11165">I can’t wait to see these two joined in marriage, and I want them to be joined properly, peacefully. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11166" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11197">I’m being honest. But here, with that warrant looming over us, I could not proclaim the name of Lorenzo Tramaglino from the altar, I just couldn’t do it and preserve my peace of mind. I care too much about him. I’d be afraid to do him a disservice. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11198" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11202">I’m sure you can understand. I’m sure all three of you can.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11203" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11245">At this, Agnese and the widow began to dispute his arguments. Don Abbondio trotted them out again, in another form, but they always ended up right where they had started until Renzo arrived, with a spring in his step and good news on his face. “The Marquis *** has arrived,” he said. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11246" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11255">“What do you mean? Arrived where?” asked Don Abbondio, standing up. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11256" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11280">“He’s arrived at the palace that once belonged to Don Rodrigo. The Marquis is the legal heir, by fideicommissum, by entail, as they say. So there should be no more doubts. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11281" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11294">For me, I’d be happy just to know that the poor man died a good death. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11295" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11311">Well, I’ve been saying a few Our Fathers for him anyway. Now I’ll say the ‘De profundis.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11312" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11318">And this Marquis is a good man.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11319" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11339">“I’m sure he is,” said Don Abbondio, “I’ve heard more than one person vouch for him, saying he’s a man of the old school. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11340" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11344">But is it really true?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11345" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11348">“Would you believe the sacristan?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11349" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11349">“Why do you ask?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11350" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11356">“Because he’s seen him with his own eyes. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11357" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11380">I was in the area, only because I was thinking, ‘They must know something there.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11381" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11387">And more than one person told me the same thing. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11388" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11405">Then I ran into Ambrogio, who was coming from that very place, and, as I was saying, he saw the Marquis taking possession of the palace. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11406" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11409">Would you like to hear from Ambrogio? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11410" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11415">I made him wait outside so you could hear from him yourself.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11416" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11419">“Show him in,” said Don Abbondio. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11420" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11446">Renzo went to summon the sacristan, who confirmed everything that Renzo had said, added some more details, and eliminated the remaining doubts. Then he left. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11447" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11456">“So he’s dead! Gone for good!” exclaimed Don Abbondio. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11457" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11466">“You see, my children, Providence still finds its way to certain people in the end. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11467" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11487">What wonderful news! What a relief for this poor village of ours! We couldn’t breathe with that man around. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11488" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11535">It was quite a scourge, this plague. But it was also a giant broom: It swept away people we’d have never been able to get rid of otherwise, my children, for they were young, fresh, and strong. Let’s face it: The priests who would have presided over their funerals one day were still seminarians. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11536" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11546">And now, in the blink of an eye they’re gone, hundreds in one swoop. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11547" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11582">We won’t be seeing the likes of him wandering about anymore, thugs in tow, with his arrogance, his airs, his self-importance, ramrod straight, staring people up and down as if they were only alive by his dispensation. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11583" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11591">Lo and behold, he is gone and we’re still here. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11592" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11598">He’ll no longer be sending his messengers around to harass honest men. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11599" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11612">He was nothing but trouble for everybody, and now we can finally say it out loud.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11613" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11620">“I forgave him with all my heart,” said Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11621" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11639">“As well you should have,” replied Don Abbondio, “but you can also thank the heavens for delivering us from him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11640" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11651">Now, getting back to us, let me repeat myself. You can all do what you think best. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11652" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11670">If you want me to perform the marriage, I’m here. If you think another way would be easier, do as you like. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11671" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11715">As for the warrant, I no longer think it’s a cause for concern. Especially since, in the meantime, a general amnesty has been issued to celebrate the birth of the Most Serene Infante. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11716" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11731">And then there’s the plague! The plague! It wiped out so many things! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11732" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11764">So, if you like…today is Thursday? On Sunday, I’ll announce your marriage banns in church, since the old ones don’t count anymore, after so much time. And then I’ll be happy to perform the ceremony myself.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11765" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11774">“You know perfectly well that’s why we came,” said Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11775" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11787">“Fine. I am at your service. And I wish to inform His Eminence right away.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11788" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11793">“Who is His Eminence?” asked Agnese. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11794" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11806">“His Eminence,” replied Don Abbondio, “is our Cardinal-Archbishop, may God preserve him.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11807" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11872">“Oh! Begging your pardon,” interjected Agnese, “but, though I may be a poor ignorant woman, I can assure you that’s not his title. When we spoke to him the second time, the same way I’m speaking to you now, one of the priests took me aside and taught me the right way to address the Cardinal. You’re supposed to say your most illustrious Lordship, and Monsignor.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11873" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11912">“Well, if he were here today, he’d teach you to call him Your Eminence, have I made myself clear? Because as of June, the Pope—may God preserve him, too—has ordered that cardinals should be given this title. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11913" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11920">And do you know why he came to this decision? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11921" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11947">Because ‘most illustrious Lordship’ was once reserved only for these godly men, and certain princes…well, even you can see what that title’s turned into nowadays, and how many people claim it. And how happily they lap it up! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11948" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11953">So what was the Pope supposed to do? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11954" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11956">Take it away from everyone? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11957" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11967">Then there’d be complaints, appeals, unpleasantness, trouble. And nothing would change. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11968" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11973">So he found an excellent solution. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_11974" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12007">Little by little, we’ll start to call bishops ‘Your Eminence.’ Then the abbots will want it. Then the provosts. Because that’s the way men are, always wanting to climb higher and higher. Then the canons…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12008" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12013">“And then the parish priests,” added the widow. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12014" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12040">“No, no,” Don Abbondio continued, “the parish priests still have to pull the weight. No need to worry that they’ll take on these bad habits. It’ll be ‘Reverend’ from now until doomsday. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12041" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12068">But I wouldn’t be surprised if the nobility, who are used to being called ‘Most Illustrious,’ just like cardinals, will want to be called ‘Your Eminence’ themselves. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12069" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12077">And if that’s what they want, that’s what they’ll get. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12078" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12092">And then, whoever the pope is by then will have to figure out a new title for cardinals. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12093" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12110">“Now let’s get back to our business. So, on Sunday I’ll read your banns in church. In the meantime, do you know what I thought would help? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12111" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12118">We’ll apply for a dispensation for two more couples. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12119" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12138">If things are happening in the curia the way they’re happening here, they’re pretty busy giving dispensations. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12139" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12155">On Sunday I already have…one…two…three marriage banns, not counting yours. And there might be more to come. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12156" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12170">And then you’ll see how much busier it’s going to get. No one wants to be single anymore. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12171" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12189">Perpetua couldn’t have picked a worse time to die. Even she would have found a suitor nowadays. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12190" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12199">And I imagine things are the same in Milan, Signora.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12200" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12211">“They certainly are. Can you believe that fifty marriage banns were read last Sunday in my parish alone!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12212" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12219">“Let me just say it: The world isn’t ready to end just yet. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12220" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12230">And you don’t have any bees buzzing around you, Signora?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12231" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12240">“No, no. I haven’t given it a single thought, nor would I want to.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12241" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12247">“Yes, I see, you prefer to be alone. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12248" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12252">Even Agnese, look. Even Agnese…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12253" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12260">“Huh? You must be kidding.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12261" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12273">“Of course I’m kidding, and it’s about time we could! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12274" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12305">We’ve been through some awful moments, haven’t we, my children? Really awful. Let’s hope these four days we still have left to live in this world will be a little better. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12306" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12355">But lucky you! If no catastrophes happen, you have your whole lives ahead of you to talk about the troubles of the past. But my clock is close to midnight and, well, scoundrels can die, plague victims can recover, but there’s no cure for old age. As the saying goes, senectus ipsa est morbus—old age itself is a disease.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12356" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12368">“Go ahead,” said Renzo, “speak Latin if you feel like it. I don’t mind.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12369" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12403">“So you’ve still got a grudge against Latin? Then I’ll teach you a lesson. When you come up to the altar with this girl, to hear a little Latin, I’ll say, ‘You don’t want Latin: Then go in peace.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12404" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12405">Is that what you’d like?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12406" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12443">“Eh! I know what I’m saying,” Renzo continued. “Church Latin doesn’t scare me. It’s an honest Latin, holy, the language of the Mass. You priests on the altar have to read what’s written in the book. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12444" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12460">I’m talking about sneaky Latin, outside the church, that ambushes you in the middle of a conversation. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12461" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12506">For example, here we are, and all our troubles are over. And you trotted out some Latin back there, in that corner, to make me think you couldn’t marry us, and that more steps were needed, and I don’t know what else. Can you put it into Italian for me now?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12507" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12526">“Shut up, you fool! Don’t go stirring things up again. Because if we draw up the balance sheet, I don’t know which of us is more sinned against. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12527" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12540">Everything is forgiven. Now not another word about it. You got in your jabs, too, Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12541" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12567">Nothing surprises me coming from you. You’re a little rascal. But her? Quiet as a mouse, the little saint, the Madonna herself, so holy you’d think it was a sin to be wary of her. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12568" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12581">Well, of course I know who she learned that from, I certainly do!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12582" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12608">In saying this, he pointed his accusing finger from Lucia to Agnese. The high spirits, the relish, with which he uttered those reprimands is almost indescribable. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12609" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12665">The news had given him a lightheartedness, a wit, that had been idle for quite some time. And we would have a long way to go until the end of this story if I were to report the remainder of that conversation, which he dragged out, believing more than once that his listeners were about to leave, and detaining them a bit longer on the doorstep, always with a little more small talk. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12666" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12720">The next day, he received a visit as welcome as it was unexpected: the Marquis himself. He was a man midway between his prime and old age, and one whose appearance seemed to vouch for the fame that had preceded him: open, courteous, calm, humble, dignified, with an air of resigned sorrow about him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12721" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12729">“I am here,” he said, “to convey the greetings of the Cardinal-Archbishop.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12730" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12735">“Oh, you are too kind.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12736" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12772">“When I was about to take my leave of that peerless man, who honors me with his friendship, he spoke to me of two young people from this parish who were betrothed, and had run into some trouble on account of that poor Don Rodrigo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12773" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12776">The Monsignor would like to have some news of them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12777" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12778">Are they alive? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12779" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12784">Has their business been taken care of?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12785" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12787">“Everything has been taken care of. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12788" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12801">In fact, I was just about to write to His Eminence, but now that I have the honor…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12802" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12804">“Are they here?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12805" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12815">“Yes, and as soon as possible, they will become man and wife.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12816" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12836">“Please tell me if there’s anything I can do to help them, and the most appropriate way. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12837" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12857">I have lost the only two children I had, as well as their mother, in this calamity, and I have come into three considerable inheritances, which I do not need, since the one I have is already more than enough. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12858" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12882">So if you know of an opportunity for me to use some of it, you would truly be doing me a favor, especially an opportunity like this.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12883" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12886">“Heaven bless you! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12887" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12893">Why couldn’t everyone be like you? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12894" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12903">Well, I, too, wish to thank you from the bottom of my heart on behalf of these two children of mine. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12904" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12925">And since your most illustrious Lordship has encouraged me to do so, yes, in fact, I will suggest a solution that might be to your liking. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12926" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12982">“You should know that these good people have decided to set up house elsewhere, and to sell the few possessions they have here under the sun: The young man’s vineyard, which is only an acre and a half, to be honest, and badly neglected. It’s worth little more than the land that it’s on, nothing more. He also has a cottage, and the bride has another: two rat holes, really. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_12983" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13000">A gentleman like yourself doesn’t know what it’s like for the poor when they want to sell off their possessions. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13054">They always end up being taken advantage of by some crook, who has maybe been eyeing their tiny plot of land for a while. Once he finds out that they’re ready to sell, the crook pretends he’s no longer interested, so the poor chase after him and sell him everything for a crust of bread. Especially in circumstances like these. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13055" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13067">“I’m sure the Marquis can see what I’m getting at. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13068" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13089">The most generous charity your Lordship could offer these two is to help them out of this bind by buying their few paltry possessions. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13090" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13124">I may be a bit biased, to be honest, since my parish would stand to gain from a patron like yourself. But it is up to you to decide what’s best. I have spoken out of deference to your wishes.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13125" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13170">The Marquis praised the suggestion, thanked Don Abbondio, and asked him to be the judge of the price, and to set it high. He then made the priest’s jaw drop by proposing that they go straight to the house of the bride, where they would presumably also find the groom. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13171" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13187">Don Abbondio was bubbling over with joy on the way to the house, as you can imagine, and soon he came up with another idea, and couldn’t resist saying it out loud. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13188" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13208">“Since your most illustrious Lordship is inclined to help these two out, there is another favor you could do for them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13209" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13299">The young man has a warrant out for his arrest, a kind of ban, for a prank he pulled in Milan two years ago. He got mixed up in the big riot that day, meaning no harm, out of sheer ignorance, like a mouse caught in a trap. Nothing serious. Kid stuff, an escapade. He wouldn’t hurt a fly! If anyone knows him, it’s me. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13300" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13342">I baptized him, I saw him grow up. If your Lordship might enjoy hearing the poor ramble on, you can ask him to tell you the story, and you’ll hear it for yourself. Since it’s an old story by now, no one is going to bother him. As I said, he’s thinking of moving to another state but, as time goes by, he might want to come back here for whatever reason, you never know. I hardly need to tell you that it’s always best not to have a criminal record. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13343" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13391">Your Lordship is a man of some influence in Milan, as is only right, and being such an important nobleman, and such a great man—no, no, don’t deny it—a recommendation, a good word from you, is more than it would take for the charges to be dropped.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13392" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13398">“Are the charges against him very serious?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13399" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13402">“No, I don’t believe so. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13403" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13423">At first they wanted to throw the book at him, but nowadays I believe it’s a mere formality.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13424" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13436">“Since that’s the case, it should be easy. I would be happy to take care of the matter.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13437" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13447">“And you don’t want people to call you a great man? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13448" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13459">Well I, for one, am going to say you are, whether you like it or not. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13460" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13479">And even if I did keep my mouth shut, it wouldn’t matter because everyone is saying the same thing. And vox populi, vox Dei—the voice of the people is the voice of God.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13480" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13486">The three women and Renzo were all at the house. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13487" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13521">I’ll leave the reader to imagine their reactions. Even the bare rough walls, the dirty windows, the squat stools, and the chipped dishes, I daresay, were amazed to receive such an extraordinary visit. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13522" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13539">The Marquis started the conversation, speaking of the Cardinal and other matters, with open cordiality as well as tactful regard. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13540" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13549">He then proceeded to make the offer that was the reason for his visit. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13550" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13600">When he asked Don Abbondio to set the price, the priest stepped forward. After a few protests and excuses, insisting that it wasn’t his place, that he’d be stumbling in the dark, and that he was just being obedient, and that it was up to them, he came up with a number that was, in his opinion, an exaggerated estimate. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13601" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13648">But the Marquis replied that, for his part, he was overjoyed. He pretended that he’d misunderstood, and actually doubled his offer. He refused any objection, and cut short all talk by inviting everyone to lunch on the day of the wedding at his palace, where he would present the notarized deed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13649" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13699">Once he was back home, Don Abbondio remarked to himself, “Now if the plague had the same effect always and everywhere, it would be a shame to speak badly of it. You might almost say we need one every generation or so, and we could draw up an agreement to do just that. But with the possibility of recovery, of course.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13700" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13728">The dispensation arrived, and so did the pardon, and, finally, the happy day. The bride and groom made their triumphant and safe way to the church where, by the blessing of none other than Don Abbondio, they became man and wife. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13729" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13770">Another even more singular triumph was their visit to the palace. You can imagine how they must have felt as they walked up that hill and entered through the front door, and the things they must have said, each in their own way. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13771" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13795">I will only report that more than one person voiced the thought, and more than once, that the only thing missing from their happy party was poor Fra Cristoforo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13796" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13805">“But one thing we do know for certain,” they later added, “is that he is in a better place than us.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13806" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13853">The Marquis welcomed them in grand style, leading them to the servants’ dining room, where he seated the newlyweds at the table, along with Agnese and the merchant’s widow. Before he retired upstairs to dine with Don Abbondio, he decided to stay for a while to keep the guests company, and indeed to help serve them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13854" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13872">I know some of you must be thinking how it would have been simpler for everyone to dine at the same table. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13873" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13918">But as I’ve explained to you, he was a good man, not an “eccentric,” as he would be called nowadays. And as I’ve told you, he was a humble man, but not a paragon of humility: willing to defer to these good people, but not to spend time with them as an equal. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13919" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13935">After the two separate meals, the deed was drawn up by an accountant, but not by Professor Argle-Bargle. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13936" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13947">The latter, by which I mean his mortal remains, was and still is in Canterelli. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13948" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13963">For those who are not from around there, I realize that an explanation might be in order. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n189" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_13964" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14019">About a half-mile above Lecco, and almost right on the border of the neighboring town Castello, there is a place, at the crossroads, called Canterelli. On one side you can see raised ground, a sort of man-made hill, with a cross on top, which is no more than a burial mound for those who died in that plague. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n190" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14020" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14046">Traditionally, they are just called victims of the plague, but those remains belong undoubtedly to the victims of that plague, which was the last and most deadly in memory. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n191" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14047" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14061">And you know that traditions, without a little push, always say too little on their own. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n192" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14062" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14083">On the way back, the only complication was the weight of all the money Renzo had to carry. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n193" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14084" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14092">As you know, however, he had already lived other lives. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n194" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14093" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14110">I’m not referring to the labor of his mind, no small thing, as it pondered how best to spend the money. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n195" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14111" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14146">To envision the projects passing through his head, the reflections, the fantasies; to hear the pros and cons, whether to invest in agriculture or industry; was like witnessing a dispute between two learned academics in the previous century. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n196" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14147" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14195">For him the dilemma was much more real. Since he was only one person, you couldn’t tell him: Why do you need to choose? Why not do both? For the means are basically the same, and two, like legs, are better than one. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n197" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14196" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14220">His every thought was dedicated to packing up and moving: the Tramaglino household to its new home, and the widow back to Milan. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n198" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14221" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14231">Many were the tears, the thank-yous, the promises to visit one another. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n199" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14232" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14258">Equally tender, though without the tears, was Renzo’s separation from the family of his host and friend. And don’t go thinking that the goodbyes with Don Abbondio were cold. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n200" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14259" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14282">Those good children had always maintained a respectful attachment to their priest who, in his heart of hearts, had always been fond of them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n201" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14283" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14290">It’s those blessed affairs that get in the way of affections. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n202" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14291" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14323">To all who wonder whether they also felt some sadness to be separated from their birthplace, from those mountains, of course they did: Since there is more than enough sadness, I was about to say, to go around. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n203" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14324" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14350">It cannot have been too deep, however, since they could have spared themselves by staying put, now that the two great impediments, Don Rodrigo and the arrest warrant, had been removed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n204" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14351" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14367">But for some time now, all three had gotten used to seeing the town where they were moving as their new home. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n205" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14368" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14392">Renzo had brought the women around to the idea by describing the advantages for workers and the many other opportunities for a good life there. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n206" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14393" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14423">Not to mention that they had all been through such bitter moments in the place they were leaving behind. And sad memories eventually spoil thoughts of the places that recall them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n207" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14424" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14443">And if they happen to be our birthplaces, those memories are liable to be even harsher and more poignant. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n208" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14444" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14498">Even the child, according to the manuscript, sleeps happily on its nurse’s breast, and reaches with greed and trust for the pap that is gently nourishing it. But when the wet nurse begins to wean the child, by spreading wormwood on her breast, the child will try to suckle, again and again, but eventually learn to break away. Crying, yes, but still breaking away. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n209" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14499" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14517">So can you believe that as soon as they arrived and settled into their new village, Renzo encountered some unpleasantness, ready and waiting? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n210" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14518" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14528">Nothing much, really, but it takes so little to unsettle a state of happiness! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n211" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14529" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14534">Here, in brief, is what happened. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n212" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14535" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14599">Gossip had started to circulate about Lucia well before her arrival in the village. Knowing how much Renzo had suffered on her account, and how steadfast and true he had always been, a word or two may have been spoken by friends partial to him and to everything about him that had sparked a certain curiosity to see the young girl, and certain expectations of her beauty. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n213" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14600" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14640">Now you know what expectations are like: fanciful, gullible, and confident. Put to the test, they become harsh, fickle: Nothing is good enough, since they don’t really know what they expected, and they ruthlessly withdraw the indulgence that had been accorded without reason. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n214" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14641" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14688">When this Lucia appeared, there were many who thought her hair should be spun from gold, her cheeks as red as roses, each eye more beautiful than the other, and I have no idea what else. They shrugged their shoulders and turned up their noses, saying, “All this fuss over her?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n215" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14689" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14698">After so much time and so much talk, they were expecting something better. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n216" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14699" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14700">And who was she, after all? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n217" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14701" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14704">A peasant girl like many others. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n218" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14705" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14714">If that’s what you want, there are far prettier ones, ripe for the picking. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n219" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14715" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14738">Under closer scrutiny, everyone found something different that was wrong with her, and some even thought she was downright ugly. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n220" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14739" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14758">But since no one said these things to Renzo’s face, no great harm had been done. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n221" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14759" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14778">The harm that was done, instead, was by those who reported such comments to him: And Renzo, well, what do you expect? He was cut to the quick. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n222" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14779" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14805">He started to obsess over them, and complain loudly to anyone who cared to speak with him, but mostly to himself. “Is it any business of yours? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n223" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14806" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14810">Who told you what to expect, anyway? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n224" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14811" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14823">Me? When did I ever say she was pretty? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n225" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14824" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14841">And when you told me she wasn’t, did I say anything other than that she was a good girl? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n226" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14842" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14844">She’s a peasant! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n227" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14845" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14853">When did I ever say I was bringing a princess here? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n228" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14854" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14856">You don’t like her? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n229" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14857" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14859">So don’t look at her. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n230" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14860" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14866">You have beautiful women of your own: Go look at them!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n231" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14867" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14886">Here you can see how a little foolishness can sometimes suffice to decide a man’s condition for life. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n232" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14887" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14907">If Renzo had followed through on his initial plans to spend the rest of his life in that village, he wouldn’t have been very happy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n233" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14908" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14915">The steady stream of nastiness had made him nasty in turn. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n234" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14916" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14928">He was rude to everyone, since anyone might have been one of Lucia’s critics. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n235" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14929" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14953">Not that he had forgotten his manners, but you wouldn’t believe how many niceties you can discard without violating the rules of proper behavior, until it ends with a knife in the belly. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n236" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14954" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14989">There was something slightly sardonic in his every word. He found something to criticize in everything. If there was bad weather for two days in a row, he would immediately remark, “What else can you expect in a place like this!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n237" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_14990" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15043">I tell you, there were more than a few people who started to find him annoying, including some who used to like him. And over time, with one thing leading to another, he found himself at war, so to speak, with almost the entire village, without ever fully understanding the reason for his unhappiness. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n238" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15044" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15059">You could say that the plague had made a commitment to right all of Renzo’s wrongs. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n239" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15060" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15114">For one thing, it had taken away the owner of another silk mill, located at the gates of Bergamo. The heir, a shiftless youth, having found nothing to amuse him in the whole factory, was intent on and indeed raring to sell, even at half price. But he wanted immediate payment, so that he could use the money immediately for less productive pursuits. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n240" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15115" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15163">Bortolo heard about the matter and ran to see it. He haggled and got a better price than he could have ever imagined. But the demand for a cash sale spoiled the deal. The amount Bortolo had set aside, little by little, by saving, was still far short of the agreed price. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n241" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15164" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15183">He asked the man for a little more time, went back home to tell his cousin, and proposed that they buy the factory together, fifty-fifty. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n242" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15184" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15203">This splendid proposal resolved all the financial doubts of Renzo, who immediately opted for industry and said yes. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n243" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15204" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15210">They went together and sealed the contract. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n244" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15211" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15261">When the new owners took possession, Lucia, with no expectations to face this time around, finally escaped the brunt of criticism, and you could even say that people didn’t mind her. Renzo came to learn that more than one person had remarked, “Did you see the pretty blockhead who just arrived?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n245" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15262" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15266">And the adjective allowed him to ignore the noun. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n246" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15267" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15280">The unhappiness he had felt in the other village taught him a useful lesson. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n247" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15281" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15302">Until then, he had been too quick to judge, and only too happy to criticize, the wives of other men, and many more things. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n248" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15303" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15331">After he realized that words have one effect on the tongue and another on the ear, he made it a habit to listen to his own words inside before uttering them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n249" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15332" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15342">Don’t go thinking, however, that there were not some annoyances there, as well. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n250" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15343" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15416">Mankind (according to our anonymous author, who you know had a strange taste in similes, but let’s quote this one, too, and may it be the last)—mankind, for as long as he is in this world, is like an invalid lying on a somewhat uncomfortable bed. All around him he sees other beds—well made, neat, and flat—and imagines that he could sleep quite comfortably in any of them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n251" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15417" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15454">But if he does manage to change beds, as soon he settles into the new one, he’ll feel a twig pricking him here, a lump pressing him there, and find himself, in short, right back where he started. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n252" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15455" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15478">This is why—the anonymous author suggests—we should think less about feeling good and more about doing good, and thus end up feeling better. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n253" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15479" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15494">Being a true man of the seventeenth century, his explanation is a bit laborious, but he is basically right. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n254" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15495" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15549">For that matter, he continues, our good people no longer faced troubles and tribulations of the type and severity I have recounted here. From then on, their life was the most peaceful, the most happy, and the most enviable. So much so that if I were to describe it, you would be bored to death. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n255" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15550" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15576">Business went like a charm. At the beginning there were some setbacks due to the shortage of workers and the bad habits and demands of the few who remained. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n256" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15577" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15598">Decrees were published restricting workers’ pay. Despite this charitable contribution, business eventually picked up, because in the end it must. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n257" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15599" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15627">Then another more reasonable decree arrived from Venice: a ten-year exemption from all personal and property taxes for foreigners who came to live in that state. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n258" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15628" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15634">For our young couple this was another windfall. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n259" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15635" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15675">Before the end of their first year of marriage, a beautiful child came into this world. As if born to fulfill Renzo’s magnanimous vow, it was a girl. And you can be sure they called her Maria. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n260" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15676" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15717">Through the years I don’t know how many more children they had, of both sexes. Agnese’s hands were full carrying them back and forth, one after the other, scolding them and planting such big kisses on their faces that they left white marks. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n261" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15718" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15744">And they were all well behaved, and Renzo wanted them to learn to read and write, saying that, since this vexatious business existed, then they should at least have the benefit of it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n262" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15745" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15770">The best part was hearing him tell his adventures. He always concluded by listing the important things he’d learned, to better govern himself in the future. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n263" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15771" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15841">“What I’ve learned,” he would say, “is not to throw myself into the fray. Not to give speeches from a soapbox. To watch who I speak with. I’ve learned not to lift my elbow too much and not to linger at the door, knocker in hand, when I’m surrounded by an angry mob. I’ve learned not to tie a bell to my foot before thinking what might come of it,” and a hundred other things. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n264" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15842" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15864">Lucia did not so much dispute his lessons as find something missing from his rambling. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n265" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15865" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15891">After hearing him repeat the same litany over and over, and bristling inside every time, one day she told her moralizing friend, “What about me? What do you think I’ve learned? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n266" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15892" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15907">I didn’t go looking for trouble: Trouble came looking for me. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n267" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15908" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15929">Unless what you mean to say,” she added, smiling sweetly, “is that it was my mistake to love and to promise myself to you.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n268" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15930" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15934">At first Renzo was dumbstruck. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n269" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15935" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15992">But after long conversations and soul-searching, they reached the conclusion that trouble often comes calling when it’s been invited in. Not even the most cautious and innocent behavior can keep it away. And when trouble does come calling, rightly or wrongly, faith in God softens the blow and turns it to a better purpose. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n270" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_15993" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_16016">While these may be the conclusions of poor people, they sound so right to me that I thought I would write them down here, as the moral of the story. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n271" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_16017" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_16037">Which, if this story hasn’t displeased you, should make you think kindly of the man who wrote it and, also, a little, of the man who revised it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap38-n272" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_16038" targetEnd="quarantana/cap38.xml#c38_16051">But if we have only succeeded in boring you instead, believe me, we didn’t do so on purpose. </note>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>