<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>2022</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed: a novel</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
          <date>2022</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Michael Moore</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="english_2022_cap31">
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10041">The plague that the Tribunal of Health had feared might enter the Milan area with the German troops really did enter, as is well known. Just as it is well known that the plague did not stop there, but went on to invade and depopulate a good part of Italy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10042" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10091">Following the thread of our story, I will now recount the main events of that calamity in the Milan area, or should I say in Milan itself, since the memoirs from that period deal almost exclusively with the city, as is the case almost always and everywhere, for reasons both good and bad. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10092" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10146">And in all honesty, my aim in telling this story is not only to depict the situation in which our characters come to find themselves, but also for us to learn together, as best and as much as we can in this short space, a period of our country’s history better known than it is understood. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10147" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10177">Of the many contemporary reports, not a single one, by itself, provides a reasonably clear and orderly picture, although not a single one fails to help to formulate just such a picture. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10178" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10288">Each of these reports, even the one by Giuseppe Ripamonti—which surpasses all the others in the quantity and selection of incidents, and especially in his manner of observing them—omits essential details that the others, instead, include. Each report contains factual errors that can be identified and corrected with the help of the others or of the few official records, both published and unpublished, that have survived: One might give you the causes while another describes only the effects, as if the two were disconnected. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10289" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10353">And all of them confuse chronology and events in strange ways, with a constant zigzagging, almost haphazard, and neither a general design nor even any details: These were common and glaring characteristics, after all, of the books of that period, at least in Italy, especially the ones written in the vernacular. Whether books in the rest of Europe were the same, the scholars may know, but I suspect they were. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10354" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10452">No later writer has set out to examine and compare these accounts in order to depict a chain of events, a history of the plague. As a result, people generally have only a shaky and slightly confused notion of it: a vague idea of great suffering and great mistakes (there were truly unimaginable amounts of both); an idea consisting more of opinions than facts—a few random facts—and lacking, more often than not, the most characteristic situations of a clear chronology, by which I mean without an understanding of the cause and effect, course, and progress of the plague. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10453" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10500">By examining and comparing with great diligence, if nothing else, all the printed reports, more than one unpublished account, and many of the few surviving so-called official documents, I have tried to put together not so much the account we need as one that has not yet been written. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10501" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10519">I have no intention of including all the official documents, or even all the somewhat noteworthy events. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10520" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10561">Nor do I wish to dissuade anyone who wishes to form a more comprehensive idea from reading the original reports. I feel too keenly the living, innate, and indescribable force, so to speak, that such works always have, no matter how they were conceived and conducted. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10562" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10621">I have only attempted to identify and verify the most well-known and important events, arrange them in chronological order, as best as reason and their nature will allow, and observe how they influenced one another, in order to provide, for now, a concise but honest and coherent account of that disaster, at least until someone produces a better version. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10622" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10639">Throughout the strip of territory crossed by the army, dead bodies were found in houses and by the roadside. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10640" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10666">Not long after, in one town or another, individuals and entire families started to fall ill and die of strange, violent ailments with symptoms that most of the living had never before seen. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10667" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10708">There were some people, however, to whom they were not new: the few who still remembered the plague that, fifty-three years earlier, had devastated much of Italy, especially in the area of Milan, where it was and is still known as the San Carlo Plague. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10709" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10713">Such is the power of charity! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10714" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10784">Amid the many varied and solemn memories of a general misfortune, charity assured that one man would stand out, a man whom it had inspired with feelings and actions that would be remembered long after the suffering was over. This suffering drove him to be a guide, relief, example, and voluntary victim, and would associate him indelibly with this troubled time. He became an emblem of the general calamity, so much so that it was named after him, like a land he had conquered or discovered. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10785" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10851">Milan’s chief medical officer, Lodovico Settala, had not only witnessed the earlier plague but had also been one of the most active, intrepid, and—despite his youth—reputable doctors. Now, harboring grave suspicions, he was on the alert for information. On the twentieth of October, he reported to the Tribunal of Health that the contagion had unquestionably broken out in Chiuso (the last village in the Lecco territory, bordering on the province of Bergamo). </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10852" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10868">Yet the tribunal took no decisions, as indicated in the report written by Settala’s lieutenant, Alessandro Tadino. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10869" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10878">Similar notifications soon arrived from Lecco and Bellano. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10879" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10908">Then the tribunal did come to a resolution, agreeing to send a commissioner to the two towns, with instructions to stop along the way in Como for a physician who could accompany him on his visits. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10909" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10961">Both men, “either from ignorance or another reason, allowed themselves to be persuaded by an ignorant old barber of Bellano that this type of ailment was not the plague” (Tadino, ivi). He claimed that, in some places, it was the normal effect of the autumnal emissions from the marshes; and in others, a result of the poverty and hardship caused by the passage of the German troops. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10962" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10978">This reassurance was conveyed to the tribunal, and seemed to set its mind at ease. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_10979" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11008">However, as more and more reports of death arrived from other areas, without pause, two delegates were once again dispatched to view and review the situation: the aforementioned Tadino and an auditor from the tribunal. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11009" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11028">By the time they arrived, the disease was already so widespread that there was no need to search for proof. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11029" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11101">They visited the province of Lecco, the Valsassina, the shores of Lake Como, and the districts of Monte di Brianza and Gera d’Adda. Everywhere they went they found towns whose gates were closed, blocking entry, and others that were almost deserted, since the townsfolk had fled and were camped out in the fields or had deserted the area completely. “The people looked,” wrote Tadino, “like so many wild creatures, holding sprigs of mint, ruta, or rosemary, or a cruet of vinegar.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11102" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11123">They inquired about the death toll. The answers were shocking. They visited the sick and the dead, and everywhere found the ugly, terrifying marks of the plague. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11124" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11183">They conveyed the bad news to the Tribunal of Health in a letter. Upon receiving it, on the thirtieth of October, the tribunal “issued the order”—according to Tadino—to send out a bulletin banning people from the towns where the contagion had appeared from entering Milan. “While the decree was being drafted,” a few hasty advance instructions were given to the sentries at the gates. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11184" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11222">In the meantime, the two delegates quickly took all the steps they thought necessary, but they returned to the city with the grim certainty that these measures would not suffice to redress and stop the course of a disease that was already so advanced and widespread. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11223" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11252">Having arrived on the fourteenth of November, and delivered both oral and written reports to the tribunal, they were then deputized to appear before the Governor and explain the situation to him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11253" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11281">So they went. And they reported back: He was exceedingly sorry to hear the news, and made a great display of emotion, but concerns about the war were far more urgent: sed belli graviores esse curas. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11282" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11317">This we know from Ripamonti, who combed through the records of the Tribunal of Health and also spoke with Tadino, who had been assigned this special mission. This was the second time the latter had been dispatched, the reader will recall, for the same purpose, and obtaining the same result. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11318" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11374">Two or three days later, on the eighteenth of November, the Governor, oblivious or heedless of the danger of such a gathering in these circumstances, issued a decree in which he ordered public festivities to be held for the birth of Prince Carlos, the first son of King Philip IV. He specified that everything was to proceed according to custom, as if no health warnings had been issued. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11375" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11449">He being, as I have already mentioned, the famous Ambrogio Spinola, who had been sent to set the war campaign on the proper footing, correct the mistakes of Don Gonzalo, and, incidentally, to govern. And here we should also recall, incidentally, that he would die a few months later, in the same war so dear to his heart. He died not of wounds suffered on the battlefield but in bed, of anxiety and grief, caused by the criticism, injustice, and unpleasantness of every sort that he had received from those whom he had served. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11450" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11501">History has deplored his fate and condemned their ingratitude, while diligently listing his military and political achievements and praising his foresight, actions, and perseverance. It might have also considered how he deployed all these qualities when the plague threatened and then invaded a people entrusted to his care, or rather, to his mercy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11502" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11545">Without oppugning that criticism, any surprise at his behavior is diminished, however, by the even greater surprise at the behavior of the people, by which I mean the people who were still untouched by the contagion, and had every reason to fear it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11546" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11601">Wouldn’t you think that the news of towns that had been so badly hit, towns that almost ring the city, no farther than eighteen or twenty miles away in places, would spark a general outcry, a desire for precautions (good or bad), or at least a sterile unease? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11602" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11620">Yet if there is one thing on which contemporary accounts agree, it is in attesting that nothing of the sort occurred. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11621" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11664">The famine of the previous year, the abuses of the soldiers, and the afflictions of the spirit were considered a more than sufficient explanation for the mortality rate. In the public squares, in the workplace, or at home, anyone who dared to hint at the danger, and who attributed the deaths to the plague, was treated to angry contempt and jeers of disbelief. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11665" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11685">The same disbelief, or rather the same blindness and obstinacy, prevailed in the Senate, in the Council of the Decurioni, and in every magistrate. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11686" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11758">As soon as the first cases of the contagious disease appeared, Cardinal Federigo, according to my research, sent a pastoral letter to the priests with strict instructions to warn the people again and again to take these cases seriously and to report any potential incidents, as well as to turn in any infected or suspicious clothing. This is yet another of the Cardinal’s unique and commendable qualities. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11759" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11770">The Tribunal of Health requested, even pleaded, for cooperation, but it received little to none. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11771" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11824">Even within the tribunal itself, attention to the epidemic fell far short of the urgent need. As Tadino points out repeatedly, and the full context of his report makes clear, it was the two physicians, convinced of the gravity and imminence of the danger, who prodded the tribunal to action, which in turn reluctantly prodded the other government bodies. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11825" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11891">We have already seen how, at the first reports of the plague, the tribunal was slow to take action, or even to gather information. Adding significantly to the delay, perhaps because of obstruction by senior magistrates, the decree to restrict entry into the city, which had been agreed to on the thirtieth of October, was not drafted until the twenty-third of the following month, and not published until the twenty-ninth, by which time the plague had already entered Milan. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11892" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11989">Tadino and Ripamonti wanted to record the name of the man who had introduced the contagion to the city, as well as more details about him and his case. In observations of the beginnings of a vast mortality, in which the victims cannot be identified by name but only vaguely indicated by their numbers in the thousands, there is often a strange curiosity to record and conserve the names of the first few carriers, as if the distinction of being the first to die in an extermination lends a fatal and memorable quality to names and otherwise quite ordinary details. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_11990" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12012">Both historians agree that it was an Italian soldier in the service of Spain. Apart from that, there is little they agree on, including his name. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12013" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12039">According to Tadino, it was Pietro Antonio Lovato, garrisoned in the Lecco territory. According to Ripamonti, it was Pier Paolo Locati, quartered in Chiavenna. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12040" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12071">They also disagree as to when he entered Milan: Tadino places it at the twenty-second of October, Ripamonti on the same day of the following month. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12072" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12082">Neither is correct, since both are contradicted by other well-documented sources. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12083" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12124">Ripamonti, writing by order of the General Council of the Decurioni, must have had many means at his disposal to obtain the necessary information. And Tadino, by virtue of his position, should have been better informed than anyone. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12125" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12175">Nevertheless, after comparing other, more accurate dates, it appears that the soldier entered Milan before publication of the decree restricting access to the city. And if you wanted to go to the trouble, you could prove, or almost, that it must have been at the beginning of that month. But the reader will, of course, exempt me from this task. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12176" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12246">Whatever the case may be, this unfortunate foot soldier and bearer of misfortune, carrying a big bundle of clothing bought or stolen from German soldiers, stopped by the house of relatives in the Porta Orientale neighborhood, not far from the Capuchin monastery. The moment he arrived, he fell ill and was taken to the hospital, where a dark swollen lump, a bubo, was found under his armpit, leading his attendant to suspect the true cause. Four days later he died. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12247" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12274">The Tribunal of Health ordered the isolation and quarantine of his relatives in their home. His clothing and hospital bed were burned. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12275" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12298">In a matter of days, two servants and a good friar who had cared for him also fell ill, all three from the plague. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12299" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12330">In the hospital, concerns about the nature of his illness were raised immediately, and precautions were taken as a result, preventing the contagion from spreading any further inside. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12331" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12345">But the soldier had sown a seed in his trail that did not take long to germinate. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12346" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12392">The first to be infected was the landlord of the house where he had lodged, a certain Carlo Colonna, lute player. Therefore, on the orders of the Tribunal of Health, all the other tenants of the house were taken to the lazaretto, where most of them fell ill, and some died shortly thereafter of what was clearly the plague. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12393" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12462">By then the contagion had already spread throughout the city, since neighbors, relatives, and servants had salvaged the tenants’ clothing and furniture despite the search and burn instructions of the tribunal. There were also new arrivals to the city, thanks to loopholes, lax application, and deft evasion of the decrees. So the plague continued to fester, creeping through the rest of the year and into the early months of 1630. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12463" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12513">Every so often, in this neighborhood or that, someone would catch and someone would die from the disease. There were still so few cases that any suspicions of the truth were banished, while the public’s dumb and deadly confidence that there was not nor had there ever been a plague was reconfirmed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12514" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12565">Many doctors, echoing the vox populi (or was it, even in this case, the voice of God?), derided the evil auguries and dire warnings of the few. They trotted out the names of common illnesses to explain away every case of plague they were called upon to treat, regardless of the signs or symptoms. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12566" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12623">Even when reports of these incidents reached the Tribunal of Health, they always arrived late, for the most part, and uncertain. Fear of quarantine and of the lazaretto made everyone wary: The ill were not reported, the gravediggers and their supervisors were bribed, and even employees of the tribunal assigned to examine the cadavers could be paid off to issue false death certificates. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12624" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12685">When the tribunal did manage to discover a victim, it ordered possessions burned, homes sequestered, and families sent to the lazaretto, so it was easy to understand the general anger and complaints, “from the Nobles, the Merchants, and the common people,” according to Tadino, who were convinced that these actions amounted to senseless and baseless harassment. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12686" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12720">The brunt of the resentment fell on the two doctors—Tadino and Senatore Settala (son of the chief medical officer)—who could not cross a public square without having obscenities or even stones hurled after them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12721" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12781">For a few months, they found themselves in a unique and memorable situation: witnessing the advance of a horrible scourge, striving in every manner to prevent it, and running into obstacles where they were looking for help, all the while being called enemies of the patria: “pro patriae hostibus,” as Ripamonti wrote. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12782" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12810">Some of that resentment was also directed at other doctors, who were likewise convinced that the contagion was real, and tried to convey their terrible certainty by suggesting precautions. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12811" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12834">Even the most moderate were accused of being credulous and obstinate: all the others, of telling blatant lies, and concocting a plot in order to profit from public fear. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12835" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12891">The chief medical officer at the time was, as I said, Lodovico Settala, a former Professor of Medicine at the University of Pavia, and later of Moral Philosophy in Milan, author of many works that were highly regarded in those days. He was known for being offered chairs at other universities—Ingolstadt, Pisa, Bologna, Padua—and turning them all down. He was nearly eighty years old, but remained one of the most authoritative men of his time. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12892" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12915">In addition to his reputation as a scientist, he was esteemed as a man, and admired and loved for his charity in treating and helping the poor. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12916" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12982">To my regret and sorrow, however, the esteem inspired by these qualities is compromised by the very thing that in those days must have earned him greater and more widespread admiration, for the poor man shared some of the most common and deadly prejudices of his contemporaries. He was ahead of his time but didn’t want to break with the common consensus, an invitation for trouble that can often make a man lose the authority he had earned in other areas. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_12983" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13033">Yet in this case, even his great authority was not enough to sway the opinion of those whom poets call profanum vulgus, profane commoners, and whom actors call their beloved public. Nor could it shield him from the animosity and the insults of those members of the public who leap more easily from judgments to demonstrations to action. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13034" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13087">One day, on his way to visit patients, a crowd started to gather around his sedan chair, shouting that he was responsible for the rumors about the plague. With his scowl and scraggly beard, he had terrorized the city, they said, all to create business for the doctors! As the crowd grew, so did its fury. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13088" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13112">Seeing the situation take a turn for the worse, the sedan chair–bearers found shelter for their master at the home of friends, who luckily lived nearby. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13113" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13208">Such was Settala’s reward for predicting the plague, identifying it, and wanting to save thousands of people from its ravages. He would eventually win back the public’s favor as a wise and—so unbearable to imagine—charitable man when, in a deplorable consultation, he participated in the torture of a poor hapless wretch, who was burnt at the stake after her flesh had been torn with red-hot tongs. She had been accused of witchcraft after her current master suffered strange stomach pains, while a previous master had fallen madly in love with her. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13209" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13271">Toward the end of March, the number of illnesses and deaths started to mount, first in the Porta Orientale area, then in every neighborhood of the city. There were strange cases of spasms, palpitations, lethargy, and delirium, together with the fatal mark of bruises and dark swollen lumps known as buboes. For the most part, the deaths were quick, violent, and often quite sudden, without any prior symptoms. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13272" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13353">The doctors who had rejected the diagnosis of the plague, unwilling to admit now what they had derided earlier, still felt obliged to give a generic moniker to the new disease, which had now become too widespread and too obvious to remain nameless. So they came up with the term malignant or pestilential fevers: a miserable compromise, indeed a bit of word play that caused terrible harm, for while seemingly acknowledging the illness it still managed to hide the truth: that the infection was being spread through human contact. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13354" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13391">Like someone waking up from a deep sleep, the magistrates began to pay closer attention to the warnings and proposals of the Tribunal of Health, and enforce its decrees and sequestering, and quarantine orders. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13392" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13436">The tribunal was constantly requesting money to meet the growing daily expenses of the lazaretto and many other services. And it made these requests to the Decurioni, while awaiting a decision on whether the expenses should be borne by the City or the Crown (a decision that I believe was never made, except in practice). </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13437" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13503">The Grand Chancellor submitted another petition to the Decurioni on the orders of the Governor, who was once again laying siege to the poor town of Casale. The Senate sent an appeal for action on two items: to provision the city with food before the contagion got even worse and stop commerce with other cities; and to support the large percentage of the population who had lost their jobs. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13504" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13540">The Decurioni tried to raise the money through loans and taxes. They distributed a little of their collection to the Tribunal of Health, a little to the poor, and a little to buy some grain, which met part of the need. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13541" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13548">But greater hardship was yet to come. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13549" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13620">In the lazaretto, although more and more people died every day, the number of inmates continued to grow. It was an arduous job to provide service and discipline, keep the sexes segregated as prescribed, and maintain or rather enforce the guidelines ordered by the Tribunal of Health. There was great confusion from the start, due to the unruliness of many inmates as well as the negligence and corruption of the attendants. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13621" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13665">Not knowing where to turn, the tribunal and the Decurioni decided to approach the Capuchins. They begged the Father Commissioner of the Province, who was acting for the recently deceased Provincial Father, to provide them with men who could govern that desolate realm. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13666" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13725">He proposed that they hire, as the director, Padre Felice Casati, a mature man renowned for his charity, energy, strength of character, and mild manner (future events would prove this reputation well deserved); and as his partner and assistant, Padre Michele Pozzobonelli, who, while still young, was as grave and severe in his thoughts as he was in demeanor. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13726" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13738">The proposal was accepted with great pleasure, and on the thirtieth of March, the two men entered the lazaretto. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13739" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13775">The President of the Tribunal of Health showed them around, to hand over command of the lazaretto to them. After summoning the attendants and employees of every rank, he announced that Padre Felice would be the new director, with primary and plenary authority. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13776" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13805">As the wretched assembly steadily grew, other Capuchins joined the staff. They became supervisors, confessors, administrators, nurses, cooks, clothing distributors, washermen, and whatever else was required. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13806" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13859">Always solicitous, even under pressure, Padre Felice made the rounds every day and night, crossing the porticos, the rooms, and the vast inner yard, sometimes holding a staff, sometimes armed only with a hair shirt. He activated and controlled everything, putting down uprisings, settling quarrels, threatening, punishing, scolding, comforting, and drying tears as well as shedding some of his own. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13860" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13876">He caught the plague early on, recovered, and resumed his duties with renewed energy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13877" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13890">Most of his brothers lost their lives, but all of them did so joyfully. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13891" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13956">Such a dictatorship was certainly a strange remedy, as strange as the calamity, as the times. If this were all we knew, there would be no better proof, indeed no better example of a primitive and badly ruled society than the fact that its leaders did not know what to do with this major responsibility other than to delegate it, and whom to delegate it to other than to those who, by their vocation, were most alien to such authority. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13957" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13990">But the brothers’ adept assumption of this responsibility is a noble example of the force and ability that charity can grant in every era and in every situation. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_13991" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14058">There was beauty in their very acceptance of this assignment, for no other reason than that no one else would, and for no other purpose than to serve, with no other hope in this world than to die a death more enviable than envied. And there was beauty in offering them this responsibility only because it was difficult and dangerous, and they were presumed to have the vigor and composure that was so needed and so rare in those times. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14059" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14172">This is why the labors and the hearts of those brothers deserve to be remembered with the admiration, tenderness, and special gratitude owed to them, in solidarity, for the great services rendered to their fellow man, and owed especially to those who provided it for no compensation. “If these Padri had not been there,” writes Tadino, “the whole city would surely have been annihilated, since it was miraculous for them to have done so much for the public benefit in so little time; with no help, or only very little, from the City. Through their industry and prudence, they cared for thousands of the poor in the lazaretto.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14173" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14227">During the seven months that Padre Felice was in charge, about fifty thousand people were admitted, according to Ripamonti, who rightly says that he would have mentioned the padre even if he had been writing about the glories of the city rather than its miseries. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14228" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14278">The public’s stubborn denial of the plague was also fading naturally and dispersing gradually as the disease spread, and spread through contact and mingling with the infected: Especially after the disease, having been confined to the poor for a time, started to infect more prominent citizens. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14279" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14296">The most noted among them, and thus deserving of special mention here, was the chief medical officer, Settala. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14297" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14305">Was the public finally ready to admit that the poor old man had been right? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14306" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14308">We’ll never know. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14309" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14321">He, his wife, two children, and seven servants fell ill of the plague. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14322" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14372">Only he and one of his children survived. The rest all died. “Such cases,” writes Tadino, “occurring as they did in the city, in Noble houses, made both the Nobility and the common people more disposed to reflect, and skeptical doctors, as well as reckless, ignorant common people, began to shut their mouths, grit their teeth, and raise their eyebrows.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14373" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14412">But sometimes the results, remedies, and vendettas, so to speak, of entrenched convictions are worse than staying the course, undeterred, against all reason and evidence. And this was one of those times. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14413" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14491">The people who had long and resolutely refused to believe that an evil seed within their midst had the ability, through natural means, to propagate and cause a massacre could no longer deny its spread. But they did not want to admit that it was airborne (which would have meant admitting both their great lie and their great guilt). They were more inclined to seek another cause, and to accept anything that was proposed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14492" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14530">Unfortunately, they found one ready and available in the ideas and traditions common to the period, not only in Italy but throughout Europe: namely, the dark arts, diabolic rituals, and plots to spread the plague through contagious poisons and black magic. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14531" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14553">The same or similar assumptions and beliefs had arisen in many previous pestilences, especially in Milan, during the plague half a century earlier. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14554" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14594">The previous year, King Philip IV of Spain had signed and sent a dispatch to the Governor of Milan, warning him that four Frenchmen had escaped from Madrid and were wanted on suspicion of spreading poisonous, pestilential unguents: He should be on alert in case they appeared in Milan. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14595" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14618">The Governor conveyed the message to the Senate and the Tribunal of Health, which did not seem to have paid it much mind until then. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14619" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14648">But after the plague had broken out and been acknowledged, however, recollections of that warning helped to confirm or even create the vague suspicion of a malicious plot. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14649" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14687">Then, two events, one driven by blind unchecked fear, and the other by an inexplicable act of mischief, converted vague suspicion of a possible attack into the suspicion, and for many the certainty, that there had really been an attack, and an actual conspiracy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14688" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14792">On the evening of the seventeenth of May, some people were convinced that they had seen individuals in the Duomo dabbing unguent on a wooden screen that divided the men’s section of the church from the women’s. They demanded that the screen be removed from the church that night, along with a number of pews that surrounded it. The President of the Tribunal of Health rushed over with four other people from his office. After inspecting the screen, the pews, and the holy water fonts, he found nothing to confirm the ignorant suspicion of foul play. Nevertheless, to humor the people, and out of an abundance of caution rather than necessity, he decided that it would suffice to wash the screen. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14793" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14813">The sheer size of that screen made a terrifying impression on the crowd, for whom an object easily became evidence. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14814" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14836">It was rumored and generally believed that all the pews, walls, and even the church bell ropes inside the Duomo had been smeared with an unguent. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14837" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14904">Nor was it said only on that occasion. All the contemporary memoirs that report the event (some written many years later) describe it with equal certainty. We might never have known the truth about what really happened, were it not for a letter from the Tribunal of Health to the Governor, which I found in the San Fedele archives, whose words I have quoted in italics. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14905" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14923">The next morning, a new and stranger, more significant sight greeted the eyes and minds of the citizens. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14924" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14953">In every part of the city, the doors of the houses and the walls had been smeared for long stretches with an unidentifiable filth, yellowish and chalky, that looked as if it had been applied with a sponge. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_14954" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15021">Either it was a foolish prank to provoke greater and more widespread fear, a criminal design to increase public confusion, or something else even I can’t imagine. There were enough eyewitnesses that I think it more reasonable to attribute this occurrence to the action of the few rather than to the hallucination of the many. It would not be the first or last act of this kind. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15022" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15078">On the topic of poisonous unguents, Ripamonti often derides and more often deplores the credulousness of the people, but he affirms that he, too, saw the splatters: “We, went to see, as well. Here and there were uneven splotches, as if someone with a sponge dipped into a purulent substance had smeared the walls. Here and there you could glimpse stains on the doors and steps, too” (75). </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15079" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15145">In the aforementioned letter, the gentlemen of the Tribunal of Health describe the event in the same terms. They inspected the substance and tested it on dogs, with no negative effects. In their opinion, such temerity proceeds from insolence rather than any evil intent, which suggests that they still had the composure not to see what was not there. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15146" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15189">In describing the event, other contemporary accounts imply that at first, many were of the opinion that it was a perverse prank. None of them mention anyone who denied this (as they certainly would have in the event that someone had—if only to call them bizarre). </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15190" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15257">I thought that it would not be inappropriate to compile and report details of this notorious collective delirium, some of which are little known, and some of which are not known at all. Because in the mistakes and especially in the mistakes of many, I find that the most interesting and useful thing to observe is precisely the path they took, their appearances, and the ways in which they entered into and took over minds. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15258" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15282">The already agitated city was in an uproar. Homeowners burned stumps of straw and charred the splattered areas. Passersby stopped and observed, shuddering in horror. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15283" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15306">Foreigners, easily identified by their unusual dress, were suspected simply because they were foreign, and subjected to citizen’s arrests on the streets and taken to the police. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15307" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15328">Examinations and interrogations were conducted of the people arrested, the ones who arrested them, as well as the witnesses. No one was found guilty. Better minds were still capable of doubting, questioning, and understanding. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15329" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15461">The Tribunal of Health published a decree promising rewards and immunity to anyone who reported the perpetrator or perpetrators of the deed. Nevertheless, we do not deem it appropriate, the gentlemen say in the aforementioned letter, dated the twenty-first of May, but evidently written on the nineteenth, the day indicated in the printed decree, that this crime remain unpunished in any manner, especially in such a dangerous and suspicious time. We have published this decree today, for the consolation and peace of mind of this Population, and to obtain evidence of the deed, etc. In the decree itself, however, there was no hint, or at least no clear one, of the reasonable and reassuring conjecture shared with the Governor: an omission that manifested both the mad obsessions of the people, and the tribunal’s complacency, as reprehensible as it was pernicious. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15462" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15473">While the tribunal was seeking, much of the public, as is often the case, had already found. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15474" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15533">Some believed it was a poisonous unguent. Some thought it was Don Gonzalo Fernández de Córdoba’s revenge for the insults he had received on his departure. Some thought it was a trick by Cardinal Richelieu to depopulate Milan and take possession of it without a struggle. Still others, who knows why, thought the perpetrator was the Count of Collato, or Wallenstein, or one Milanese gentleman or another. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15534" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15564">And there was no shortage, as I have said, of those who saw this event as nothing more than a foolish prank, which they attributed to students, noblemen, or army officials who had grown bored with the siege of Casale. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15565" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15601">When the much-feared infection and widespread death toll did not immediately occur, the early panic subsided momentarily, and the matter was or appeared to be consigned to oblivion. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15602" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15617">A number of people were still not convinced that there really was a plague. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15618" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15693">And since some victims in both the lazaretto and the city had actually recovered, “it was said by the common people, and also by many biased doctors, that it was not a true plague, because otherwise everyone would have been dead” (Tadino, 93). It is always strange to hear the final arguments of an opinion eventually defeated by overwhelming evidence. To erase all doubts, the Tribunal of Health found a solution befitting the need, a way to speak to eyes, as the times seemed to demand or suggest. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15694" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15741">At one of the Pentecostal feasts, the citizens would customarily gather at the San Gregorio cemetery, outside the Porta Orientale, to pray for the victims of the previous plague buried there. Excited by this opportunity for pomp and diversion, everyone had turned out in festive clothing. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15742" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15753">On that same day, an entire family had died from the plague. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15754" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15797">At the busiest hour of the Pentecostal feast, with many people milling about in carriages, on horseback, or on foot, the bodies of that family were transported to the cemetery on a cart, naked, by order of the tribunal, so the crowd could see for itself the undeniable signs of the plague. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15798" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15822">Wherever the cart passed, cries of revulsion and terror would break out. A long murmur followed in its wake. Another murmur preceded it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15823" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15848">Who could deny the plague now? It was gaining more believers on its own every day, but this event played no small role in persuading them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15849" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15864">So at the beginning, no plague, absolutely not, by any count: The very utterance of the word was prohibited. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15865" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15874">Then came the “pestilential” fevers, admitting the idea indirectly, through an adjective. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15875" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15903">And then, not an actual plague, well, yes, there was a plague, but only in a sense. Not a proper plague, mind you, but something for which there was no other name. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15904" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15939">Finally, it was a plague without a doubt and without dissent. But another idea had already taken root, the idea of poison and sorcery, which distorted and confused the idea expressed in a word that could no longer be retracted. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15940" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15961">You do not need to be well versed in the history of ideas and of words, I believe, to realize that many words have followed a similar course. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15962" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15997">Thank heavens that so few are of this nature and importance, pay such a high price before they are believed, and are associated with such attributes. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_15998" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_16032">Most of this long and twisted course could have been avoided, however, in both lesser and greater affairs, if the tried and true methods of observing, listening, comparing, and thinking before speaking had been adopted. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap31-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_16033" targetEnd="quarantana/cap31.xml#c31_16059">But speech, by itself, is so much easier than all the rest put together that we, too—by which I mean we humans in general—deserve a measure of indulgence. </note>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>