<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>2022</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed: a novel</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
          <date>2022</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Michael Moore</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="english_2022_cap37">
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10063">A slight drizzle began the moment Renzo crossed the threshold of the lazaretto and turned right, heading back toward the same alley that he had followed beneath the city walls that morning. A few impetuous drops drummed and bounced off the dry white road, raising a cloud of fine dust. A moment later, those drops became a shower, and before he could even reach the alley, the rain started coming down in torrents. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10064" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10116">But Renzo didn’t mind. He splashed about, enjoying the refreshment as the green grass and leaves swooshed and hummed, trembling, dripping, shiny, and newly green. He took big deep breaths. And in this reprieve of nature, he felt more freely and vividly the positive turn his destiny had taken. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10117" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10212">That feeling would have been even more pure and complete if Renzo had been able to guess that, only a few days later, the rain would wash away the contagion. After that downpour, although the lazaretto could not restore to the living all the lives it contained, it ceased to swallow any others. Within a week, homes and shops opened their doors, and talk of the quarantine quieted to a whisper. All that would remain of the plague were the occasional vestiges that a scourge always leaves in its wake. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10213" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10264">And so our traveler went on his merry way, without worrying about where or how or when or even if he should stop to spend the night. His only concern was to keep moving and get home as quickly as possible, find someone with whom to speak, tell his story, and then set off immediately for Pasturo to find Agnese. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10265" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10296">As he walked his head was filled with the events of the day, but amid the miseries, the horrors, and the dangers a single thought floated to the top: “I have found her! She has recovered! She is mine!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10297" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10328">And then he would jump up and down, splashing water everywhere, like a poodle shaking off after a swim in the pond. Sometimes he was happy just to rub his hands together, and to continue on with even greater ardor. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10329" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10382">As he stared at the road ahead, he pieced together, so to speak, his thoughts from the morning and day before. He took special delight in remembering the thoughts he had tried to expel: the doubts and difficulties, of not just whether he would find her, but if he would find her alive among the multitude of the dead and dying. “And I found her alive!” he concluded. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10383" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10437">He thought back to the most dreadful circumstances of that day. He pictured himself with the door knocker in his hand: Will she be there or won’t she? And the rude welcome he found! He had barely enough time to absorb his disappointment before the deranged mob was upon him. And the lazaretto, that sea of people! “I tried to find her there! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10438" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10440">And I did!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10441" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10466">He remembered his surveillance of the procession of convalescents: What an awful moment! How heartbreaking not to find her among them! At that point, nothing had mattered to him anymore. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10467" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10471">And the women’s quarter! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10472" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10486">And there, behind that hut, when he least expected it, that voice, that unmistakable voice! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10487" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10490">And to see her, see her on her feet! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10491" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10503">But then? There was still that one last knot of the vow, tighter than ever. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10504" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10506">This, too, had been untied. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10507" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10527">And his hatred of Don Rodrigo, gnawing at him constantly, exacerbating every difficulty, poisoning every joy. That, too, had vanished. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10528" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10559">I cannot imagine a man more alive with joy, if not for his uncertainties about Agnese, his sad forebodings about Padre Cristoforo, and the persistence of the plague. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10560" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10570">He reached Sesto toward evening. The rain showed no sign of stopping. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10571" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10592">Although he was drenched to the bone, he didn’t even consider seeking lodgings, knowing how difficult it would be. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10593" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10616">His only discomfort was his appetite, since it would take much more than a meager soup from a Capuchin to nourish a joy like his. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10617" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10638">He looked around for a bakery, saw one, and got two loaves of bread, which were extended to him with tongs, accompanied by all the other ceremonies. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10639" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10647">One in his pocket, one in his mouth, and he was on his way again. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10648" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10666">By the time he got to Monza, night had fallen, but he still managed to find the gate that set him on the right road. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10667" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10692">Apart from that (which, to be honest, was a big advantage), you can imagine what the road looked like, and what it was turning into from one moment to the next. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10693" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10740">Sunken between two embankments (as all the roads used to be: I’m sure I mentioned this earlier), like a riverbed, on that night you could well have called the road, if not a river, then at least a millstream, with potholes waiting to suck in your feet and your shoes. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10741" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10787">Renzo navigated it as best he could without losing his patience, without swearing, and without regrets, knowing that no matter how difficult it was, every step would lead him forward, the rain would stop when it pleased God, daybreak would arrive at the usual time, and the distance he had traveled would then be behind him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10788" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10803">I should add that he only started thinking when he couldn’t avoid it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10804" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10871">Thoughts were distractions. His mind was more occupied with revisiting the sad years that had passed by: so many predicaments, so much adversity, so many times that he’d been about to lose all hope and give up. He contrasted those memories with his dreams of a very different future: the arrival of Lucia, the wedding, setting up house, telling stories about the past, and spending the rest of their lives together. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10872" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10962">And what did he do whenever he found himself at a fork in the road? Whether inexperience, the darkness, or pure chance always put him on the right path, I couldn’t tell you. When in his later years he’d tell the story in great detail, and at great length (everything leads me to believe that our anonymous author heard the story, more than once, from Renzo himself), he would say that as far as he could remember, the whole night might as well have been a dream. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10963" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10975">The fact remains that, at daybreak, he found himself by the banks of the Adda. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_10976" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11024">It never stopped raining but, at one point, it slowed from a deluge to a thin, soft, and steady drizzle. The high scattered clouds created a veil that was thick but soft and diaphanous. By the light of dawn, Renzo could see the surrounding countryside, and in the middle, his own village. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11025" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11039">At the sight of it, his words fell short. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11040" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11062">I myself can add nothing except to say that everything he saw—the mountains, the nearby Resegone, and the Lecco territory—had become something that belonged to him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11063" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11127">He looked down at himself, and was startled to realize how different his outward appearance was, compared to how he felt inside. His clothes were wrinkled and stuck to his body. He was drenched from his head to his waist, and covered in mud from the waist down. The few clean spots looked more like they were the splatters and stains. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11128" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11158">If he had seen himself in a full-length mirror, he would have been even more shocked: the brim of his hat drooped and hung limply, while his hair hung down, sticking to his face. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11159" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11197">He may have been tired, but he didn’t feel that way. The combination of the early morning breeze, the chill of the night, and the light rain only increased his sense of triumph and his desire to walk even faster. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11198" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11225">He’s in Pescate. He’s walking along the lower stretch of the Adda, and casting a melancholy gaze at Pescarenico. He crosses the bridge. He traverses the roads and fields in what feels like an instant, and arrives at the home of his friend and host, who was already awake, and standing in the doorway to check on the weather. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11226" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11270">He looked up at that drenched, muddy, and—let’s just say it—filthy, dirty figure, who somehow still appeared lively and carefree. In all his days, he’d never seen a man who had looked worse, and yet was still so happy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11271" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11278">“Oh!” he said. “Already back? And in this weather? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11279" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11280">How did it go?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11281" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11288">“She’s there,” said Renzo, “she’s there.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11289" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11289">“Healthy?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11290" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11293">“Recovered, which is better. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11294" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11303">I’ll have to thank the Lord and the Blessed Virgin as long as I live. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11304" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11313">But great things. Amazing things. I’ll tell you everything later.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11314" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11317">“What in the world happened to you?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11318" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11320">“Aren’t I beautiful?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11321" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11338">“Honestly, you could use your top half to wipe down your bottom half. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11339" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11347">But wait a minute. Let me build you a nice fire.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11348" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11361">“I won’t say no. Do you know where my search for Lucia took me? To the gates of the lazaretto. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11362" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11372">But that didn’t stop me! The weather did its job, and I did mine.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11373" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11404">His friend went out and came back with two armloads of firewood. He set one pile down on the floor, the other on the hearth, and quickly got a nice fire going using the embers from the night before. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11405" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11432">Meanwhile Renzo took off his hat, shook it a couple of times, and tossed it on the floor. Peeling off his doublet was more of a struggle. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11433" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11471">From the pocket of his breeches he removed his dagger. The sheaf was wet, as if he had left it to soak. He set it on a bench and said, “My knife is drenched, too. But it’s only water! Not blood! Thank God. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11472" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11475">But I came close! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11476" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11483">I’ll tell you about it later,” and he rubbed his hands together. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11484" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11509">“Can you do me another favor?” he added. “Can you fetch me that bundle I left up in the bedroom? It’ll take a while before the clothes on my back are dry.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11510" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11534">Returning with the bundle, his friend said, “I imagine you must be hungry, too. I’m sure there was plenty to drink while you were on the road, but did you find anything to eat?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11535" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11553">“I managed to buy two loaves of bread late yesterday, but to tell you the truth, they barely hit the spot.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11554" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11585">“Let me take care of you,” said the friend. He filled a kettle with water and then hooked it to the chain, adding, “I’m going to milk the cow. When I’m back with the milk, the water will be ready and we can cook a nice polenta. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11586" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11591">In the meantime, make yourself comfortable.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11592" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11616">Left to himself, Renzo struggled to peel off the rest of his clothing, which was glued to his skin. He dried himself off and got dressed in clean clothes from head to toe. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11617" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11630">The friend returned and went to the kettle. Renzo sat down in the meantime, and waited. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11631" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11641">“Now I can feel how tired I am,” he said, “what a slog! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11642" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11653">But this is nothing: I’ve got stories enough to tell all day. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11654" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11656">Milan is in terrible shape! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11657" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11661">The things you see! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11662" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11666">The things you touch! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11667" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11674">Things that make you feel disgusting. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11675" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11688">I’d almost say that this little downpour is just what was needed to rinse away the filth. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11689" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11698">And the things those gentlemen down there wanted to do to me! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11699" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11699">I’ll tell you all about it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11700" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11710">But if you saw the lazaretto, you’d drown in misery. But enough. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11711" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11714">I’ll tell you the whole story. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11715" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11743">She’s there, and she’ll come here, and she’ll be my wife. And you have to be my witness. And plague or no plague, for a few hours at least I want us to be happy.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11744" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11825">As promised, he spent the whole day telling the story to his friend, who, especially since it continued to drizzle, spent the day at home, sitting next to Renzo or busying himself with his wine vat and cask, and other chores in preparation for the vintage. Renzo was only too happy to lend him a hand, since he was the type who, as he used to say, gets more tired from doing nothing than from working. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11826" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11851">But he could not resist making a quick trip to Agnese’s house, to peek through one window in particular, and to rub his hands together again. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11852" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11863">He returned before anyone could see him and went straight to bed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11864" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11883">He got up before daybreak. Although the skies were still not clear, the rain had stopped, so he set out for Pasturo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11884" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11905">It was early when he arrived, still feeling anxious and eager to bring all these matters to a close, as you the reader might be, too. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11906" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11920">He asked around for Agnese, heard that she was fine, and was directed to the isolated cottage where she lived. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11921" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11967">Arriving there, he called out her name from the street. At the sound of his voice, she raced to the window, and stood there with her mouth agape, struggling to emit I don’t know what word or sound. Renzo went first, saying, “Lucia has recovered. I saw her the day before yesterday. She sends her greetings and will come soon. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11968" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11977">And then I’ve got…I’ve got some things to tell you.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_11978" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12018">Between her surprise at his appearance, her happiness at the news, and her eagerness to know more, Agnese would start to exclaim, then to ask a question, but never completing either one. Then, forgetting the precautions she had long been accustomed to taking, she said, “I’m coming downstairs to open up for you.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12019" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12029">“Wait. And the plague?” said Renzo. “You haven’t had it, I believe.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12030" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12033">“I haven’t. And you?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12034" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12041">“I have. But you have to be careful. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12042" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12054">I’ve just come from Milan and, as you’ll hear, I was in the plague up to my ears. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12055" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12076">Yes, I’ve changed my clothes, from head to toe, but it’s a nasty disease. It sticks to you, sometimes, like a curse. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12077" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12117">And since God has preserved you so far, I want you to be careful until this contagion has ended. Because you are our mother, and I want us all to live together joyfully for many years to come, in recompense for the great suffering that we, or at least I, have had to bear.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12118" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12120">“But…” Agnese started to say. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12121" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12128">“Shhh!” Renzo interrupted. “No ifs, ands, or buts. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12129" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12143">I know what you want to say, but as you’ll hear, ‘but’ is a word we don’t need to use anymore. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12144" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12158">Let’s go someplace in the open, where we can speak freely, without danger, and you’ll hear about everything.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12159" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12184">Agnese pointed to a garden behind the house, adding, “Go in around the back. You’ll see two benches facing each other that are perfect for us. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12185" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12187">I’ll be right there.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12188" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12284">Renzo went to sit on one bench. A minute later, Agnese was on the other. And since you, my readers, know all about the events leading up to their reunion, can you imagine if you had been there yourself, to witness with your own eyes their animated conversation, to hear with your own ears their stories, questions, explanations, exclamations, condolences, and rejoicing—about Don Rodrigo, Padre Cristoforo, and all the rest—and their descriptions of the future, as bright and rosy as their dreams from the past? I’m sure that you would not only have enjoyed it, but you would have been the last to leave. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12285" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12320">Yet you wouldn’t much care to read it, in my opinion, and would much rather imagine what they were saying, if I were to set the whole conversation down on paper, with mute words of ink, and not a single new event to relate. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12321" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12398">The conclusion was reached that all three of them would set up their new household in the Bergamasque village where Renzo had already established himself. As for when, nothing could be decided since it depended on the plague and other circumstances. As soon as the danger was past, Agnese would return home to wait for Lucia, unless Lucia got there first. In the meantime, Renzo would stop by Pasturo often to see his mother and keep her informed of any new developments. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12399" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12430">Before he left, he offered her money, saying, “I still have all those coins. I made my own vow, not to touch them until things were cleared up. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12431" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12450">So, if you need money, bring me a bowl filled with water and vinegar, and I’ll drop fifty shiny new scudi inside.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12451" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12472">“No, no,” said Agnese, “I’ve already got more than enough for me. Keep what you have for yourself: You’ll need it to set up house.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12473" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12490">Renzo went back to his village, buoyed by the joy of finding another person he loved safe and sound. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12491" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12518">He spent the rest of the day and night at his friend’s house. The next morning, he set off on the road again, this time toward his adopted village. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12519" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12546">He found Bortolo in good health, and less afraid of losing it, since in the past several days, things had quickly taken a turn for the better there, too. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12547" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12588">Fewer people were falling ill, and they were no longer suffering from the same terrible disease. Gone were the deadly bruises and the violent symptoms. Instead there were low, mainly intermittent fevers, with, at most, small discolored swellings that could be treated like normal boils. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12589" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12612">The village was already looking different. The survivors were starting to emerge, contacting one another and exchanging condolences and congratulations. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12613" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12647">Talk was already underway about reopening the factories. The bosses were already thinking of finding and hiring workers, especially in trades where there had already been shortages before the epidemic, such as silk-working. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12648" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12671">Renzo promised his cousin he would return to work, without pretense (provided he received the required approvals) once he was married and settled in the village. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12672" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12723">In the meantime, he made the necessary preparations: He found a bigger house, which misfortune had made easy and inexpensive, but he had to dip into his savings to equip it with furniture and household equipment. He didn’t have to sacrifice too much because everything was so cheap, and there were more things to buy than people to buy them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12724" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12740">After I don’t know how many days, he returned to his hometown, which he found had changed even more remarkably. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12741" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12779">He hurried off to Pasturo at once. Agnese was in good spirits and ready to return home, if her home was still there. So he accompanied her to Pescarenico, but I will not tell you everything they must have felt or said at the sight of those familiar places again. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12780" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12786">Agnese found everything as she had left it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12787" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12812">She could not resist saying that, for once, since the house had belonged to a poor widow and a poor girl, the angels must have kept watch over it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12813" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12861">“That other time,” she added, “you would have thought that God had his eyes somewhere else, and wasn’t thinking of us, since he allowed the few possessions we had to be taken away. Well, now He’s gone and done the opposite, because He found a way to send me a tidy sum of money that helped me replace everything. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12862" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12895">Well, not exactly everything. There was Lucia’s trousseau, all nice new things, which they stole along with the rest: That still has to be taken care of. But lo and behold, now we’re retrieving everything we lost. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12896" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12962">If someone had only told me when I was struggling to put together that first trousseau: ‘Poor woman, do you think you’re doing this for Lucia? You have no idea who you’re doing it for! Heaven knows what sort of creature will get those linens, that fabric.’ As for Lucia, who really does need a trousseau, now a good soul is going to take care of it, a woman I don’t even know.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12963" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12996">Agnese’s first order of business was to make her poor little cottage as hospitable as she could manage for that good soul. Then she went looking for some silk to spin, to kill time by keeping busy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_12997" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13024">Renzo, for his part, was not idle during those already long days. Luckily he had a second trade. He started farming again. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13025" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13060">Occasionally, he helped his friend, who was fortunate in times like these to have at his service a worker, and such a skilled worker at that. Other times, he cultivated and tilled Agnese’s garden, which had gone to seed in her absence. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13061" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13086">As for his own land, he did not tend to it at all, for it was as tangled as a head of hair, and required more than two hands to revive it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13087" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13131">He did not even set foot in it, or in his house for that matter. The sight of such devastation would have been too painful, and he had already decided to get rid of everything, at any price, and to invest what little profit he could make from it into his new home. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13132" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13169">If the survivors were like people returned from the dead, then you could say that Renzo’s village considered him resurrected twice over. Everyone welcomed and congratulated him, and they all wanted to hear his story. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13170" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13175">You might be wondering: What about that warrant for his arrest? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13176" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13201">He didn’t let it trouble him. He almost didn’t give it a second thought, assuming that the men in charge of executing it weren’t thinking about it, either, and he was not wrong. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13202" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13288">And it wasn’t just because the plague had turned so many things upside down. As you might have noticed in other parts of this story, it was common in those days for both general and specific decrees against individuals to remain null and void if they were not acted on immediately, unless some powerful personal animosity kept them alive and enforceable. These decrees were like bullets from a musket that have missed their target and end up on the ground, where they don’t threaten anyone. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13289" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13299">But that was a consequence of the great ease with which those decrees were issued. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13300" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13318">A man’s actions are limited, especially when orders outstrip his ability to carry them out. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13319" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13328">For what enters the sleeve might not fit through the cuffs. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13329" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13419">— If anyone is wondering how Renzo got along with Don Abbondio during this time, I’ll just say that they kept their distance from each other. The priest was afraid to hear any hint of marriage, since the mere mention of the word conjured up images of Don Rodrigo with his bravi, on the one hand, and the Cardinal with his arguments, on the other. Renzo did not want to tempt fate by stirring up difficulties and useless talk. He was determined not to bring up the matter before its time had come. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13420" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13426">If he needed to talk, he could go to Agnese. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13427" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13433">“Do you think she’ll come soon?” one would ask. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13434" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13453">“I hope so,” the other would answer. And a little later, the person who answered would ask the same question. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13454" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13479">They managed to pass the time with these and similar methods, but the more time passed, the slower it seemed to go by. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13480" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13581">I’ll condense all that time into a single moment for the reader with a short summary. A few days after Renzo’s visit, Lucia left the lazaretto with the good widow. Upon leaving, they had to quarantine, so they confined themselves to the widow’s home. They spent part of the time putting together Lucia’s trousseau, to which Lucia herself contributed, despite the widow’s protests. Once their quarantine had been lifted, the widow left her shop and house in the care of her brother, the commissioner, and they made their preparations for the trip. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13582" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13633">I could simply say: They left, they arrived, and all that followed, but despite my desire to hurry things along for the reader’s sake, three things happened during that interval that we cannot ignore. And for two of them, at least, I think the reader would agree that I would be wrong to do so. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13634" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13698">First, after the commotion of their first confidences, Lucia was able to tell the widow about her adventures in greater detail, and in a more orderly fashion. She spoke more openly about the Signora who had sheltered her at the Monza convent. The widow told her a few things that unlocked many mysteries and filled her with a sad and fearful astonishment. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13699" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13756">She learned that the hapless nun had been ordered by the Cardinal to a convent in Milan under suspicion of atrocious acts. After much raging and struggling, she had repented and confessed. Her current life was a voluntary punishment so severe that no one could imagine anything worse, short of death. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13757" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13793">If someone wishes to know more details about this sad story, I refer you to the book I mentioned earlier. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13794" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13821">Second, Lucia, with more sorrow than surprise, learned from the other Capuchins in the lazaretto that Fra Cristoforo had died from the plague. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13822" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13849">Finally, in an effort to complete what she called her “duties” before leaving, Lucia wanted to know what had happened to her former protectors, and if either of them was still alive. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13850" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13865">The widow accompanied her to the house, where they learned that both were now among the multitudes of the departed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13866" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13907">For Donna Prassede, there was nothing left to say about her except that she was dead. But since Don Ferrante was a learned man, our anonymous author felt he should say a little more about him. At my own risk, I will transcribe more or less what he wrote. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13908" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13954">He tells us that Don Ferrante was one of the most resolute deniers of the plague from the first mention, an opinion he upheld consistently until the bitter end, not by raising a ruckus, like the common folk, but through arguments that no one could criticize, at least, as incoherent. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13955" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13994">“In rerum natura,” he would say, “only two categories of things exist: substances and accidents. If I can prove that the contagion is neither one nor the other, then I will have demonstrated that it does not exist, and that it is, in fact, a chimera. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13995" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13997">So hear me out. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_13998" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14004">Substances must be either spiritual or material. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14005" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14021">No one would claim that the contagion is a spiritual substance, so it is pointless to suggest that it is. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14022" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14029">Material substances must be either simple or compound. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14030" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14042">Well, the contagion is not a simple substance—air, water, fire or earth—as can be demonstrated in a few words. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14043" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14063">It is not air, otherwise it would immediately float up to its own sphere, rather than pass from one body to another. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14064" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14073">It is not water, otherwise it would be damp and dry out in the winds. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14074" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14078">It is not fire, otherwise it would burn. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14079" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14084">It is not earth, otherwise it would be visible. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14085" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14107">Nor is it a compound substance, because then it would have to be something tangible, that you could see or touch. Has anyone seen this contagion? Has anyone touched it? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14108" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14114">“Let us now consider whether it might be an accident. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14115" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14117">Here the possibilities are even worse. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14118" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14144">These fine doctors tell us that the plague is communicated from one body to another. This is their main argument, their pretext, for issuing so many senseless orders. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14145" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14182">Now, if it was an accident, that would mean the plague was transmitted accidentally. But these two words are contradictory, since in all philosophy, there is nothing more clear, more liquid than this: an accident cannot pass from one body to another. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14183" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14213">So to avoid crashing into Scylla, one monster, officials are forced to say that this is a manufactured accident, which only steers them toward Charybdis, another monster. Because if the contagion is manufactured, then it is not communicable and it does not propagate, contrary to all their babble. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14214" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14226">In light of this, what is the point of talking about cutaneous bruises, cutaneous eruptions, and clusters of pimples…?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14227" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14234">Once a man burst out with, “What a bunch of rubbish!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14235" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14250">“No, no,” Don Ferrante continued, “that’s not what I’m saying. Science is science. You just have to know how to apply it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14251" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14279">Cutaneous bruises, cutaneous eruptions, pimple clusters, swollen glands, purple buboes, black boils: they’re all respected words, each with its own good and proper meaning. What I am saying is that they have nothing to do with the question at hand. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14280" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14293">Who would deny that such things may or rather do exist? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14294" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14300">What we need to know is where they come from.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14301" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14308">This is where Don Ferrante began to run into trouble. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14309" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14351">When he was simply attacking the idea of a contagion, everyone was all ears. Never underestimate the authority of a learned man trying to prove to the public things of which they are already persuaded. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14352" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14424">But then he started identifying and trying to demonstrate that the physicians’ error lay not in their assertion that a dreadful general disease existed, but rather in the cause they assigned to it. This was in the early days, when no one wanted to even hear the word plague, so his assertions faced rebellious, intractable tongues, rather than sympathetic ears. No one wanted to hear his long sermons, so he could only expound on his doctrine in bits and pieces. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14425" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14458">“Even those who believe this contagion is airborne must admit its true cause,” he would say, “and that is the fatal conjunction of Saturn and Jupiter. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14459" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14468">And who ever heard of influences propagating…? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14469" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14475">Would physicians deny that such influences exist? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14476" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14482">Deny the existence of the stars? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14483" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14501">Or would they say that the stars are up there doing nothing, like needles in a pincushion? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14502" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14539">But what I cannot figure out about the physicians is this: They admit that we are all living under an evil conjunction, and then come to tell us, and with what gall: ‘Don’t touch this,’ ‘Don’t touch that,’ and we’ll be safe! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14540" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14556">As if avoiding contact between earthly bodies could prevent the virtual effect of celestial bodies! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14557" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14563">And all that fuss about the burning of rags! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14564" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14569">Poor people! Would you burn Jupiter? Would you burn Saturn?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14570" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14602">His fretus—meaning, on the basis of these arguments—he took no precautions against the plague. He caught it and went to bed to die, like an operatic hero, blaming it on the stars. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14603" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14607">And his famous library? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap37-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14608" targetEnd="quarantana/cap37.xml#c37_14615">You might be able to find it at the secondhand bookstalls that line the canal. </note>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>