<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>2022</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed: a novel</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
          <date>2022</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Michael Moore</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="english_2022_cap3">
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10016">Lucia entered the ground-floor room while a distressed Renzo was relating the news to an equally distressed Agnese. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10017" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10072">Both of them turned toward the one who knew more than them, and from whom they were awaiting an explanation that could only be painful. Both of them, in their sorrow and with the different types of love they felt for Lucia, could barely contain their equally different annoyance with her at having kept silent about a matter—especially a matter like this. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10073" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10088">Although Agnese was anxious to hear what her daughter had to say, she could not hold back a few words of reproach. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10089" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10097">“To keep such a thing from your mother!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10098" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10108">“Now I’ll tell you everything,” Lucia replied, drying her eyes with her apron. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10109" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10122">“Tell me!” shouted the parent. “Tell me!” shouted the groom. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10123" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10137">“Mother of God!” Lucia exclaimed. “Who would have believed he would go this far!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10138" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10210">Choking back her tears, she related the events of a few days earlier. While she was lingering behind her companions on her way home from the silk-spinning mill, Don Rodrigo had passed by in the company of another man. He tried to detain her with words that, as she put it, were not very nice. Ignoring him, she quickened her step to catch up with her friends. In the meantime she heard the other man guffaw and Don Rodrigo say, “How much do you want to bet?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10211" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10240">The next day, the two men were at the same spot, but this time Lucia was surrounded by her companions, her eyes lowered. The second man snickered and Don Rodrigo said, “We’ll see, we’ll see.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10241" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10252">“Thank heavens,” Lucia continued, “it was the last day at the mill. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10253" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10255">I immediately told—” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10256" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10274">“Told who?” asked Agnese, not without some resentment, eager to hear the name of the confidant Lucia had preferred to herself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10275" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10288">“Padre Cristoforo, in confession, Mother,” Lucia replied in a soft apologetic tone. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10289" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10348">“I told him everything the last time you and I went to the monastery chapel. If you remember, that morning I busied myself, with one thing, then another, so I could linger behind to wait for other people from the village going in that same direction, and walk in their company. Because after that encounter, I was so frightened of the streets…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10349" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10359">Upon hearing the revered name of Padre Cristoforo, Agnese simmered down. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10360" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10372">“You did the right thing,” she said, “but why didn’t you tell your mother everything?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10373" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10430">Lucia had two good reasons for not telling her. The first, so as not to upset or frighten the good woman over something she could not remedy. The second, to avoid the risk of sending tongues wagging with a story that was best kept safely buried: especially since Lucia had initially hoped that her wedding would put an end to the loathsome persecution. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10431" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10440">Of these two reasons, however, she only offered the first. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10441" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10470">“And you,” she added, turning to Renzo with a voice meant to make a friend see the error of his ways, “was I supposed to tell you, too? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10471" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10475">Well, now you know, unfortunately!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10476" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10483">“What did the padre tell you?” asked Agnese. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10484" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10516">“He told me to get married as quickly as we could, and in the meantime to stay home and pray to God. He hoped that once Don Rodrigo stopped seeing me, he’d stop bothering me. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10517" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10563">It was then that I forced myself,” she continued, turning to Renzo again, without raising her eyes to his face, and turning bright red, “that I asked you so boldly to hurry things up, so we could get married before the date we had set. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10564" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10570">Who knows what you must have thought of me! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10571" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10591">But I was doing it for our own good, and I had been advised, and I was convinced…and this morning, it was the farthest thing from my mind…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10592" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10602">Her words were cut short by a violent burst of tears. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10603" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10628">“That scoundrel! That monster! That villain!” shouted Renzo, pacing back and forth in the room, occasionally clutching the handle of his dagger. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10629" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10637">“What a predicament, for the love of God!” exclaimed Agnese. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10638" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10665">The young man stood before Lucia while she wept. He gazed at her with a tenderness both dejected and irate, and said, “I’ll make that murderer regret this!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10666" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10674">“No, Renzo, please, for the love of heaven!” Lucia shouted. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10675" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10680">“No, no! For the love of heaven! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10681" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10697">The Good Lord also looks out for the poor. How can you expect him to help us if we do wrong?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10698" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10705">“No, no, for the love of heaven!” echoed Agnese. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10706" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10736">“Renzo,” said Lucia more calmly, radiating hope and determination, “you have a trade and I’m a good worker. Let’s go far away, to someplace where he’ll never hear of us again.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10737" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10740">“And then what, Lucia? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10741" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10746">We’re still not man and wife! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10747" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10755">Do you think Don Abbondio will let us get married somewhere else? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10756" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10759">A man like him? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10760" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10764">If we were already married, then we could…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10765" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10790">Lucia started crying again and all three remained in silence, with a dejection that stood in stark contrast to their festive attire. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10791" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10801">“Listen to what I have to say, children,” Agnese said after a few moments had passed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10802" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10816">“I came into the world before you, and I know a thing or two about it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10817" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10829">There’s no need to be so upset. Things are never as bad as they seem. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10830" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10862">To us poor folk things always seem more entangled than they really are because we don’t know which end to grab. But sometimes an opinion, a word or two from an educated man…Here’s what I want to say. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10863" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10887">Take my advice, Renzo. Go to Lecco and look up Professor Argle-Bargle—but don’t call him that, for the love of heaven, it’s a nickname. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10888" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10896">Look up Professor Argle-Bargle and tell him…now what’s his name? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10897" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10910">Oh, darn! I don’t know his real name. But everyone calls him that. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10911" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10928">Well, go looking for a tall, thin, bald man with a red nose and a raspberry birthmark on his cheek.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10929" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10934">“I know him by sight,” Renzo said. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10935" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10942">“Good,” Agnese continued. “He’s a prince among men. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10943" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10982">I’ve seen more than one person who was in a stickier situation than a fly in honey, not knowing where to turn, and after just one hour alone with Professor Argle-Bargle (be careful not to call him that!), I’m telling you, they were able to laugh about it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_10983" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11012">Take with you those four capons—poor things—whose necks I was supposed to wring for the Sunday banquet, and bring them to him. Because you should never go empty-handed to see a gentleman. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11013" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11037">Tell him everything that happened and see what he has to say, off the top of his head, things that would never occur to us in a year.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11038" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11114">Renzo embraced this proposal enthusiastically. Lucia approved and Agnese, proud of her solution, took the poor animals from the coop, one at a time, squeezed their eight legs together as if she was making a bouquet of flowers, tied them together with string, and handed them to Renzo. After giving and receiving words of encouragement, he left by the back door so that none of the boys would see him. Otherwise they would have run after him calling, “The groom! The groom!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11115" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11142">Crossing the fields, or rather “the places,” as the locals call them, he went down the footpaths, growing more agitated as he reflected on his misfortune, and pondering what to say to Professor Argle-Bargle. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11143" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11189">I’ll leave it to the reader to imagine what the journey must have been like for those poor animals, tied together and carried upside down by their claws, by a man who, in the grips of so many passions, had a gesture to accompany each thought agitating his mind. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11190" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11241">One moment he was punching the air in a rage, the next he was raising his arms in despair, and the next waving them menacingly, all the while shaking the birds violently and jiggling their four dangling heads up and down. Through it all, they kept pecking at one another, as is too often the case with fellows in misfortune. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11242" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11253">Once he reached Lecco, he asked for the lawyer’s residence. It was pointed out to him and he headed in that direction. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11254" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11288">At the lawyer’s front door he was overcome by the shyness typical of the unlettered poor in the company of a learned gentleman, and he forgot all the speeches he had prepared. After a glance at the capons, however, he took heart. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11289" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11301">Entering the kitchen, he asked the maid if he could speak to the lawyer. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11302" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11333">She laid her eyes on the animals and, as if accustomed to such offerings, grabbed hold of one end while Renzo pulled on the other, so the lawyer would see that he had not come empty-handed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11334" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11344">The master of the house appeared right when the woman said, “Give ’em here and go in.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11345" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11365">Renzo made a deep bow. The lawyer welcomed him kindly saying, “Come, my son,” and ushered him into his study. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11366" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11464">It was a large room in which portraits of the twelve Caesars were arranged on three of the walls. The fourth was occupied by a large shelf of dusty old books. In the middle of the room was a desk piled high with depositions, petitions, claims, and decrees, surrounded by three or four chairs. An armchair to one side had a high square back and corners topped by two wooden horn-shaped ornaments. It was upholstered in leather with large bosses, some of which had fallen off long ago, leaving places where the unfastened edges curled up. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11465" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11496">The lawyer was in his dressing gown, that is to say, attired in a threadbare garment he had worn many years earlier, when he used to go to Milan to argue important cases before the court. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11497" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11511">He closed the door and encouraged the young man to speak, saying, “Tell me about your case.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11512" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11518">“I wish to speak with you in confidence.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11519" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11528">“Well, here I am,” the lawyer replied, “speak,” and sat down in his chair. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11529" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11553">Renzo, standing before the desk with one hand on the crown of his hat, while turning it with the other, began his prepared speech. “I would like to know from you, a learned man…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11554" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11561">“Just the facts,” the lawyer interrupted. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11562" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11572">“You’ll have to excuse me. We poor folk don’t know how to speak properly. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11573" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11575">So what I’d like to know…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11576" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11596">“Damn it! You’re all the same! Rather than tell me the facts, you want to ask questions, since you’ve already cooked up some scheme or other.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11597" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11600">“I’m sorry, sir. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11601" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11614">I’d like to know whether it’s against the law to threaten a priest for refusing to perform a marriage.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11615" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11629">“Now I see,” said the lawyer to himself, although he really hadn’t. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11630" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11632">“Now I see.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11633" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11668">He instantly turned serious, but a seriousness mixed with compassion and concern. He pursed his lips, emitting an inarticulate sound that hinted at a sentiment which was clearly expressed by his first words. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11669" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11673">“A serious case, my son, a case that is indeed contemplated by the law. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11674" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11680">You were right to come to me. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11681" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11697">It is a clear-cut case, provided for in a hundred decrees, and…to be precise, in a decree issued last year, by the present governor. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11698" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11705">Now I’ll show it to you, so we can get to the heart of the matter.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11706" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11732">As he spoke, he stood up from his chair and stuck his hands into that jumble of papers, rearranging them from bottom to top, as if sifting through grain in a barrel. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11733" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11734">“Where is it, now? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11735" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11738">Come out, come out, wherever you are! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11739" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11744">You need to have so many things at hand! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11745" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11754">But it must be here. It’s an important decree! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11755" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11757">Ah! Here it is!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11758" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11776">He plucked out a piece of paper, spread it out, glanced at the date, and adopting a more serious expression, shouted, “The fifteenth of October 1627! Right I was! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11777" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11788">From last year. A fresh decree—these are the ones we have to worry about. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11789" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11791">Do you know how to read, my son?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11792" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11795">“A little, sir.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11796" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11802">“Well, then. Look over my shoulder and you’ll see.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11803" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11829">Waving the decree in the air, he started to read aloud, racing through some passages in a mumble, and pausing on others more deliberately, with great expression, if needed: </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11830" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11928">“Whereas, by the decree published by order of the Duke of Feria on the fourteenth of December 1620, and confirmed by the Most Illustrious and Excellent Gonzalo Fernández de Córdoba, etcetera, urgent and severe measures were taken against the oppressions, coercions, and acts of tyranny that some dare to commit against His Majesty’s devoted vassals, and nevertheless, the frequency of the violations, and their maliciousness, etcetera, have increased to such an extent as to force His Excellency, etcetera. Therefore, after consultation with the Senate and the Council, etcetera, he has decided upon the publication of the present decree. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11929" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11984">“And, starting with acts of tyranny, experience shows that many, both in the cities and in the countryside…Did you hear that?…of this State, in a tyrannical manner, do intimidate and oppress the vulnerable in various ways, such as forcing people to sell or to lease properties…etcetera— “Where are you? Ah, here you are. Listen to this: “—and to perform or not perform marriages—” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11985" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11990">“My situation exactly,” said Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_11991" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12039">“Listen, listen, there’s more, and then we’ll see the penalties.” “To testify or not, to leave one’s place of residence, etcetera, force some to pay a debt, another to leave a certain personage alone, another to purchase his flour at a specific granary—This part has nothing to do with us. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12040" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12061">Ah, here we are—force a priest not to perform his duties, or to do things he should not. Eh?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12062" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12070">“It sounds like this decree was tailor-made for me.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12071" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12102">“Eh? It really does. Listen, listen: All these and other such criminal acts, whether committed by feudal lords, noblemen, burghers, farmers, or commoners— No one’s left out: It’s like the Last Judgment! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12103" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12198">Now you’ll hear the penalties. “All these and other such criminal actions, although already prohibited, the determination has nevertheless been reached that stricter measures are required, and His Excellency, by the present decree, without exception, etcetera, orders and commands that anyone who commits in any manner whatsoever the above-mentioned crimes or similar ones, shall by all the judges of this State be subjected to monetary and corporal punishment, ranging from banishment, to the galleys, and even death—a mere bagatelle!—at the discretion of His Excellency, or of the Senate, depending on the gravity of the cases, persons, and circumstances. And this un-re-mis-si-bly and with all severity, etcetera. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12199" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12203">That’s quite a mouthful, isn’t it? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12204" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12229">And look at the signatures: Gonzalo Fernández de Córdoba, and farther down, Platonus, and even farther down, Vidit Ferrer. They didn’t miss a thing.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12230" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12261">As the lawyer read, Renzo followed slowly with his eyes, trying to figure out the exact meaning and to identify the sacrosanct words that seemed to help his case. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12262" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12282">The lawyer, amazed to see his new client more attentive than terrified, said to himself, “Is he a hardened criminal?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12283" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12294">“Aha!” he said aloud. “I see that you’ve cut off your forelock. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12295" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12306">You were smart to do so. But since you are placing yourself in my hands, there was no need. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12307" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12323">The case is serious, but you don’t know what I’m capable of, given the chance.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12324" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12383">To understand the lawyer’s remark, you need to know or recall that in those days, bravi and hooligans of every sort used to sport a forelock that they pulled over their face, like a visor, when they assaulted someone, in circumstances where they needed a disguise, and the deed required both strength and caution. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12384" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12462">The decrees did not fail to remark on this fashion. His Excellency [the Marquis de la Hinojosa] commands that anyone who wears his hair so long that it covers his forehead down to his eyebrows, or wears a braid in front of or behind his ears, will incur the penalty of three hundred scudi, and in the event of inability to pay, to three years in the galleys, for the first offense, and for the second, an even greater monetary or corporal punishment, at the discretion of His Excellency. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12463" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12524">Allowing, however, that in the event of baldness or other reasonable cause such as a birthmark or scar, such men may, for the sake of their decorum and health, wear their hair as long as necessary to cover such defects and no more, being careful not to exceed duty and pure necessity, in order (not) to incur the penalties imposed on other transgressors. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12525" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12601">Barbers are likewise ordered, under penalty of one hundred scudi or three yanks of the corda to be administered in public, and even greater corporal punishment, at the discretion as above, not to leave those whose hair they cut with the above-mentioned braids, forelocks, curls, or hair that is longer than customary, either in the front, on the sides, or behind the ears, but that it be the same length, as above, except in cases of baldness or other defects, as above. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12602" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12626">The forelock was almost an element of one’s armor, a badge worn by bravi and other troublemakers, who as a result were commonly known as ciuffi or “forelocks.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12627" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12683">This term has remained and is still alive in dialect with a more innocuous meaning. Every single one of my Milanese readers, perhaps, will remember having been called as a child a ciuffo or ciuffetto by parents, a teacher, a neighborhood friend, or a servant. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12684" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12699">“The truth is that, being a poor boy,” Renzo replied, “I’ve never worn a forelock in my life.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12700" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12724">“We’re getting nowhere,” the lawyer replied, shaking his head with a smile that was both mischievous and impatient, “if you don’t trust me, we’re getting nowhere. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12725" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12741">Let me tell you, son, that he who lies to his lawyer is a fool who’ll tell the truth to the judge. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12742" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12753">You have to speak plainly to a lawyer, who can then proceed to make things more complicated. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12754" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12771">If you want me to help you, you have to tell me everything, from A to Z, with your heart in hand, the way you would your confessor. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12772" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12800">You have to give me the name of the person who hired you to commit the crime. Of course it’ll be a person of some standing, in which case I’ll go to him to pay my respects. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12801" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12813">I won’t let him know that you told me he hired you. Trust me. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12814" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12827">I’ll tell him I’m coming to request his protection for a poor maligned youth. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12828" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12838">And I’ll make the necessary arrangements with him to settle the matter to our mutual satisfaction. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12839" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12846">And by saving himself, you see, he’ll also be saving you. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12847" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12881">Now if this escapade turns out to have been of your own doing, I still won’t drop you. I’ve gotten other clients out of worse predicaments…So long as you didn’t attack a person of standing, let me be clear, I promise to get you out of this mess. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12882" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12938">It’ll cost you, I’m sure you realize. You have to tell me the name of the injured party. And depending on his condition, status, and temperament, we’ll decide whether to restrain him with some protection or find a way to bring him up on criminal charges, to scare him off. Because if you know how to manipulate the decrees, no one’s guilty and no one’s innocent. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12939" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12960">As for the priest, he’ll keep his mouth shut if he knows what’s good for him. And if he’s hardheaded, there’s a remedy for that, too. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_12961" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13001">There’s a way out of every predicament, but it takes a man like me. And your case is serious, I’m telling you, very serious. The decrees speak plainly: If this matter were to be decided in the courts, just between us, they’d lock you up and throw away the key. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13002" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13031">I’m speaking to you as a friend. You have to pay for your escapades. If you want to come out of this with your freedom, money, and reputation intact, you’re going to have to trust someone who cares about you, and do everything I say.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13032" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13079">While the lawyer spouted these words, Renzo stared at him in amazement, like a simpleton in a public square gazing at a magician who fills his mouth with straw and then extracts an interminable stream of ribbons. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13080" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13111">When he realized what the lawyer was trying to say, however, and his misunderstanding of the situation, he snipped those ribbons, saying, “Oh, sir, what have you understood? You’ve got it backward. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13112" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13143">I didn’t threaten anyone. I don’t do things like that. Ask anyone in my village. They’ll tell you I’ve never had any trouble with the law. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13144" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13170">I’m the victim here, and I’ve come to you to find out how justice can be done. And I’m glad that I saw that decree.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13171" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13177">“Damn it!” the lawyer exclaimed, his eyes popping out. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13178" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13181">“Look at the mess you’ve made. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13182" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13193">You people are all the same. Aren’t you people capable of saying things plainly?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13194" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13207">“I’m sorry, but you didn’t give me the time. Now I’ll tell you what happened. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13208" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13249">You see, today I was supposed to get married.” Renzo’s voice filled with emotion. “I was supposed to marry a girl I’ve been seeing since this summer. And today, as I was saying, was the day set by the priest, and everything had been arranged. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13250" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13287">Then the priest started digging up excuses…Well, to get to the point, I made him speak clearly, as was only right, and he admitted that he’d been forbidden, at the risk of his life, to perform this marriage. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13288" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13292">That tyrant Don Rodrigo…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13293" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13311">“Get out!” the attorney cut him off in an instant. “Get out!” he said, knitting his brows, wrinkling his red nose, and grimacing. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13312" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13321">“The nerve of you coming here to annoy me with all your nonsense! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13322" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13346">You can talk that way with one another, since you don’t know how to weigh your words! But don’t go talking nonsense with an honest man who knows their true worth! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13347" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13369">Get out! You don’t know what you’re talking about. I don’t waste my time with children. I don’t want to hear any more of your confabulations!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13370" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13371">“I swear…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13372" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13381">“Get out, I’m telling you. What do you expect me to do with your oaths? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13382" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13389">I want nothing to do with this. I wash my hands of it!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13390" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13399">And he walked away, rubbing his hands together as if he really was washing them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13400" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13410">“Learn to speak. And don’t go trying to ambush an honest man with such surprises.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13411" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13455">“But listen, please listen,” Renzo repeated in vain. The lawyer, still shouting, pushed him out of his study with both hands. And when they were on the threshold, he opened the door, called the maid, and told her, “Give this man back what he brought. I want nothing from him!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13456" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13486">In all the time she’d worked there, the woman had never received an order like that. But it was said so forcefully that she did not hesitate to obey. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13487" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13511">Taking the four birds, she handed them back to Renzo with a look of compassionate disdain, as if to say: “You must have done something really awful.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13512" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13549">Renzo wanted to make his apologies, but the lawyer was adamant. More dismayed and frustrated than ever, the young man had to return home with the rejected victims to tell the women what a fat lot of help his expedition had been. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13550" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13580">— In Renzo’s absence, after sadly removing their festive attire and putting on their ordinary clothes, the women resumed their deliberations. Lucia sobbed and Agnese sighed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13581" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13640">After her mother spoke at length about the great results they could expect from the lawyer’s consultation, Lucia said they had to try to help themselves in every way possible. Padre Cristoforo was a man who would not only offer advice: He would also take action when it came to helping the poor, and it would be a good idea to tell him what had happened. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13641" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13682">“Certainly,” said Agnese, and they both set about looking for a way. The monastery was about two miles away, but on that day, neither of them felt brave enough to go there, nor would any sensible person have advised them to do so. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13683" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13706">As they were weighing their alternatives, a knock came on the front door together with a soft but distinctive “Deo gratias.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13707" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13746">Wondering who it might be, Lucia ran to open the door and in came a lay Capuchin mendicant, making a short familiar bow, and carrying over his left shoulder a bag that he kept twisted shut with his hands. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13747" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13753">“Oh, Fra Galdino!” the two women said. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13754" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13766">“May the Lord be with you,” he replied, “I have come to beg for walnuts.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13767" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13776">“Go and fetch some walnuts for the friars,” Agnese said. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13777" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13823">Lucia stood up and stepped toward the other room. Before leaving, however, she waited for a moment behind the back of Fra Galdino, who remained standing in the same position. Placing her finger over her lips, she gave her mother a look, pleading for secrecy with tenderness and a certain authority. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13824" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13834">The friar, observing Agnese as if from a distance, asked, “What about the wedding? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13835" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13852">Wasn’t it supposed to be today? In town I noticed a certain hubbub, as if something had happened. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13853" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13854">What was it?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13855" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13867">“The Reverend Father took sick and we had to postpone,” she answered hastily. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13868" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13879">If Lucia hadn’t given her the signal, Agnese would probably have given a different answer. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13880" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13889">To change the subject, she asked, “And how is the collection going?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13890" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13895">“Not very well, my good woman. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13896" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13899">This is all I’ve managed to get.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13900" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13915">He removed the bag from his shoulders and weighed it in his hands. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13916" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13931">“This is everything. I had to knock on ten doors to gather this abundance.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13932" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13953">“Well, the harvests have been poor, Fra Galdino, and when you have to ration bread, it’s hard to be generous with anything else.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13954" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13966">“And what is the solution, my good woman, to bring back the days of plenty? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13967" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13967">Charity. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13968" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13983">Do you know the story of the miracle of the walnuts? It happened many years ago, at our monastery in Romagna.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13984" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13989">“No, I don’t. Please tell me about it.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_13990" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14012">“Well, you should know that in that monastery there used to be a Padre Macario, a living saint. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14013" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14061">One winter day, he was out walking along a path through a field that belonged to one of our benefactors, another good man. Padre Macario saw the owner near one of his big walnut trees. Four peasants with spades had started to dig up the tree, to set its roots out to dry. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14062" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14073">‘What are you doing to that poor tree?’ Padre Macario asked. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14074" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14092">“ ‘Ah, Padre, it’s been years since it’s given me any walnuts. I’m going to chop it up for firewood.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14093" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14107">“ ‘Leave it alone,’ the friar said. ‘This year it will produce more nuts than leaves.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14108" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14153">“The benefactor, knowing what kind of a man he was talking to, immediately ordered the workers to cover the roots back up with dirt. He called out to the friar, who had continued on his way, ‘Padre Macario, I’ll donate half of the harvest to the monastery.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14154" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14166">“Word of the prophecy soon spread and everyone was eager to see the walnut tree. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14167" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14180">When spring arrived it filled with an abundance of blossoms, and over time, an abundance of nuts. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14181" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14201">Our good benefactor did not have the satisfaction of gathering them himself: Before the harvest, he departed this world to receive the rewards for his charity. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14202" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14210">But the miracle was even greater, as you will hear. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n189" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14211" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14220">That good man had left behind a son of an altogether different disposition. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n190" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14221" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14260">When the harvest arrived, the friar went to collect the half that had been promised to the monastery, but the son claimed he knew nothing of it, and went on to say—the gall!—that he didn’t realize that the Capuchins knew how to harvest walnuts. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n191" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14261" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14264">Do you know what happened then? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n192" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14265" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14289">One day—wait till you hear this—the scalawag had invited over a group of friends of his same ilk and, in the midst of their revelry, was telling the story of the walnuts and making fun of the monks. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n193" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14290" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14308">These miscreants wanted to see the big pile of walnuts so he took them to the granary. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n194" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14309" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14341">But guess what? He opened the door, headed for the corner where the pile had been deposited, and just as he was saying, ‘Look,’ he took a look himself, and saw…a big pile of dried walnut leaves! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n195" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14342" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14345">That’ll teach him! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n196" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14346" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14391">And rather than lose, the monastery gained. Because after word of this miracle got out, the walnut collection went even better thanks to other benefactors, one of whom, feeling sorry for the poor mendicant friar, donated a donkey to the monastery to help carry the loot home. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n197" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14392" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14427">And so much oil was made from the nuts that there was enough for all the poor, each according to need. For we are like the sea, taking in water from every side and then feeding it back to the rivers.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n198" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14428" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14453">In that moment Lucia reappeared with her apron so full of walnuts that she struggled to hold it up by the corners, even with her arms outstretched. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n199" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14454" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14497">Fra Galdino removed his bag, placed it on the floor, and opened it up to receive this kind offering; Agnese made a stern, disapproving face at Lucia for her generosity. But Lucia looked back at her as if to say: “I’ll explain later.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n200" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14498" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14515">Fra Galdino gushed with words of praise, good wishes, promises, and gratitude. Putting his bag back over his shoulder, he started to leave. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n201" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14516" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14556">But Lucia called him back, saying, “I need you to do a favor for me. Could you tell Padre Cristoforo that I need to speak with him? Ask him if he couldn’t pay us the courtesy of coming to see us right away, since we can’t get to the church ourselves.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n202" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14557" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14559">“That’s all? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n203" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14560" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14570">Within the hour Padre Cristoforo will have heard your request.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n204" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14571" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14572">“I’m counting on you.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n205" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14573" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14574">“Have no doubts.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n206" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14575" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14591">At that he left, a little heavier and a lot happier than when he had arrived. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n207" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14592" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14633">That a poor girl could summon Padre Cristoforo with such confidence, and that the mendicant friar would agree to convey the message without any indication of surprise or difficulty, should not lead anyone to think that Cristoforo was some ordinary friar. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n208" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14634" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14664">On the contrary, he was a man of great authority in his order and in the surrounding region. But such was the vocation of the Capuchins that nothing seemed too low or too high for them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n209" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14665" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14724">A Capuchin was accustomed to everything: tending the sick and being tended to by the powerful, entering palaces and huts with the same humble yet confident demeanor, in the same house being alternately a nobody and someone essential to all decision-making, seeking charity for everything and providing it to anyone who requested it at the monastery. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n210" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14725" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14760">As he walked down the road he could just as easily run into a prince who would reverently kiss the tip of his cordon as he would a gang of delinquents acting as if they were fighting, only to turn around and splatter his beard with mud. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n211" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14761" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14836">In those days the word friar was uttered with both the greatest respect and the harshest scorn. The Capuchins, perhaps more than any other order, aroused opposite feelings and experienced opposite fortunes. Since they had no possessions, wore a particularly strange habit, and more openly professed their humility, they were more exposed to the veneration and slander that such qualities can invite depending on the different moods and different thoughts of men. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n212" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14837" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14846">Once Fra Galdino had left, Agnese exclaimed, “All those walnuts! After a harvest like this!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n213" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14847" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14896">“Forgive me, Mother,” Lucia replied, “but if we had made the same donation as everyone else, Fra Galdino would have continued on his rounds for who knows how long before his shoulder bag was full. God knows when he would have made it back to the monastery. And with all the other gossip he would have heard and shared by then, God knows if he would have remembered my message.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n214" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14897" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14941">“Good thinking. Anything that bears fruit is an act of charity,” said Agnese, who despite her faults was a kindhearted woman always ready, as the saying goes, to walk through fire for her only daughter, in whom she had invested all her aspirations. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n215" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14942" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14972">In the middle of all this Renzo arrived, wearing an expression that was both angry and humiliated. He flung the capons on a table—and this was the last sad chapter for those poor animals that day. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n216" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14973" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14980">“Nice advice you gave me!” he told Agnese. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n217" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_14981" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_15000">“And such a nice man that Professor Argle-Bargle. A man who really cares for the poor!” and he related his consultation with the lawyer. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n218" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_15001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_15043">The woman, dismayed by how badly things had turned out, still wanted to prove that her advice had been good, and that Renzo must have mishandled the situation, but Lucia interrupted the argument, announcing that she hoped she had found a better solution. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n219" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_15044" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_15058">Renzo welcomed this new source of hope, as would anyone in the grips of trouble or misfortune. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n220" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_15059" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_15076">“But if the padre can’t fix this,” he added, “then I will, one way or the other.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n221" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_15077" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_15085">The women urged him to be calm, patient, and prudent. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n222" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_15086" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_15108">“Tomorrow,” Lucia said, “Padre Cristoforo will surely come, and you’ll see for yourself that he’ll find the kind of solution that we common folk cannot even imagine.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n223" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_15109" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_15122">“I hope so,” said Renzo, “but no matter what, I’ll get what’s mine by right, even if I have to fight for it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n224" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_15123" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_15128">For in the end, there is justice in this world.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n225" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_15129" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_15149">Amid the sad talk and the comings and goings herein described, the day had gone by and the sky was growing dark. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n226" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_15150" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_15162">“Good night,” said Lucia sadly to Renzo, who could not seem to make himself leave. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n227" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_15163" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_15169">“Good night,” replied Renzo, even more sadly. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n228" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_15170" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_15179">“A guardian angel will help us,” Lucia replied, “be prudent and resign yourself.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n229" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_15180" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_15207">Her mother added more advice along the same lines, and the groom left at last, his heart in turmoil. He kept repeating to himself the same strange words. “In the end there is justice in this world.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap3-n230" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_15208" targetEnd="quarantana/cap3.xml#c3_15222">For a man overcome by grief truly does not know what he is saying. </note>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>