<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>2022</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed: a novel</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
          <date>2022</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Michael Moore</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="english_2022_cap33">
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10037">One night toward the end of August, as the plague reached its peak, Don Rodrigo was making his way back to his home in Milan, accompanied by the faithful Griso, one of the three or four members of his household that had survived. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10038" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10065">He had been carousing with his drinking buddies, who liked to get together to while away the melancholy of those days. Every time they met there were always a few new faces more, and a few old faces less. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10066" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10100">That evening Don Rodrigo had been one of the jolliest of the bunch. He had kept the whole party in stitches with his jokes, including a mock eulogy for Count Attilio, who had been carried off by the plague two days earlier. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10101" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10129">As he walked home, however, he felt an ache, a fatigue, a wobbling in his legs, a shortness of breath, and an inner burning that he wanted to blame on the wine, the late hour, the season. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10130" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10155">He didn’t make a sound the whole way, and the first words out of his mouth, once he got home, were to order Griso to light the way to his bedroom. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10156" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10194">When they got there, Griso studied his master’s face: It was distraught and feverish, his eyes glazed and bulging. During times like these, even beggars had to acquire, as they say, the eyesight of a physician, so Griso kept his distance. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10195" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10214">“I’m fine, damn it,” said Don Rodrigo, who could tell from Griso’s manner what he was thinking, “never been better. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10215" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10225">But I might have had too much to drink. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10226" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10237">They had this wonderful Vernaccia!…A good night’s sleep and I’ll be good as new. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10238" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10253">I’m so tired…Can you get rid of that candle? The light is blinding me…it’s bothering me!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10254" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10263">“The Vernaccia is playing tricks on you,” said Griso, keeping his distance. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10264" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10274">“Go to bed now. A little sleep will do you good.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10275" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10279">“Yes, you’re right. That is, if I can sleep. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10280" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10283">Anyway, I’m fine. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10284" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10308">Put the bell near me, for good measure, in case I need something tonight. And listen closely in case I do ring. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10309" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10332">But I won’t be needing anything…Will you get that damned lamp out of here!” he repeated, as Griso carried out his orders, getting only as close as necessary. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10333" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10339">“What the devil! It’s unbearable!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10340" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10360">Griso took the candle and, wishing his master a good night, hurried out of the room while his master settled in. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10361" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10367">But the blankets weighed on Don Rodrigo like a ton of bricks. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10368" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10380">He pushed them away and curled up to sleep, since he was dead tired. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10381" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10408">No sooner would he close his eyes, however, then he would wake up with a start, as if someone had shaken him as a prank. He could feel his temperature rising, and with it, his agitation. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10409" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10471">His thoughts ran to the month of August, to the wine, and to his overindulgence, on which he wanted to blame everything. But these ideas were immediately pushed aside by the thought that accompanied everything in those days, arriving from every direction, invading every drunken conversation, since it was easier to joke about than to ignore: the plague. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10472" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10489">After much tossing and turning, he finally fell asleep. He then proceeded to have the worst, most unsettling dreams in the world. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10490" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10533">One dream followed the next, and he found himself high, high up, in the middle of a crowd in what looked like a big church. He had no idea how he had gotten there, or how the idea had even come to him, especially at a time like this. And it infuriated him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10534" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10566">He looked at the people around him. They all had sallow, ravaged faces with a dazed, bewildered look in their eyes, and their mouths gaping. Their clothes hung from their bodies in tatters, and he could see bruises and buboes through the holes. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10567" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10606">“Keep your distance, you dogs!” he heard himself shouting, staring at the door, which was far, far away. He accompanied his shout with a threatening look. Rather than move away, he recoiled from their foul bodies, which were brushing against him from every side. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10607" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10656">But none of those inanimate souls showed any sign of moving or of having heard him. Instead, they came even closer. One in particular seemed to be poking an elbow or something into his left side, between his heart and his armpit, giving him a sharp stabbing pain. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10657" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10676">When he turned to get away from it, he immediately felt something else stabbing him in the same place. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10677" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10724">Incensed, he reached for his sword, which the mob had somehow pushed upward. Maybe the hilt was what was pressing against him. But when he went to grab it, he felt not the sword but an even sharper pain. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10725" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10744">He hollered, struggled to breathe, and wanted to shout even louder when suddenly all those faces seemed to turn in the same direction. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10745" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10795">He followed their gazes. He spied a pulpit, and something smooth, round, and shiny slowly emerged from above the railing, becoming more and more distinct: a bald head, then two eyes, a face, a long white beard; a friar standing erect, rising waist-high above the railing. It was Padre Cristoforo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10796" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10833">After glaring at the assembled congregation, he seemed to stare straight at Don Rodrigo, raising his hand in the same gesture he had made in the great hall of the nobleman’s palace. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10834" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10870">Don Rodrigo responded by raising his own hand in anger, and made as if to lunge at and grab Padre Cristoforo’s outstretched arm. A voice muttering silently in his throat broke into a loud shout, which woke him up. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10871" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10937">He lowered the arm he had raised in his sleep. He struggled to collect himself and open his eyes, since the late morning sun irritated him as much as the candlelight from the night before. He recognized his bed and his room, and realized it had all been a dream. The church, the people, the friar—all had vanished. All except for one thing: the pain in his left side. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10938" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10970">In that same moment, he felt a violent, labored palpitation of the heart, a buzzing, a constant whistling in his ears, a burning inside, and a heaviness in his limbs, worse than when he had turned in for the night. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10971" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10997">He hesitated for a moment or two before daring to examine the spot that was hurting. When he finally found it, he took an anxious look. And there it was: a filthy swollen purple bubo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_10998" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11026">He knew he was lost. He was overcome by terror, and perhaps by the even greater terror that he would fall into the grips of the monatti, and be carted off and tossed into the lazaretto. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11027" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11057">As he searched for a way to avoid this ghastly fate, he could feel his thoughts clouding over, darkening. He could feel the moment approaching when the only thought left would be succumbing to despair. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11058" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11065">He grabbed the bell and shook it violently. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11066" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11073">Griso, who had been on the alert, appeared immediately. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11074" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11094">He stopped a certain distance from the bed. He gave a wary glance at his master and knew that his suspicions on the night before had been correct. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11095" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11109">“Griso!” cried Don Rodrigo, struggling to sit up. “You have always been so loyal.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11110" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11111">“Yes, sir.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11112" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11116">“I’ve always been good to you.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11117" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11119">“Out of the goodness of your heart.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11120" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11124">“You are the one person I can trust.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11125" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11125">“That I am.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11126" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11128">“I’m sick, Griso.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11129" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11131">“I noticed.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11132" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11148">“If I recover, I’ll be even better to you than I was in the past.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11149" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11162">Griso gave no answer, and stood there waiting to see where this preamble might lead. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11163" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11176">“I don’t trust anyone but you,” Don Rodrigo continued. “Can you do me a favor, Griso?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11177" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11186">“At your command,” the man answered, with the usual formulaic response to this unusual request. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11187" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11194">“Do you know where the surgeon Chiodo lives?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11195" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11197">“Of course I do.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11198" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11209">“He’s a good man who will keep an illness secret, for a price. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11210" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11242">Go and summon him. Tell him I’ll pay him four—no six—scudi to visit, or more, if he asks for more. But he has to come immediately. And in such a way that no one notices.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11243" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11251">“Good idea,” said Griso, “I’ll go and be right back.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11252" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11258">“Listen, Griso. Get me a little water first? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11259" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11266">I’m burning up. I can’t stand it anymore.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11267" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11277">“No, sir,” replied Griso, “not without the doctor’s orders. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11278" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11285">These are strange illnesses. There’s no time to waste. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11286" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11294">Keep still. I’ll be here with Chiodo in two shakes of a lamb’s tail.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11295" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11299">Then he left, closing the door behind him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11300" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11316">Sinking back beneath his blankets, Don Rodrigo imagined himself accompanying Griso to Chiodo’s home. He counted his footsteps, calculating the time. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11317" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11333">Every so often he took another look at the bubo but immediately turned away in disgust. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11334" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11363">As more time passed, he listened carefully to hear whether the surgeon was arriving. The effort it took to concentrate suspended his feeling of sickness and kept his wits sharp. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11364" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11381">Suddenly, he heard a tinkling in the distance, but it seemed to be coming from the next rooms, not the street. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11382" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11403">He listened more carefully. It got louder and steadier, accompanied by a shuffling of feet. A horrible suspicion crossed his mind. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11404" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11478">He sat up and paid even closer attention. He heard a thud in the next room, like a weight being set down carefully. He thrust his legs out of the bed and tried to get up. As he stared at the door, it opened, and two sinister faces in filthy tattered red robes walked toward him: It was the monatti! He could see Griso’s face, half-hidden behind the door, spying on him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11479" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11483">“You dirty traitor!…Away from me, you dogs! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11484" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11484">Biondino! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11485" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11575">Carlotto! Help! Murder!” cried Don Rodrigo. He stuck a hand under his pillow, groping for his pistol. He managed to pull it out, but at his first cry the monatti had already rushed the bed. The quicker of the two was upon him before he could do anything. He yanked the pistol from Don Rodrigo’s hand and tossed it away, then pushed him down on the bed and held him there. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11576" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11589">“You rat! Damn the monatti! Damn the ministers of the tribunal! Damn the do-gooders!” Don Rodrigo cursed with rage and contempt. “Hold him there till we take him away,” said the monatto’s accomplice as he walked toward the safe. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11590" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11604">Griso came in and started helping him pick the lock. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11605" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11622">“You scoundrel!” cried Don Rodrigo, glaring from beneath the man who was holding him and attempting to slip out of his strong arms. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11623" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11637">“Let me kill that ingrate,” he told the monatti, “and then you can do whatever you want with me.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11638" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11682">He tried to call his other servants again with the little voice he had left. But it was useless, since the abominable Griso had given them the night off, with fake orders from the master himself, before going to the monatti with a proposal to join forces and divvy up the spoils. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11683" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11697">“Be good, now, be good,” said the lout who had pinned the hapless Rodrigo to his bed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11698" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11713">Turning to face the two who were ransacking the room, he shouted, “Let’s do this fair and square!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11714" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11735">“You, you,” Don Rodrigo bellowed at Griso, who was busy breaking into the safe, digging out money and possessions, and dividing everything up. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11736" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11737">“You! And after everything…! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11738" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11740">You hellhound! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11741" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11745">I’m going to come out of this, then you’ll pay!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11746" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11763">Griso held his breath and, as best he could, avoided facing the source of these words. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11764" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11772">“Hold him tight,” said the other monatto. “He’s delirious.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11773" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11776">By this point it was true. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11777" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11810">After a loud cry, after one last violent wrench to free himself, Don Rodrigo suddenly collapsed, exhausted and unconscious. His eyes were still open, however, as if in a trance, and every so often he revived or moaned. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11811" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11851">The monatti took him, one by the feet, the other by the shoulders, and placed him on the stretcher they had left in the next room. One came back to retrieve the loot. Then they lifted their sorry burden and carried him away. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11852" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11874">Griso stayed behind to quickly wrap in a bundle whatever struck his fancy, then left. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11875" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11920">He had been careful not to touch the monatti or let them touch him. In the final fury of looting, however, he had taken his master’s clothes from where they lay near the bed and shaken them without a second thought, to see if there was any money in them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11921" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11951">But he would have second thoughts the next day, when, as he was stuffing his face at a greasy tavern, he was suddenly gripped by chills, his eyesight clouded over, his strength failed, and he collapsed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11952" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11985">Abandoned by his companions, he, too, fell prey to the monatti. They stripped him of everything valuable in his possession and threw him on a cart, where he died before reaching the same lazaretto that had just welcomed his master. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_11986" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12045">Now we will leave Don Rodrigo behind in this nest of despair, and go in search of another man, whose story would never have intersected with Don Rodrigo’s had it not been forced upon him. Indeed, it is certain that neither of them would have even had a story: I am speaking, of course, of Renzo, whom we last saw at his new silk mill, where he was going by the name of Antonio Rivolta. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12046" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12138">He had been in the area for four or five months when hostilities broke out between the Republic of Venice and the Kingdom of Spain; this assuaged his fears about his arrest and extradition to Milan. Bortolo rushed to tell him that he could work for him again. He was fond of Renzo, and knew that the talented youth was a skilled worker who would be a great help to the factory foreman. Not to mention that he was also not afraid of Renzo aspiring to take his job because of his cousin’s damned misfortune of not knowing how to hold a pen. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12139" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12151">I felt obliged to mention this, since it certainly factored into Bortolo’s decision to bring Renzo back to the mill. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12152" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12163">Would you readers have preferred a more idealistic Bortolo? Well, you’ll have to create your own. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12164" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12166">That’s simply the way he was. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12167" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12176">So Renzo stayed on to work for him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12177" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12220">Every now and then, he would fantasize about quitting his job and becoming a soldier, especially after being blessed with a letter from Agnese. There was no lack of opportunity, since Venice needed men during that time. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12221" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12265">The temptation grew even stronger when there was talk of invading Milan. And of course he dreamed of returning home, the conquering hero, seeing Lucia again, and finally being able to tell her everything. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12266" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12277">But Bortolo always managed to bring him back down to earth. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12278" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12311">“If they’ve got to go,” he would say, “they can go without you. You can go later, in your own sweet time. And if they come back with bandages wrapped around their heads, won’t you be glad you stayed home? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12312" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12321">There’ll be no shortage of desperate men ready to pave the way to Milan. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12322" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12349">But can you imagine what they’ll go through before they set foot there?…Me, I’m not convinced. Venice can talk tough, but Milan is hardly a sitting duck. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12350" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12361">We’re talking about Spain, after all, and you know what a big deal Spain is. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12362" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12372">Venice might be strong in its own backyard, but it’ll take a lot more than that to take on the Spanish Empire. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12373" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12401">“Be patient. Aren’t you happy here?…I know what you mean, but everything’s going to work out if the heavens above decide they will, and you can bet, without doing anything crazy, that things will work out for the best. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12402" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12404">Some saint or other will intercede. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12405" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12412">Believe me, a soldier’s life is no life for you. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12413" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12423">What sense does it make to go from spinning silk to shooting and killing? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12424" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12431">Why would you want to get mixed up with people like that? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12432" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12437">That’s a job designed for a certain type of man.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12438" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12451">At times Renzo would resolve to travel under an assumed name, in disguise. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12452" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12466">But Bortolo managed to dissuade him every time, with arguments that are all too easy to imagine. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12467" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12541">Once the plague broke out in the Milanese state, right on the border of Bergamo, as I have said, it was only a matter of time until it crossed into Venetian territory. And…please don’t be upset with me if I refrain from telling you the history of the plague in Bergamo. For anyone interested, there is a publicly commissioned study by a certain Lorenzo Ghirardelli, a rare and little-known book, even though it contains perhaps more material than all the more famous accounts of the plague combined. Well, who knows what determines the fame of a book? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12542" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12585">Getting back to Renzo, what I meant to say is that he also caught the plague and recovered from it on his own. By doing nothing. He was on death’s door, but his robust constitution defeated the illness: In just a few days he was out of danger. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12586" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12616">With his return to health, his memories, desires, hopes, and plans for the future came flooding back, more powerful than ever. That is to say, he thought of Lucia more than ever. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12617" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12630">What would become of her at a time like this, when being alive was the exception rather than the rule? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12631" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12639">And to be so near yet have no news of her? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12640" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12648">And to remain, for God knows how much longer, in such uncertainty! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12649" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12674">And what if this uncertainty were to vanish and, once all danger was past, he found out that Lucia was still alive? There was always that other mystery, the messy business of her vow. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12675" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12703">“I’m going to go to her myself and get to the bottom of this,” he said to himself, even before he was strong enough to stand. “So long as she’s alive! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12704" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12751">Find her? I’ll find her. I have to hear from her lips, once and for all, what this vow is about. I’ll let her know that she can’t keep it, and I’ll take her away with me, she and poor Agnese, if she’s alive! She’s always been fond of me, and I’m sure she still is. So what if there’s a warrant on my head? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12752" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12763">Those who are alive have other things on their minds. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12764" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12780">You should see the kinds of people walking around here, with warrants of their own, but free as the day!…So are criminals the only ones who get a safe-conduct? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12781" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12790">And in Milan, everyone says that things are even more chaotic. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12791" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12799">If I miss a good opportunity like this—[yes, he was talking about the plague! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12800" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12830">Look at how our blessed inclination to refer and subordinate everything to ourselves influences the words we choose!]—I won’t get another one like it!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12831" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12836">You can always hope, dear Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12837" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12856">As soon as he could drag himself out of bed, he went looking for Bortolo, who had managed to avoid the plague up to this point and was very cautious. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12857" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12872">So rather than enter his house, Renzo called out to him from the street and made him come to the window. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12873" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12879">“Aha!” said Bortolo. “You cheated death. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12880" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12882">Good for you!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12883" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12899">“I’m still a little shaky on my legs, as you can see, but I’m out of danger.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12900" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12906">“I wish I were in your shoes. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12907" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12934">Once upon a time it was enough to say, ‘I’m fine.’ Nowadays we’re happy if we can say, ‘I’m better.’ ” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12935" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12946">After wishing his cousin the best of luck, Renzo told him of his decision. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12947" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12981">“Go on ahead then, and may God bless you,” Bortolo replied. “You try to steer clear of the police, and I’ll try to steer clear of the epidemic. And if God is on our side, we shall meet again.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12982" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12990">“Oh, I’ll be back, and I won’t be back alone, not if I can help it! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12991" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12992">I can only hope!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_12993" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13010">“Come back in good company, because, God willing, there’ll be work for everyone, and we can do it side by side. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13011" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13021">So long as I’m still here, and this evil hour has passed!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13022" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13028">“We’ll meet again! We can! We must!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13029" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13033">“God willing!” Bortolo repeated. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13034" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13061">For several days Renzo exercised to test and rebuild his strength. As soon as he felt fit for the journey, he prepared to leave. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13062" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13169">He strapped a money belt under his clothes with the fifty scudi that he had never touched or mentioned, not even to Bortolo. He also took some money that he’d been setting aside by scrimping on everything. He tucked a bundle of clothes under his arm, and put a letter of recommendation from his most recent master in his pocket, using the name Antonio Rivolta, just to be safe. In his trouser pocket he stuck a dagger, which was the bare minimum that an honest man should carry in those days. And toward the end of August, he set off, three days after Don Rodrigo had been taken to the lazaretto. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13170" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13207">To avoid arriving in Milan in a state of complete ignorance, he took the road to Lecco, so he could stop by his home village. Hopefully he would find Agnese alive and well, and glean some information he was very anxious to hear. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13208" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13224">The few people who had recovered from the plague were like a privileged class among the rest of the population, since almost everyone else was languishing or dying. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13225" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13271">Those who had been untouched by the disease so far lived in constant fear of it. They moved about furtively, warily, with suspicious looks on their faces, taking measured steps, in a combination of haste and hesitation, since anything could be fatal to them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13272" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13367">Those who had recovered, on the other hand, were almost confident (since it would have been more miraculous than rare for the plague to strike twice), moving through the epidemic freely and resolutely, like medieval knights, armored from head to toe, and mounted on horses that, as much as possible, were likewise outfitted. In this manner, they wandered wherever fate might lead (hence the glorious name of knights-errant) among the poor pedestrian riffraff of city and country folk whose only weapon to ward off death and soften the blow were the rags on their backs. Ah, the knighthood! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13368" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13384">Such a beautiful, wise, and useful profession. Just the thing to place at the beginning of a treatise on political economy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13385" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13450">Renzo made his way home beneath a beautiful sky and through a beautiful countryside with this same confidence, but tempered by the apprehensions that the reader knows, and saddened by the frequent sight and ceaseless thought of the general calamity. For long stretches of plaintive solitude, he ran into no one except the occasional wandering shadow rather than a living being, or corpses being carted to the common grave without funeral rites, without singing, without mourners. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13451" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13474">Toward midday, he stopped in a forest to eat a little bread and cheese that he had brought with him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13475" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13545">There was plenty of ripe fruit along the road—figs, peaches, plums, apples—more than he could need or want. All he had to do was detour into the fields and pick them, or gather the culls beneath the trees, from which they had rained down like hail. The crops had been quite abundant, especially with fruit, but there was almost no one to harvest them. Even the grapes were so plump that they covered their leaves, and were left to the mercy of the first passerby. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13546" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13551">As evening fell, Renzo arrived in his village. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13552" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13616">No matter how much he had prepared himself, he felt heartsick at the sight of it. He was suddenly overwhelmed with painful memories and painful forebodings. In his ears he could still hear the tolling of the bells that had accompanied and pursued him as he fled the town. In a way, he could also hear the deathly silence now looming over it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13617" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13659">As he entered the small piazza in front of the church, his dread increased. And he expected to feel even worse at the end of his trek, since he was headed toward the place that he had once thought of as Lucia’s home. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13660" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13709">Now, at best, it could be called Agnese’s house. The only blessing he hoped to receive from heaven was to find her alive and in good health, and to be able to ask if he could stay with her, assuming (rightly) that his own home was inhabited only by mice and weasels. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13710" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13736">He cut through a field to avoid being seen, taking the same path he had once followed in the dead of night, in better company, to catch the priest by surprise. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13737" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13769">Halfway down the path, there was his old vineyard to one side and his old cottage to the other, and he planned to stop there for a moment to check on the condition of both. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13770" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13830">He stared straight ahead as he walked, both hoping and fearing that he would see someone. After a few steps, he did, in fact, spot a man in shirtsleeves, sitting listlessly on the ground, leaning against a jasmine bush. From his posture and his features, he looked a lot like Gervaso, the poor half-wit who had acted as his second witness on that failed earlier expedition. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13831" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13846">But as he came closer, he saw that it was in fact Tonio, the smarter one, who had led the way that day. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13847" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13879">The plague had sapped both his body and his mind, and brought out a slight, veiled resemblance to his feebleminded brother in his face and every gesture. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13880" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13888">“Oh, Tonio,” Renzo said, stopping in front of him, “is that you?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13889" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13896">Tonio looked up, without moving his head. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13897" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13900">“Tonio! Don’t you recognize me?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13901" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13914">“When your time is up, it’s up,” replied Tonio, sitting there, his mouth agape. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13915" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13924">“So you caught it, too, eh? Poor Tonio. Don’t you recognize me anymore?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13925" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13937">“When your time is up, it’s up,” is all he replied, with an inane smile. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13938" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13950">Seeing he could get nothing more out of him, Renzo continued on his way, even sadder than before. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13951" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13968">A dark figure came around the corner, whom he immediately recognized as Don Abbondio. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_13969" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14011">He was walking very slowly, leaning on his cane as if it was leaning on him. When he came closer, it was clear from his pale, haggard face that he, too, had been through the storm. The priest stared Renzo up and down. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14012" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14034">Was this someone he knew? There was something foreign about his clothing (and foreign it was, since it came from Bergamo!). </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14035" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14080">“It’s him, no question,” he said to himself, raising his hands to the sky in a gesture of disgruntled surprise, waving his cane in the air with his right hand. His poor arms were swimming in sleeves that used to be snug. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14081" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14105">Renzo walked toward him, lengthening his stride, and bowed. Although, as you know, they had not been exactly on good terms the last time they’d met, he was still the parish priest. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14106" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14111">“It’s you? You’re here?” exclaimed Don Abbondio. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14112" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14116">“Yes, I’m here, as you can see. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14117" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14121">Have you heard anything from Lucia?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14122" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14127">“How am I supposed to know? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14128" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14132">I don’t know anything. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14133" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14142">She’s in Milan, if she is still of this world. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14143" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14144">But you…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14145" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14148">“And Agnese, is she alive?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14149" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14159">“Maybe. But what do I know? She’s not here. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14160" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14160">But…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14161" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14161">“Where is she?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14162" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14187">“She went to stay in the Valsassina, with relatives in Pasturo, as you know. They say that the plague isn’t wreaking havoc there like it is here. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n189" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14188" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14190">But you, I was asking…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n190" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14191" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14194">“I’m sorry to hear it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n191" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14195" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14198">And Padre Cristoforo?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n192" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14199" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14205">“He left a while ago. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n193" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14206" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14206">But…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n194" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14207" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14221">“I know. I heard in a letter. I was wondering if he’d come back here by any chance.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n195" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14222" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14229">“Oh, of course. We haven’t heard another word from him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n196" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14230" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14231">But you…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n197" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14232" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14236">“I’m sorry to hear that, too.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n198" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14237" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14250">“But I was saying, you? What are you doing in these parts, for the love of God? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n199" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14251" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14256">Did you forget that minor detail of the warrant for your arrest…?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n200" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14257" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14258">“What do I care? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n201" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14259" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14262">They’ve got other things on their minds. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n202" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14263" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14273">I wanted to come check on my affairs myself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n203" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14274" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14278">You really don’t know if…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n204" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14279" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14292">“What did you want to see? No one is left. Nothing is left. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n205" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14293" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14310">As I was saying, with the minor detail of that warrant, to come here, to this village, in the jaws of the wolf, was that a smart thing to do? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n206" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14311" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14357">A word to the wise from an old man who, unlike you, is forced to keep his wits about him, and who speaks to you from the love in his heart: Before anyone sees you, lace up your boots, and go back from where you came. And if someone has seen you, the faster you leave the better. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n207" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14358" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14365">Is this any time for you to be here? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n208" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14366" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14378">Don’t you know they came looking for you, turning your house upside down, ransacking it from floor to ceiling…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n209" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14379" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14383">“Unfortunately I do know, the swine!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n210" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14384" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14385">“Well?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n211" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14386" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14393">“As I said, I don’t care. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n212" type="comm" status="insertion">What about Don Rodrigo? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n213" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14394" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14400">Is he still alive? Is he here?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n214" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14401" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14418">“I’m telling you, no one’s left. I’m telling you to stop worrying about what’s happening here. I’m telling you that…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n215" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14419" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14423">“I’m asking if he’s here.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n216" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14424" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14426">“For heaven’s sake! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n217" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14427" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14428">Careful what you say! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n218" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14429" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14439">How can you still have all that fire inside after everything that’s happened?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n219" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14440" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14443">“Is he here or not?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n220" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14444" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14446">“He’s not, enough now. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n221" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14447" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14453">But the plague, my son, the plague! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n222" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14454" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14462">Who in his right mind would be wandering around in times like these?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n223" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14463" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14481">“You’d think there was nothing but plague in the world…Let me speak for myself: I caught it, so now I’m in the clear.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n224" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14482" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14489">“Well! Wasn’t that a sign? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n225" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14490" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14506">When you survive something like that, you should thank God, and…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n226" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14507" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14509">“I do, every day.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n227" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14510" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14516">“And don’t go looking for more trouble, I’m saying. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n228" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14517" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14520">Do as I do…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n229" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14521" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14529">“You had it, too, Father, unless I’m mistaken.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n230" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14530" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14532">“Yes, I did! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n231" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14533" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14551">A wicked abomination it was. It’s a miracle I’m still alive. Look at the shape it left me in! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n232" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14552" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14579">Now I really need some peace and quiet to get back on my feet. In fact, I was starting to feel a little better…for heaven’s sake, what are you doing here? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n233" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14580" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14580">Go back!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n234" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14581" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14586">“Still rattling on about my going back? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n235" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14587" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14593">Well, if I wanted to go back, I may as well have stayed where I was. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n236" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14594" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14598">You keep asking, ‘What did you come here for?’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n237" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14599" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14605">Really? I’ve come home!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n238" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14606" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14607">“Ah, your home…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n239" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14608" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14614">“Tell me, how many people have died?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n240" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14615" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14632">“Ach!” exclaimed Don Abbondio. And starting with Perpetua, he went down a list of individuals and whole families. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n241" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14633" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14661">Renzo had unfortunately been expecting such news, but to hear the names of so many people he knew, the names of friends, of relatives, overwhelmed him with grief. With his head lowered, he kept exclaiming, “Poor boy!” “Poor girl!” “Poor things!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n242" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14662" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14669">“So you see!” continued Don Abbondio. “And it’s not over. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n243" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14670" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14694">If the ones who are left don’t get smart and chase the nonsense out of their heads, then all we’ve got left is to wait for the end of the world.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n244" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14695" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14704">“Don’t worry. I have no intention of staying here.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n245" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14705" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14713">“Ah, thank heaven you finally understand. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n246" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14714" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14723">So does this mean you intend to return to Bergamo?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n247" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14724" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14729">“That’s no concern of yours.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n248" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14730" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14739">“What? Don’t tell me you’re going to make even more trouble for me!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n249" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14740" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14756">“Like I said, that’s none of your concern. I’m not a child anymore. I can think for myself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n250" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14757" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14767">But I hope you won’t tell anyone you saw me. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n251" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14768" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14777">You are a priest. I am a member of your flock. You wouldn’t want to betray me.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n252" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14778" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14786">“I see,” Don Abbondio grumbled, “I see. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n253" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14787" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14792">You want to ruin yourself, and to ruin me while you’re at it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n254" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14793" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14810">Haven’t you already been through enough? Haven’t I already been through enough? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n255" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14811" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14814">I see, I see.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n256" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14815" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14828">Muttering these last words between his teeth, he continued on his way. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n257" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14829" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14840">Renzo stood there, sad, disconsolate, wondering which way to go. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n258" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14841" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14883">On the list of the dead recited by Don Abbondio, there was a family of peasants who had all been carried away by the plague, except for a young man, a childhood friend who was almost the same age as Renzo. His house was just outside the village. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n259" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14884" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14886">He decided to pay him a visit. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n260" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14887" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14906">Along the way he passed by his own vineyard. From the outside he could already tell what kind of condition it was in. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n261" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14907" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14934">Not a single branch or leaf of the trees he had planted peered over the wall. The only thing he could see was the vegetation that had grown in his absence. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n262" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14935" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14950">At the entrance, not even the hinges of the gate were left. He took a look around: “My poor vineyard!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n263" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14951" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14971">For two successive winters, whenever the villagers needed firewood, they would go to “the poor boy’s place,” as they called it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n264" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14972" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14986">Everything had been pulled up by the roots or roughly chopped down: grapevines, mulberries, and fruit trees of every kind. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n265" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_14987" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15048">You could still see the vestiges of the old plantings through new growth in crooked lines where there used to be straight rows. Here and there fresh twigs or shoots sprouted from mulberry, fig, peach, cherry, and plum trees. But even they were choked and crowded out by a dense variety of new growth that had germinated and flourished, untended by human hands. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n266" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15049" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15096">There was a riot of nettles, ferns, ryegrass, scutch, goosefoot, wild oat, green amaranth, chicory, sorrel, cockspur, and the like, otherwise known as weeds by farmers throughout the world. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n267" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15097" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15151">There was a tangle of stalks competing to climb higher or spread wider than each other, creeping along the ground in every direction, through a jumble of leaves, flowers, and fruits of a hundred different colors, shapes, and sizes. Ears of wheat and corn were topped by tufts and clusters of white, red, yellow, and blue flowers. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n268" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15152" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15270">Amid this riot of vegetation, certain plants stood out more prominently and conspicuously than others, though they were no better, or at least, not most of them. The tallest was pokeweed, with its reddish outstretched branches and majestic dark-green leaves, some of which already had purple edges and dangling bunches of berries, which ranged in color from deep purple on the bottom to violet then green, with tiny white blossoms on the tip. The large woolly leaves of the mullein were on the ground while its stem was in the air, its tall spikes spattered and speckled with bright yellow flowers. Then there was the thistle’s prickly stems, leaves, and calyx, with tufts of white and purple flowers blooming or silvery-gray plumes breaking off and blowing away in the wind. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n269" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15271" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15366">In one spot, a clump of wild morning glories had climbed and wrapped itself around the shoots of a mulberry tree, covering it with their drooping leaves and dangling white trumpet flowers. In another, a bryony, with its red berries, had wound itself tightly around the fresh shoots of a grapevine, which, after searching in vain for a more solid support, had wrapped its own tendrils around the bryony in turn. They had twisted their feeble stems and not dissimilar leaves around one another and pulled each other down, as often happens when the weak lean on each other for support. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n270" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15367" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15404">Brambles were everywhere, traveling from one plant to the next, creeping up and down, bending or lengthening the branches at will. They also traversed the front of the vineyard, as if to bar entrance even to the owner. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n271" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15405" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15429">But Renzo didn’t have the heart to enter his vineyard in that condition, and might have spent even less time looking at it than we have in sketching it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n272" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15430" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15455">He walked straight to his destination, the cottage. He crossed the garden, wading knee-deep through the weeds that had invaded and covered it just like the vineyard. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n273" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15456" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15498">He set foot on the threshold of one of the two ground-floor rooms. At the sound of his footsteps and the sight of his appearance, rats scampered and fled in every direction, burrowing under the filth that covered the floor on which the Landsknechts had slept. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n274" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15499" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15505">He glanced at the walls: cracked, dirty, blackened with soot. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n275" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15506" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15514">He looked up at the loft: a canopy of cobwebs. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n276" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15515" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15517">That’s all that was left. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n277" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15518" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15567">Distraught, he ran from the house, back the way he came, retracing the path he had made a few moments earlier. After a few steps, he took a footpath to the left that cut through the fields. Without seeing or hearing another living soul, he approached the cottage where he had thought he might stop and rest. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n278" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15568" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15572">It was already getting dark. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n279" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15573" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15602">His friend was in the doorway, sitting on a wooden stool, his arms crossed and his eyes staring at the sky, like a man whom misfortune had driven mad and solitude had turned wild. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n280" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15603" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15648">Hearing footsteps, he turned to see who it might be. Between the branches and the leaves, he thought he caught a glimpse of someone who had been pestering him. “Go bother someone else!” he said in a loud voice, standing up and shaking his hands. “Didn’t I do enough yesterday? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n281" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15649" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15659">Leave me alone for a while. That would be an act of mercy!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n282" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15660" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15671">Renzo, not knowing what he meant, called him by his name. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n283" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15672" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15678">“Renzo?” said the other man, both excited and skeptical. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n284" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15679" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15685">“One and the same,” replied Renzo, and they ran toward each other. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n285" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15686" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15699">“It really is you!” said his friend when they were close. “I’m so happy to see you! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n286" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15700" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15702">Who would believe it? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n287" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15703" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15717">I thought you were Paolino the gravedigger, who’s always coming here to bug me, to get me to help him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n288" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15718" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15727">You see I’m the only one left. I’m alone, all alone, like a hermit!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n289" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15728" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15733">“Unfortunately I do know,” said Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n290" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15734" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15748">Quickly trading and overlapping greetings, questions, and answers, they entered the cottage together. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n291" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15749" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15775">Without interrupting their conversation, his friend busied himself playing the host, as best he could manage with so little warning and at a time like this. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n292" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15776" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15806">He put a kettle of water on the fire and started to make polenta, handing the wooden spoon over to Renzo, so he could stir. Then he went out saying, “I’m alone, all alone!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n293" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15807" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15850">He came back in with a small pail of milk, a little dried meat, some fresh cheese, and figs and peaches, and set everything on the table. Once the polenta had been turned out onto a wooden board, they sat down and thanked each other, one for the visit, the other for the hospitality. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n294" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15851" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15914">After an almost two-year absence, they suddenly found themselves closer than they had been during the days when they used to see each other all the time. Because both of them, according to the manuscript, had learned that kindness is a balm for the soul, both in the giving and the receiving. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n295" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15915" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15959">Of course for Renzo no one could take Agnese’s place, or console him in her absence. This was not only because of their special lifelong affection, but also because she alone held the key to what he was intent on deciphering. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n296" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_15960" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16017">For a moment he was torn between continuing on to Milan or going to see Agnese first, since she was not so far away. But she wouldn’t know anything about Lucia’s health, so he kept with his original plan: to go to Milan straightaway to rid himself of his doubts, hear what Lucia had to say, and then return to her mother with the news. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n297" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16018" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16075">His friend told him many things he didn’t know, and some things that he knew only vaguely, about Lucia’s adventures, the persecutions she had suffered, and the way Don Rodrigo had fled with his tail between his legs, never to be seen in the area again; in short, the whole complicated mess. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n298" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16076" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16149">He also learned Don Ferrante’s real surname—which for Renzo was no minor detail. Agnese had dictated it to a scribe, but heaven knows how he had transcribed it, and how the Bergamo interpreter who had read the letter to Renzo had pronounced it. If he had used that name to go looking for the house in Milan, he probably wouldn’t have found a single person who knew what he was talking about. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n299" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16150" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16162">Yet that was the only thread he had to search for Lucia. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n300" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16163" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16215">As for the warrant, his friend confirmed that it was a remote threat, nothing to worry about. The Mayor had died of the plague, and no one knew when another one would be sent. Most of the police had abandoned the area, and the few who remained had more on their mind than pursuing old cases. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n301" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16216" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16236">He told his friend about his own adventures, and heard a hundred other stories in exchange, about the passage of the army, the plague, the anointers, the incredible occurrences. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n302" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16237" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16278">“Such awful things,” his friend said, while accompanying him to a bedroom vacated by the plague, “things I’d never thought we’d live to see, enough to drain all the joy from life.” But it was a relief to be able to talk about them between friends. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n303" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16279" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16319">At the break of day, both men were in the kitchen. Renzo had prepared for his journey by hiding his money belt under his doublet, and tucking his dagger into the pocket of his breeches. To travel lightly, he left his bundle with his host. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n304" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16320" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16379">“If things go well there,” he said, “if I find her alive, if…enough already…I’ll be back. First, I’ll run to Pasturo, to give poor Agnese the good news, and then, and then…But if, by chance, if the news is bad, God help us…I don’t know what I’ll do or where I’ll go. But in that case, I do know that you won’t see me around here anymore.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n305" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16380" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16411">As he stood speaking in the doorway, he leaned his head back and gazed with both tenderness and sorrow at dawn breaking over his village, a sight he had not seen for such a long time. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n306" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16412" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16439">His friend told him, as people will do, to keep his hopes up. He insisted that he bring along something to eat and accompanied him for a stretch of the way. Then he bid him farewell, again wishing him all the best. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n307" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16440" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16465">Renzo walked at a leisurely pace. His goal was to reach the outskirts of Milan that day, and enter the city early the next morning, to begin his search at once. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n308" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16466" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16486">His journey was uneventful. Nothing happened that might distract Renzo from his thoughts, except for the usual misery and despair. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n309" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16487" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16507">Like the day before, he stopped by a wood for a bite to eat and a nap. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n310" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16508" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16531">On his way through Monza, he passed by an open shop with bread loaves on display. He asked for two, so that he would have more for later. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n311" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16532" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16578">The baker gestured at him to stay outside, and passed him a bowl of water and vinegar on a small palette, telling him to toss the coins into it. Then he gave him the two bread loaves with a long pair of tongs, one at a time, which Renzo stuck in his pockets. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n312" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16579" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16646">In the late afternoon he arrived in Greco, a town he’d never heard of. But he did remember the places he’d been during his last trip, managed to calculate the distance from Monza, and determined that he wasn’t far from the city, so he left the main road to cut through the fields in search of a hut where he could spend the night to avoid running into any more trouble at inns. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n313" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16647" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16667">What he found was even better than he’d expected. He saw a gap in a hedge that circled a barnyard, took a chance, and went through. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n314" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16668" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16711">No one was about. In one corner he noticed a big barn, with piles of hay inside and a ladder leaning against the side. He took a look around and then climbed up, not knowing what he’d find. He settled down and fell asleep immediately, not waking up until dawn. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap33-n315" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16712" targetEnd="quarantana/cap33.xml#c33_16771">Then, he crawled to the edge of that giant bed. Sticking his head out and seeing no one, he climbed down the same way he had climbed up, left the way he had arrived, and set out on the footpath, using the Duomo as his lodestar. After a short walk, he reached the walls of Milan, between Porta Orientale and Porta Nuova, and very close to the latter. </note>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>