<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>2022</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed: a novel</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
          <date>2022</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Michael Moore</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="english_2022_cap34">
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10042">As for how to enter the city, Renzo had heard something about strict orders not to let anyone enter its gates without a health certificate. But he’d also heard that a resourceful man who seized the moment could easily evade this decree. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10043" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10110">And he was right. Apart from the general reasons for lax enforcement of orders during that period, and the specific ones making it so difficult to execute them strictly, Milan was in such a state by then that no one saw the point of guarding it, and what to guard against. Anyone who arrived would probably seem more careless about their own health than threatening to the health of Milan’s citizens. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10111" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10147">With this in mind, Renzo planned to enter through the first gate he saw. And if he ran into some obstacle, he would circle the wall from the outside until he found another gate with easier entry. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10148" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10158">God knows how many gates he imagined Milan had! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10159" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10191">When he arrived beneath the walls, he stopped to look around, like a man who, not knowing which road to take, thinks it best to wait and look for a sign before deciding on a direction. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10192" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10248">To the right and the left, all Renzo could see were two stretches of a crooked road. Opposite him was a wall. There was no sign of human life. From one spot on the ramparts, however, a column of thick dark smoke rose, widening and curling into woolly clouds that vanished into the stagnant gray air. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10249" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10277">It was the smoke of burning clothing, beds, and other infected household goods. Grim fires like these burned constantly, not only there but also along other parts of the wall. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10278" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10328">The weather was sweltering, the air heavy, the sky covered by an even, motionless cloud or haze that blocked the sun without promising rain. The surrounding countryside was fallow in places and arid everywhere. Every plant was discolored, not a bead of dew on their limp and withered leaves. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10329" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10356">Such solitude, such silence, near a big city increased Renzo’s sense of foreboding and apprehension as his thoughts grew darker. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10357" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10386">He stood there for a while, then took his chances and turned right, not realizing that he was heading toward Porta Nuova, though it was close, since it was hidden behind a bastion. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10387" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10407">After a few steps, he heard a tinkling of bells, starting and stopping, and then some male voices. He continued on. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10408" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10469">As he rounded the corner, the first thing he spotted was a wooden sentry box and a weary shabby-looking guard standing at the door, leaning on his musket. Behind the box was a stockade, and beyond that, the gate: namely, two roughly built walls connected by a parapet that sheltered the two large swinging doors. The doors were wide open, as was the entrance to the stockade. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10470" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10492">But on the ground directly in front of the opening lay a grim impediment: a stretcher onto which two monatti were lowering a poor man in order to carry him away. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10493" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10505">It was the chief customs officer, who had just been found to have the plague. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10506" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10539">Renzo stood still, waiting for them to finish. After they departed, the gate was still open behind them. Renzo saw his opportunity and started to run. The guard shouted at him threateningly, “You there!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10540" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10559">Renzo stopped in his tracks and, looking the man in the eye, pulled out a half-ducat from his pocket, and held it up to show the guard. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10560" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10595">The guard—who had either already had the plague, or feared the plague more than he loved half-ducats—gestured at Renzo to toss the coin to him. When it landed at his feet, he whispered, “Make it quick!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10596" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10639">Renzo didn’t need to be told twice. He passed through the stockade, then the gate, and continued on without anyone noticing or minding. That is until he had taken another forty steps, and a customs officer shouted “You there!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10640" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10654">This time Renzo pretended not to hear and, without turning around, started to walk more quickly. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10655" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10702">“You there,” the customs officer shouted again, but in a voice that indicated impatience rather than a determination to be obeyed. So when Renzo continued to ignore him, the officer shrugged his shoulders and returned to his sentry box, more worried about keeping his distance from pedestrians than inquiring into their business. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10703" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10733">The road Renzo had taken used to lead, and still does, to the canal known as the Naviglio. It was lined on both sides by hedges or garden walls, churches and monasteries, and only a few houses. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10734" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10770">As Renzo looked ahead of him, all he could see was a tall column at the end of the street alongside the canal, bearing a cross: the Sant’Eusebio Cross. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10771" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10807">Upon reaching the fork in the road at the halfway point, he looked in both directions. To his right, a man was walking toward him on the road called the Santa Teresa Stradone. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10808" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10830">“A human being, at last!” Renzo said to himself, and turned that way, thinking he might get directions. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10831" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10863">The man had also noticed the approaching stranger and from the distance eyed him warily, with suspicion, especially when he realized that, rather than continuing past, the stranger was walking straight up to him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10864" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10895">Renzo, always the respectful country lad, removed his hat as he approached the man. With his left hand holding the hat, and his right inside the crown, he went up to the man. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10896" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10924">But the man took a step back, his eyes popping out, raised his knotty walking stick, and pointed its steel tip at Renzo’s waist, shouting, “Keep your distance!” “Oh! Oh!” cried Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10925" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10976">He put his hat back on, having no desire to get into a fight, as he would later tell the story. He turned his back on the bizarre man and continued on his way, that is to say, in the direction in which he was already going. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10977" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10991">The other man also went on his way, his whole body shaking, and kept looking over his shoulder. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_10992" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11043">When he arrived home, he claimed he had been accosted by an anointer; though this young man appeared meek and mild, he had the face of an evil imposter, and he was hiding a little box of unguent or a packet of powder (he wasn’t sure which), in the hat he was carrying, ready to play a dirty trick on him if he hadn’t chased him away. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11044" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11061">“One more step,” he added, “and I’d have run him through before he got the better of me, the scoundrel. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11062" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11084">Unfortunately, we were in an isolated place. If it’d been the center of Milan, I’d have called for help and got people to grab him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11085" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11094">They’d have found that evil potion in his hat for sure. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11095" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11134">But I was there by my lonesome, so the best I could do was scare him away, and keep myself out of harm’s reach. It only takes a second to throw a little powder, and they’re quite good at it. And they’ve got the devil on their side. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11135" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11145">Now he’s making the rounds in Milan: God only knows how many victims he’s taken!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11146" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11186">For the rest of his life, which was a long life indeed, he would repeat this story whenever the conversation turned to the anointers, adding, “Anyone who still insists it isn’t true had better not say it to my face. Seeing is believing!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11187" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11258">As he continued on his way, Renzo, far from realizing what a narrow escape he’d just made, and shaken more by anger than by fear, was reflecting on that greeting, and trying to imagine exactly what the unknown man had thought of him. But it all seemed so irrational that he reached the conclusion that the man must have been half crazy. “Getting off to a bad start,” he thought, “there must be an evil star for me here in Milan. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11259" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11276">At first everything went smoothly at the gates. But now that I’m inside, trouble awaits me at every corner. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11277" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11293">Never mind…with the help of God…when I find…that is, if I can find…then none of this will matter.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11294" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11316">At the bridge he turned left without hesitation, down Via San Marco, correctly guessing that it led to the center of the city. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11317" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11361">As he went, he looked around, hoping to find another human being, but the only body he saw was a corpse rotting in a ditch between the few houses (which were even fewer back then) and a stretch of the road. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11362" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11403">After he passed it, he heard someone call out, “You there!” He looked in the direction of the voice and saw a poor woman standing on the nearby balcony of an isolated house, surrounded by a brood of children. As she called out to him, she gestured with her hand. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11404" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11434">He ran toward her, and when he got closer, “Young man,” she said, “for the sake of your own dearly departed, could you do us the kindness of going to the commissioner to tell him we’ve been forgotten here? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11435" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11465">They locked us up on suspicion, because my poor husband died. And as you can see, they nailed the door shut. No one has come to bring us food since yesterday morning. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11466" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11490">In the many hours we’ve been here, not a single Christian has happened by who would do me this kindness, and these poor innocent children are dying of hunger.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11491" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11514">“Hunger!” exclaimed Renzo. “Here you are,” he said, digging into his pockets to take out the two loaves of bread, “send me down something to put them in.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11515" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11538">“May God bless you. Just a minute,” said the woman, and she went to look for a basket and a rope to lower it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11539" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11584">While he waited, Renzo remembered the last time he had come to Milan, when he had found bread near the cross. He said to himself, “Ah: So this is reparations. I’m glad I did not give the bread back to the bakery that day, for this is truly an act of mercy.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11585" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11622">“As for the commissioner, ma’am,” he added as he placed the loaves in the basket, “I’m afraid I can’t help you there, because, to tell you the truth, I’m a foreigner, and I don’t know my way around. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11623" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11639">But if I do come across someone local, who looks kind enough to speak with me, I’ll let him know.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11640" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11657">The woman implored him to do just that, and gave him the name of her street so he could give directions. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11658" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11673">“And might I ask you for a favor,” Renzo went on to say, “a true act of charity, if it’s no trouble? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11674" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11689">Would you happen to know where I can find the house of a nobleman, a grand signore, here in Milan, who goes by the name of ***?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11690" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11705">“I’ve heard of that house,” the woman replied, “but I’m not sure where it is. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11706" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11716">If you keep walking in this direction, I’m sure you’ll find someone to tell you. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11717" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11723">And please don’t forget to tell them about us.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11724" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11730">“You can count on me,” said Renzo, and he continued on his way. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11731" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11774">With every step he heard a sound growing closer and louder, a noise he had first noticed as he spoke with the trapped woman. It was the sound of wheels and horses, a tinkling of bells, and every now and then, a crack of the whip accompanied by a shout. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11775" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11780">He looked straight ahead but could see nothing. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11781" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11826">At the end of the street, he found himself in Piazza San Marco, where the first thing he saw was two upright beams with a rope and some pulleys. He quickly recognized what used to be an all-too-familiar sight in those days: the abominable instrument of torture, the strappado. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11827" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11885">There was just such an instrument not only there but on nearly every square and major street. This allowed the deputies in each neighborhood, who had been given the most arbitrary powers, to apply it immediately to anyone whom they thought deserved punishment: people who had broken quarantine, disobedient servants, anyone. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11886" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11907">It was one of the many extreme and ineffective remedies that was used so indiscriminately in those days, and especially in moments like this. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11908" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_11999">While Renzo was looking at the instrument and wondering why it had been built there, he heard that same sound growing nearer. From around the corner of the church he saw a man appear shaking a bell: the apparitore, followed by two horses that struggled to move forward, straining their necks and digging in their hooves as they pulled a cartload of dead bodies. After this came another cart, and then another, and another. Monatti were on both sides of the horses, urging them on with lashes, punches, and curses. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12000" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12073">Most of the corpses were naked, though some were loosely covered in rags. They were piled high and jumbled together, like a nest of snakes slowly uncoiling in the warmth of spring. At every jolt, every bump in the road, the tragic heap shook and came apart grotesquely. Heads dangled, maidens’ braids unraveled, and arms slid out of the tangled mass of limbs to bang against the wheels, rendering an already horrifying sight even more heartbreaking and foul. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12074" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12093">Renzo stopped in a corner of the square, near the railing of the canal, and took a moment to say a prayer for these unknown dead. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12094" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12107">An atrocious thought suddenly crossed his mind: “Maybe there, mixed in there, hidden beneath…Oh Lord! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12108" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12120">Let it not be so! Keep this thought from my mind!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12121" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12149">Once the funeral procession had passed, Renzo crossed the square and continued along the left side of the canal, for no other reason than that the procession had gone in the opposite direction. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12150" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12175">After the few short steps between the side of the church and the canal, he saw the Marcellino Bridge on the right, crossed it, and came out into Borgo Nuovo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12176" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12227">Looking up, and still hoping to find someone to give him directions, he saw a priest in a doublet at the end of the street, holding a walking stick in one hand. He was standing by a partly open door, his head lowered, and his ear pressed up against the opening. A few minutes later, Renzo watched him raise his hand to make the sign of the cross. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12228" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12250">He assumed the priest had just heard someone’s confession, and he said to himself, “The very man I’m looking for. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12251" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12282">If a priest performing his duties can’t show a little charity, love, and grace, then there must be none left in the world.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12283" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12300">In the meantime, the priest was walking away from the door and toward Renzo, hewing very carefully to the middle of the road. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12301" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12331">Renzo doffed his hat when the priest was close to him, gesturing that he wished to have a word and, at the same time, stopping to indicate that he would come no closer. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12332" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12356">The other man also stopped, ready to listen, though he set his walking stick on the ground before him, as if to mark a barrier. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12357" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12417">Renzo asked his question, which the priest answered, giving him not only the name of the street where the house was located, but also—since he could see that the poor boy needed it—the route, indicating the right and left turns, churches and crossroads that he would pass along the six or eight blocks it would take to get there. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12418" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12445">“May God keep you healthy, in these times and always,” said Renzo. And as he was about to set off, “One more favor,” he added. He told him about the poor forgotten woman. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12446" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12469">The good priest thanked him for giving him the opportunity to do a good and necessary deed, and assured him that he would inform the proper authorities. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12470" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12496">Then he continued on his way, as did Renzo. As he was walking, he repeated the route to himself, so he would not have to ask for directions at every corner. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12497" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12525">You cannot imagine how hard this was for him, not because he struggled to remember directions, but because he was filled with a new sense of apprehension. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12526" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12537">Now that he knew the name of the street and how to get there, he was consumed with dread. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12538" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12621">These were the clues he had wanted and sought out, because he could not manage without them. And though nothing in his conversation had hinted at any semblance of an evil omen, he was still afraid of what he would find once he got there. Can you blame him? As he got closer to the moment when his questions would finally have answers, when he would hear either, “she’s alive” or “she’s dead,” he was so overwhelmed that, right then and there, he would rather have remained completely in the dark and gone back to the beginning of the journey that was finally about to end. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12622" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12653">But he pulled himself together and thought, “Come now! If we start to act like children, what will happen?” With these words of self-encouragement, he continued on to the heart of the city. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12654" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12669">But what city was this? It looked even worse than it had the year before, in the midst of a famine! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12670" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12721">Renzo was just then passing through the crossroads known as the Porta Nuova carrobio (in those days there was a cross in the center, opposite the old church of Sant’Anastasia, where San Francesco di Paola stands today), one of the poorest and most desolate parts of the city. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12722" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12773">So violently had the epidemic ravaged this neighborhood, and so appalling was the stench of dead bodies left to rot, that the few survivors had been forced to move. This solitary and forlorn sight filled the passerby with a despondency made worse by horror and disgust at the garbage and other debris that the inhabitants had left behind. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12774" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12826">Renzo quickened his pace, urging himself on with the thought that his destination was not in this neighborhood, and hoping that, before reaching it, he would find a scene that was different, at least in part. In fact, he emerged into an area just a short distance away that made him think this was still a city of the living. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12827" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12914">But what had the city become, and who were the living? All the front doors were locked, out of suspicion or terror, except for those left wide open after being abandoned or broken into. Other doors had been nailed shut after those inside had died or been infected by the plague. Still others were marked with a charcoal cross, to signal to the monatti that there were dead bodies inside to be carted away. It all looked very random, depending on whether a Tribunal of Health commissioner or another official had come by and been struck by the urge to follow or disobey orders. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12915" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12981">Rags were everywhere, as were (even more repulsive) the filthy bandages, infected straw, and bedding tossed from the windows. Scattered about were the bodies of people who had dropped dead on the street and been left there until the cart came around to carry them away, or who had fallen off the carts or been tossed from a window. Rampant, relentless disaster had turned men into beasts and erased human compassion and decency. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_12982" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13033">Gone were the sounds of shops, the clattering of carriages, the cries of street vendors, the chatter of passersby. Only rarely was the deathly silence broken by any sounds other than those of funeral processions, the moaning of the poor, the anguish of the sick, the howls of the dying, and the shouts of the monatti. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13034" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13089">At dawn, at noon, and in the evening, the tolling of a bell in the Duomo marked the time to recite the prayers selected by the Archbishop. The bells of other churches rang in response, and then you would have seen people appearing at their windows to pray in unison, and heard voices and sobs murmuring through the air, giving forth a sadness tinged with feelings of comfort. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13090" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13154">By then, an estimated two-thirds of the city’s inhabitants had died, while most of the others had fled or were sick. The flow of foreigners into the city had trickled down to almost nothing. Of the few people who were out and about, you would not, on a long walk, have come across a single person who did not have something strange about him, some hint of a fatal change in circumstances. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13155" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13209">The most prominent citizens went out with neither cape nor cloak, which in those days were considered essential articles of civilian dress. Priests went about without their cassocks, and even friars wore doublets. Dispensed with, in short, was any garment whose hem might brush against something or (even scarier) facilitate the work of the anointers. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13210" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13304">Apart from dressing in clothing that was as short and tight as possible, everyone was shabby and unkempt. Men who used to shave now had scruffy faces, and neatly kept beards had grown long. Heads of hair were long and tangled, not only from the neglect born of advanced despondency, but also because barbers had been under suspicion ever since the arrest and conviction of one of their own, Gian Giacomo Mora, as an infamous anointer. His name has long been notorious in the city, but he deserves more general and lasting compassion. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13305" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13357">Most people kept a walking stick or even a pistol in one hand, as a warning to anyone who came too close. In the other hand, they usually carried smelling salts, or perforated metal or wooden balls holding sponges that had been soaked in medicated vinegars. As they went about, they would occasionally place them under their nose or even hold them there the whole time. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13358" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13391">Some wore a vial around their necks containing a little quicksilver, convinced that it had the power to absorb and retain pestilential exhalations. Every few days they were careful to replenish it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13392" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13416">Gentlemen now went out without their usual entourage, but they could be seen carrying a bag over their arms on their way to shop for food. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13417" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13434">When two friends ran into each other on the street, they would say hello from a distance, in hurried, wordless gestures. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13435" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13506">Everyone, as they walked, had all they could do to dodge the disgusting, deadly obstacles that littered or in places completely covered the ground. Everyone tried to stay in the middle of the road for fear of other types of filth or even deadlier objects tossed from windows; for fear of the toxic powder rumored to be often thrown at pedestrians from above; for fear of walls that might be smeared with unguent. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13507" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13532">Hence ignorance—the reverse of courage and caution—increased distress and spread unfounded terrors, usurping the sensible health precautions it had disdained at the start of the plague. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13533" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13598">These scenes from the lives of the healthy and well-to-do were the least grotesque and piteous aspect of a situation that could be seen all around. After so many images of misery, with even more gruesome scenes to come, I will not linger to describe to the reader the sight of the plague stricken—the poor, children, and women—dragging themselves or lying in the streets. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13599" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13636">So dire were the circumstances that an observer might find an almost desperate comfort in the very thing that makes the strongest and saddest impression on posterity or from afar: Namely, the thought that so few of the living were left. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13637" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13679">In the midst of this desolation, Renzo was still many yards away from the street he had to enter when he heard a jumbled commotion in which he could discern the same horrid ringing as before, coming from the direction in which he was heading. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13680" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13778">When he reached the corner of one of the widest streets in the city, he saw four carts stopped in the middle. The street was as alive with movement as a grain market, with the hustle and bustle of the crowd, the filling and emptying of sacks, monatti entering and exiting houses with bundles on their shoulders that they then deposited on the carts. Some of these ghouls were wearing the red uniform, others had no such insignia, while many bore the even more appalling distinction of multicolored plumes and bows, which they wore in a display of cheerfulness amid all the public grief. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13779" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13791">From one window, then another, the doleful cries of, “Up here, monatti” rang out. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13792" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13808">“I’m coming, I’m coming,” was the grim and sinister reply from that wretched swarm. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13809" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13825">Tenants grumbled, telling them to hurry up, and monatti cursed in response. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13826" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13870">As he entered the street, Renzo quickened his step, trying to avoid looking at the crowd for any longer than the time needed to dodge it. But suddenly, he caught sight of a singular scene of pity, a pity that invited the mind to contemplate it. He stopped, almost unwillingly. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13871" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13927">Descending from one of those doorways and moving toward the convoy came a woman whose appearance suggested a youth that was advanced but not yet passed. She radiated a beauty that was shrouded and dimmed but not ruined by great emotion and fatal languor: the soft yet majestic beauty that runs in Lombard blood. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13928" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13968">Her gait was weary, but not unsteady. Her eyes were dry, but showed the sign of many tears. In her grief there was something peaceful and profound that attested to a soul fully aware of and alive to pain. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13969" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13997">But it was not her appearance alone, amid so much misery, that singled her out for pity and reawakened a feeling that in human hearts had become numb and exhausted. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_13998" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14037">In her arms, she was holding the lifeless body of a little girl of about nine years of age. The child had been lovingly dressed in a pure white garment, with her hair neatly parted on either side of her face, as if her mother’s hands had prepared her for a long-promised celebration, offered to her as a reward. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14038" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14115">She was held not prone but upright, seated on one arm, with her chest leaning against her mother’s bosom, as if she were still alive, except for a pale and waxen little hand that dangled lifelessly to one side. Her head rested on her mother’s shoulder with an abandon more powerful than sleep; resting on her mother in such a way that, although the likeness of their faces might not have shown it, clearly indicated which of the two was still sentient. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14116" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14134">One of the loathsome monatti came forward to remove the child from her arms, but with unusual deference, an almost involuntary hesitation, taking a step back, yet without any sign of disrespect or contempt. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14135" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14159">“No, please don’t touch her,” she said, “I should be the one to place her on the cart.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14160" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14179">She opened her hand, revealing a purse, and dropped it into the outstretched palm of the monatto. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14180" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14202">“This is for you,” she said, “now promise me you won’t remove a stitch from her body,” she added, “and that you will bury her in the ground exactly as she is now.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14203" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14243">The monatto placed a hand over his heart, and then, with the utmost care, almost obsequiously—more from the new sentiment that had overtaken him than the unexpected compensation—set about making room on the cart for the lifeless girl. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14244" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14276">The mother kissed her child’s forehead and laid her down as if she were on a bed, arranging her tenderly and covering her with a white sheet. She then uttered the final words: “Farewell, Cecilia! Rest in peace! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14277" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14284">Tonight we will join you, and we shall be together forever. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14285" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14296">Pray for us until that moment comes, and I will be praying for you and for the others.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14297" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14318">Turning once more to the monatto, she said, “Sir, when you pass by here this evening, you will need to come upstairs to take me, too, and not just me.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14319" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14345">With that, she went back inside the house, and appeared at the window a moment later, holding another girl in her arms, this one even younger. The child was still alive, though the signs of death were on her face. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14346" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14366">The mother stood there contemplating the undignified funeral rites of her older daughter until the cart started to move and she could see it no longer. Then she disappeared. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14367" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14410">And what else could she do but place her one remaining child on the bed, and lie down next to her so that they might die together? Just as the flower blooming on a stem and the unopened bud beside it fall with the same swipe of the scythe that levels all the grass in the field. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14411" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14429">“Oh Lord!” exclaimed Renzo. “Grant her wish! Take her to you! Take her to you, her and her little baby! They have suffered enough!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14430" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14484">Once he had recovered from that rare emotion, and while he was trying to remember the route, and whether he was supposed to take the first street, and turn right or left, he heard another, different commotion from that same corner. It was a confused sound of imperious shouts, soft moans, the sobbing of women, the bawling of children. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14485" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14495">He continued on, his heart filled with the usual dark and gloomy foreboding. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14496" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14514">At the crossroads, he saw a bewildered multitude advancing on one side, and stopped to let them pass. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14515" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14604">They were the sick being brought to the lazaretto. Some pushed and shoved, resisting in vain, crying in vain that they wanted to die in their own beds, and hurling useless insults at the curses and commands of the monatti leading them away. Others walked in silence, numb, showing no sign of grief or any other feeling. There were women with babies clutching their necks, and children more frightened by the shouts, orders, and their company, than by the vague thought of death. With shrill cries they begged for their mothers, for their trusted arms, for their homes. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14605" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14648">Ah! And maybe their mother, whom they thought they had left behind asleep in her bed, had actually collapsed into it, suddenly taken by the plague, and was lying there, senseless, to be carted away to the lazaretto herself, or, if the cart arrived too late, to the common grave. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14649" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14682">And maybe—oh tragedy worthy of even more bitter tears!—she had forgotten everything, even her children, left with only one thought in the throes of her suffering: to die in peace. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14683" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14755">Yet despite all the turmoil, there were still examples of fortitude and piety: fathers, mothers, children, spouses, who supported their loved ones and accompanied them with words of comfort. Not only adults, but boys and girls also guided their younger, more vulnerable siblings, and with the wisdom and compassion of grown-ups urged them to be obedient, assuring them that they were going to a place where people would look after them and help them to get better. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14756" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14778">Amid these tender and melancholic scenes, our traveler was seized by one thought that kept him in a state of agitation. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14779" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14819">The house had to be nearby, and who knows whether among those people…Once the whole company had passed, and his doubts had ceased, he turned to a monatto who was walking behind him and asked for the street and the house of Don Ferrante. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14820" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14827">“Go to hell, you yokel,” came the reply. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14828" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14866">Rather than responding in kind, Renzo asked a commissioner who was following behind the group and looked a little more human. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14867" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14886">Pointing a stick in the direction from which he’d come, the man said, “The first street on the right, then the last big house on the left.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14887" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14901">His heart gripped by a new and deeper anxiety, the young man heads in that direction. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14902" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14949">He reaches the street. He immediately picks out that house from the others, which are smaller and humbler. He approaches the main door, which is shut, places his hand on the knocker, and holds it there for a second, as if he were dipping his hand into an urn before extracting the slip of paper that will decide his fate. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14950" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14958">Finally, he lifts the knocker and gives a resolute knock. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14959" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14986">A few moments later, a window opens slightly. A woman sticks her head out, to see who’s there, with a scowl as if to say: “Monatti? Vagrants? Commissioners? Anointers? Demons?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_14987" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15012">“Ma’am,” asked Renzo in a shaky voice, looking up, “would there happen to be a young country girl working here who goes by the name of Lucia?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15013" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15024">“She’s not here anymore. Go away!” replied the woman, moving to close the window. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15025" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15028">“Just a moment, please! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15029" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15032">She’s not here anymore? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15033" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15033">Then where is she?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15034" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15040">“At the lazaretto,” and once again she started to shut the window. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15041" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15047">“One moment, for heaven’s sake! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15048" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15050">With the plague?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15051" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15054">“Why else? Don’t act surprised. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15055" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15055">Be gone with you now.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15056" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15058">“Oh, no! No! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15059" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15062">Wait, was she very sick? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15063" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15065">How long has she…?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15066" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15072">In the meantime the window really had closed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15073" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15085">“Ma’am! Ma’am! One word, for the love of God! For the sake of your dearly departed! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15086" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15092">I won’t ask you for anything: please!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15093" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15098">But he might as well have been talking to a wall. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15099" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15130">Distressed by the news, and angered by the way it was delivered, Renzo grabbed the knocker again, lifting it to knock desperately, but then, leaning against the door, he held it still. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15131" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15156">In his agitation, he turned around to see if some neighbor was nearby to give him more accurate information, a clue, an explanation. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15157" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15243">But the first and only person he saw was another woman, maybe twenty steps away. Her face expressed terror, hatred, impatience, malice. She had a distraught look in her eyes, which wanted to stare both at and away from him. She opened her mouth as if to scream bloody murder, while at the same time holding her breath. She raised her two bony arms, stretching and curling her gnarly hands into claws, as if she were trying to grab something. She seemed to want to call out to people but without attracting the attention of one person in particular. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15244" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15257">When their eyes met, she snarled and shook as if she had been trapped. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15258" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15293">“What the devil…?” Renzo started to say, also raising his hands toward the woman who, having lost all hope of catching him off guard, unleashed the scream she had been holding back. “The anointer! Catch him! Catch him! Catch the anointer!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15294" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15313">“Who, me? You lying witch! Shut your mouth!” shouted Renzo, and he lunged at her to try to scare her into silence. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15314" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15325">But he immediately realized that he needed to worry about himself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15326" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15363">At the sound of the old woman’s shrieks, people came running from every direction. Not as big a crowd as there might have been three months earlier, but big enough to get the better of a solitary man. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15364" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15403">At the same time, the window opened again, and the same rude woman from before stuck her whole head out and added her voice to the commotion: “Catch him! Catch him! He must be one of those scoundrels roaming the streets to anoint the doors of decent people!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15404" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15442">Renzo had no time to lose. He knew in a heartbeat that he’d be better off fleeing than standing there trying to explain himself. He looked to the right and the left, to see where there were fewer people, and he took off in that direction. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15443" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15490">He shoved aside one man who was blocking his way, and jabbed another man sprinting toward him in the chest, pushing him back eight or ten steps. Off he ran, clenched fist in the air, knuckles ready for anyone that got in his way. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15491" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15514">The road ahead was open, but he could hear the pounding of feet on the pavement behind him, and the harsh loud cries of, “Catch him! Catch the anointer!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15515" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15528">He didn’t know how many people were chasing him, and he couldn’t see where he would find safety. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15529" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15592">Ire became rage, and distress turned into despair. As his eyes darkened, he placed his hand on his dagger, unsheathed it, stopped, and turned around with the most threatening scowl of his life. Brandishing the shiny blade in his outstretched hand, he shouted, “Whoever’s got the guts, come on! You want to be anointed, you swine? I’ll anoint you alright!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15593" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15640">To his amazement, and with a vague feeling of relief, he saw that his pursuers had stopped, and were hesitating. But they continued to shout and made frantic hand movements, as if gesturing to people far behind him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15641" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15700">He turned around and saw (since the hubbub had kept him from noticing it in the moments before) the advance of a cart, or rather a procession of the usual death carts, and with their usual entourage. And behind them in the distance, another mob of people were getting closer, hoping to give chase to the anointer and nab him, but the carts were blocking their way. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15701" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15759">Caught between two fires, Renzo realized that the very thing that terrified them could be his salvation. This was no time to be squeamish. He put his knife back in its sheaf, went to one side of the street, and started running toward the carts. He ran past the first one, then spotted a nice empty space in the second. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15760" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15780">He took aim, jumped, and landed on it with his right foot, while his left was still in the air and both arms were raised. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15781" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15818">“Bravo! Bravo!” exclaimed the monatti altogether. Some of them had followed the procession on foot, others were sitting on the cart, while still others—to show you how appalling things were—sat atop the dead bodies, drinking from a large flask being passed around. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15819" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15821">“Bravo! Nice jump!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15822" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15846">“So, you’re seeking the protection of the monatti, are you? You couldn’t have found better sanctuary in a church,” said one of the two on the cart where Renzo had landed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15847" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15867">As the convoy approached, most of his attackers had turned and run, but not without a few parting cries of, “Catch him! Catch the anointer!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15868" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15897">Some of them withdrew only gradually, stopping every now and then to turn around and direct jeers and threatening gestures at Renzo, who answered from the cart in kind by shaking his fist in the air. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15898" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15939">“Let me take care of this,” said one monatto. Ripping a filthy rag off a corpse, he quickly knotted it and, taking it by one corner, held it up like a slingshot, and made as if to throw it at the most persistent, shouting, “Take this, you swine!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15940" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15964">At that gesture Renzo’s pursuers fled in horror. All he could see now were the backs of his enemies and the swift kick of their heels in the air like fulling hammers. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15965" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15985">The monatti let out a triumphant cry, an unsettling roar of laughter. A prolonged, “Ha-ha,” as if to accompany his flight. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_15986" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16009">“Ha-ha! Who says we can’t protect an honest man?” the monatto said to Renzo. “One of us is worth more than a hundred of those cowards!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16010" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16026">“Indeed. I owe my life to you,” replied Renzo, “and I thank you with all my heart.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16027" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16042">“For what?” asked the monatto. “You deserved it. Anyone can see that you’re a good boy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n189" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16043" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16081">You’re right to smear unguent nowadays: Spatter them, exterminate them, they’re worth nothing till they’re dead. You know how they repay us for the jobs we do? They swear at us, saying once this blight is over, they’ll string up the lot of us! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n190" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16082" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16104">Well, before the plague is over they’ll all be gone, and we monatti’ll be the only ones left, celebrating victory and living it up in Milan!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n191" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16105" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16150">“Long live the plague! Death to the rabble!” exclaimed his partner. With this horrid toast he put the bottle to his lips and, holding it steady with both hands while the cart jostled, took a long slug and passed it to Renzo, saying, “Now drink to our health!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n192" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16151" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16173">“Good health to you, each and every one, with all my heart,” cried Renzo, “but I’m not thirsty, I really don’t feel like drinking right now.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n193" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16174" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16198">“You had quite a scare, from what I could see,” said the monatto, “but you look like a poor thing. You don’t look like an anointer.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n194" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16199" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16204">“Everyone has to do what he can,” said the other. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n195" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16205" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16249">“Give it here,” said a monatto who was walking next to the cart. “I want another slug. To the health of its owner, who’s lying somewhere in this lovely company…I think he’s buried in the pile over there.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n196" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16250" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16269">With an evil, ghastly snicker, he pointed to the cart in front of Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n197" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16270" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16305">Then, in a solemn gesture, adopting a more sinister and cruel expression, he nodded his head in that direction. “With your permission, boss, might a poor little monatto have a taste of what’s in your wine cellar? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n198" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16306" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16322">There are some excellent vintages. We’re the ones who placed you in the cart to bring you on a long vacation, after all. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n199" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16323" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16340">And wine is so bad for your Lordship: It makes you sick immediately! We monatti are made of sterner stuff.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n200" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16341" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16400">Amid the laughter of his fellow monatti, he grabbed the flask and held it up. But before drinking, he turned to Renzo, staring him straight in the face, and with a mix of pity and scorn, said, “You must have made a pact with an awfully young devil. If we hadn’t come along to rescue you, a fat lot of help he would have been!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n201" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16401" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16412">With another snicker, he put the bottle to his lips. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n202" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16413" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16424">“And us? What about us!” shouted voices from the cart in front. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n203" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16425" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16477">The scoundrel, having drunk his fill, tossed the flask to his buddies with both hands. They passed it from man to man until the last monatto emptied it, swung the bottle around, and sent it crashing to the pavement, shouting, “Long live the plague!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n204" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16478" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16497">He chased these words with a raunchy song, his voice immediately joined by all the other members of that vile crew. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n205" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16498" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16533">That infernal tune, accompanied by the tinkling of the handbells, the squeaking of the carts, and the clip-clop of horses, echoed in the silence of the empty streets and resounded in the houses, wrapping a bitter fist around the hearts of the few remaining inhabitants. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n206" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16534" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16550">Are there no limits on what a man will do for his own convenience? Or on what he might sometimes like? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n207" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16551" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16591">The danger Renzo had just outrun made the company of those dead bodies and those living ghouls more than tolerable. And anything that removed him from their unseemly conversation was, I was about to say, like music to his ears. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n208" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16592" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16663">Still in shock and gasping for breath, he took a moment to thank Providence for getting him out of that predicament without inflicting or receiving harm. And now he prayed for Providence to help rescue him from his rescuers. He kept one eye on them and one eye on the road, looking for the right moment to slip off the cart undetected, without giving them the opportunity to cause a racket or make a scene that would turn passersby against him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n209" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16664" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16682">Suddenly, he thought he recognized the corner they were passing. He took a closer look. He was sure of it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n210" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16683" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16684">And do you know where he was? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n211" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16685" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16706">On Corso di Porta Orientale, the same street that he had slowly walked up, and quickly run down, some twenty months earlier. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n212" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16707" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16741">He immediately remembered that it led straight to the lazaretto. To find himself on the right road, without having to inquire, to search, had to be a gift from Providence, and a good omen for the rest of his journey. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n213" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16742" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16777">At that very moment, a commissioner was coming toward the carts, shouting at the monatti to stop and I don’t know what else. So the convoy halted and their music turned into a loud squabble. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n214" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16778" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16806">One of the monatti on Renzo’s cart jumped down. Renzo told the other, “Thank you for your kindness. May God bless you,” and he, too, jumped off, but on the other side. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n215" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16807" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16819">“On your way, on your way, poor little anointer,” the man replied. “It’ll take a bigger man than you to wipe out Milan.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n216" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16820" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16826">Luckily there was no one there to hear. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n217" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16827" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16898">The convoy had stopped on the left side of the road. Renzo quickly takes the opposite side and, hewing close to the wall, heads straight for the bridge. He crosses, continues down the road through the borgo, and recognizes the Capuchin monastery. As he approaches Porta Orientale, he can see the corner of the lazaretto. He passes through the gate. The scene outside the enclosure unfolds before his eyes. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n218" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16899" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16966">It was no more than a hint, a sample of what awaited him inside, but it was already indescribable: a vast, otherworldly scene. From the two sides of the lazaretto that Renzo could see, he spotted a swarm of people. The sick were being herded in, while others were sitting or lying down outside on the edges of the moat, too weak to walk inside or having collapsed after walking out of the shelter in desperation; still other poor souls wandered about aimlessly, in a daze. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n219" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_16967" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_17020">More than a few had lost their minds. One deranged man was recounting his hallucinations to a miserable wretch who was lying on the ground, oppressed by the disease. Another was having convulsions. A third looked around with a smile on his face, as if he was watching a comedy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n220" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_17021" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_17113">But the strangest and loudest sound in this grim gaiety was a high, steady singing that seemed to come not from that miserable horde, but instead, rose above it. It was a country love song, joyous and playful, known as a villanelle. Renzo searched to find the source of the sound, the person who could be so cheerful in a time and place like this. He saw a poor wretch sitting at the bottom of the moat, singing at the top of his lungs, his head leaning back. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n221" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_17114" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_17141">Scarcely had he taken a few steps along the southern side of the building when Renzo heard an extraordinary sound amid the multitude, and from the distance voices shouting, “Look! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n222" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_17142" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_17212">Grab him!” He stood on tiptoe and saw a giant horse galloping full speed with a strange rider on top: a delirious man who, seeing the animal untethered and unguarded next to a carriage, had quickly mounted it, bareback, and, pounding its neck with his fists and digging into its sides with his heels, spurred it on in a fury. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n223" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_17213" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_17252">Already weary and dismayed from the sight of so much misery, Renzo arrived at the gates of a place where more people were gathered than he had seen on his whole journey there. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap34-n224" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_17253" targetEnd="quarantana/cap34.xml#c34_17269">He walked up to the gate, passed underneath its arch, and for a moment, stood still in the middle of the portico. </note>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>