<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>2022</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed: a novel</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
          <date>2022</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Michael Moore</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="english_2022_cap4">
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10024">The sun had not yet fully breached the horizon when Padre Cristoforo left his monastery in Pescarenico to make his way up to the cottage where he was awaited. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10025" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10064">Pescarenico is a hamlet on the left bank of the Adda (or “the lake,” as we prefer to call it), not far from the bridge; a cluster of houses, inhabited for the most part by fishermen, decorated here and there by trammels and nets hung out to dry. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10065" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10094">The monastery was located (and the remains of the building still are) on the road from Lecco to Bergamo, opposite the entrance to the hamlet. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10095" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10131">The sky was crystal clear. As the sun slowly rose from behind the mountain, you could see its light shining on the summits across the river and making its way down the slopes and into the valley, as if it were rapidly unfurling. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10132" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10150">An autumn breeze lifted the withered leaves off the branches of the mulberry trees and deposited them a few feet away. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10151" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10187">In the vineyards to the right and the left, the foliage shimmered in various shades of red on the still unpruned shoots. And the freshly tilled soil, brown and distinctive, stood out in the fields of bleached stubble glistening with dew. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10188" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10204">It was a happy scene, but every human figure that appeared cast a pall on Padre Cristoforo’s gaze and his thoughts. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10205" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10224">Here and there he would come across beggars, ragged and skinny, seasoned practitioners or driven by need to hold out their hands. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10225" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10267">In silence they passed by Padre Cristoforo, staring at him piteously. Although they had nothing to hope for from him, since a Capuchin never placed his fingers on money, they would bow in gratitude for the charity they had received or were on their way to seeking at the monastery. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10268" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10279">The sight of laborers scattered in the fields was even more heartbreaking. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10280" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10311">Some were sowing seed parsimoniously, sparely, begrudgingly, as if they were risking something they cared about deeply. Others struggled to wield their spades, turning over the soil half-heartedly. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10312" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10351">A scrawny girl, leading an emaciated cow by a rope while it grazed, took a look around and then stooped down quickly to steal some herbs to feed her family, having learned from hunger that men, too, can subsist on grass. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10352" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10375">At every step of the way, these sights cast a deeper pall over the monk, who was already walking with a sad foreboding in his heart that he was about to hear of a new adversity. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10376" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10384">But why was he so concerned about Lucia? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10385" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10401">And why, as soon as he heard, had he acted so promptly, as if he had been summoned by the Father Provincial? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10402" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10407">And who was this Padre Cristoforo? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10408" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10414">All of these questions deserve an answer. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10415" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10429">Padre Cristoforo of *** was a man closer to the age of sixty than fifty. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10430" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10471">His head, bald except for a small crown of hair that circled his scalp, in compliance with the Capuchin Rule, looked up every now and then in a movement that revealed something proud and restless; and then, in a humble reflex, immediately looked down. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10472" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10513">A long white beard covered his cheeks and chin, and brought out the prominent features of the upper part of his face, to which a long habit of abstinence had lent gravity rather than removed passion. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10514" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10566">He had two sunken eyes that were usually lowered to the ground, but at times would flash in a sudden spark of liveliness, like two skittish horses being led by a coachman whom they knew through experience they could not best, but would still try to buck every now and then, and pay for it immediately with a hard tug on their bit. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10567" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10586">Padre Cristoforo had not always been a friar, nor had he always been a Cristoforo: His Christian name was Lodovico. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10587" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10625">He was the son of a merchant from *** (these asterisks reflect the discretion of my anonymous author) who, in his later years, finding himself well-to-do, and having only one son, had renounced commerce and dedicated himself to living the life of a gentleman. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10626" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10650">In his newfound leisure, the former merchant’s body was slowly penetrated by shame over all the time he had spent making a living in the world. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10651" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10671">Obsessed by this thought, he studied every possible way to make people forget that he had once had to work for a living. And he wished that he, too, could forget. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10672" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10702">But the shop, the bolts of fabric, the ledger, and the yardstick constantly reappeared in his memory like the ghost of Banquo to Macbeth, even amid the pomp of banquets and the smiles of sycophants. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10703" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10726">And you could not even begin to describe how carefully the poor guests had to avoid any word that might seem to allude to their host’s former station in life. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10727" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10779">One day, for example, toward the end of a banquet, when the merriment was so lively and so genuine that you couldn’t tell who was having more fun, the horde that was emptying the plates or the host who had set them out, he started teasing one of the guests, the world’s heartiest eater, with amiable condescension. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10780" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10802">The guest, responding in turn, with all the candor of a child and not a hint of malice, answered, “Eh! I’m going to act like the shopkeeper who pretends he hasn’t heard.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10803" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10841">The second the word came out of his mouth he cringed. With a hesitant expression, he looked at his host, whose face had clouded over. Both men wished the word could be taken back, but it was too late. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10842" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10872">The other guests thought, each to himself, how to smooth over the small scandal and change the subject. But they kept their thoughts to themselves, and in that silence the gaffe became even more conspicuous. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10873" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10891">Each of them avoided looking at the others. Each of them felt that all the others were thinking what they themselves wanted to hide. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10892" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10912">All joy, for that day, had fled the room. And the imprudent, or to be more precise, the unlucky man was never invited back. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10913" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10965">Lodovico’s father thus spent his last years in constant anxiety, always fearing that he would be mocked, never stopping to think that selling is no more ridiculous than buying, and that the profession he had become so ashamed of was one that he had exercised for many years, in public, and without remorse. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_10966" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11000">He raised his son as if he were a noble, according to the standards of the time, and to the extent allowed by law and custom. He hired tutors for him in the arts of letters and chivalry. And he died, leaving behind a young and wealthy heir. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11021">Lodovico had developed aristocratic habits, and the flatterers among whom he’d grown up had accustomed him to being treated with great deference. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11022" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11074">But when he wanted to mingle with the town’s leading citizens, he met a very different reception. And he saw that, if he wanted to be in their circle, he would have to enroll in a new school of patience and submission, willing to be looked down upon, willing to swallow new humiliations. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11075" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11090">This lifestyle did not accord with Lodovico’s upbringing or his character. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11091" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11094">He took his distance from them, irritated. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11095" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11119">But then he regretted that distance, since he felt that they should really have been his companions. If only they could have been more agreeable. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11120" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11160">With this mixture of eagerness and resentment, unable to frequent them as friends yet wanting to associate with them in some fashion, he began competing with the town’s aristocrats in ostentation and grandiosity, thus purchasing wholesale their hostility, envy, and ridicule. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11161" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11177">Over time his temperament, both honest and violent, led him into more serious rivalries. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11178" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11216">He felt an instinctive, sincere horror at injustice and bullying, a feeling heightened by the status of the main perpetrators: the very men he so deeply resented. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11217" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11269">As a way of acting on all these passions at the same time, he sided with the weaker, losing party, put bullies in their place, stuck his nose into other people’s quarrels, and sought quarrels of his own. As a result, he gradually took on the role of protector of the oppressed and avenger of wrongs. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11270" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11286">It was a heavy responsibility, and of course poor Lodovico ended up with enemies, obligations, and concerns. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11287" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11328">In addition to the wars outside, he was constantly tormented by inner conflicts, since to win his battles (not to mention the ones he lost), he had to adopt forms of deception and violence that his conscience could not condone. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11329" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11366">He had to retain a number of bravacci. For the sake of his own security and his need for the most vigorous assistance, he had to choose the most daring and vile companions, out of love for justice, and was forced to live with scoundrels. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11367" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11434">It bothered him so much that on more than one occasion, when he was either upset by an unfortunate outcome or anxious about an imminent danger, annoyed to be constantly on his guard, disgusted by the company he kept, worried about the future and the dwindling of his fortune with each passing day, through both good deeds and bad, he began to fantasize about becoming a friar, the most common expedient in those days for escaping trouble. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11435" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11462">But what might have remained a lifelong daydream became a genuine resolution because of an accident, the most serious that had ever befallen him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11463" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11494">One day he was walking down a street of his city, accompanied by two bravi and a certain Cristoforo, who in the past had worked as an apprentice to his father but, after the shop was closed, became steward of Lodovico’s household. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11495" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11531">He was a man of about fifty who had been fond of Lodovico since his youth, and present at his birth. Between wages and gifts, Lodovico had provided him not only with a livelihood but also with the means to support and raise a large family. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11532" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11585">In the distance Lodovico spotted a certain gentleman, an arrogant bully by profession. Although the man had never spoken with Lodovico, he was his cordial enemy, a sentiment heartily reciprocated, since one of the benefits of this world is for complete strangers to hate and be hated in turn. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11586" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11607">This man, escorted by four bravi, walked straight ahead, with a haughty gait, head held high, and mouth twisted into a proud, scornful expression. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11608" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11660">Both men walked close to the wall, but Lodovico (pay attention) had the wall to his right. According to custom, that gave him the right not to break away from the wall to let another person pass (there was a law for that, too), which mattered a great deal in those days. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11661" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11686">The other man claimed, on the contrary, that, as a nobleman, he had the right of way, and that it was up to Lodovico to move to the middle of the road, in deference to a different custom. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11687" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11731">For here, as in many other instances, there were two opposing customs, and no decision had been rendered on which of the two should prevail. This created the opportunity for a war to break out every time an obstinate man ran into someone else of the same temperament. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11732" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11746">The two approached each other, hugging the wall, like moving figures on a bas-relief. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11747" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11774">Once they were face-to-face, the aristocrat, with an imperious air, sized up Lodovico and in a corresponding tone of voice told him, “Move.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11775" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11779">“You move,” replied Lodovico. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11780" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11783">“I have the right of way.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11784" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11789">“With men of your class, the right is always mine.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11790" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11801">“Only if the arrogance of your class were the law for mine.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11802" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11825">The bravi of both men came to a halt, each behind his master, glowering at one another, hands on their daggers, ready for battle. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11826" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11855">Onlookers gathered around, keeping their distance but watching the event unfold. Their presence made the rivals even more unwilling to back down. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11856" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11869">“To the middle of the road, you lowlife tradesman, or I’ll teach you once and for all how to behave with a gentleman!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11870" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11874">“Liar! Who are you calling a lowlife?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11875" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11884">“You’re the liar, for calling me a liar!” was the rejoinder prescribed by the chivalric code. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11885" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11911">“If you were a gentleman, like me,” the gentleman added, “I would show you with my sword and cape that the liar is you.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11912" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11925">“Ah, a good excuse for you not to back up your insults with deeds.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11926" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11936">“Throw this rogue in the mud,” said the gentleman, turning to his men. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11937" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11949">“We’ll see about that,” replied Lodovico, immediately taking a step back and placing his hand on his sword. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11950" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11965">“You impudent dog!” cried the other, unsheathing his own weapon. “I’ll shatter my sword after it’s been dirtied with your filthy blood.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11966" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11981">At this they lunged at each other. The men on both sides rushed in to defend their masters. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_11982" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12017">The fight was uneven, both in number, and because Lodovico was more intent on fending off blows and disarming the enemy than on killing him. But his opponent wanted him dead at all costs. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12018" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12058">Lodovico had already been stabbed in his left arm by a bravo, and grazed on one cheek. His adversary charged forward to finish him off, when Cristoforo, seeing his master in extreme danger, came at the gentleman with his dagger. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12059" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12072">The man, turning his full rage on the steward, ran him through with his sword. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12073" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12098">At the sight, Lodovico snapped and thrust his sword into the stomach of the murderer, who fell, dying at almost the same time as poor Cristoforo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12099" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12154">The gentleman’s bravi, bruised and bloodied and realizing that the battle was lost, took to their heels. Lodovico’s men, who were also battered and bruised, seeing no one left to fight and not wanting to get caught in the mob of people rushing toward them, took off in another direction. And Lodovico found himself alone, in the middle of the crowd, with the two dying men at his feet. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12155" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12156">“What happened?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12157" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12162">“There’s one.” “There’s two.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12163" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12170">“A hole right through the stomach!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12171" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12175">“Who got killed?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12176" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12178">“That tyrant.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12179" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12184">“Holy Mother of God, what mayhem!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12185" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12188">“Seek and you shall find.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12189" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12193">“You get what you deserve in the end.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12194" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12198">“He’s done for, too.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12199" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12201">“What a blow!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12202" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12207">“This must be serious.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12208" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12211">“And that other poor soul!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12212" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12215">“Good Lord, what a sight!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12216" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12218">“Save him, save him.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12219" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12223">“He’s not long for this world, either.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12224" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12233">“Look at the state he’s in! Bleeding everywhere!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12234" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12236">“Run, run. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12237" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12241">Don’t let yourself get caught!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12242" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12266">These words, which could be heard above the din of the crowd, expressed the general consensus. And with that advice came help. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12267" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12299">The fight had taken place near a Capuchin church: sanctuary, as everyone knows, that cannot be breached by the police or by the complex of things and people known as the justice system. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12300" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12346">The wounded murderer was taken or rather carried there, almost unconscious, by the crowd. The friars received him from the hands of the people, who entrusted him to them saying, “He’s a good man who killed an arrogant scoundrel. It was self-defense. He was forced into it.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12347" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12404">Lodovico had never, until that moment, taken a life. Although murder was so common in those days that everyone’s ears were used to hearing about it, and eyes to seeing it, to watch one man die for him and another because of him came as a new and unspeakable shock, awakening unfamiliar feelings. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12405" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12440">The fall of his enemy, the alteration in his face, which in a moment passed from fury and menace to defeat and the solemn stillness of death, was a sight that transformed the murderer’s heart in an instant. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12441" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12492">Having been carried inside the monastery, Lodovico had no idea where he was or what he was doing there. When he came to his senses, he found himself in a bed in the infirmary, in the hands of the Brother Surgeon (the Capuchins normally had one in each monastery), who was wrapping in medicated gauze and bandages the two wounds he had received in the clash. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12493" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12520">A padre assigned to tend to the dying, a service he had often had to provide on the road, was called to the place of combat. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12521" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12553">A few minutes later he returned, entered the infirmary, and approached the bed where Lodovico was lying. “Be consoled,” he said, “at least Cristoforo died well. He told me to ask for your forgiveness and to offer you his own.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12554" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12601">These words revived poor Lodovico, and awakened in him even more sharply and vividly the confused feelings crowding into his heart: grief for his friend, consternation and remorse over the fatal blow inflicted by his own hand, and anguished compassion for the man he had killed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12602" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12607">“And the other man?” he asked the friar anxiously. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12608" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12612">“He was already dead when I got there.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12613" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12649">As they spoke, the doors of the monastery bustled with curious onlookers, until the police dispersed the crowd and stationed themselves at a distance from the gate, but close enough for no one to leave unobserved. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12650" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12703">A brother of the dead man, two of his cousins, and an elderly uncle arrived, armed from head to toe, with a large retinue of bravi, and started to circle the crowd, glaring scornfully and threateningly at the onlookers, who did not dare to say, “He got what he deserved,” although it was written on their faces. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12704" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12753">As soon as Lodovico could gather his thoughts, he called for a Brother Confessor and asked him to seek out Cristoforo’s widow, and on his behalf to beg forgiveness for having been the cause—unwillingly, of course—of her desolation, and at the same time to assure her that he would take care of the family. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12754" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12809">Reflecting next on his own affairs, he could feel rekindling inside, more vividly and earnestly than ever before, the idea of becoming a friar. He felt as if God himself had set him on this path and given him a sign by leading him to a monastery at this juncture in life. His decision was made. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12810" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12819">He asked to see the Father Guardian, to whom he expressed his desire. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12820" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12835">In reply he was told to be wary of hasty decisions, but that if he persisted in his intentions, he would not be turned down. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12836" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12878">Then, in the presence of a notary, Lodovico dictated that his remaining possessions (which were still a hefty patrimony) were to be donated to Cristoforo’s family: a sum to his widow, as if he were establishing a second dowry, and the rest to the eight children whom Cristoforo had left behind. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12879" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12899">Lodovico’s decision could not have been more opportune for his hosts, who were in quite a predicament on his account. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12900" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12921">The idea of sending him away from the monastery, thereby exposing him to justice—namely, the revenge of his enemies—was not even contemplated. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12922" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12966">It would have been tantamount to renouncing the privileges of the Order, discrediting the monastery among the people, drawing the condemnation of every Capuchin in the universe for allowing a violation of their common rights, and rankling the ecclesiastical authorities, who considered themselves the guardians of those rights. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12967" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12997">On the other hand, the family of the murdered man, which was powerful in its own right and through its associates, was intent on revenge, and would treat as an enemy anyone who tried to get in the way. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_12998" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13033">History does not tell us that they mourned the dead man, or that his relatives wept over him. It only says that they were all in a frenzy to get their hands on the murderer, dead or alive. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13034" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13042">But now the murderer, by donning the Capuchin habit, had settled everything. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13043" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13068">In a sense, he was making amends, doing penance, acknowledging his guilt implicitly, and withdrawing from every challenge. In other words, he was an enemy laying down his arms. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13069" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13093">The dead man’s relatives could believe and protest all they wanted that he had become a friar out of desperation and fear of their wrath. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13094" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13131">At the same time, to reduce a man to giving up his earthly possessions, shaving his head, walking barefoot, sleeping on a burlap sack, and living on alms should seem like a fitting punishment to even the most pompous injured party. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13132" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13202">The Father Guardian presented himself, humble yet self-assured, to the brother of the deceased. After countless protests of his respect for the illustrious house, and his desire to appease it as best he could, he spoke of Lodovico’s repentance and decision, implying diplomatically that the house should consider them sufficient, and intimating, more subtly and artfully, that, like it or not, this was the way things would be. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13203" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13222">The brother flew into a rage, which the Capuchin allowed to blow over, saying repeatedly, “You have every right to be upset.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13223" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13247">The brother hinted that, in one way or another, his family would have its satisfaction. The Capuchin, whatever he might have thought, did not disagree. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13248" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13263">In the end the brother requested, or rather imposed, one condition: that his brother’s killer leave the city immediately. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13264" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13293">The guardian, who had already decided on this course of action, told him that it would be done, letting the other man believe, if he wished, that it was an act of obedience. And so the matter was concluded. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13294" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13385">The family was happy, since it had emerged with its honor intact. The friars were happy, since they had saved a man and their privileges without making any enemies. The lovers of chivalry were happy, since they saw a commendable conclusion to the affair. The people were happy, since they saw a beloved man being kept out of danger, at the same time as they admired a conversion. And finally, happiest of all, amid his grief, was our Lodovico, who had embarked on a life of expiation and servitude that could, if not undo the crime, then at least atone for it, and relieve him of the intolerable pangs of remorse. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13386" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13417">For a moment he was beset by the suspicion that he was only acting out of fear. But he was immediately consoled by the thought that even an unjust opinion was a form of punishment and a means of atonement. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13418" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13454">So at the age of thirty, he donned the tunic. And having to give up his own name, according to custom, and take another, he chose one that reminded him every minute of the day of the reason for his atonement: He took the name Fra Cristoforo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13455" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13480">— As soon as the Investiture Ceremony was over, the guardian instructed him that he would be leaving the next day to do his novitiate in ***, sixty miles away. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13481" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13488">The novice made a deep bow and requested one favor. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13489" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13546">“Padre,” he said, “before leaving this city, where I have killed a man, where I am leaving behind a family that has been cruelly injured, allow me to at least make amends for my deed. Allow me to at least show my regret that I am unable to remedy the harm I have done by asking forgiveness of the dead man’s brother, and alleviating, if God should bless my intention, the rage from his heart.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13547" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13581">The guardian felt that this proposal, in addition to being innately good, would also help to further reconcile the family with the monastery. He went at once to see the brother and convey Fra Cristoforo’s request. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13582" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13600">At such an unexpected proposal, the brother felt both a sense of surprise and a renewed indignation, though not without some complacency. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13601" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13611">After giving it a moment’s thought, he said, “Come by tomorrow,” and set a time. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13612" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13621">The guardian returned to the monastery, bringing the novice the desired consent. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13622" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13662">The nobleman immediately realized that the more solemn and resounding the apology, the more it would elevate his status among his relatives and the public. And it would add a nice page (to say it with modern eloquence) to the family history. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13663" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13688">He quickly notified all of his relatives that, at noon the next day, they were to grace him with their presence (as they used to say back then), on the occasion of an apology to be made to the family as a whole. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13689" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13727">At noon, the palace was bustling with nobles of every age and sex. It was a swirl, a blend of wide capes, tall feathers, dangling swords, a soft rustling of starched collars, embroidered cassocks weaving in and out. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13728" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13744">The vestibules, courtyard, and road teemed with servants, pages, bravi, and onlookers. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13745" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13783">Fra Cristoforo observed the pageantry, guessed the reason behind it, and felt a slight unease. After a moment, however, he said to himself, “It’s only right. I killed him in public, in the presence of many of his enemies. That was an affront. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13784" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13883">This is reparations.” So with his eyes lowered and the Father Guardian by his side, he passed through the gates to the house and crossed the courtyard, surrounded by a crowd that looked him up and down with a most unceremonious curiosity. He climbed the stairs and, surrounded by a second crowd of nobles that parted to let him through, followed by a hundred stares, he came into the presence of the master of the house. The latter, flanked by his closest relatives, was standing in the center of the room, his eyes on the ground and his chin in the air, gripping the hilt of his sword with his left hand, while pressing to his chest the lapel of his cape with his right. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13884" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13914">Sometimes the face and demeanor of a man have such a spontaneous expression, almost an effusion of the inner self, that a crowd of spectators will reach a single judgment of that self. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13915" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13944">The face and demeanor of Fra Cristoforo made it clear to the onlookers that he had not become a friar or arrived at that humiliation out of fear of man, a consideration that started to appease everyone. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13945" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13975">When he saw the injured party, he quickened his step, knelt at the man’s feet, crossed his arms over his chest, and bowing his shaven head, uttered these words: “I am the murderer of your brother. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_13976" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14002">God knows that I would pay with my own blood to bring him back to you, but since I can do nothing more than make my futile and belated apologies, I beg you to accept them out of love of God.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14003" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14021">All eyes were on the novice and the man to whom he was speaking. All ears were listening. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14022" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14037">When Fra Cristoforo fell silent, the room was filled with a murmuring of compassion and respect for him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14038" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14098">The nobleman, who had been standing there with an attitude of forced cordiality and compressed rage, was shaken by these words. Leaning toward the kneeling man, he said, in an altered voice, “Stand up, sir. The crime…or rather, the deed…but the habit you wear…not only that, but you yourself…Please, Padre, stand up…My brother…I cannot deny…was a gentleman…a man…who could be impetuous…a bit of a temper. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14099" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14105">But God’s will be done. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14106" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14119">Let us speak no more of this…But, Padre, you must not stay in this position.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14120" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14126">Taking him by the arm, he helped him up. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14127" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14146">Fra Cristoforo, standing but with his head still bowed, replied, “Can I therefore hope for your forgiveness? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14147" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14156">And if I receive forgiveness from you, from whom should I not expect it? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14157" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14166">Oh, if I could only hear from your mouth the word ‘forgiveness.’ ” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14167" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14170">“Forgiveness?” the man asked. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14171" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14176">“You no longer need it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14177" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14190">But as you wish, of course, of course, I forgive you from my heart, and all of us…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14191" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14198">“All of us! All of us!” shouted the onlookers in unison. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14199" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14228">The friar’s face lit up in joyful appreciation, yet beneath it one could still detect a humble, deep contrition for his sin, which human forgiveness could not repair. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14229" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14254">The nobleman, overcome by that appearance, and surrendering to the general commotion, threw his arms around his neck to give and receive the kiss of peace. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14255" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14273">Cries of “Bravo! Well done!” broke out from each corner of the hall. Everyone crowded around the priest. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14274" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14281">The servants arrived with a great abundance of refreshments. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14282" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14307">The nobleman approached Cristoforo, who indicated that the time had come for him to take his leave, and said, “Padre, please have something to eat. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14308" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14340">Allow me this proof of your friendship,” and he started to serve him before anyone else. But Cristoforo, taking a step back with polite resistance, said, “Such things are no longer for me. But let it never be said that I refused your gifts. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14341" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14374">I am about to depart on a journey. If you would be so kind as to have a piece of bread brought to me, so that I may say I have benefited from your charity, eaten your bread, and received a token of your forgiveness.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14375" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14411">Deeply moved, the nobleman ordered that it be done. A waiter immediately appeared, in full livery, carrying the bread on a silver platter, and presented it to the friar. Taking it and expressing his appreciation, Fra Cristoforo placed it in his bag. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14412" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14498">He then asked permission to take his leave. Embracing the master of the house one more time, as well as anyone nearby who managed to steal a moment, he broke away with difficulty. He had to fight his way through the vestibule, through the crush of servants and even bravi, who kissed the hem, the cord, and the hood of his habit. He found himself in the street, carried as if in triumph, and accompanied by a crowd of the common people all the way to the gates of the city. And from there he left, beginning his journey on foot to the place of his novitiate. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14499" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14528">The brother of the slain man and his relatives, who on that day had expected to savor the bitter joy of pride, found themselves filled instead with the serene joy of forgiveness and goodwill. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14529" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14552">The company lingered on for a while longer, with unusual good humor and cordiality, in discussions that none of them had expected on their way there. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14553" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14575">Rather than satisfaction exacted, outrages avenged, and challenges won, they sang the novice’s praises and spoke of meekness and reconciliation. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14576" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14624">The man who would have told the story for the fiftieth time of how his father, Count Muzio, on that famous occasion, had put in his place the Marquis Stanislao, a notorious braggart, spoke instead of the penance and the amazing patience of Fra Simone, who had died many years earlier. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14625" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14688">After the company had left, the master, still filled with emotion, marveled at what he had heard and what he had said. “That devil!” he muttered between his teeth (we have to be careful to transcribe his exact words). “That devil! If he’d stayed on his knees a minute longer, I would have been the one apologizing to him for his killing my brother.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14689" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14713">Our story points out that, from that day forth, the nobleman was a little less impulsive, and a lot more affable. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14714" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14741">Fra Cristoforo walked away with a sense of consolation he had not felt since the fateful day for which he would atone the rest of his life. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14742" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14768">The novice’s vow of silence came easily to him, lost as he was in thoughts of the labors, sacrifice, and humiliation he would suffer to pay for his sin. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14769" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14801">When he stopped at the home of a benefactor at dinnertime, he ate almost voraciously the bread of forgiveness he had received. But he saved one piece and placed it back in his bag, to keep as a perpetual reminder. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14802" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14856">— I have no intention of telling the story of his life in the cloister. I will only say that, in carrying out, always willingly and scrupulously, his regularly assigned duties to preach and to minister to the dying, he never missed a chance to perform two others that he had imposed on himself: to settle disputes and to protect the oppressed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14857" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14888">In this vocation there were unconscious traces of his old lifestyle and vestiges of his warrior spirit that the humiliations and self-mortification of monastic life had not completely extinguished. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14889" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14931">His language was usually humble and measured, but when justice or truth were at stake, his old temper would suddenly flare, seconded and modified by the solemn emphasis he had gained through preaching, lending a unique character to his language. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14932" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14961">His whole demeanor, like his appearance, betrayed a long war between a fiery, resentful disposition and the opposite desire, which usually prevailed, always alert and guided by higher motives and inspiration. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_14962" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_15010">A fellow friar and friend, who knew him well, once compared him to words that are overly colorful in their natural form, which some people, even the educated, utter when passion overflows, but in a fractured form, with a couple of letters changed for the sake of propriety. Words that, despite this disguise, maintain their original energy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_15011" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_15029">If a poor unknown girl, in a dire situation like Lucia’s, were to ask for Padre Cristoforo’s help, he would come running. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_15030" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_15067">Since it was Lucia herself, he came all the more quickly, for he knew and admired her innocence, was already worried about the dangers facing her, which he had learned of from her confession, and felt a holy indignation over the depraved harassment to which she had been subjected. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_15068" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_15116">In addition to which, having advised her, as the lesser of evils, to say nothing and to keep quiet, he now feared that his advice might have had an unintentionally dire effect. His innate propensity toward charity was increased, in this case, by the scrupulous anxiety that often torments good people. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap4-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_15117" targetEnd="quarantana/cap4.xml#c4_15158">But while I’ve been telling you the story of Padre Cristoforo, he has in the meantime arrived and appeared at the door. And the women, abandoning the squeaky spinning wheel they had been turning, stood up and said in a single voice, “Padre Cristoforo. God bless you for coming!” </note>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>