<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>2022</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed: a novel</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
          <date>2022</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Michael Moore</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="english_2022_cap6">
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10014">“How can I be of assistance to you?” asked Don Rodrigo, staking himself in the center of the room. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10015" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10040">This was how his words sounded, but the way he said them clearly meant: Mind whom you’re speaking with, watch what you say, and be quick about it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10041" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10060">There was no faster or surer way to muster Padre Cristoforo’s courage than to treat him disdainfully. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10061" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10110">He had been hesitating, searching for the right words and fingering the beads on the rosary he wore for a belt, as if hoping to find inspiration in one of them, but Don Rodrigo’s provocation instantly brought to his lips a few too many. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10111" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10156">Realizing how important it was not to ruin his chances, or rather, and more to the point, the chances of others, he hastened to temper the sentences that had sprung to mind, and instead, with cautious humility, said, “I have come to propose an act of justice, to beg for your charity. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10157" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10187">Certain disreputable characters have used your name to intimidate a poor priest, prevent him from performing his duties, and oppress an innocent young couple. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10188" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10211">With a single word, you can stop them, restore the force of law, and bring relief to those who have suffered such cruel violence. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10212" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10218">You can, and therefore…your conscience, your honor…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10219" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10230">“I’ll allow you to speak about my conscience the day I come to you to make my confession. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10231" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10266">As for my honor, you should know that I and I alone am its guardian, and anyone who thinks they can share this responsibility is an insolent fool.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10267" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10332">Padre Cristoforo thus stood forewarned that Don Rodrigo would twist his words, turn their conversation into a quarrel, and block any chance of getting to the point. So he doubled his resolve to be patient and swallow whatever the other man felt like saying. He quickly responded, in a subdued tone, “If I have said anything to displease you, it was not my intention. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10333" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10348">Correct me if I’m wrong, or if I have spoken out of turn. But please hear me out. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10349" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10400">For the love of heaven, of God, before whose presence we all must appear…” As he said this, he grasped the wooden skull attached to his rosary and lifted it before the eyes of his glowering listener. “Do not persist in refusing a justice that is so simple and so deserved by the poor couple. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10401" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10421">Remember that God is always watching over them, and their cries of pain are heard in heaven. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10422" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10426">Innocence is powerful to his—” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10427" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10464">“Eh, Padre,” Don Rodrigo cut him off brusquely, “I have great respect for the habit you wear. But if there’s anything that might make me forget this, it’d be to see the habit on a man who dares to stick his nose into my business in my own home.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10465" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10497">Although these words set the priest’s face ablaze, he continued on, with the look of someone swallowing bitter medicine. “You know I don’t deserve to be called a spy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10498" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10515">You know in your heart that my visit here today is neither cowardly nor contemptible. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10516" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10536">Hear what I have to say, Don Rodrigo, and heaven pray the day may never come that you will regret not having done so. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10537" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10556">Do not place your pride…such pride, Don Rodrigo! Such pride before mankind maybe, but not before God! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10557" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10561">Whatever you might do here on earth, up there—” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10562" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10594">Don Rodrigo cut him off angrily, but not without a shudder of dread. “When I get a hankering to hear a sermon, you must realize that I’m perfectly capable of going to church like other people. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10595" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10598">But in my own home? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10599" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10616">Oh!” He continued, with a derisive sneer, “You flatter me. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10617" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10620">A preacher in my house? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10621" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10625">Only princes can afford such a luxury!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10626" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10667">“The same God that calls on princes to account for the word he brings to them in their palaces; that same God is now showing you his mercy by sending his minister, unworthy and poor though he may be, but still his minister, to intercede on behalf of an innocent—” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10668" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10698">“Let me be brief,” said Don Rodrigo, making as if to go. “I don’t know what you’re insinuating. What I do know is that there must be some girl you care about. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10699" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10720">Go confide in whomever you wish. But do not take the liberty of wasting a gentleman’s time with such petty annoyances.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10721" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10774">At Don Rodrigo’s movement, the friar blocked his path, but with great respect, of course. Raising his hands, to both plead with and stop him, he continued to speak. “I do care about her, it’s true, but no more than I do about you. Two souls that I care about more than my own blood. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10775" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10792">Don Rodrigo! The only thing I can do for you is pray to God, and I’m happy to do so. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10793" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10807">Do not tell me not to. I do not want a poor innocent girl to be filled with fear and distress. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10808" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10814">One word from you is all it would take.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10815" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10836">“Well, then,” said Don Rodrigo, “since you think I can do so much for this person, and you’ve taken her to heart…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10837" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10861">“Yes?” Fra Cristoforo resumed anxiously, knowing from Don Rodrigo’s demeanor not to yield to the optimism his words would seem to suggest. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10862" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10872">“Well, then, advise her to come place herself under my protection. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10873" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10886">She will want for nothing, and no one will dare harass her, on my word as a gentleman.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10887" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10898">At this, the indignation the priest had struggled to repress boiled over. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10899" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10927">All his resolve to be prudent and patient went up in smoke. His old self joined with the new; in a moment like this, Fra Cristoforo was truly two men in one. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10928" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10963">“Your protection!” he exclaimed, taking two steps back and leaning defiantly on his right foot. With his right hand on his hip he pointed his left index finger at Don Rodrigo and glared at him with two fiery eyes. “Your protection! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10964" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10977">I’m glad you spoke this way, and that you made such a proposal. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10978" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10986">Now you’ve gone too far. You don’t frighten me anymore!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10987" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10989">“How dare you speak to me like this!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10990" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11005">“I’m speaking to a man who has been forsaken by God, and can no longer be feared. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11006" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11008">Your protection, you say? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11009" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11039">I already knew that that innocent girl was under God’s protection. But you…now I’m more certain than ever that I should hold nothing back when I speak to you. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11040" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11056">Lucia, I say. See how I say her name with my head held high, without batting an eye.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11057" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11060">“How dare you! In this house!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11061" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11071">“I pity this house. A curse is hanging over it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11072" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11089">Wait and see whether divine justice will have any consideration for this pile of rocks, or any fear of your petty gang of thugs. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11090" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11107">Did you think that God made a creature in his own image to give you the pleasure of tormenting her? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11108" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11115">Did you think that God couldn’t defend her? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11116" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11124">You have rejected his warning and brought down his judgment upon yourself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11125" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11138">The Pharaoh’s heart was as hard as yours, and God was still able to break it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11139" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11160">Lucia is safe from you. Mark my words, although I am just a poor friar. As for you, listen carefully to what I promise you. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11161" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11163">The day will come…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11164" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11193">Until that moment Don Rodrigo had been at a loss for words, stunned, caught between anger and shock. But at the first sounds of a prophecy, his anger was joined by a remote and mysterious dread. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11194" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11218">He grabbed that threatening hand in the air and, raising his voice to cut off the ominous voice of the prophet, shouted, “Out of my sight, you insolent peasant, you cowled beggar!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11219" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11229">These sharp words immediately quieted Padre Cristoforo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11230" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11280">The idea of mistreatment and villainy had long been associated, in his mind, with the need for sufferance and silence. Don Rodrigo’s compliments, however, drained him of all fury and passion. He resolved to listen in silence to whatever the man cared to add. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11281" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11321">So he calmly withdrew his hand from Don Rodrigo’s clutches, lowered his head, and stood still, like a shaken tree that, at the lull of the wind in the midst of a storm, opens its branches into their natural shape and receives the hail that the heavens rain down upon it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11322" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11331">“You vile upstart!” Don Rodrigo went on, “You think you’re my equal? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11332" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11358">The habit on your cowardly back is the only thing standing between you and the caresses I usually bestow on people of your class to teach them manners. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11359" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11369">This time you can leave on your own two feet. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11370" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11406">But next time…” With this he pointed with imperious disdain at the door opposite the one through which they had entered. Padre Cristoforo bowed his head and exited, leaving Don Rodrigo to furiously pace the field of battle. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11407" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11450">As the friar closed the door behind him and entered the next room, he noticed a man slowly sneaking away, brushing against the wall, as if he did not wish to be seen from the room where the colloquy had taken place. He recognized the elderly servant who had welcomed him at the outside entrance. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11451" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11475">He had belonged to that house for maybe forty years, since before Don Rodrigo was born, having entered into the service of the master’s father, another breed of man altogether. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11476" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11547">Upon his death, the new master dismissed the whole staff and hired a new crew, keeping only that one servant. Despite his age, and despite moral convictions and a manner of behavior completely contrary to Don Rodrigo’s, he had two qualities to compensate for these faults: a high regard for the dignity of the house, and years of experience with protocol, whose ancient traditions and minute particulars he knew better than anyone. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11548" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11625">In the master’s presence the poor old man would never dare to insinuate, much less openly express, his disapproval of the goings-on he witnessed every day. The most he ever did was mutter a criticism of his fellow servants, who would only laugh, and indeed, seemed to enjoy teasing him, trying to get him to say more than he had meant to, and to sing the praises of the way things used to be in the old days. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11626" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11655">The master only ever received word of those criticisms together with reports of the laughter they had provoked, so he, too, was amused rather than stung by them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11656" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11670">Not to mention that, on days of invitation or reception, the old man became a serious, important personage. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11671" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11714">Padre Cristoforo looked at the servant as he passed, greeted him, and continued on his way. The elderly man, however, came alongside him mysteriously, placed his finger to his lips, and then, with the same finger, signaled that the friar should follow him into a dark corridor. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11715" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11730">There he whispered, “Padre, I heard everything. I need to speak with you.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11731" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11734">“Tell me quickly, my good man.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11735" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11753">“Not here. I’d be in trouble if the master found out…But I know many things, and I’ll try to come to the monastery tomorrow.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11754" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11756">“Is some kind of mischief being plotted?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11757" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11777">“There’s definitely something in the air. I’d already noticed earlier, but now I’ll be on the lookout, and I hope to discover everything. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11778" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11781">Leave it to me. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11782" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11792">The things I see and hear!…Hellish things! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11793" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11802">I’m in a place that…But I want to save my soul.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11803" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11834">“May God bless you!” As he whispered these words, the priest placed his hand on the white head of the servant, who, although he was his senior, had bowed down before him like a child. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11835" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11846">“God will reward you,” Padre Cristoforo continued, “I’ll be waiting for you tomorrow.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11847" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11863">“I’ll come,” the servant replied, “but you have to leave immediately and please, for the love of heaven, don’t mention my name.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11864" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11907">At this he took a look around and moved toward the other end of the corridor, to a hall next to the courtyard. Seeing that the coast was clear, he beckoned to the good friar, whose expression was a clearer response to his last remark than any number of spoken promises. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11908" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11919">He pointed to the door, and the friar left, without uttering another word. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11920" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11931">The old man had eavesdropped at his master’s door. Had he done the right thing? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11932" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11940">And was Fra Cristoforo right to praise him for it? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11941" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11960">According to the most common and least controversial rules, what he did was wrong. But couldn’t this case be considered an exception? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11961" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11971">And are there exceptions to the most common and least controversial rules? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11972" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11984">The reader will have to settle these important questions by him- or herself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11985" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11997">I have no wish to pass judgment. All I want are the facts of the story. — </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11998" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12040">Once he was outside, with his back to that bleak house, Fra Cristoforo could breathe easier. He rushed downhill, his face flushed with anger, feeling agitated and upset, as anyone can imagine, by what he had heard and said. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12041" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12082">But the servant’s unexpected appearance had lifted his spirits. He felt as if heaven had given him a visible sign of its protection. “Here’s a thread,” he thought, “a thread that Providence has placed in my hands. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12083" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12087">In that very house! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12088" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12095">One I hadn’t even dreamed of seeking!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12096" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12122">Amid these ruminations, he looked up to the west and saw that the setting sun was about to touch the mountaintop, and realized how little daylight remained. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12123" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12175">Though his bones ached, weary from the various fatigues of the day, he quickened his pace so he could bring news of some kind to his wards and then reach the monastery by nightfall, which was one of the most rigid and strictly enforced rules of the Capuchin order. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12176" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12195">Meanwhile, at Lucia’s cottage, plans had been hatched and debated that I should share with the reader. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12196" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12241">After the friar’s departure, the three left behind had remained in silence for some time: Lucia sadly preparing the meal; Renzo constantly on the verge of leaving, so as not to see her so dejected, yet unable to tear himself away; and Agnese, who appeared to be fully intent on her spinning wheel. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12242" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12259">In reality, however, she was concocting a plan, and when it seemed ripe, she broke the silence by saying: </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12260" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12261">“Listen, my children. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12262" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12300">If you’re smart enough and brave enough, and if you trust your mother…” Lucia was startled to hear Agnese refer to Renzo as one of her children. The older woman continued: “I promise to get you out of this mess, better, perhaps, and more quickly than Padre Cristoforo, good man though he is.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12301" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12333">Lucia stood there, looking at her mother with a face that expressed more astonishment than trust in such an incredible promise. Renzo said at once, “Smart? Brave? Tell us, go ahead and tell us what we have to do.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12334" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12348">“Isn’t it true,” Agnese continued, “that it would be a big step forward if you were already married? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12349" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12359">And that all the rest would be easier to fix?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12360" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12387">“Of course,” said Renzo, “if we were married…our marriage would be honored the whole world over. Not far away from here, in the Bergamo area, they welcome silk-workers with open arms. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12388" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12426">Do you know how many times my cousin Bortolo has been urging me to go there to live with him, saying I’d make a fortune, like him? And if I never did, it’s because…Oh, why hide it?…It’s because my heart is here. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12427" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12453">Once we’re married, we could all move there, set up house, and live in peace and quiet, beyond the clutches of this scoundrel, and far from the temptation to do something I’d regret. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12454" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12456">Isn’t that so, Lucia?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12457" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12461">“Yes,” said Lucia, “but how?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12462" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12476">“Like I said,” continued her mother, “if you’re smart and brave, the deed is easy.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12477" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12492">“Easy?” exclaimed the pair together, since the deed had turned out to be so extraordinarily and painfully difficult. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12493" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12498">“Easy, if you know how to go about it,” Agnese replied. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12499" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12505">“Listen carefully. I’ll try to explain. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12506" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12541">People I know have told me—and I’ve seen a case myself—that to perform a wedding, you need the presence of the priest, but not necessarily his consent. He just has to be present.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12542" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12547">“What do you mean?” Renzo asked. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12548" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12550">“Listen and I’ll tell you. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12551" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12559">You need a clear plan and to find two witnesses who are quick on their feet. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12560" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12575">You go to the priest. You have to catch him by surprise, so he doesn’t have time to get away. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12576" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12592">The man says: Father, this is my wife. The woman says: Father, this is my husband. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12593" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12614">The priest has to hear them, as do the witnesses, and the marriage is done, as holy as if the Pope himself had performed it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12615" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12633">Once the words are pronounced the priest can scream and shout, carry on to high heavens, but he’d be wasting his breath. You’ll be man and wife.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12634" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12636">“Really?” exclaimed Lucia. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12637" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12660">“Of course,” said Agnese, “do you think in the thirty years I’ve spent in this world before the two of you came along I haven’t learned a thing or two? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12661" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12693">It’s like I said. In fact, that’s exactly how a friend of mine, who wanted to marry against her parents’ wishes, managed to get her way. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12694" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12736">The priest, who suspected she might make an attempt, was on his guard. But those two devils were so clever that they caught him at just the right time, said their vows, and became man and wife. Although the poor girl did come to regret it three days later.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12737" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12815">Agnese was right about both the possibility and the risks of failure. That is to say, the only ones who resorted to this expedient were people to whom the usual avenue had been blocked or rejected, so priests were very careful to avoid being forced into cooperation. And when such a couple, accompanied by witnesses, still managed to surprise a priest, he did all he could to escape, like Proteus from the clutches of those who wanted to force a prophecy from him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12816" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12826">“What if it’s true, Lucia,” said Renzo, looking at her expectantly, imploringly. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12827" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12832">“What do you mean, if!” said Agnese. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12833" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12838">“You think I’m making it all up? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12839" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12858">After everything I’ve done for you, you still don’t believe me? In that case, you can get out of this mess on your own. I wash my hands of it!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12859" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12874">“No, please, don’t abandon us,” Renzo replied, “I only meant that it seems too good to be true. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12875" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12886">I’m in your hands. You are like a mother to me.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12887" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12905">These words chased away Agnese’s brief spat of indignation. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12906" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12927">“Then why,” asked Lucia meekly, “didn’t Padre Cristoforo think of it, Mamma?” “Why?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12928" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12939">Agnese replied. “Of course he’ll have thought of it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12940" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12945">But he didn’t want to say anything.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12946" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12953">“Why not?” the two young people asked as one. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12954" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12970">“Because…because. Well if you must know, the priests say that it’s not really right.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12971" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12986">“Do you mean they don’t really like it, but when it’s done it’s done?” asked Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12987" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12993">“What do you want me to say?” replied Agnese. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12994" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13009">“They make the laws as they see fit. And we poor people don’t understand everything. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13010" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13023">And then, so many things…You see, it’s like punching another man. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13024" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13039">It’s not right. But once it’s done, not even the Pope can take it back.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13040" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13051">“If it’s not right,” said Lucia, “then we shouldn’t do it.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13052" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13065">“What!” cried Agnese. “Do you think I’d advise you to do anything against the fear of God? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13066" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13099">If it were against your parents’ wishes to marry some fool…but since I’m in favor, and this boy here is the groom, and the troublemaker is a scoundrel, and the priest…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13100" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13106">“It’s as clear as day,” added Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13107" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13150">“Not a word to Padre Cristoforo beforehand,” Agnese continued, “but once the deed is done, and done well, what do you think he’ll have to say? ‘Oh, my, haven’t we been the naughty children. But what’s done is done.’ Because that’s the way priests are supposed to talk. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13151" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13161">But in his heart, believe me, he’ll be happy, too.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13162" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13185">Lucia still seemed unconvinced, not sure of how to respond to her mother’s reasoning. Renzo, on the other hand, was encouraged and said, “In that case, consider the deed as good as done.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13186" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13191">“Slow down,” said Agnese, “what about witnesses? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13192" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13201">You have to find two people who are willing, and in the meantime know how to keep their mouths shut! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13202" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13217">Then you have to surprise the priest, who’s been holed up in the rectory for two days now. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13218" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13251">And make him stay there. Even though he’s a bit on the heavy side, believe me, as soon as he sees you appear together, he’ll become as quick as a cat, and flee like the devil from holy water.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13252" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13274">“I’ve got it! I know a way!” shouted Renzo, pounding his fist on the table so hard that the dishes jumped. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13275" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13288">He then proceeded to spell out his thinking, which Agnese approved in each and every detail. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13289" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13296">“I don’t like any of this,” said Lucia, when her fiancé had finished, “it’s too sneaky. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13297" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13313">Everything we’ve done so far has been honest. Let’s hold strong to our faith, and God will find a way. Padre Cristoforo himself said so. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13314" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13317">Let’s wait to hear his opinion.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13318" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13331">“Take the advice of someone who knows a little more than you,” Agnese said, with a serious expression on her face. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13332" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13337">“Do we really need to ask for anyone else’s opinion? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13338" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13342">God helps those who help themselves. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13343" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13349">We’ll tell the padre everything once the deed is done.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13350" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13356">“Lucia,” said Renzo, “would you let me down now? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13357" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13366">Haven’t we done everything like good Christians? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13367" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13373">Shouldn’t we already be husband and wife? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13374" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13384">Didn’t the priest set the day and time? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13385" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13398">Whose fault is it if we have to think for ourselves now? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13399" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13402">No, you’re not going to let me down. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13403" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13408">I’m leaving and I’ll be back with the answer.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13409" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13424">Saying goodbye to Lucia with a pleading gesture, and to Agnese with an air of complicity, he was out the door. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13425" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13467">Troubles sharpen your wits. Until yesterday, Renzo had walked the straight and narrow path in life without ever having occasion to tax his brain. Now he had to come up with a plan that would do credit to a jurist. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13468" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13518">With this in mind he went straight to the cottage of a certain Tonio, which was not far away. He found Tonio in the kitchen, one knee pressed against the hearth of the fireplace, one hand gripping the rim of a kettle set in the hot embers, and stirring a small buckwheat polenta with a wooden spoon. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13519" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13552">His mother, brother, and wife were seated at the table. Three or four little children were standing next to their father, staring at the kettle, waiting for the moment when he would pour out the contents. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13553" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13572">But there was none of the joy that the sight of supper usually gives to those who have earned it through hard work. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13573" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13612">The size of the polenta had been determined by the harvest rather than by the number and appetite of the mouths to be fed. Each of them, casting a sidelong glance at the communal meal with rabid desire, seemed to be thinking of how much of their appetite would remain unfulfilled. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13613" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13644">As Renzo was exchanging greetings with the family, Tonio poured the polenta onto a wooden board, forming a small moon beneath a big circle of steam. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13645" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13692">The women did not forget their manners, asking Renzo, “Would you like to join us?” a courtesy that the peasants of Lombardy—and of countless other countries—never fail to pay someone who stops by at mealtime, even a rich glutton who has just risen from his own well-laden table while his hosts are down to their last spoonful. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13693" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13722">“Thank you,” answered Renzo, “I only stopped by for a word with Tonio. And if you like, Tonio, so as not to disturb the women, we can go to the tavern to have a bite and talk.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13723" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13763">For Tonio the offer was as welcome as it was unexpected. The women, and even the children (who, on the subject of food, learned to add and subtract at a very early age) did not mind the withdrawal from the polenta competition of a rival, and the most formidable rival at that. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13764" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13773">Without further questions, he went with Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13774" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13832">At the village tavern, they were able to sit wherever they pleased, and in perfect solitude, since poverty had weaned all the regular customers from this bower of delights. After ordering what little was available, and emptying a pitcher of wine, Renzo told Tonio, with a mysterious air, “If you can do me a small favor, I can do you a big one.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13833" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13839">“Your wish is my command. Speak up,” Tonio replied, pouring more wine. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13840" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13846">“Today I’d walk through fire for you.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13847" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13865">“I hear that you owe the priest twenty-five liras on the lease for farmland you worked last year.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13866" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13872">“You’re ruining my appetite, Renzo! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13873" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13878">Why’d you bring that up? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n189" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13879" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13885">So much for my good mood!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n190" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13886" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13905">“The only reason I mention your debt,” Renzo explained, “is because, if you want, I can help you repay it.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n191" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13906" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13907">“Really?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n192" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13908" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13908">“Really. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n193" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13909" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13911">Would that make you happy?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n194" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13912" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13912">“Happy? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n195" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13913" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13917">Of course it would! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n196" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13918" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13941">Especially since I wouldn’t have to deal with the priest’s dirty looks, the shaking of his head every time I run into him. He never stops nagging me. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n197" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13942" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13953">‘Tonio, don’t forget.’ ‘Tonio, when are we going to see each other about our little business?’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n198" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13954" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13980">It’s so bad that during the homily, when he stares at me with those eyes, I’m almost afraid that he’s going to say, right there in public, ‘What about those twenty-five liras!’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n199" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13981" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13986">I’m so sick of those twenty-five damn liras! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n200" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13987" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14004">Once I’ve paid up, he’s supposed to give me back my wife’s gold necklace, which I could trade for plenty of polenta.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n201" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14005" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14018">“Well, if you could do me this one favor, the twenty-five liras are yours.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n202" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14019" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14020">“Tell me more.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n203" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14021" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14028">“But…!” Renzo added, placing his index finger over his lips. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n204" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14029" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14036">“Do you even have to ask? You know me!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n205" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14037" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14059">“The priest is cooking up all sorts of nonsense to delay my wedding, but I want to speed things up. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n206" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14060" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14090">They tell me it’s a sure bet if the two spouses, with two witnesses, appear before the priest, and I say, ‘This is my wife,’ and Lucia says, ‘This is my husband,’ then we’re as good as married. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n207" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14091" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14093">Do you get what I’m saying?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n208" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14094" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14099">“You want me to be your witness?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n209" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14100" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14101">“Exactly.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n210" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14102" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14108">“And you’ll pay the twenty-five liras that I owe?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n211" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14109" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14110">“That’s my intention.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n212" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14111" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14119">“You’d better keep your word!” “We have to find a second witness.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n213" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14120" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14121">“I’ve got just the person. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n214" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14122" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14133">That half-wit, my brother Gervaso, will do anything I tell him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n215" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14134" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14138">Will you buy him a drink?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n216" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14139" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14143">“And something to eat,” answered Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n217" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14144" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14151">“We can bring him along to celebrate. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n218" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14152" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14154">Will he know what to do?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n219" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14155" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14168">“I’ll show him. You know, I got his share of the brains in the family.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n220" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14169" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14169">“Tomorrow…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n221" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14170" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14170">“Good.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n222" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14171" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14172">“Toward evening…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n223" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14173" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14173">“Great.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n224" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14174" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14183">“But…!” said Renzo, placing his finger over his lips again. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n225" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14184" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14205">“Come on,” replied Tonio, tilting his head toward his right shoulder and raising his left hand. The look on his face said, “Don’t insult me.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n226" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14206" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14216">“But if your wife asks, and you know she will…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n227" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14217" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14238">“I’ll come up with a fib. I’ve already told her so many we’ll never even the score. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n228" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14239" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14248">I’ll find some excuse to set her mind at ease.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n229" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14249" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14260">“Tomorrow morning,” said Renzo, “we’ll have more time to talk and get all the details straight.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n230" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14261" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14284">At that they left the tavern. Tonio headed home, trying to figure out what kind of a fib to tell the women. Renzo, for his part, was preparing to report to Agnese and Lucia the arrangements he had made. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n231" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14285" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14295">Agnese in the meantime had been struggling in vain to win over her daughter. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n232" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14296" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14328">Lucia would have none of it, rejecting first one and then the other argument. If the action was wrong, then it should not be done. If it was right, then why not tell Padre Cristoforo? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n233" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14329" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14365">Renzo returned in triumph. He delivered his report and concluded with an “ahem,” by which he meant to say, “What a man I am! Isn’t that the perfect solution? Who would have thought of it!” and a hundred similar things. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n234" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14366" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14414">Lucia shook her head softly. The two enthusiastic conspirators paid her little mind, the way you treat a child to whom you’ve given up trying to explain something, planning to convince her later by pleading or demanding. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n235" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14415" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14426">“All right,” said Agnese, “all right, but…you haven’t thought of everything.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n236" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14427" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14431">“What did we leave out?” replied Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n237" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14432" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14438">“Perpetua. You forgot about Perpetua. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n238" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14439" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14467">Tonio and his brother—she’ll let them in. But when she sees the two of you…Think. I’m sure she’s been given instructions to keep you as far away as a hungry boy from a tree of ripe pears.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n239" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14468" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14474">Puzzled, Renzo asked, “So what should we do?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n240" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14475" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14479">“Don’t worry. I’ve thought of everything. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n241" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14480" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14503">I’ll come with you. I’ve got a trick to get her attention. I’ll work my magic on her so she won’t notice the two of you sneaking in. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n242" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14504" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14512">I’ll stop by, get her talking…you’ll see.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n243" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14513" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14525">“God bless you!” exclaimed Renzo. “I’ve always said that you come to our aid in everything.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n244" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14526" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14547">“But all of this will be for nothing if she refuses to be convinced,” Agnese said, pointing to her daughter. “She keeps saying it’s not right.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n245" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14548" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14562">Renzo lent his own eloquence to the cause, but Lucia wouldn’t budge. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n246" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14563" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14593">“I don’t know how to respond to your arguments,” she said, “but I do know that, to do things the way you say, we’ll have to lie, be sneaky, deceitful. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n247" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14594" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14599">Oh, Renzo, this is not how we began! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n248" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14600" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14636">I do want to be your wife”—there was no way she could utter this word, and express this intention, without blushing—“I want to be your wife, but in the right way, with the fear of God, at the altar. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n249" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14637" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14641">Let’s place ourselves in the hands of God. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n250" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14642" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14660">Don’t you think that he has a better solution for getting us out of this mess than all your scheming? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n251" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14661" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14667">And why would we keep secrets from Fra Cristoforo?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n252" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14668" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14707">The argument was still going, with no end in sight, when the friar’s arrival was announced by a hurried pitter-patter of sandals and the sound of a cowl flapping, like the wind beating inside a slackened sail. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap6-n253" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14708" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14727">Everyone quieted down, and Agnese had barely enough time to whisper into Lucia’s ear, “Mind yourself. And don’t breathe a word to the padre of what we just discussed.” </note>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>