<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>2022</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed: a novel</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
          <date>2022</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Michael Moore</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="english_2022_cap8">
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10002">“Carneades! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10003" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10079">Now, who in the world was he?” Don Abbondio was muttering to himself, as he sat in his chair in an upstairs room, a small book open in front of him, when Perpetua came in to deliver the message. “Carneades! I’m sure I’ve seen that name somewhere. He must have been a great scholar, some ancient know-it-all. It’s one of those names. But who in the world was he?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10080" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10116">That’s how oblivious the poor man was of the storm gathering over his head. You should know that Don Abbondio enjoyed doing a bit of reading every day. A neighboring priest, who had a few books on a shelf, would lend him this or that volume, wherever his hand happened to fall. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10117" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10165">The one Don Abbondio was meditating on in that moment, while convalescing from his fear-induced fever (though he had already recovered more completely than he’d admit) was a panegyric in honor of Saint Carlo Borromeo that had been delivered with great feeling, and heard with great admiration, at the Milan cathedral two years earlier. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10166" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10208">In it the saint was compared, for his love of learning, to Archimedes. This much Don Abbondio could handle, since Archimedes had done such odd things, and was so well known, that it didn’t take a lot of schooling to know a thing or two about him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10209" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10224">But then the orator had to go and compare him to Carneades. And here our reader had run aground. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10225" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10235">That was when Perpetua came in to announce the visit of Tonio. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10236" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10243">“At this hour?” Don Abbondio also said, as was only natural. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10244" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10245">“What do you expect. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10246" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10255">They’ve got no manners. But if you don’t catch him now…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10256" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10267">“You’re right. If I don’t catch him now, who knows when I will? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10268" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10269">Send him up…Wait, wait. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10270" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10279">Are you quite sure it’s him?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10280" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10290">“Of course I am!” replied Perpetua, and headed downstairs. She opened the door and glanced around, asking, “Now where did you get to?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10291" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10307">Tonio appeared, and at the same moment, so did Agnese. She came forward and greeted Perpetua by name. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10308" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10318">“Good evening, Agnese,” said Perpetua, “where are you coming from at this hour of the night?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10319" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10325">“I’m coming from…” and she named a nearby village. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10326" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10338">“And wouldn’t you know it,” she continued, “I stayed longer than I expected, all on your account.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10339" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10352">“Oh? How is that?” asked Perpetua. Turning to the two brothers she said, “Go on in, I’ll be right up.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10353" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10388">“Because,” Agnese replied, “one of those women who love to talk about things they know nothing about…can you believe it? She had the nerve to say that you didn’t end up marrying Beppe Suolavecchia, or Anselmo Lunghigna, because they wouldn’t have you. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10389" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10401">Well, I told her that you were the one who turned them down, first one and then the other…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10402" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10402">“Wouldn’t you know it! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10403" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10407">Oh, that liar! That big fat liar! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10408" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10410">Tell me her name!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10411" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10420">“Please don’t ask. I don’t want to cause any trouble.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10421" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10430">“But you have to tell me, you owe it to me. Oh, that liar!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10431" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10449">“Not another word…you can’t imagine how sorry I was not to know the whole story, so I could set her straight.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10450" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10474">“Can you believe the things people make up!” Perpetua exclaimed again. She quickly added, “As for Beppe, everyone knows and could see for themselves…Ah, Tonio. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10475" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10483">Come in and go right on up, I’ll be there in a second.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10484" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10496">From inside, Tonio answered yes, and Perpetua continued her passionate tale. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10497" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10515">Across from Don Abbondio’s front door, there was a path between two modest cottages that led into a field. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10516" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10532">Agnese headed in that direction, as if she wanted to go somewhere private so she could speak more freely. Perpetua followed close behind. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10533" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10556">Once they’d turned the corner and were in a spot where you couldn’t see what was happening at Don Abbondio’s house, Agnese gave a loud cough. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10557" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10602">That was the signal. Renzo heard it, gave Lucia’s arm an encouraging squeeze, and both of them came forward, on tiptoe, creeping close to the wall. When they got to the door, they gave it a gentle push, quiet as mice, and entered the vestibule where the two brothers were waiting. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10603" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10622">Renzo closed the door behind him, softly softly, and all four went up the stairs without making a sound. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10623" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10643">Once they had reached the landing, the two brothers approached the door to Don Abbondio’s room, which was right by the stairs. The bride and groom flattened themselves against the wall. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10644" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10652">“Deo gratias,” said Tonio in a clear voice. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10653" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10654">“Tonio, is that you? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10655" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10660">Come in,” replied the voice from inside. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10661" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10678">The summoned man opened the door just wide enough for him and his brother to slip through, one after the other. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10679" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10703">A ray of light shone through the crack, painting a white stripe on the dark floor of the landing, and giving Lucia a start, as if she had been discovered. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10704" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10737">Once the brothers were inside, Tonio closed the door behind him. The bride and groom stood still in the shadows, their ears pricked, holding their breath. The loudest sound was the pounding of Lucia’s poor heart. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10738" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10771">Don Abbondio was sitting on an old chair, as we were saying, in the dim light of a small oil lamp, ensconced in an old dressing gown, with an old skullcap on his head that framed his face. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10772" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10816">Two thick tufts of hair that slipped out from under the skullcap, two thick eyebrows, a thick mustache, and a thick goatee, all white and scattered over his dark wrinkled face, looked like snow-covered bushes sprouting from a cliff in the clear moonlight. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10817" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10832">“Aha!” was his greeting, as he removed his glasses and placed them inside his book. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10833" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10850">“The Reverend Father will say I’m late,” said Tonio, bowing, as did Gervaso, but more awkwardly. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10851" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10858">“Obviously you’re late. In more ways than one. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10859" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10863">Don’t you realize that I’m sick?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10864" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10866">“Oh, I’m sorry.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10867" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10887">“You must have heard. I’m sick and don’t know when I can appear in public again…But why did you bring along that…that boy?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10888" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10892">“To keep me company, Father.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10893" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10894">“All right now, let’s have a look.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10895" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10911">“Here’s twenty-five new berlingas, the ones with Saint Ambrose on horseback,” said Tonio, removing a pouch from his pocket. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10912" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10936">“Let’s have a look,” repeated Don Abbondio. Taking the pouch, he put his glasses back on, opened it, fished out the berlingas, counted them, turned them over, turned them over again, and found no signs of counterfeiting. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10937" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10946">“Now you’ll give me back my Tecla’s necklace, Father.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_10947" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11006">“What’s fair is fair,” replied Don Abbondio. He went to a cupboard, dug a key out of his pocket, and looking around as if to shield himself from curious eyes, opened one side of the door, covered the opening with his body, stuck his head inside, for a look, and his arm, to get the necklace. He took it, closed the cupboard, and gave it to Tonio, saying, “Are you happy now?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11007" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11019">“Would you mind putting it in writing?” Tonio asked. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11020" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11027">“That, too!” said Don Abbondio. “They know every trick in the book. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11028" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11033">My, how suspicious the world has become. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11034" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11038">Don’t you trust me?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11039" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11044">“Of course I do, Reverend Father. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11045" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11048">You’ve got me wrong. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11049" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11076">But since my name is in your little black book, in the debit column…Well, since you’ve gone to the trouble of writing it once, then…it’s a short step from life to death…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11077" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11116">“Fine, fine,” interrupted Don Abbondio. Grumbling, he pulled open a desk drawer, removed pen, inkpot, and a sheet of paper, and started writing, repeating aloud the words as they emerged from his pen. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11117" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11167">Meanwhile Tonio, and at his cue Gervaso, stood right in front of the desk, to block the scribe’s view of the door. Pretending to be idle, they shuffled their feet on the floor, giving the signal to the two outside to come in, and at the same time covering up the sound of the couple’s footsteps. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11168" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11177">Don Abbondio, immersed in his writing, noticed nothing. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11178" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11208">At the shuffling of the four feet, Renzo took one of Lucia’s arms, gave it another encouraging squeeze, and stepped forward, pulling her behind him. She was shaking so badly that she couldn’t have moved on her own. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11209" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11225">They came in slowly slowly, on tiptoe, holding their breath, and hid behind the two brothers. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11226" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11265">In the meantime Don Abbondio carefully reread what he had written, without lifting his eyes from the paper. He folded it in four saying, “Are you happy now?” Removing his glasses from his nose with one hand, he handed the paper to Tonio with the other, and looked up. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11266" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11296">Tonio, stretching out his hand to take it, stepped to one side, while Gervaso, at a nod from his brother, stepped to the other. And in the middle, like a scene on which a curtain has opened, Renzo and Lucia appeared. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11297" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11333">Don Abbondio got a blurry and then a clear view of them. He was shocked, astounded, infuriated. He deliberated and came to a decision. All in the time it took Renzo to say the words, “Reverend Father, in the presence of these witnesses, this is my wife.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11334" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11393">His lips had barely come to rest when Don Abbondio, dropping the piece of paper, grabbed and picked up the lamp with his left hand, and yanked the table cover with his right, pulling it toward himself angrily, sending the book, paper, inkpot, and sand tumbling to the floor. Springing between the chair and the desk, he ran toward Lucia. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11394" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11431">The poor girl, in her soft and now trembling voice, had just begun to utter the words, “And this…” when Don Abbondio rudely threw the table cover over her head and face, to keep her from pronouncing the complete formula. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11432" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11461">Having dropped the lamp he’d been holding, he used that hand to gag her with the cloth, almost suffocating her. And all the while he kept shouting at the top of his lungs, “Perpetua! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11462" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11464">Perpetua! Treachery! Help!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11465" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11503">The wick of the lamp dying on the floor cast a dim flickering light on Lucia, who, in a state of complete panic, did not even try to disentangle herself. She looked like a roughly modeled clay statue over which the artist had thrown a damp rag. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11504" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11545">With the lights out, Don Abbondio let go of the poor girl and felt his way toward the door to the next room. Once he found it he entered, locked himself inside, and continued to shout, “Perpetua! Help!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11546" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11578">In the front room, everything was in an uproar. Renzo, groping around with his hands like in a game of blindman’s bluff, was trying to stop the priest. At last he found the door and pounded on it, shouting, “Open up! Open up! Don’t make such a scene!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11579" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11593">Lucia was calling to Renzo in a faint voice, “Please, please, we have to leave, for the love of God.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11594" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11609">Tonio was crawling about on all fours, sweeping the floor with his hands, trying to find his receipt. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11610" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11622">And Gervaso was jumping up and down and shouting, like a man possessed, looking for the doorway to the stairs and an escape to safety. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11623" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11639">In the midst of all this pandemonium, I cannot resist pausing for a moment of reflection. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11640" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11674">Renzo—who had snuck into another man’s house, was holding him hostage, and was raising a ruckus at night—looked for all the world like the aggressor. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11675" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11699">Don Abbondio, ambushed, forced to flee, and terrorized while he was attending peacefully to his own business, looked like the victim. In reality, however, he was the aggressor. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11700" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11712">Such is often the way of the world…I mean, the way of the world in the seventeenth century. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11713" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11738">The besieged man, seeing that his enemy showed no signs of retreating, opened a window that gave onto the church square, and started shouting, “Help! Help!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11739" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11779">The moon shone brightly. The shadow of the church, and farther ahead, the longer and sharper shadow of the bell tower, cast a dark shape across the illuminated grass plane of the piazza. Every object stood out distinctly, as if it were day. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11780" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11791">Yet there was no sign of a living soul as far as the eye could see. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11792" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11818">Attached to the wall of the church, on the side facing the rectory, there was a humble abode, a closet, really, where the sacristan slept. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11819" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11851">He was woken up by the wild cries, jumped out of bed in a frenzy, opened the canvas shade covering one of his little windows, and stuck his head out. With his eyes half shut, he called out, “What’s wrong?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11852" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11862">“Quick, Ambrogio! Help! There’s people in my house!” Don Abbondio shouted. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11863" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11909">“I’m coming right away,” the sacristan replied. He pulled his head back in, closed the shade, and although half-asleep and more than half-cocked, he was able to come up with a solution on the spur of the moment, one that would provide even more help than requested, without drawing him into the fray, whatever the trouble might be. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11910" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11955">He grabs hold of his britches, which he kept on the bed, tucks them under his arm like a three-cornered hat, and scrambles down a wooden ladder. He runs to the bell tower, grabs a hold of the rope to the larger of the two bells, and starts yanking away. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11956" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11975">“Dong, dong, dong, dong.” The peasants sit up in their beds with a start. The field hands sleeping in the haylofts prick up their ears and jump to their feet. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11976" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11977">“What’s that? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11978" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11983">The bell sounding the alarm? Fire? Thieves? Bandits?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_11984" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12035">Many of the women advise, or rather, beg their husbands not to budge, to let others rush out. Some of the men get up and go to the window. The lazy ones, as if yielding to their wives’ pleas, crawl back under the covers. The braver and more curious go downstairs to grab their pitchforks and muskets, and run toward the sound. Still others wait to see. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12036" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12073">Before the peasants had heeded the call, even before they were fully awake, the sound of the bells had reached the ears of other groups who, already up and dressed, were keeping vigil not far away: the bravi, in one place, and Agnese and Perpetua in another. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12074" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12093">Let me briefly fill you in on what the first group had been up to since last we saw them, with one division in the ruined house, the other at the tavern. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12094" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12151">Once the three at the tavern saw that the doors to all the houses were closed and the street deserted, they hurried out quickly, as if they suddenly realized how late it was, saying they wanted to get home right away. They conducted a final survey of the village, to make sure that everyone had turned in. Not a living soul, not the slightest sound. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12152" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12170">They also sneaked past our poor little cottage, the quietest house in the village, since no one was home. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12171" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12183">Then they went straight to the ruined house and delivered their report to Griso. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12184" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12247">He immediately stuck an old hat on his head, tossed an oilcloth wrap covered with seashells around his shoulders, grabbed a pilgrim’s staff, and said, “Time to make our move, bravi: Keep your mouths shut, and remember your orders.” He went first and the others followed. In a minute they were at the cottage, by the opposite route taken by our little brigade, which was off on its own expedition. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12248" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12305">Griso held his troops a few yards back, and went ahead by himself to scout around. Seeing the house deserted and quiet from the outside, he gestured to two of his henchmen to come forward, gave them the order to climb very carefully over the wall surrounding the courtyard and, once inside, to hide in a corner, behind a bushy fig tree he had spotted that morning. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12306" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12323">Then he knocked very softly, intending to say that he was a lost pilgrim seeking shelter until daybreak. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12324" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12333">No answer. He knocks again, a little louder. Not a peep. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12334" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12363">He goes to call a third member of his gang, gets him to slip into the courtyard like the other two, with orders to slowly detach the bolt from the door, so they can easily get in and out. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12364" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12372">Everything is done with the utmost caution and is rewarded with solid success. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12373" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12407">Griso calls to the others, and sends them over the wall to hide with the first three. He closes the front gate stealthily and posts two sentinels inside. Then he goes straight to the garden door. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12408" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12416">He knocks there, too, and waits, as well he would have to. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12417" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12437">Very carefully he detaches the bolt on that door, as well. No one calls out, “Who’s there?” from inside. No one makes a sound. Things couldn’t go more smoothly. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12438" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12460">Next step. “Psst!” he calls to the men behind the fig tree, and with them, enters the ground-floor room, where that morning he had treacherously begged for a piece of bread. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12461" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12485">He takes out his tinderbox, lights a lantern he has brought, and goes into the next room to see if anyone is there: no one. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12486" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12497">He turns back, goes to the bottom of the stairs, looks, listens: solitude and silence. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12498" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12544">He leaves two other sentries on the ground floor and asks Laughless, a bravo from the Bergamo countryside, to follow him. Laughless’s job was to do the threatening, the silencing, and the ordering: all the talking, in short, so that his accent would make Agnese think the gang had come from Bergamo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12545" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12573">With Laughless by his side and the others behind, Griso climbs the stairs softly, cursing in his heart at the sound of every squeaky stair and every henchman’s footstep. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12574" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12577">He is finally at the top. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12578" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12581">Their victim’s nest. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12582" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12612">He softly pushes the door to the front room. It yields, opens a crack. He pokes his head inside: All is pitch-black. He puts his ear against the opening, to listen for anyone snoring, breathing, or moving about: nothing. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12613" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12646">Next step. Holding the lantern right in front of his face to see without being seen, he pushes the door wide open, sees a bed, and is upon it. The bed is all smooth and made, with the border of the blanket folded over the pillows. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12647" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12678">He shrugs his shoulders, turns to his companions, signals to them that he is going to check the other room, and that they should follow him nice and slowly. He enters, follows the same ritual, comes up with the same results. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12679" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12692">“What the devil is this?” he says. “Did some dirty rat squeal on us?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12693" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12709">Everyone starts looking around a little less cautiously, poking into every corner, turning the place upside down. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12710" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12749">While they’re busy doing this, the two sentinels at the front gate hear the pitter-patter of hurried steps coming closer and closer. Imagining that whoever it might be will likely pass by, they fall silent but remain alert. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12750" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12757">The footsteps come to a stop right at the gate. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12758" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12791">It’s Menico, the neighbor boy, who has come running to deliver Padre Cristoforo’s warning to the two women to flee from their home, immediately, for the love of heaven, and take refuge at the monastery, because…well, you know why. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12792" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12821">He lifts the latch to the bolt, to knock, and feels it dangling in his hand, detached and torn out. “What’s this?” he thinks, and gives a fearful push to the door: It opens. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12822" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12857">Menico sets one foot inside, very warily, and suddenly feels someone grab both arms while two muffled voices, one on his right and one on his left, say in a threatening voice: “Be quiet or be dead!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12858" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12881">Instead the boy lets loose a scream. One of the villains places a hand over his mouth. The other takes out his dagger to scare him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12882" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12924">The boy shakes like a leaf, and doesn’t even try to shout. But all at once, the first tolling of the bell is heard, followed by a steady pealing. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12925" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12981">“Suspicion always haunts the guilty mind,” a wise man once said. Both villains thought they heard the bells ringing out their first and last names, as well as their nicknames: They let go of Menico’s arms, free his hands and mouth, look each other in the face, then race toward the ruined house where most of the troop has gathered. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_12982" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13000">Menico hightails it out to the street, heading for the bell tower, where there were bound to be people. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13033">The dreadful tolling had the same effect on the scoundrels ransacking the cottage from top to bottom. They were startled and bewildered, crashing into each other as each looked for the quickest way out. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13034" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13068">Although they were all men used to staring danger in the face, they were petrified by a danger they could not see, nearby, that might suddenly descend upon them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13069" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13085">It took all of Griso’s authority to keep them together in orderly retreat rather than mad flight. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13086" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13181">Like a dog herding pigs, running this way and that after each stray animal, grabbing one by the ear and dragging him back inside, prodding another with his muzzle, and barking at another to get him in line, the false pilgrim grabs hold of one bravo who is already halfway out the door, and yanks him back in. He uses his walking stick to drive back this man or that heading in the same direction. He shouts at the others who are running about aimlessly. Finally he manages to scrape them together in the middle of the courtyard. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13182" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13197">“Quick, quick! Pistols in hand, knives out, all together, then we’ll leave. That’s how it’s done. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13198" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13207">Who do you think will come near us if we stay together, you idiots! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13208" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13222">But if we let them snatch us one by one, even the peasants will start thrashing us. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13223" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13223">Shame on you all! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13224" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13228">Line up behind me, as one!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13229" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13240">After this short harangue, he took the lead and was the first one out. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13241" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13266">The cottage, as I said, was on the far side of the village. Griso took the outbound road and the others filed behind him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13267" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13285">Let us send them on their way and take a step back to catch up with Agnese and Perpetua, whom we had left on a certain path. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13286" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13311">Agnese had managed to get the maid as far from Don Abbondio’s house as she could, and for a while, her plan had gone well. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13312" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13327">That is, until Perpetua remembered that she had left the door open and wanted to go back. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13328" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13367">There was no talking her out of it. To avoid raising her suspicions, Agnese had to turn around with her and follow, trying to hold her back every time she saw an opportunity to get Perpetua more upset over the story of marriages gone up in smoke. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13368" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13400">She pretended to hang onto Perpetua’s every word, and, now and again, to show she was paying attention or to revive the gossip, she would interject words like, “naturally,” “now I understand,” “but of course,” “obviously,” “and then?” “what about him?” “and you?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13401" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13418">In the meantime, Agnese was carrying on an entirely different conversation with herself. “Will they be out by now? Or will they still be inside? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13419" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13437">We were idiots not to agree on a signal to let me know when the deed was done! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13438" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13441">What a mistake! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13442" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13464">Well, it’s too late now. The best I can do is keep her away as long as I can. Worse comes to worst, I’ll have wasted a little time.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13465" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13535">This stopping and going brought them close to the house of Don Abbondio, which still couldn’t be seen, however, since it was around the bend. Perpetua, at a crucial point in the story, put up no resistance to being held in place, and was indeed unaware of the elements being used against her, when all of a sudden they could hear, echoing from above in the motionless void of the sky, through the vast silence of the night, the first desperate cries of Don Abbondio: “Help! Help!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13536" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13543">“Saints in heaven, what was that?” shouted Perpetua, wanting to run. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13544" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13553">“What can it be? What can it be?” said Agnese, grabbing hold of her skirt. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13554" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13560">“Saints in heaven, didn’t you hear?” replied the other, breaking loose. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13561" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13570">“What is it? What is it?” repeated Agnese, grabbing hold of her arm. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13571" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13584">“You devil!” exclaimed Perpetua, pushing the other woman away to free herself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13585" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13596">She started running when, from farther away, but shriller and more immediate, came the cries of Menico. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13597" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13605">“Saints in heaven!” shouted Agnese, in turn, galloping after the other woman. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13606" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13632">They had just picked up their heels when the bells started tolling. One stroke, two, three, and then on and on. The bells would have spurred the women on, as if they needed it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13633" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13676">Perpetua arrived at Don Abbondio’s house a moment before Agnese. While she was pushing on the door, it opened from the inside, and who should appear on the threshold but Tonio, Gervaso, Renzo, and Lucia. Having finally found the stairs, they had come racing down in leaps and bounds. Hearing the dreadful tolling of the bells, they had run as fast as they could to safety. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13677" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13693">“What is it? What is it?” Perpetua asked the brothers, gasping for breath. Their only reply was to shove her to the side and run. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13694" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13707">“And you two, what are you doing here?” she asked Renzo and Lucia, once she recognized them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13708" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13713">But they, too, left without a word. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13714" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13737">Perpetua, in a hurry to be where she was most needed, asked no more questions. She dashed into the corridor and raced toward the stairs as best she could in the dark. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13738" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13750">The still unmarried couple found themselves facing Agnese, who arrived huffing and puffing. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13751" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13770">“Ah, you’re here!” she said, struggling to get the words out. “How did it go? Why are the bells tolling? I thought I heard…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13771" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13780">“Let’s go home,” said Renzo, “before people get here.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13781" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13809">No sooner had they started off when Menico came running, spotted them, and still shaking all over, asked in a choked voice, “Where are you going? Turn around. This way. To the monastery!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13810" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13814">“Are you the one who…?” Agnese started to ask. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13815" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13819">“What now?” asked Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13820" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13825">Lucia, overwhelmed and trembling, was dumbstruck. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13826" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13833">“There’s a devil in the house,” gasped Menico, “I saw them myself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13834" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13872">They tried to kill me. Padre Cristoforo told me. He said to come right away. You, too, Renzo. And then I saw them. It’s sheer luck that I’ve found you all here! I’ll tell you everything later, when we’re away from the village.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13873" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13914">Renzo, who was the most levelheaded of the group, thought that, whatever direction they took, they’d better take it immediately, before people started arriving. The safest thing was to do what Menico advised—or rather ordered—with all the force of a frightened boy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13915" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13930">Once they were on their way and out of danger, they could ask him for a more complete explanation. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13931" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13934">“Keep walking,” Renzo told Menico. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13935" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13940">“Follow him,” he told the women. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13941" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13989">They turned and walked quickly toward the church, crossed the square, where, thank heavens, not a living soul was around, and entered an alley between the church and Don Abbondio’s house. At the first gap in the hedge, they slipped through and out into the fields. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_13990" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14008">The quartet had gone maybe fifty yards when the villagers began filling up the town square; the crowd swelled by the minute. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14009" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14028">Everyone looked into one another’s faces with a question. No one had an answer. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14029" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14038">The first to arrive ran to the door of the church. Locked. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14039" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14063">They ran to the bell tower. One man placed his mouth over a small window, a slit, really, and bellowed, “What the devil is going on?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14064" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14085">When Ambrogio heard a voice he recognized, he let go of the rope. Reassured by the hubbub that many people had gathered, he answered, “I’m coming to open up.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14086" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14107">He quickly slipped into the garment he had tucked under his arm, and unlocked the door. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14108" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14111">“What’s all this ruckus?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14112" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14113">“What?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n189" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14114" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14118">“Where?” “Who?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n190" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14119" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14156">“What do you mean who?” said Ambrogio, with one hand holding a side of the door, and the other on the hem of the breeches he’d put on so hastily. “What? You don’t know? People in the priest’s house! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n191" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14157" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14159">Be brave, boys. To the rescue.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n192" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14160" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14177">They all turned and swarmed toward the house, keeping their ears pricked. All quiet. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n193" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14178" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14193">Others ran to the door. It was locked and seemed to be undamaged. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n194" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14194" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14208">They looked up. Not a window was open. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n195" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14209" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14212">“Anyone home? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n196" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14213" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14218">Reverend Father! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n197" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14219" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14221">Reverend Father!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n198" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14222" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14277">Don Abbondio had just realized that his assailants were gone, stepped back from the window, and shut it. In that moment he was squabbling in a low voice with Perpetua, who had left him alone in this mess. When he heard his name being called by the voice of the people, he had to go back to the window. Seeing the huge rescue operation underway, he regretted having sounded the alarm. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n199" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14278" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14279">“What happened?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n200" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14280" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14284">“What did they do to you?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n201" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14285" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14288">“Who are they?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n202" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14289" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14300">“Where did they go?” fifty voices shouted as one. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n203" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14301" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14310">“They’re all gone. But thank you. You can go home now.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n204" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14311" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14314">“But who was it?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n205" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14315" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14318">“Where did they go?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n206" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14319" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14322">“What happened?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n207" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14323" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14348">“People up to no good, the kind that come out at night. But they escaped. Go home, they’re gone. Another time, my children. Thank you for your kindness.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n208" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14349" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14357">And saying this, he stepped back and closed the window once more. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n209" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14358" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14387">Some people started to grumble, some to jeer, some to curse. Others shrugged their shoulders and were about to leave when a man arrived, huffing and puffing, barely able to form words. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n210" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14388" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14417">He lived in the house almost directly opposite Agnese and Lucia. Hearing a noise from their cottage, he had leaned out his window and seen the bravi scattering in the courtyard while Griso struggled to round them up. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n211" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14418" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14456">“What are you doing, boys?” he cried after catching his breath, “The devil isn’t here. He’s at the other end of the street, at Agnese Mondella’s place. Armed men are inside. It looks like they’re trying to kill a pilgrim. Who knows what the devil they’re up to!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n212" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14457" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14460">“What? What?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n213" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14461" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14465">A tumultuous assembly began. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n214" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14466" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14467">“We have to go!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n215" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14468" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14470">“We have to see!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n216" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14471" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14473">“How many of them are there?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n217" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14474" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14476">“How many are we?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n218" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14477" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14479">“Who are they?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n219" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14480" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14484">“The Consul! Get the Consul!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n220" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14485" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14500">“Here I am,” replied the Consul from within the crowd. “Here I am. But if you want to help me, you have to follow orders. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n221" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14501" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14504">Quick. Where’s the sacristan? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n222" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14505" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14508">To the bells, to the bells! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n223" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14509" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14520">Quick. Someone run to Lecco for help. Gather around now…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n224" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14521" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14566">Some ran, some squeezed their way through the crowd to escape. A second man arrived who had seen the bravi making their getaway, and shouted, “Hurry, boys, hurry! Someone’s making off with a pilgrim. Thieves or bandits. They’ve already left the village. After them! After them!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n225" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14567" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14622">At this announcement, without awaiting their captain’s orders, the crowd swarmed down the street. While this army advanced, some of the leaders deliberately slowed their pace, allowing the men behind them to come to the front while they themselves disappeared into the rear. The motley crew finally reached its destination. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n226" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14623" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14638">The traces of the invasion were fresh and plain to see: The front gate was wide open, the bolt torn off. But the invaders had disappeared. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n227" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14639" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14654">Entering the courtyard, the garden door is also wide open and its bolt torn off. Voices call out, “Agnese!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n228" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14655" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14655">“Lucia!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n229" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14656" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14660">“The pilgrim, where’s the pilgrim?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n230" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14661" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14665">“The pilgrim must’ve been imagined by Stefano!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n231" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14666" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14672">“No, no. Carlandrea saw him, too.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n232" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14673" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14674">“Pilgrim, where are you?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n233" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14675" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14676">“Agnese?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n234" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14677" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14677">“Lucia?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n235" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14678" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14679">No one answers. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n236" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14680" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14687">“They’ve been kidnapped!” “They’ve been kidnapped!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n237" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14688" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14731">At that point, some men raised their voices to propose that everyone pursue the kidnappers. It was an act of infamy! A disgrace to the village if any old scoundrel could come by and make off with the women, like a hawk stealing chicks from a deserted barnyard. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n238" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14732" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14763">Another, more tumultuous, assembly was held. Someone in the brigade (exactly who, no one ever found out) started a rumor that Agnese and Lucia had taken refuge in a house. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n239" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14764" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14789">The rumor spread quickly and gained credibility, until all talk of pursuing the fugitives was dropped, and the brigade broke up, each man returning to his own home. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n240" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14790" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14817">There was a murmuring, a din, a knocking and opening of doors, an appearing and disappearing of lamps, a questioning by women from the windows, an answering from down below. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n241" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14818" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14836">The street was deserted and silent again, the discussions continued in the houses, then settled down amid yawns, to resume the next day. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n242" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14837" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14945">There were no more incidents, except for one the following morning. The Consul was standing in his field, chin in his hand, elbow resting on the handle of his shovel, which was half dug in the ground, with one foot propped on the top edge. As I was saying, he stood there reflecting on the previous night’s mysteries, and on the lowest common denominator between what he should do and what he would rather do. Coming toward him, he saw two strapping men with hair like highborn Frankish kings, men who closely resembled the pair (though it was not them) who had accosted Don Abbondio five days earlier. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n243" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14946" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14995">With an even less ceremonious manner than those two, they informed the Consul that he should think twice before delivering any report on the events of the previous night to the Mayor, that if questioned he should not tell the truth, and that he should not talk or encourage the talk of the villagers, if he hoped to die in bed one day of natural causes. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n244" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_14996" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15048">— For a while our fugitives continued at a brisk pace, in silence, turning around, now one, now the other, to make sure they weren’t being followed. All three were exhausted from the escape, the racing of their hearts, anxiety over their present state, sadness over their failed mission, and a vague apprehension over the new and unknown danger. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n245" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15049" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15083">Their exhaustion was increased by the constant pursuit of the bells, which, as they grew softer and duller in the distance, began to take on a more gloomy and sinister sound. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n246" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15084" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15085">The tolling finally stopped. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n247" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15086" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15127">The fugitives, finding themselves in an uninhabited field and hearing not even a breeze, started to slow down. The first to break the silence, after she had caught her breath, was Agnese, by asking Renzo what had happened, and questioning Menico about the devil in her house. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n248" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15128" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15164">Renzo told his sad story quickly. All three of them then turned to the boy, who reported the friar’s warning in more detail, and told them what he himself had seen and risked, which unfortunately confirmed the warning. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n249" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15165" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15252">The listeners understood this better than Menico, and it made their blood run cold. All three of them stopped at the same time, and looked at one another in shock. In a spontaneous gesture, they reached out to place a hand on the boy’s head or his shoulders, as if to caress him and thank him wordlessly for having been their guardian angel, and to show how sorry they were for the distress he had suffered. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n250" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15253" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15297">“You should go home now, so your parents don’t worry about you,” Agnese told him. Remembering the two coins she had promised, she took four from her pocket and gave them to him, adding, “There. I pray to God we will see each other again soon. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n251" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15298" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15334">And then…” Renzo gave him another berlinga, and made him promise not to breathe a word about the message the friar had delivered. Lucia hugged him and wished him goodbye with her heart in her throat. The boy said an affectionate farewell to everyone, and turned back. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n252" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15335" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15350">The three continued on their way, lost in thought: the women first, and Renzo behind, as if he were guarding them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n253" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15351" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15405">Lucia clung to her mother’s arm and refused, gently but deftly, the hand the young man offered her on the trickiest patches of their trip through the fields. Even amid this turmoil, she was ashamed of having spent so much time alone with him, and so intimately, rather than waiting to become his wife, which should have been so simple. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n254" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15406" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15456">Now that the dream had vanished so painfully, she feared she had gone too far, and regretted it. Of the many reasons for which she trembled, one was the modesty born not from a guilty acquaintance with sin, but rather from naïveté, like the fears of a child who trembles in the shadows without knowing why. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n255" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15457" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15464">“What about my house?” Agnese suddenly asked. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n256" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15465" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15480">Although the question was important, no one answered, because no one could provide a satisfactory reply. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n257" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15481" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15498">They continued on their way in silence, and soon, at last, they came out into the piazza in front of the monastery’s church. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n258" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15499" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15507">Renzo went to the door and gave it a good push. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n259" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15508" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15536">It opened and the moon, shining through the crack, illuminated the pale face and silver beard of Padre Cristoforo, who had been standing there waiting. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n260" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15537" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15551">Seeing that no one was missing, he said, “Thank God,” and gestured for them to come in. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n261" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15552" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15614">Next to him was another Capuchin, the lay sacristan, whom, through pleading and reasoning, he had persuaded to wait up with him, leave the door slightly ajar, and be ready to welcome in the poor endangered souls. It took all the friar’s authority and his saintly reputation to obtain this inconvenient, dangerous, and irregular compliance from the lay brother. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n262" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15615" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15625">Once they were all inside, Padre Cristoforo closed the door behind them very quietly. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n263" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15626" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15657">At that the sacristan could no longer contain himself. Taking the padre aside, he whispered in his ear, “But, Padre, Padre! At night…in the church…with women…closing…the rules…but, Padre!” and he shook his head. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n264" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15658" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15670">As he listened to the man struggling to get the words out, Padre Cristoforo thought, “Will you look at this. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n265" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15671" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15723">Had it been a fugitive from justice, Fra Fazio wouldn’t have given it a second thought. But a poor innocent girl, escaping from the clutches of a wolf…” “Omnia munda mundis,” he said, suddenly turning toward Fra Fazio, forgetting that the man did not understand Latin. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n266" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15724" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15733">This lapse made all the difference. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n267" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15734" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15764">If he had tried to reason with him, the brother would have found a hundred counterarguments, and heaven knows how and when the debate would have ended. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n268" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15765" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15791">But hearing those grave words with their mysterious meaning, and uttered so resolutely, made Fra Fazio feel as if all of his doubts had been settled. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n269" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15792" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15801">He quieted down and said, “All right, then. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n270" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15802" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15838">I’ll take your word for it.” “You can trust me,” answered Padre Cristoforo. In the flickering light of the lamp burning before the altar, he approached the refugees, who had been standing there anxiously, and said to them, “Children, thank the Lord, who has delivered you from a grave danger. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n271" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15839" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15880">If things had gone differently…” And here he started to explain at length what he had told the little messenger in brief. He didn’t suspect that they knew more than him, and assumed that Menico had found them at home in peace, before the crooks arrived. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n272" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15881" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15907">No one corrected his misunderstanding, not even Lucia, who felt a slight remorse over deceiving such a man, but it had been a night of treachery and tricks. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n273" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15908" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15924">“After this,” he continued, “the village is no longer safe for you, my children. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n274" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15925" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15940">You were born here, you have never harmed anyone, but this is what God has ordained. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n275" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15941" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15968">It is a test, my children. Bear it with patience, with trust, and without hatred. And know that the day shall come when you will make peace with what is happening now. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n276" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15969" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15979">I have arranged a temporary refuge for you. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n277" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_15980" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16023">Very soon, I hope, you will be able to return safely to your home. Whatever happens, God will provide, and for the best. And I will do my utmost to be worthy of the grace He has granted me, in choosing me as His minister, in the service of you poor, dear afflicted souls.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n278" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16024" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16033">Turning to the two women, “You,” he continued, “can stay in ***. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n279" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16034" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16049">There you will be beyond the reach of danger, and at the same time not too far from your home. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n280" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16050" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16068">Go to our monastery there, ask for the Father Guardian, and give him this letter. For you, he will be like another Padre Cristoforo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n281" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16069" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16089">And you, too, dear Renzo, you must seek protection from the anger of others, as well as your own. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n282" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16090" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16105">Bring this letter to Padre Bonaventura of Lodi, at our monastery at Porta Orientale in Milan. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n283" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16106" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16127">He will act as your father, guide you, and find you work, until you can return here to live in peace. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n284" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16128" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16145">Go to the lakeshore, near the mouth of the Bione, a river not far from Pescarenico. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n285" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16146" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16160">There you’ll see a boat docked. Call out ‘Boat.’ You’ll hear, ‘Who for.’ Answer, ‘Saint Francis.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n286" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16161" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16179">The boat’ll take you on board and carry you to the opposite shore, where a cart will be waiting to take you all the way to ***.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n287" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16180" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16215">Anyone who wonders how Padre Cristoforo was able to arrange for all of this transportation, by land and by water, and so quickly, obviously doesn’t know the power of a Capuchin monk reputed to be a saint. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n288" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16216" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16222">There was still the custody of the houses to consider. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n289" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16223" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16238">The padre agreed to hold on to the keys, and to hand them over to whomever Renzo and Agnese indicated. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n290" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16239" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16270">Agnese, removing her keys from her pocket, sighing deeply to think of her house unlocked, the devil inside, and God knows what was even left to take care of. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n291" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16271" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16305">“Before you leave,” said the priest, “let us all pray to the Lord, so that he may accompany you on this journey, now and forever. Above all that he may give you the strength and the charity to want what he wants for you.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n292" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16306" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16317">So saying, he knelt down in the middle of the church, and everyone knelt with him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n293" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16318" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16348">After they had prayed in silence for a few moments, the priest, in a soft but clear voice, uttered these words: “We pray to you also for the poor sinner who has brought us to this pass. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n294" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16349" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16367">We would be unworthy of your mercy if we did not beseech you, from our hearts, to think of him, who has such great need of it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n295" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16368" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16392">Despite our tribulations, we can find consolation in being on the path on which you have set us. We can offer up to you our troubles, for which we shall be rewarded. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n296" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16393" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16402">But him!…He is your enemy, the wretch, and he defies You! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n297" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16403" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16425">Take pity on him, oh Lord. Touch his heart and reconcile him to You. Grant him all the blessings that we can wish for ourselves.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n298" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16426" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16446">Then, standing up quickly, he said, “Come, children, there’s no time to waste. God will watch over you. His angel will accompany you. Go now.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n299" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16447" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16477">As they rose, with an emotion for which there are no words, but can express itself without them, the priest added, in an altered tone of voice, “My heart tells me we shall soon meet again.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n300" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16478" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16494">The heart, of course, to those who heed it, always has some wisdom to share about the future. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n301" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16495" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16499">But what does the heart know? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n302" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16500" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16508">Only a fraction of that which has already happened. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n303" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16509" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16538">Without awaiting an answer, Padre Cristoforo headed for the sacristy. The travelers left the church and Fra Fazio closed the door, bidding them farewell, also in an altered tone. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n304" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16539" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16559">Renzo, Lucia, and Agnese proceeded, quietly quietly, to the shore where they had been directed. They saw the boat waiting for them, exchanged the password, and boarded. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n305" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16560" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16585">With one oar, the boatman pushed off from the shore. Rowing the other with two arms, he headed toward the beach on the opposite side. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n306" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16586" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16620">Not a breeze stirred the air. The lake lay smooth and flat, and would have appeared motionless but for the slight trembling and rippling of the moon, which was mirrored in the water from the sky above. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n307" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16621" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16666">The only sound you could hear was the dull lapping and slow splashing of the waves over the pebbles on the beach, the more distant gurgling of the water breaking around the piers of the bridge, and the rhythmic slapping of the two oars slicing the blue surface of the lake, coming up dripping, and dipping back in again. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n308" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16667" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16683">The wake of the boat formed a rippled streak behind the stern as the boat drew farther and farther away from the lido. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n309" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16684" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16707">The silent passengers, twisting their heads to look back, gazed at the mountains and the moonlit village, dappled in places by broad shadows. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n310" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16708" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16751">They could make out the houses, the huts. Don Rodrigo’s big palace, with its flat tower rising above the pile of humble dwellings on the hillside of the promontory, standing upright in the shadows; his house looked like a cruel master in the midst of a slumbering group, both keeping vigil and contemplating a crime. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n311" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16752" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16816">Lucia saw it and shivered. She allowed her eyes to slowly follow the descent of the slope to their little village. Gazing at the far end, she could see her cottage, the thick foliage of the fig tree rising above the courtyard wall, and the window of her room. Sitting, as she was, in the bottom of the boat, she rested her arm on the edge, laid her face on her arm as if to sleep, and wept to herself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n312" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16817" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16872">Farewell mountains rising from the waters and reaching to the sky; jagged peaks familiar to one who has grown up among you, etched in her mind no less clearly than the faces of those she holds dear. Farewell rivers, whose roaring she knows as well as the voices of home. Farewell small white villages, clinging to the slopes like flocks of grazing sheep. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n313" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16873" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16885">Nothing could be sadder than the footsteps of one who, having grown up among you, must take her leave! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n314" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16886" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16929">Such a moment crushes the fantasies of a man who departs freely, dreaming of seeking his fortune elsewhere. Dismayed to have ever resolved such a thing, he would turn back but for his dreams of wealth. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n315" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_16930" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_17012">The more he advances across the plain, the more his weary eyes are repelled by the unending sameness. The air feels heavy and dead. Dejected and confused, he enters the tumultuous city, unable to breathe amid house after house, street after street. Standing before buildings admired by many a foreigner, he thinks, with restless desire, of the fields in his home village, the little house that caught his eye long ago, which he will buy once he returns to his mountains, a wealthy man. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n316" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_17013" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_17044">But what about a girl who has never nursed even a fleeting desire to leave the mountains? Who has pictured her future in that setting, only to be cast out by a perverse force! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n317" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_17045" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_17088">Torn in a single moment from her most cherished habits and fondest hopes. She leaves the mountains behind to follow in the footsteps of strangers she had no wish to meet, unable to even imagine the moment when she might return. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n318" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_17089" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_17114">Farewell childhood home, where lost in private thoughts, she had learned to hear the difference between normal footsteps and the footsteps of the youth she awaited with a mysterious fear. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n319" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_17115" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_17142">Farewell home she might never know, at which she had stolen many a blushing glance; the home where she had envisioned a married life, serene and lifelong. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n320" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_17143" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_17178">Farewell church, where peace of mind had so often returned while singing the Lord’s praises. Where her marriage banns had been posted and the Mass prepared. Where the secret yearning of her heart was supposed to be solemnly blessed and love ordained and made holy. Farewell! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n321" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_17179" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_17207">He who gave you such bliss is everywhere and would never trouble the joy of his children, except to make it more certain and great. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap8-n322" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_17208" targetEnd="quarantana/cap8.xml#c8_17238">Such was the nature, though not the letter, of Lucia’s thoughts, which differed only slightly from those of her two fellow pilgrims, as the boat brought them closer to the right bank of the Adda. </note>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>