<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>2022</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed: a novel</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
          <date>2022</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Michael Moore</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="english_2022_cap9">
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10026">The boat’s impact against the shore shook Lucia from her thoughts. After discreetly drying her tears, she raised her head as if she had just woken up. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10027" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10052">Renzo climbed out of the boat first. He held out his hand to Agnese, who then offered her hand to her daughter. All three sadly thanked the boatman. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10053" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10111">“For what,” he replied, “we are here on this earth to help one another.” He pulled his hand away, almost with distaste, as if he had been asked to commit a crime, when Renzo tried to slip him a few of the coins he had brought along that night, planning to make a generous donation to Don Abbondio if the priest, despite himself, had served his purpose. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10112" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10134">As promised, a cart was waiting for them. The driver greeted his three passengers and helped them climb aboard. With a “Giddyap” to the horse and a crack of the whip, they were off. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10135" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10163">The author of the manuscript does not describe that nighttime journey, nor does he disclose the name of the town where Fra Cristoforo had directed the two women. Indeed, he refuses to do so quite explicitly. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10164" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10175">Later in our story, the reasons for his reticence will become clear. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10176" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10204">Lucia’s adventures during her stay there became entangled with the shadowy intrigues of a member of a family that was very powerful during the period when the author was writing. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10205" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10239">To explain that person’s, or rather, her strange behavior in this particular case, he also had to give a brief account of her previous life. Her family enjoyed a stature that the patient reader will come to understand. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10240" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10260">But my diligent research discovered through other sources things that the author’s circumspection had sought to hide. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10261" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10325">A Milanese historian who mentions the same person does not give either her name or the name of the town, it’s true. As for the place, however, he does say that it was a noble and ancient town which was a city in all but name. At one point he writes that the Lambro River passes through it. At another, that it had an archpriest. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10326" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10336">By piecing together these bits of information we can deduce, without a doubt, that it was Monza. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10337" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10355">In the vast treasury of educated guesses, there may well be more subtle possibilities, but none, I believe, that are more certain. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10356" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10399">We could also, on the basis of sound conjecture, say the name of the family with which Lucia became entangled. But although it has been extinct for some time, I thought it best to keep their name inside my pen, to avoid wronging the departed and to leave something for the educated to investigate. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10400" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10436">Our travelers arrived in Monza, then, shortly after sunrise. The driver entered a tavern. A regular customer of the place and an acquaintance of the host, he ordered a room where they could eat and then escorted the trio inside. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10437" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10477">Thanking the man, Renzo tried to get him to accept some money, too. Like the boatman, however, the driver aspired to a more distant but greater reward. He, too, pulled his hand away and, as if to escape temptation, hurried off to feed his horse. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10478" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10548">After an evening like the one I have just described, and a night that each of you can imagine for yourself, spent in the company of such worries, with the constant fear, at every stirring of the late autumn breeze, of some unpleasant encounter; amid the constant lurching of the uncomfortable vehicle, which rudely awoke anyone who had begun to nod off; the three of them could hardly believe they were now sitting on a stable bench, and in any type of room at all. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10549" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10572">Their breakfast was of the sort afforded by the food shortages of the day, their meager resources before an uncertain future, and little appetite. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10573" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10594">All three thought back to the banquet to which, two days before, they had been expecting to sit down, and each heaved a sigh. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10595" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10626">Renzo would have liked to remain in Monza for at least a day, to make sure the women were situated, and their basic needs taken care of. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10627" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10664">But the padre had instructed Agnese and Lucia to send him on his way immediately, so they reminded Renzo of those instructions along with many other reasons: that people would talk, that prolonging their separation would be more painful, that he would soon be able to come by to give and receive any news. Finally, he decided to leave. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10665" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10677">They agreed, as best they could, on how they would meet again, hopefully as soon as possible. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10678" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10704">This time Lucia did not hide her tears. Renzo struggled to hold back his own. Squeezing Agnese’s hand tightly, he said, in a choked voice, “Until we meet again,” and left. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10705" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10736">The women would have been at quite a loss were it not for the good driver, who had been instructed to take them after breakfast to the Capuchin monastery and provide them with all the assistance they required. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10737" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10754">So they set out with him for the monastery, which, as everyone knows, is not far from Monza. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10755" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10776">Once they had reached the gate, he rang the bell and asked for the Father Guardian, who came at once and opened their letter on the spot. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10777" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10783">“Oh, Fra Cristoforo!” he exclaimed, recognizing the handwriting. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10784" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10800">The tone of his voice and the expression on his face clearly indicated that he was saying the name of a close friend. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10801" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10857">In the letter, I should add, our good Cristoforo had recommended the women with such warmth, and described their situation with such emotion, that the Father Guardian made occasional gestures of surprise or indignation. Looking up from the piece of paper, he gazed at the women with compassion and interest. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10858" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10879">When he had finished reading, he remained in thought for a few moments and then said, “The best person for this is the Signora…if she wishes to assume the responsibility…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10880" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10931">Drawing Agnese aside, to the piazza in front of the monastery, he asked her a few questions, which she answered to his satisfaction. Returning to where Lucia was standing, he said to both women, “My dear ladies, I’ll do my best. And I hope to find you a refuge that is quite safe, quite honorable, until God has provided for you in a better manner. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10932" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10935">Would you come with me, please?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10936" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10954">The women nodded respectfully, and the friar continued. “Good. I will accompany you straight to the convent of the Signora. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10955" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10994">Walk a few steps behind me, please, since people like to gossip, and God only knows how they’ll wag their tongues if they see the Father Guardian on the street with a pretty girl…with two women, I meant to say.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10995" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10998">With these words he set out. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_10999" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11032">Lucia blushed. The driver smiled, giving a knowing glance at Agnese, who could not resist doing the same. They let the friar go on ahead, following about ten steps behind him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11033" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11050">This allowed the women to ask the driver the question they had not dared to raise with the Father Guardian. Who was this Signora? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11051" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11064">“The Signora,” he replied, “is a nun, but a nun unlike the others. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n38" type="comm" status="insertion">Not to suggest that she’s an abbess or a prioress. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11065" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11232">In fact, from what I hear, she’s one of the youngest members of the convent. But her family goes way back, and the blood in their veins runs blue. They came from a powerful house in Spain. That’s why they call her the Signora, to show that she’s a noble. The whole town calls her that, since they say there’s never been anyone quite like her in the convent. And her family down in Milan has a lot of influence, and they always get their way. So you can imagine what it’s like here in Monza; her father, even though he’s never around, is still the leading citizen. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11233" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11299">That’s why she has the run of the convent. Even outsiders have a lot of respect for her. And when she promises to do something, she does it. So if that good friar manages to place you in her care, and she accepts you, you’ll be as safe as you would be on the altar, I can tell you that much.” As he approached the town gate, which in those days was surrounded by the rubble of a collapsed tower and the ruins of an old castle (which a dozen of my readers might remember seeing when it was still standing), the Father Guardian stopped and turned around to see if the others were still following. Then he passed through the gates and headed toward the convent. He stopped again, on the convent’s threshold, to wait for his little brigade. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11300" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11334">He asked the driver to come back in a couple of hours for a message. The man promised he would and took his leave of the women, who showered him with thanks and messages for Padre Cristoforo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11335" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11361">The friar accompanied mother and daughter into the outermost courtyard of the convent, then left them in the quarters of the stewardess, the laywoman who oversaw the convent, and went by himself to request the favor. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11362" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11394">After keeping them waiting for a while, he reappeared joyously, to tell them to come with him. And not a minute too soon, since Agnese and Lucia were struggling to extricate themselves from the prying questions of the stewardess. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11395" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11410">Crossing a second courtyard, the Father Guardian advised the women on how to behave with the Signora. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11411" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11425">“She is well inclined toward you,” he said, “and is capable of doing you all the good in the world. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11426" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11448">Be humble and respectful, answer honestly any questions it may please her to ask, and when there are no more questions, leave everything to me.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11449" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11481">They entered a ground-floor room that led to the nun’s parlor. Before setting foot inside, the guardian, pointing to the door, whispered to the women, “She’s here,” as if to remind them of his advice. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11482" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11553">Entering the parlor, Lucia, who had never been to a convent before, looked around for the Signora, so that she might curtsey to her. Seeing no one, she stood there, not knowing what to do. When the priest and Agnese walked toward a corner, she looked in their direction and noticed an oddly shaped window, covered by two thick, tightly wrought iron gratings, only a palm’s width apart from each other. Behind them stood a nun. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11554" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11577">From her face, she looked to be about twenty-five. Her appearance created an initial impression of beauty, but a dejected, faded, and, I would almost say, disheveled beauty. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11578" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11642">A black veil was stretched flat across her head, and draped down evenly on either side of her face. Right below it was a bright white linen band, lowered partway down a forehead of a different but no less brilliant whiteness. A second pleated band circled her face, coming to a close under her chin in a wimple that spread over her chest, covering the neckline of a black habit. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11643" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11664">Her forehead would often wrinkle, as if from a painful spasm, in a rapid motion of her black eyebrows. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11665" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11760">Two eyes, also as black as coal, sometimes stared directly at people with a haughty inquisitiveness; other times they were quickly lowered, as if to seek a hiding place. There were moments when a careful observer might deduce that those eyes were pleading for affection, for sympathy, for pity. There were others when he might think he had caught a sudden glimpse of a deep and long-repressed hatred, something vaguely menacing and cruel. When she stared into space, some people imagined a proud apathy, while others suspected the anguish of a hidden thought, a familiar preoccupation that overpowered any interest in her surroundings. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11761" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11779">Her pale cheeks sloped downward in a delicate, graceful curve that had been altered and hollowed through a slow exhaustion. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11780" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11807">Her lips, although colored by only the barest hint of faded rose, stood out from her general pallor, and their movements, like those of her eyes, were quick, lively, and filled with passion and mystery. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11808" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11839">The shapely grandeur of her person disappeared, however, into a certain laxness in her bearing, or rather it appeared to be disfigured by movements that were sudden, erratic, and too resolute for a woman, much less a nun. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11840" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11903">Even the way she wore her habit suggested a deliberate or unconscious announcement of just how unique a nun she was. Her cincture was tied around her waist with a certain worldly care, and from her headband, a single lock of black hair emerged, betraying a neglect or scorn for the rules prescribing that a nun’s hair be kept short from the moment it was cut during the solemn investiture ceremony. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11904" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11952">Agnese and Lucia did not notice, since they were unpracticed in distinguishing between one nun and another. The Father Guardian, who was not seeing the Signora for the first time, was already accustomed, as were many others, to the aura of strangeness that emanated from her person and her manner. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11953" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11986">At that moment she was, as I was saying, standing near the grate with one hand resting on it languidly, and her pale white fingers entwined in the empty spaces. She stared at Lucia, who was coming forward hesitantly. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_11987" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12023">“Reverend Mother and illustrious Signora,” said the Father Guardian, his head bowed and one hand on his chest, “this is the poor girl to whom I hope you may extend your true protection. And this is her mother.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12024" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12059">Thus introduced, mother and daughter curtsied deeply. The Signora gestured with her hand that this was sufficient and said, turning to the priest, “I am happy to oblige our good friends the Capuchin friars. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12060" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12081">But,” she continued, “to better understand what I can do for her, could you please explain to me in greater detail the case of this young girl.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12082" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12088">Lucia turned red and bowed her head. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12089" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12122">“What you should know, Reverend Mother,” Agnese began to say. But the Father Guardian gave her a look that stopped her short and replied, in turn, “This girl, illustrious Signora, was recommended to me, as I mentioned, by a fellow friar. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12123" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12158">To escape grave danger she had to leave her hometown secretly. She needs sanctuary, for a time, a place where she can live anonymously, and where no one would dare bother her, even if…” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12159" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12163">“What dangers?” the Signora interrupted. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12164" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12175">“Please, Father Guardian, do not speak to me in riddles. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12176" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12189">You must know that we nuns prefer to hear every detail of a story.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12190" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12205">“Dangers,” he replied, “that to the Reverend Mother’s pure ears would best be left unsaid.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12206" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12214">“Oh, of course,” the Signora said quickly, appearing to blush. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12215" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12216">But did she really? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12217" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12250">Anyone who observed the quick expression of indignation that appeared on her face might have wondered, especially compared to the more innocent color that occasionally spread over Lucia’s cheeks. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12251" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12319">“I will only say,” the Father Guardian continued, “that a tyrannical lord—for, unlike your illustrious Ladyship, not all the world’s powerful use God’s gifts for His greater glory, and to help their neighbor—a tyrannical nobleman tormented this child with indecent flattery. When that failed, he had the gall to pursue her openly, and forcefully, giving the poor girl no choice but to flee her home.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12320" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12331">“Come closer, my child,” said the Signora to Lucia, beckoning to her with one finger. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12332" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12351">“I know that the Father Guardian is the voice of truth. But no one is better informed of this affair than you. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12352" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12363">You are the one who should tell us whether this nobleman did indeed pursue you improperly.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12364" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12374">As for coming closer, Lucia was quick to obey. Answering the nun was another matter. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12375" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12410">Any question about that particular subject, even if it had been asked by one of her peers, would have left her more than a little flustered: Coming from that lady, with a hint of malicious skepticism, crushed what little courage she had. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12411" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12422">“Signora…Mother…Reverend…” she stammered, giving no sign of being able to say more. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12423" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12442">At this point Agnese, as the person who, after Lucia, was certainly the best informed, felt authorized to come to her rescue. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12443" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12481">“Your Ladyship,” she said, “I can testify that my daughter hated that lord like the demon hates holy water. He was the devil in the flesh. Forgive me for my poor speech. We’re simple people. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12482" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12552">The fact is that my poor girl was betrothed to a good God-fearing boy of our same class. And if our priest had been more of a man, at least what I call a man…I know I’m talking about a religious man, but Padre Cristoforo, a friend of the Father Guardian here, is just as religious as he is, and he’s a most charitable man, and if he was here, he could attest—” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12553" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12574">“You’re quick to speak without being spoken to,” the Signora broke in with a haughty, angry exclamation that made her look almost ugly. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12575" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12594">“Silence! I know a thing or two about parents always answering on their children’s behalf!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12595" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12614">Mortified, Agnese gave Lucia a look as if to say, “The trouble you get me into, with your always being so tongue-tied.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12615" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12642">The guardian also gestured to the girl, winking at her and nodding to indicate that the time had come to step out of her shell and rescue her poor mother. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12643" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12656">“Reverend Lady,” Lucia began, “what my mother was saying is the God’s honest truth. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12657" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12672">The boy who was courting me”—at this she turned bright red—“I accepted of my own free will. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12673" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12688">Please excuse me if I speak too boldly, but it is only so that you won’t think badly of my mother. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12689" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12705">As for that nobleman (God forgive him!), I would rather die than fall into his hands. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12706" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12754">Could your Ladyship be so merciful as to protect us, since we are reduced to begging for shelter and disturbing good people? May God’s will be done. You can be certain, your Ladyship, that no one will offer more heartfelt prayers on your behalf than we poor women.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12755" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12763">“You, I can believe,” said the Signora, softening her tone. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12764" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12772">“But I would rather speak with you alone. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12773" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12797">Unless there is a need for further clarification, or further reasons, to attend to the concerns of the Father Guardian,” she added immediately, addressing him with a studied courtesy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12798" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12816">“Indeed,” she continued, “I’ve already found an idea. Here’s what I think would be the best thing to do for the moment. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12817" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12828">The stewardess of the convent married off her youngest daughter a few days ago. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12829" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12848">These two women could take the room that is now free, and take over some of her old chores. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12849" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12899">To tell you the truth”—and here she hinted to the friar that he should come closer to the grating—“since the harvest was so poor, we were thinking of not replacing the girl. But I will speak with the Mother Abbess. One word from me…and as a favor to the Father Guardian…I think we can consider it as good as done.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12900" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12925">The guardian began to thank her, but the Signora interrupted him. “No need to make such a fuss. If I were in need, I know that I, too, could always count on the help of the Capuchin friars. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12926" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12949">In the end,” she continued, with a smile that disclosed a hint of bitter irony, “are we all not brothers and sisters?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12950" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12988">At this, she summoned a lay sister (in a singular distinction, two of them had been assigned to her personal service) and ordered them to notify the abbess and make the necessary arrangements with the stewardess and Agnese. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12989" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12996">She then dismissed the sister, took leave of the Father Guardian, and detained Lucia for a private conversation. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_12997" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13016">The friar accompanied Agnese to the door, giving her additional instructions, and went off to write a detailed report to his friend Cristoforo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13017" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13033">“What an odd bird this Signora is,” he thought as he went on his way, “very odd indeed! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13034" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13048">If you manage to get on her good side, you can get her to do what you want. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13049" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13061">I’m sure Cristoforo hardly expected that I would be able to serve him so quickly and so well. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13062" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13078">Such a good man! Always taking on new obligations: There’s no stopping him! But he does it for the best. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13079" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13109">This time it went well for him, since he found a friend who, without too much fuss or ceremony, found a solution to the problem in the wink of an eye. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13110" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13126">He’ll be happy, and realize that his brothers down here are also quite capable.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13127" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13215">The Signora, who in the presence of the seasoned Capuchin had measured her actions and her words, no longer worried once she was alone with the naïve peasant girl. The things she said became stranger and stranger. Rather than report them, we think it best to briefly relate the background of this unhappy woman. Just enough to explain that odd and mysterious behavior we have just witnessed, and to understand the reasons for things that later came to pass. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13216" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13234">She was the youngest daughter of Prince ***, a leading Milanese nobleman, who could be considered one of the wealthiest men in the city. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13235" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13275">But the high opinion he held of his title made him feel as if his possessions were barely sufficient to keep up appearances, and that they were, indeed, quite meager. His thoughts were dedicated solely to conserving his estate undiminished, undivided in perpetuity, to the best of his abilities. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13276" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13323">The manuscript does not tell us exactly how many children he had. It only hints that he had sent to the cloister all of the younger children, boys and girls, so that his property would remain intact for his firstborn son, who was destined to preserve the family: In other words, he begot children, and then tormented himself by tormenting them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13324" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13341">The unhappy child who is our concern was still hiding in its mother’s womb when its fate was irrevocably sealed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13342" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13366">The only thing left to decide was whether that fate was to be a monk or a nun: a decision that required not the child’s consent but its presence. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13367" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13397">When she was born, her father, the Prince, wanting to give her a name that would immediately suggest the idea of the cloister, and a name that had been borne by a saint of high birth, called her Gertrude. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13398" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13439">The first toys placed in her hands were dolls dressed up as nuns. Then came holy cards with pictures of nuns. These gifts were always accompanied with a lot of fuss about how they must be well cared for, how precious they were, and the rhetorical question, “Isn’t she the pretty little doll?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13440" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13480">When the Prince, the Princess, or the heir apparent—who alone of the males was being raised at home—wished to compliment the little girl on her lovely appearance, they could seemingly find no better way to express themselves than to say, “You look just like a mother abbess!” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13481" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13490">No one ever told her outright, “You have to become a nun.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13491" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13505">Instead the idea was taken for granted and brought up only incidentally, every time they spoke of her future. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13506" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13551">Whenever little Gertrude would act somewhat arrogantly and imperiously—as she tended to do—they would say, “You are a little girl. It’s not right for you to behave in this way. Once you have become mother abbess, then you can do as you wish, and boss everyone around.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13552" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13627">At other times the Prince, reprimanding her for the overly lax and casual manners to which she was inclined, would say, “Now, now! This is no way for someone in your position to act. If you wish to receive the respect that is your due one day, you will have to start learning how to control yourself. Remember that in all things you must be the first in the convent, because your family name is something you take with you wherever you go.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13628" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13660">Words like these impressed upon the young girl’s mind that she was to become a nun. And the words that issued from her father’s mouth had a greater impact than all of the others put together. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13661" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13704">While the Prince’s customary demeanor was that of an austere master, when it came to the future of his children his facial expression and his every word emanated an unshakeable resolve and a sullen guardianship of his authority that lent his opinions a sense of fatal necessity. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13705" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13734">At the age of six, Gertrude was transferred to the convent where we first met her, for the sake of her education but especially to set her on the road to the vocation imposed upon her. The choice of place had not been made casually. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13735" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13780">Lucia and Agnese’s kindly guide had mentioned that the Signora’s father was the most powerful man in Monza. If we combine this testimony, for what it’s worth, with other clues that the anonymous author allows to slip through occasional lapses in his vigilance, we could also assume that he was the feudal lord of the town. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13781" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13818">Whatever the case may be, he enjoyed immense authority. And he thought that in Monza, more than anywhere else, his daughter would be treated with the deference and decorum that might entice her to choose that convent as her permanent residence. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13819" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13891">Nor was he wrong. The abbess and some of the other meddling nuns who were ready to stir the pot, so to speak, were overjoyed to be offered the pledge of his protection, which would be useful in times of particular need as well as glorious in general throughout the year. They accepted the proposal with expressions of gratitude that, despite their fervency, were hardly exaggerated. And they complied fully with the intentions that the Prince had intimated regarding the permanent situation of his daughter: intentions that concurred perfectly with their own. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13892" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13950">The moment Gertrude entered the convent, she was given the sobriquet of “la Signorina,” and a place of distinction at the table and in the dormitory. Her conduct was held up as an example to the other students. Endless sweets and caresses, seasoned with the slightly deferential familiarity that so enchants children when they find it in people who normally treat children with an air of superiority. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_13951" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14025">Not that all the nuns were conspiring to draw the poor girl into the trap. There were many simple sisters who would have been appalled by the idea of sacrificing a daughter to such venal ends. But busy as they were with their particular chores, some were unaware of the scheme, some saw nothing wrong with it, some abstained from looking into it, and some kept quiet to avoid creating a useless scandal. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14026" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14071">There were, however, one or two, who remembered how, through similar arts, they had been led to a decision they would later regret. And they felt compassion for the poor innocent child, which they expressed through tender, melancholy caresses. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14072" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14088">Gertrude didn’t have the least suspicion of some underlying mystery, so the plot moved forward, and it might have until the end, if she had been the only girl in the convent. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14089" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14103">Among her fellow pupils, however, there were some who knew that they were destined to be married. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14104" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14148">Little Gertrude, raised on notions of her own superiority, spoke grandly about her future destiny as an abbess and as the princess of the convent, and wanted at all costs to be an object of envy for the others. But she was surprised and irked to see that some of them felt no envy at all. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14149" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14186">In contrast to her own majestic—though narrow and cold—images of leading the convent, they boasted a dazzling array of images of weddings and banquets, receptions and balls, vacations in the country, clothing and carriages. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14187" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14211">These sent Gertrude’s mind buzzing like a beehive placed before a basket of freshly picked flowers. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14212" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14255">Her parents and teachers had cultivated her innate vanity in order to make her like the cloister. But when this passion was aroused by ideas more congenial to her nature, she chased after them with a lively and spontaneous ardor. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14256" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14327">So as not to be outdone by her classmates, and at the same time to gratify her new inclination, she would say that, after all, no one could place a veil over her head without her consent, and that she, too—better than any of them—could get married, live in a palace, and enjoy the world. That she could, if she had wanted to, if she would like to, if she did indeed want to. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14328" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14362">Which was, in fact, what she wanted. The need for her consent, an idea that until then had nestled, unobserved, in a corner of her mind, started to grow and to take on its full measure. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14363" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14377">She constantly appealed for its help, so as to enjoy her visions of a more amenable future. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14378" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14423">This idea, however, never failed to be chased by another: that she would have to refuse to give that consent before her father, the Prince, who considered it a fait accompli, or acted as if he did. At the thought, the daughter’s spirit fell short of the confidence that her words professed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14424" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14448">She would then compare herself to her classmates, whose high confidence stood in sore contrast to her own wavering resolve, and feel the painful envy toward them that she had initially thought she herself would inspire. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14449" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14476">And her envy made her hate them. Sometimes that hatred took the form of slights, rudeness, and insulting remarks. Sometimes their shared hopes and desires briefly placated her hatred, making her feel the semblance of a momentary intimacy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14477" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14530">Sometimes, while wanting to enjoy something real and present, she contented herself with the preferential treatment she was accorded, and made the other girls feel her superiority. Sometimes, unable to bear any longer her fears and desires in solitude, she went to them meekly, as if to beg for their kindness, advice, and courage. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14531" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14580">While waging these deplorable little wars with herself and with others, she crossed the threshold of puberty and entered that critical age when a sort of mysterious power seems to inhabit the spirit and enhances, adorns, and strengthens every inclination, every idea, sometimes transforming or steering them down an unexpected path. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14581" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14628">Until that point, Gertrude’s dreams of the future had settled on external splendor and pomp. But now something tender and affectionate, which had at first spread softly, like a fog, started to unfurl and to dominate her fantasies. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14629" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14695">In the deepest recesses of her mind, she had built a splendid retreat where she could take refuge from the present, and welcome characters who had been pieced together from odd bits and vague memories of childhood, the little she had been able to see of the outside world, and the things she had learned from the gossip of her classmates. She spent time with these characters, conversed with them, and replied on their behalf. It was a place where she gave orders and received every type of flattery. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14696" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14711">Now and again, thoughts of religion would intrude to disturb these brilliant and hard-won festivities. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14712" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14742">But religion, as the poor girl had been taught and understood it to mean, did not prohibit pride. On the contrary, it sanctified it, and proposed it as a means to attain earthly happiness. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14743" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14757">Emptied of its substance, religion thus became just another one of her fantasies. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14758" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14816">But in those moments when religion ruled Gertrude’s imagination, the unhappy child, overwhelmed by vague fears, and seized by a vague sense of duty, imagined that her revulsion for the cloister, and her resistance to her elders’ hints as to her choice of station, were a sin. And she promised in her heart to atone for it by closing herself voluntarily in the cloister. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14817" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14881">According to the law, a girl could not be admitted into the order until she had been examined by a priest, known as the vicar of the nuns, or by his deputy, to ensure that she was doing so of her own free will. This examination could not be conducted until one year after she had expressed her wishes to the vicar in a written supplication. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14882" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14920">The nuns who had accepted the sad assignment of assuring that Gertrude would make the eternal vow with the least possible awareness of what she was doing seized on one of the moments we have described to get her to transcribe and sign just such a document. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14921" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14962">To persuade her, they repeated to her over and over again that it was a mere formality that could not take effect (which is true) except through other, later acts that would express her will. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14963" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14982">No sooner had the supplication reached its destination than Gertrude regretted having signed it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_14983" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15000">Then she regretted her regret, spending days and months in an endless wavering between conflicting feelings. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15024">For a long time, she kept the fact that she had taken this step hidden from her companions, partly out of fear of exposing a firm decision to dissent, partly out of shame that she might be admitting a mistake. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15025" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15036">In the end she was overcome by the desire to pour out her soul, and to seek counsel and encouragement. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15037" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15065">According to another law, a girl cannot be admitted to the examination of her vocation until she has spent at least one month away from the convent where she received her education. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15066" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15110">One year had already gone by since her supplication had been sent, and Gertrude was notified that she would soon be taken away from the convent and accompanied to her father’s house, where she was to remain for one month and take all the steps necessary to complete the application she had begun. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15111" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15149">The Prince and the rest of the family treated all of this as a given, as if she had already taken her vows, but the girl had something different in mind. Rather than proceed through the next steps, she was contemplating how to retract the first. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15150" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15170">In her distress, she decided to confide in one of her companions, a girl who was always candid and ready to give firm advice. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15171" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15197">She suggested that Gertrude inform her father of her change of heart in a letter, since she did not have the courage to deliver to his face a plain, “This is not what I want.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15198" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15221">And since there is no such thing as free advice in this world, her advisor made Gertrude pay by mocking her ineptitude. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15222" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15241">The letter was written in secret, compiled by four or five of her confidantes, and delivered through carefully contrived routes. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15242" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15252">Gertrude was filled with anxiety, awaiting a reply that never arrived. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15253" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15306">Instead, a few days later, the abbess summoned her to her cell and, with an attitude of mystery, disgust, and compassion, made dark allusions to the Prince’s great wrath, or to a mistake the girl had committed, while hinting, nevertheless, that if she behaved properly there was reason to hope that all would be forgotten. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15307" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15316">Gertrude understood, and did not dare to ask any further questions. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15317" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15324">The much dreaded and desired day finally arrived. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15325" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15365">Although Gertrude knew she was heading into battle, the very fact of leaving the convent, leaving behind the walls that had imprisoned her for eight years, riding in a carriage through the open countryside, seeing once again the city, and her home, filled her with a sense of tumultuous joy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15366" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15391">As for the battle awaiting her, the poor girl, following the instructions of her confidantes, had already readied herself and, as we say nowadays, made her plan. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15392" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15423">“If they try to force me,” she thought, “I will be firm. I will be humble and respectful, but I will not consent. All I have to do is refuse to say ‘yes’ again, and I shall refuse. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15424" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15451">If they try to win me over through kindness, then I shall be even kinder. I will weep. I will pray. I will move them to pity. In the end I expect nothing other than not to be sacrificed.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15452" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15466">As often happens with such expectations, however, neither one nor the other came to pass. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15467" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15495">Days went by without a word from either her father or the other family members concerning her supplication or its retraction, without anything at all being proposed to her, without receiving either tenderness or threats. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15496" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15508">Her parents were serious, unkind, and curt with her, never explaining why. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15509" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15544">One could see that they regarded her as disobedient, unworthy. A mysterious anathema seemed to have fallen upon her, separating her from the other members of the family and allowing her to join them only long enough to make her feel uneasy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15545" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15561">Occasionally, and only at established hours, she was admitted to the company of her parents and her eldest brother. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15562" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15584">The intimacy they seemed to share made the desolation to which Gertrude had been abandoned even more tangible and painful. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15585" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15616">No one spoke to her. Every time she would timidly venture a few words on anything other than a necessary matter, she was either ignored or rewarded with a distracted, contemptuous, or severe glance. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15617" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15667">Whenever she could no longer bear this bitter and humiliating discrimination, and insisted and tried to be close to her family, whenever she begged for a little love, she immediately sensed that she was touching, indirectly but clearly, the raw nerve of her vocation. It was subtly hinted to her that there was only one way to regain her family’s affection. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15668" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15714">At such moments Gertrude, who would not have wanted their love under such conditions, was compelled to withdraw, to reject the first signs of the kindness she had so desired, and to return, of her own free will, to her place of excommunication, leaving in her wake a lingering appearance of guilt. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15715" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15741">Her current situation contrasted painfully with the joyous daydreams that used to occupy Gertrude’s time, and still did in the secrecy of her mind. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15742" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15766">She had hoped that, in the splendid and sociable home of her father, she would be able to enjoy at least some real taste of the things she had imagined. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15767" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15802">Instead she was as strictly and completely cloistered as she had been at the convent. The idea of taking a stroll outside was out of the question. The only need she had for going out was eliminated by a private chapel that connected the house to the church next door. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15803" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15814">Companionship was more dreary, more begrudging, and less varied than in the convent. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15815" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15839">Every time a visit was announced, Gertrude was obliged to go upstairs to the top floor and lock herself in her chambers, alone but for a handful of elderly domestics. This is also where she dined when there were guests. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15840" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15916">The servants complied, in manner and speech, with the example and intentions of their masters. And Gertrude, who would have been more inclined to treat them with an aristocratic familiarity, found herself having to be grateful for any shred of affection that they showed her, as if she were one of them. She stooped to begging for it and was humiliated, and increasingly pained, when she was repaid with blatant disregard, accompanied, however, by a slightly obsequious formality. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15917" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15939">Gertrude could not help but notice, however, that one young page, unlike all the rest, treated her with respect, and felt a compassion of a particular kind for her. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n189" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15940" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15971">More than anyone she had met before, his demeanor resembled that of her ideal creations, within the order of things she had so fervently contemplated in her imagination. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n190" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_15972" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16016">Gradually something imperceptible and new came over the girl’s manner: an unusual tranquility and disquiet, as if she had found something she cared about, that she wanted to stare at all day without being noticed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n191" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16017" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16055">She was watched even more closely to see what was happening and what was not. One morning she was surprised by one of the maids while secretly folding a sheet of paper on which she would have done better to write nothing. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n192" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16056" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16075">After a brief struggle, the paper remained in the hands of the maid, and from her it passed into the hands of the Prince. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n193" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16076" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16101">Gertrude’s terror at the sound of his footsteps can be neither described nor imagined, with a father like that, so irate, together with the burden of her own guilt. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n194" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16102" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16126">When she saw him appear, with that angry scowl, and that piece of paper in his hand, she longed to be a hundred feet below the ground, never mind in a cloister. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n195" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16127" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16183">His words were short but cruel. The punishment that he immediately threatened was to lock her in her room, under the watch of the woman who had made the discovery. But this was only the beginning, a temporary solution. There was a threat, a feeling in the air, of a punishment that was more dire, more uncertain, and therefore all the more dreadful. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n196" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16184" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16208">The page was immediately fired, of course. A terrible fate was threatened against him should he ever breathe a word of what had happened. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n197" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16209" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16233">In issuing these warnings, the Prince slapped him twice, firmly, to associate the episode with a memory that would rid the lad of any temptation to brag. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n198" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16234" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16257">It was not hard to find some sort of excuse for dismissing a page. As for his daughter, word was circulated that she was indisposed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n199" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16258" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16293">So Gertrude was abandoned to anxiety, shame, remorse, fear of the future, and the sole company of a woman she despised, the witness to her indiscretion and the reason for her disgrace. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n200" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16294" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16323">The woman in turn despised Gertrude, thanks to whom she herself had been reduced to the dull life of a jailer, without knowing for how long, and as the eternal guardian of a dangerous secret. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n201" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16324" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16356">The first confused turmoil of emotions slowly subsided, only to return to her mind, one at a time, where they were magnified and remained to torment her thoughts more sharply and indiscriminately. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n202" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16357" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16365">Whatever could that mysteriously threatened punishment be? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n203" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16366" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16380">A multitude of the strangest and most varied punishments assailed Gertrude’s heated and naïve imagination. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n204" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16381" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16419">The most likely seemed to be a return to the convent in Monza, where she would reappear no longer as the Signorina, but as a sinner, to be locked up until who knows when! And who knows how she would be treated! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n205" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16420" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16439">What most pained an imagination like hers, already so full of pain, was the fear of shame. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n206" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16440" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16505">Every sentence, every word, every comma, of that cursed letter passed through her mind again and again. She imagined them being observed, pondered by an unexpected reader, so different from the person to whom they were destined. She pictured them passing before the eyes of her mother, her brother, or goodness knows who. All else paled by comparison. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n207" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16506" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16547">Nor did the image of the boy who had been the source of the scandal fail to drop by frequently to torment the poor prisoner. Imagine the strange impression his phantom must have made in the company of the other ghostly visitors, who were so grave, so cold, so menacing, so unlike him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n208" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16548" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16592">But precisely because she could not separate him from them, nor go back momentarily to those fleeting pleasures without the immediate appearance of the suffering that had resulted, she gradually began to revisit them rarely, to repress her memories, to wean herself from them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n209" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16593" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16619">Nor did she dwell more at length or more willingly on the bright happy fantasies of the earlier days. They were too distant from her current circumstances, and from any likelihood of a future. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n210" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16620" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16647">The only castle that was not in the air, the only place where Gertrude could imagine a peaceful, honorable refuge, was the convent, which she had decided to enter, for eternity. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n211" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16648" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16668">Such a decision (she was certain) would take care of everything, settle every debt, and change her situation in an instant. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n212" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16669" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16715">The thoughts of what the rest of her life would be, it’s true, rebelled against this proposal. But times had changed. From the abyss into which she had fallen, and compared to the fears that sometimes gripped her, to become a nun who was feted, respected, and obeyed sounded comfortable. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n213" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16716" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16774">Her former aversion was attenuated by two very different and alternating sentiments: a fantastical, tender, devoted remorse over her offense; and pride, sharpened and aggravated by the manners of her jailer, who (often, it’s true, after being provoked by Gertrude) took revenge by instilling fear of that threatened punishment, or scolding her for her lapse. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n214" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16775" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16788">Later, to show her good side, the maid would adopt a protective tone that was even more odious than an insult. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n215" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16789" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16835">On these various occasions, Gertrude’s desire to escape from her jailer’s clutches and appear to her in a state superior to her current rage and pity became so vivid and sharp as to make anything that would fulfill it seem acceptable. — </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n216" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16836" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16885">One morning, after four or five long days of confinement, Gertrude, who had been provoked and enraged to an extreme by the teasing of her guard, threw herself into a corner of the room and sat there for a long time with her face hidden between her hands, seething. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n217" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16886" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16901">At the same moment she was overcome by the need to see other faces, to hear other words, to be treated differently. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n218" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16902" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16912">She thought of her father, her family. The thought retreated in terror. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n219" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16913" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16932">But she realized that it was up to her to befriend them, and she felt a sudden joy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n220" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16933" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16948">It was followed by a confusion, a sudden repentance for her sin, and an equal desire for atonement. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n221" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16949" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16967">She had already dwelt on this idea, but never before had she entered into it so ardently. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_cap9-n222" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_16968" targetEnd="quarantana/cap9.xml#c9_17009">She stood up from the corner, went to a desk, picked up the fatal pen once again, and wrote her father a letter filled with enthusiasm and contrition, affliction and hope, begging for his forgiveness, and showing herself ready to do all that she could, without conditions, to please he whom she had to please. </note>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>