<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>2022</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed: a novel</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
          <date>2022</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Michael Moore</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="english_2022_intro">
        <note xml:id="english_2022_intro-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10037">History can veritably be defined as an illustrious war against Time, for by emancipating the years it has imprisoned, and indeed reduced to corpses, it restores them to life, musters them for review and sends them forth into battle anew. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_intro-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10038" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10092">The illustrious Champions of History, however, who in this Conflict offer Masses of palm and laurel, plunder only the most glittering and opulent spoils, embalming with ink the Exploits of Princes and Potentates as well as other Eminences, embroidering gold and silk threads with the finest needle of their genius to form a perpetual tapestry of glorious Deeds. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_intro-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10093" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10155">Yet my feeble talent is unworthy of the sublime and perilous heights of such arguments, which wander amid Labyrinths, Political Intrigues, and the blaring of the Trumpets of War. Save that, having chanced upon news of memorable events that befell, admittedly, humble laborers of low birth, I gird myself to bequeath such memory to Posterity by relating the Tale, or rather the Report, in its unadorned truth. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_intro-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10156" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10181">In which upon a miniature theater one shall behold woeful Tragedies filled with Horrors and Scenes of great Wickedness, with interludes of heroic Feats and angelic goodness to counter the workings of the devil. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_intro-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10182" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10311">And verily, in the consideration that our climes are under the protection of our Lord the Catholic King, the Sun that never sets, and that above us shines, by reflected Light, the Moon that never wanes, the Hero of noble lineage, serving pro tempore in the King’s stead, and the Multitude of Senators, fixed stars, and the other Esteemed Magistrates, wandering planets casting light everywhere, thereby forming a most noble Firmament. So where shall we seek the cause for this world’s transformation into an Inferno of ever increasing tenebrous, wicked, and cruel actions by rash and reckless men if not in the diabolic arts and incantations, since human wickedness alone would not suffice to repel so many Heroes, who with eyes of Argus and arms of Briareus do traffic in public emoluments. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_intro-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10312" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10370">For which reason in relating this Tale that took place in my green years, whereas most of the persons who perform their parts herein have departed the Stage of the World, paying their tributes to the Fates, no mention shall be made of their names, that is of their family relations, also out of due respect. The same practice shall apply to places, for which only the general Territory shall be indicated. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_intro-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10371" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10412">Nor shall any man deem this a flaw in the tale, a defect in my rude Creation, lest the selfsame Censor be ignorant of Philosophy. The better schooled men are in Philosophy, the better will they observe that nothing is absent from said Narrative. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_intro-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10413" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10429">It being self-evident and universally subscribed to that names are nothing other than pure accidents… </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_intro-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10430" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10465">“By the time I have endured the heroic effort of transcribing this story from the manuscript’s faded chicken scratch and, as the saying goes, brought it to light, who will endure the effort of reading it?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_intro-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10466" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10496">This doubt occurred to me while I was struggling to decipher the scribble that came after the word accidents. It forced me to stop my copying and think more seriously about how best to proceed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_intro-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10497" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10525">“It may well be,” I said to myself as I leafed through the manuscript, “that this avalanche of conceits and figures of speech will not go on for the entire length of the work. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_intro-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10526" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10558">Our seventeenth-century friend wanted to flaunt his virtuosity at the beginning. Later, however, as the story goes on, and at times for long stretches, the style will become more natural and plain. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_intro-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10559" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10566">No doubt. But it’s so common! So vulgar! So full of mistakes! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_intro-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10567" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10580">Lombard idioms abound! Malapropisms, arbitrary grammar, mangled sentences. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_intro-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10581" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10643">Not to mention the Spanish flourishes tossed in here and there. What’s worse, in the most terrifying and heartrending parts of the story, which should inspire awe or reflection—in every passage, in short, that does indeed require some rhetoric, but a rhetoric that is discreet, refined, and tasteful—he never fails to serve up another helping of what we find in the introduction! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_intro-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10644" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10671">By cobbling together the most contradictory qualities with astonishing skill, he manages to sound both uncouth and affected on the same page, in the same sentence, and in the same word. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_intro-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10672" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10700">Out come the bombastic declamations, composed of pedestrian solecisms, and everywhere the ambitious awkwardness so characteristic of the writing of that century, at least in this country. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_intro-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10701" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10720">In short, it would be unpresentable to today’s readers. They are too sharp and too repelled by this type of extravagance. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_intro-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10721" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_107401">Thank goodness I realized this at the beginning of this wretched business. I wash my hands of it.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_intro-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10741" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10782">As I was closing the messy compilation to set it back on the shelf, however, it felt wrong for such a beautiful story to remain unknown. Because it was as a story, although the reader might disagree, that I found beautiful, I repeat, quite beautiful. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_intro-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10783" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10800">“Why not,” I thought, “take the series of events from the manuscript and rewrite them?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_intro-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10801" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10826">Hearing no reasonable objection, I immediately embraced this resolution, which is how the present book originated, as I have explained with a candor equal to the importance of the book. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_intro-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10827" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10879">Some of the events and certain customs described by our author seemed so new, so strange, to put it mildly, that before believing them, I needed to question other witnesses. So I pored through the records of the time, to see if that really was the way of the world in those days. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_intro-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10880" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10931">This inquiry cleared all my doubts. At every step I found similar and even more remarkable things. When I came across news of characters whose very existence I had doubted, having never heard of them outside of the manuscript, my mind was made up. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_intro-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10932" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10956">I will quote some of these documents, as needed, to lend credibility to things whose strangeness might make the reader inclined to deny them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_intro-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10957" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10971">But in rejecting our author’s diction as unacceptable, what shall I replace it with? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_intro-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10972" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10975">This is the crux of the matter. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_intro-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10976" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_11015">Anyone who barges in uninvited to redo another man’s work might be asked to render a strict accounting of his own, and, in a sense, is required to. This rule is both de facto and de jure, and I claim no immunity from it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_intro-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_11016" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_11062">Indeed, to be as compliant as possible, I had planned to provide a detailed explanation of the style of writing I adopted. With this in mind, throughout my work I tried to foresee every imaginable criticism, in order to offer a preemptive rebuttal. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_intro-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_11063" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_11104">Nor would this have been difficult, since (in all honesty) I could not think of a single criticism for which there was not a triumphant reply, and a reply of the type that does not so much settle questions as restate them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_intro-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_11105" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_11171">I often set two criticisms within arm’s reach of each other and let them fight it out. Or by examining them closely, comparing them carefully, I was able to discover and to prove that although they appeared to be contradictory, they made the same mistake of neglecting the facts and principles upon which their opinions should have been based. Then, to their great surprise, I put the two criticisms together and sent them both packing. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_intro-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_11172" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_11185">No author would ever have provided such solid proof that he had done a good job. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_intro-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_11186" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_11211">And then? When I was about to herd together all the objections and rebuttals and arrange them in some sort of order, Lord have mercy! They amounted to a book! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_2022_intro-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_11212" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_11262">So I set aside my proposal for two reasons with which the reader will certainly concur: the first, that it might seem ridiculous to write one book to justify another, or rather, its style; the second, that one book at a time is quite enough, if not too much. </note>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>