<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Supervisione codifica</resp>
          <persName xml:id="ER">Ersilia Russo</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="ML">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Leggo Manzoni. Quaranta commenti alla Quarantana</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Università di Bologna "Alma mater studiorum"</pubPlace>
        <date>2023</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed Lovers: a Milanese Story of the Seventeenth Century. With The Column of Infamy by Alessandro Manzoni. In Three Volumes</title>
          <editor xml:id="Ben">Pier Paolo Benucci</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans</publisher>
          <date>1845</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName xml:id="BP">Anonymous</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl xml:id="historiapatria">Giuseppe Ripamonti, Historia patria.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="raguaglio">Alessandro Tadino, Raguaglio dell’origine et giornali successi della gran peste contagiosa e malefica seguita nella città di Milano, e suo Ducato dall’anno 1629 all’anno 1632, Milano, 1648.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="LC">Lanfranco Caretti.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="sentirmessa">Alessandro Manzoni, Sentir messa.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduction, cap. 1 </p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="English_1845">
        <p xml:id="P1">
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n1" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10037">
          "Historie may bee truely defined as an illustrious warre waged aginste Time for snatching from his hands the Years his Prisoners, already become corpses; she brings them againe to life, passes them in review, and arranges them in line of Battle.        </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n2" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10038" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10092">
          But the illustrious Champions, who in this Arena reape a harvest of Palms and Laurels, bear off only the most magnificient and brilliant spoiles, embalmning with their ink the enterprizes of Princes, Potentates, and high and mighty Personages, mingling with the fine needle of the mind threads of Golde and Silk, which forme a perpetual embroiderie of glorious Actions.
          </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n3" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10093" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10155">
            However, it is not easy for my weaknesse to elevate itselfe to such arguments and to such dangerous sublimities, losing myselfe in the Labyrinthe of Political Intrigues and amidste the noise of sounding Brasse.
            Simply having a knowledge of some memorable facts, although merely relating to people of the base classe and of little importance, I prepare to hande down to Posterity a Memorie of them, giving a sincere and ingenious recital or, may bee, relation.
          </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n5" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10156" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10181">
            In which will bee seen, as in a narrow Play-house, mournful Tragedies of horrour and scenes of mighty wickednesse, with interludes of virtuous and angelick goodnesse opposed to diabolical operations.
          </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n6" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10182" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10311">
              And truly considering that our climes are situate under the empyre of the Catholick King our Lorde, who is the Sunne which never sets, and that above them, with a reflected light, like that of the Moone, which never wanes, shines forth the Hero of a noble Race, which pro tempore sways all lands, and that the illustrious Senators who are fixed Starrs, and the other respectable Magistrates, who are wandering Planets, shed light everywhere, thus forming a most noble Heaven, one can finde no other cause, seeing it changed into a Hell of dark actions, of wickednesse, and of crime, which daring men multiply ever more, save diabolical artes and charmes, since human malice by itselfe would bee unable to resist so many Heroes, who, with the eyes of Argus and the arms of Briareus, laboured for the publick good.
          </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n7" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10312" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10370">
              Therefore, in describing the events which occurred in the Spring of my Life, although the greater number of those persons who play their parts in this Historie have already departed from the Scene of this World, rendering themselves Tributaries to the Fates, we shall, from proper Respect keep silence with regarde to their names — this is to saye, their parental names; and the same regarde will be observed towards places, merely indicating the Territories generaliter. 
          </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n8" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10371" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10412">
              No one will say that this is an imperfection in the relation, or a deformity in my simple work, unlesse it bee some Critick who is abstaining from all Philosophical Food; for men, who are well versed in Philosophie, see clearly that the substance of the Narrative will lack nothing. 
          </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n9" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10413" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10429">
              For it is an evident thing, and not to bee denied, that names are but pure — the purest accidents —" 
          </note>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="P2">
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n10" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10431" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10465">
              But when I shall have had the heroic constancy to transcribe the history from this almost obliterated and illegible handwriting, when I shall have brought it to light, as people say, will there be any one found willing to endure the fatigue of reading it?
          </note>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="P3">
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n11" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10467" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10496">
              This reflection, arising from the labour of deciphering this scrawl, caused me to suspend my transcribing, and reflect more seriously upon what was proper to be done.
          </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n12" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10498" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10525">
              — "It is true," said I to myself, turning over the leaves of the manuscript, "it is true, that this hail of conceits and poetical images does not continue thus uninterruptedly throughout the entire work.
          </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n13" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10526" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10558">
              The good Roccoco has wished in the beginning to shew his power; later in the course of the narrative, and sometimes for whole passages together, the style proceeds in a far more natural and simple manner.
          </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n14" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10559" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10580">
              Yes; but then how vulgar he is! how unequal! how incorrect! Provincial idioms in abundance, phrases improperly applied, arbitrary grammatical constructions, halting periods.
          </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n15" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10581" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10611">
              And then this sprinkling of Spanish elegance; and then what is worse, in the most terrible or most affecting parts of the story, upon every occasion where the reader's surprise or thought should be excited,
          </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n15_0" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10612" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10626">
           in all those passages, in short, which certainly require a little rhetoric, but a grave, refined, tasteful sort of rhetoric, 
          </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n151" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10627" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10643">
        the good man never fails to return to his early style.
          </note>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="P4">
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n16" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10644" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10671">
              And then uniting with an admirable ability the most opposite qualities, he succeeds in being at once rough and affected, in the same page, in the same period, and even in the same word.
          </note>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="P5">
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n17" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10672" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10700">
              He presents us with bombastic declamations, composed of vulgar solecisms, and with that ambitious dulness which is the striking characteristic of our writers of that age.        </note>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="P6">
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n18" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10701" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10720">
              In truth, it is no fit work to present to readers of the present day; they are become too malicious, and too much disgusted with this species of extravagance.             </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n19" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10721" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10740">
              It is happy for me that this thought has occurred to me at the commencement of the unfortunate work, and I will wash my hands of it." 
          </note>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="P7">
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n20" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10741" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10782">
              In the very act of closing the old manuscript, so as to lay it aside, I felt grieved that so beautiful a history should remain entirely unknown; for as far as the history itself goes it might chance to appear equally beautiful to the reader — for as I say, it seemed to me beautiful, very beautiful.
          </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n21" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10783" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10800">
              Why could one not, thought I, take the series of events from the manuscript, and improve the style?
          </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n22" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10802" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10812">
              — no reasonable objection having presented itself, this resolution was immediately taken.  
          </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n23" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10813" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10826">
              And this is the origin of the present work, explained with a sincerity equal to the importance of the work itself.
          </note>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="P8">
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n24" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10827" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10879">
              Certain facts, and certain customs described by our author, appeared to us so novel, so strange, not to say improbable, that before giving credence to them we wished to question other witnesses, and therefore commenced searching among the memoirs of those times to discover whether really the world were then such as our author describes.
          </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n25" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10880" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10900">
              This research dissipated all our doubts; at every step we encountered something similar, perhaps even worse;
          </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n26" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10901" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10931">
              but what decided us yet more was to meet again with certain personages, regarding whose existence we had been in doubt, having only heard them spoken of in the manuscript.
          </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n26_1" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10932" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10956">
            Upon the proper occasions, we will quote these testimonials, to induce our readers to believe things which, from their strange character, they would be tempted to deny.
        </note>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="P9">
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n27" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10957" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10975">
              But rejecting as intolerable the style of our author, what style have we to substitute? Here is the difficulty.
          </note>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="P10">
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n28" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10976" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_10999">
              Whoever unrequested busies himself with repairing the work of another, exposes himself to the necessity of rendering an exact account of his own labours, and in a certain way contracts the obligation.
          </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n29" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_11000" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_11015">
              This is a rule of right and reason from which we do not in the least desire to screen ourselves.
          </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n30" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_11016" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_11037">
              Nay, even wishing to conform to it with a good grace, we had proposed to render here a minute account of the mode of writing which we have employed;
          </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n31" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_11038" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_11062">
              and with this object in view, during the whole of our labours, we have sought to divine all possible or probable criticisms with the intention of refuting them in anticipation.
          </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n32" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_11063" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_11104">
              Neither would the difficulty have been here, since — our love of truth obliges us to confess — no criticism presented itself to our mind without bringing a triumphal answer along with it, one of those answers which we do not say solve the question, but change it.
          </note>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="P11">
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n33" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_11105" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_11171">
              Often also opposing two criticisms, we caused them to combat one with the other; or examining them well, or comparing them attentively, we succeeded in discovering and proving that, opposed as they might seem in appearance, they were nevertheless of the same species, and both occasioned by a want of proper attention to the facts and principles upon which a judgment should be formed. 
          </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n34" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_11172" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_11185">
              There certainly never was a writer who could prove so clearly that he was right.
          </note>
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n35" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_11186" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_11211">
              But what? when we were about to arrange all these objections and replies in some order, alas! we found ourself on the point of writing another book. 
          </note>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="P12">
          <note xml:id="English_1845-n36" type='comm' target="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_11212" targetEnd="quarantana/intro.xml#intro_11262">
              Perceiving this, we banished the idea, from two reasons, which the reader will certainly find conclusive: the first, because a book written to justify another, or rather the style of another, might appear ridiculous; the second, because one book at a time is enough, especially when the book is not a profitable one.
          </note>
        </p>
      </div>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
