<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Codifica automatizzata</resp>
          <persName xml:id="P1">Maria Levchenko</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>Scheda editoriale</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Penguin Random House</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>1972</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Alessandro Manzoni</author>
          <title>The Betrothed: a novel</title>
          <editor>Angelini, Cesare</editor>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Penguin Random House</publisher>
          <date>1972</date>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Translated by</resp>
            <persName>Bruce Penman</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Introduzione, cap. 1</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="english_1972_cap6">
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n1" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10001" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10014">‘In what way can I be of assistance to you?’ said Don Rodrigo, taking up his stance in the middle of the room. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n2" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10015" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10040">His words were as we have just reported them; but his way of uttering them plainly said: remember to whom you are speaking, consider what you are saying, and be brief. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n3" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10041" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10060">Now there was no swifter nor surer way of putting fresh heart into Father Cristoforo than to treat him in a high-handed manner. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n4" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10061" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10110">He had been in a state of uncertainty, searching for words, and running the beads of the rosary at his belt through his fingers, as if he hoped to find a suggestion for his opening remarks concealed in one of them; but Don Rodrigo’s manner had such an effect on him that he felt more words coming to his lips than he needed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n5" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10111" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10156">But he remembered how important it was not to damage his own interests, or, more vital still, the interests of others, and he revised and softened the phrases which thronged into his mind. With cautious humility, he said: ‘I have come to suggest an act of justice, to implore an act of charity. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n6" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10157" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10187">Certain men of evil life have made use of your honour’s name to terrorize a poor curé, to prevent him from doing his duty and to deprive a pair of innocent people of their rights. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n7" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10188" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10211">With one word you can confound those wicked men, restore power to the forces of righteousness and raise up those who have been so cruelly cast down. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n8" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10212" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10218">You can do it, I repeat, and the influence of conscience, of honour …’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n9" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10219" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10230">‘You may speak to me about my conscience, when I present myself to you for confession. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n10" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10231" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10266">As for my honour, I would have you know that I am its sole guardian. If anyone tries to argue with me about the way I guard my honour, in my eyes he is making a presumptuous attack on me.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n11" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10267" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10332">Father Cristoforo could see from these words that Don Rodrigo would take everything he said in the worst possible sense, and try to turn the conversation into a quarrel, to prevent him from getting to grips with the real problem. So the friar summoned up fresh stocks of patience, and resolved to swallow whatever insults the other might choose to utter. He quickly answered in a submissive tone: ‘If I have said anything that displeases you, it was certainly contrary to my intention. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n12" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10333" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10348">Pray correct me, and reprove me, if I show myself unable to speak in a suitable manner; but I beg you to hear me out. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n13" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10349" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10400">For the love of Heaven, and of the God before whose presence we must all one day appear –’ (as he said these words, he took the little wooden death’s-head on his rosary between his fingers, and held it up before the eyes of his scowling listener) – ‘do not be obstinate in the denial of an act of justice which is so easy to perform, and so clearly due to those poor folk. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n14" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10401" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10421">Remember that God has them always in his sight, and that their cries and their groans are heard on high. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n15" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10422" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10426">Innocence is a mighty thing in his …’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n16" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10427" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10464">‘Father Cristoforo!’ said Don Rodrigo abruptly, ‘I have the greatest respect for the habit you wear; but if anything could make me forget that respect, it would be to see the habit on the back of a man who dared to enter this house as a spy.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n17" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10465" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10497">This last word brought a flush to the friar’s face, but he went on with the air of a man swallowing a very bitter medicine: ‘You know that I do not deserve the name of spy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n18" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10498" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10515">You know in your heart that there is nothing cowardly or contemptible about the errand on which I have come. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n19" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10516" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10536">Listen to my words, sir; God forbid that the day should ever come when you repent of not having listened to them. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n20" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10537" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10561">Do not put your own glory – and what sort of glory can it be called, Don Rodrigo, even in the sight of men! – while in the sight of God … You, sir, have much power here below, but …’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n21" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10562" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10594">‘Are you aware’, said Don Rodrigo, interrupting him angrily, but not without an inward shudder of fear, ‘that any time the fancy takes me to hear a sermon, I am quite capable of finding my own way to church, like anyone else? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n22" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10595" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10616">But in my own house …! – Ah, I see it now!’ he went on, with a forced, mocking smile. ‘You want to give me more than my due. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n23" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10617" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10625">The services of a private chaplain – that is the privilege of a prince.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n24" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10626" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10667">‘And the same God who expects princes to account for the use they make of his Word, which he causes them to hear in their palaces, the same God in his great mercy sends you his servant, wretched and unworthy though he may be, on behalf of an innocent girl …’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n25" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10668" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10698">‘Well, Father Cristoforo,’ said Don Rodrigo, moving towards the door, ‘I have no idea what you are talking about, except that there seems to be some girl who means a great deal to you. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n26" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10699" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10720">You can go and inflict your confidences on anyone you like; but don’t take the liberty of wasting any more of a gentleman’s time with them.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n27" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10721" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10774">When Don Rodrigo moved toward the door, the friar stood in his way, very respectfully, raising his hands in supplication, and also in order to prevent his escape. ‘It is true that the girl means a great deal to me,’ he said, ‘but I care just as much about you … two souls that mean more to me than my own life. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n28" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10775" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10792">Don Rodrigo! the only thing I can do for you is to pray for you; but I shall do it with all my heart. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n29" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10793" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10807">Do not reject my appeal; do not keep a poor innocent girl in anguish and terror. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n30" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10808" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10814">One word from you can put everything right.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n31" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10815" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10836">‘Very well,’ said Don Rodrigo, ‘since you believe that I can do so much for this person; since this person means so much to you …’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n32" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10837" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10861">‘Yes …?’ said Father Cristoforo anxiously; for Don Rodrigo’s attitude and expression did not inspire confidence in the hope suggested by his words. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n33" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10862" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10872">‘Then advise her to come and place herself under my protection. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n34" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10873" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10886">She will lack nothing, and no one will dare to molest her, as sure as I am a knight.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n35" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10887" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10898">The friar had controlled his indignation up to this point with some difficulty, but now it burst out. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n36" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10899" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10927">All his good resolutions of calm and prudence went up in smoke. His old character found itself for once in complete accord with his new one. On occasions like this, Fra Cristoforo really had the strength of two men. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n37" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10928" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10963">‘Your protection!’ he cried, stepping back a couple of paces. Poised boldly on his right foot, with his right hand on his hip, he raised the other hand with forefinger outstretched towards Don Rodrigo, and looked him straight in the eye, with a furious glare. ‘Your protection indeed! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n38" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10964" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10977">It is just as well that you used those words, that you made that infamous proposal to me. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n39" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10978" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10986">You have filled the measure even to overflowing, and I no longer fear you.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n40" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10987" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10989">‘What language is this, friar?’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n41" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_10990" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11005">‘The right language to use to a man abandoned by God, who can no longer inspire fear. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n42" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11006" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11008">You speak of your protection. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n43" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11009" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11039">I knew before that the poor innocent was under the protection of God, but now you have made me feel the truth of it with such certainty that I no longer need to choose my words. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n44" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11040" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11056">Her name is Lucia – see with how high a head and how steady a gaze I pronounce it.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n45" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11057" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11060">‘What! In my own house …’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n46" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11061" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11071">‘I pity this house; the curse of God is hanging over it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n47" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11072" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11089">You will see if the justice of God can be overawed by a few bricks, or terrorized by a few hired thugs. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n48" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11090" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11107">You believe that God made a creature in his own image to give you the pleasure of tormenting her. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n49" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11108" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11121">You think that God will not defend her, and you despise his warning! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n50" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11122" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11124">You have judged yourself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n51" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11125" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11138">The heart of Pharaoh was as hard as yours; but God knew the way to break it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n52" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11139" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11160">Lucia is safe from you. I tell you so, poor friar as I am; and as for you yourself, you shall hear what I have to tell you. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n53" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11161" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11163">A day will come …’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n54" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11164" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11193">Up to this point, Don Rodrigo had been suspended between rage and amazement, too stunned to speak. But now that the friar’s words took on this prophetic note, a hint of mysterious terror was added to the anger that he felt. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n55" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11194" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11218">He reached out and grabbed that threatening hand; and, raising his voice to drown the words of the prophet of doom, he shouted: ‘Get away from me, you presumptuous peasant, and take that coward’s uniform with you.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n56" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11219" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11229">The sheer clarity of these words brought immediate calm to Fra Cristoforo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n57" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11230" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11280">Abuse and insult had been associated in his mind, so thoroughly and for such a long time with patient suffering and silent acceptance that this mode of address calmed his wrath and quenched his fires, and left him with nothing but a firm resolution to listen quietly to whatever Don Rodrigo might care to add. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n58" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11281" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11321">He gently withdrew his hand from the nobleman’s clutch, lowered his head, and stayed motionless; just as, when the wind drops in the middle of a great storm, a tempest-tossed oak reverts to its natural shape, spreading out its branches to receive the hail which heaven sends. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n59" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11322" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11331">‘You behave like what you are,’ Don Rodrigo went on, ‘a yokel educated above his station. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n60" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11332" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11358">You can thank the robe that covers your rascally back for protecting you from the blows we usually give your sort, to teach them how to speak to their betters. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n61" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11359" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11369">You can leave on your own two feet this time; and we’ll see what happens next.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n62" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11370" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11406">He pointed, with imperious contempt, towards a door facing the one by which they had come in. Father Cristoforo bowed his head and went out, leaving Don Rodrigo pacing fiercely up and down the field of battle. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n63" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11407" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11450">The friar shut the door behind him, and looked round the room where he now stood. He saw a man creeping away along the wall very quietly, as if to avoid detection from the room where the interview had taken place. He recognized the old servant who had opened the front door to him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n64" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11451" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11475">The old man had served that family for perhaps forty years, since before Don Rodrigo was born. His first master had been Don Rodrigo’s father, a very different sort of man. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n65" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11476" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11547">On his death the new master had made a clean sweep of most of the servants, bringing in new faces; but he had kept on this particular retainer, partly because he was already an old man, and partly because, although his principles and habits were entirely different from those of Don Rodrigo, he had two compensating virtues – a high opinion of the dignity of the house, and a profound knowledge of ceremonial, of which he knew the oldest traditions and the minutest details better than anyone else. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n66" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11548" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11625">In his master’s presence the poor old man would never have ventured even to hint at his disapproval of the things he saw happening all day long, much less to express it openly. Even with his fellow-servants, the most he would allow himself was an occasional exclamation, a rebuke muttered between his teeth. They used to laugh at him, and sometimes amused themselves by egging him on to say more than he intended, or to sing the praises of the old way of life in that house in earlier days. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n67" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11626" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11655">His criticisms never reached his master’s ears except as part of an account of the merriment they had caused; and so Don Rodrigo treated them with mockery but without resentment. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n68" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11656" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11670">On days of festivity and hospitality the old man came into his own again as a serious and important personage. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n69" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11671" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11714">Father Cristoforo looked at him in passing, bade him good day, and was walking on; but the old man came up to him with a mysterious air, put his finger to his lips, and then motioned him, with the same finger, towards a dark passage. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n70" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11715" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11730">When they were there, he said, ‘Father, I heard everything, and I must talk to you.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n71" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11731" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11734">‘Be quick about it then, my good fellow.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n72" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11735" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11753">‘I can’t talk here. It would be terrible if the master caught me … but I’ve many things to tell you. I’ll try and come to the monastery tomorrow.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n73" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11754" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11756">‘Is there some plot afoot?’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n74" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11757" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11768">‘There’s something in the air, for certain; I’d noticed it earlier on. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n75" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11769" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11777">But now I’ll keep a special watch, and with luck I’ll find out all about it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n76" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11778" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11781">Leave it to me. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n77" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11782" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11796">The things I have to hear and see! Flames of hell … what a house I serve! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n78" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11797" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11802">But I want to save my own soul.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n79" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11803" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11834">‘The Lord bless you!’ said the friar softly, laying his hand on the servant’s head. Though older than the friar, he stood before him with bowed head, like a son. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n80" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11835" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11846">‘The Lord will reward you,’ added Father Cristoforo. ‘Be sure to come tomorrow.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n81" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11847" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11863">‘I will,’ said the servant. ‘But now you must go at once, father. And for God’s sake, never mention my name.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n82" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11864" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11907">He looked round, and went along the passage to another room, which opened into the courtyard. Seeing that the coast was clear, he called the good father, whose face conveyed a surer answer to the last appeal than any verbal protestation could have done. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n83" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11908" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11919">The servant pointed the way to the great door, and the friar went off without another word. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n84" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11920" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11931">The man had listened at his master’s door. Had he done well? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n85" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11932" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11940">And did Father Cristoforo do well to praise him for it? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n86" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11941" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11960">According to the commonest and most unquestioned rules of conduct, it was a most unseemly action. But could this particular case not be regarded as an exception? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n87" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11961" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11971">And can there be exceptions to the commonest and most unquestioned rules? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n88" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11972" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11984">These are important matters, which the reader can decide for himself, if he feels like it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n89" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11985" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11997">We do not propose to sit in judgement; it is enough to for us to have facts to relate. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n90" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_11998" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12040">Once outside, Father Cristoforo turned his back on that house of ill omen, and began to breathe more freely. He hastened down the hillside, very red in the face, deeply stirred and confused, as anyone can imagine, both by what had been said to him and by what he had said himself. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n91" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12041" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12082">But the totally unexpected approach which the old servant had made to him cheered him greatly. He felt that Heaven had given him a visible sign of its favour. ‘This is a thread,’ he said to himself, ‘a thread which Providence has put into my hand. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n92" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12083" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12095">In that very house! and without the idea of seeking it there having even crossed my mind!’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n93" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12096" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12122">As he thought these things over, he raised his eyes toward the west, saw the sun very low in the sky, scarcely clearing the mountain top opposite, and realized there was very little time left before nightfall. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n94" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12123" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12175">Though his bones ached heavily within him after all the varied ill usage of the day, he quickened his pace. He wanted to make his report, dismal as it was, to the friends who trusted in him, and get back to the monastery before the gates were shut for the night. (This was one of the most definite and strictly enforced rules of the Capuchin order.) </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n95" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12176" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12195">Meanwhile in Lucia’s cottage certain plans had been put forward and carefully considered, about which the reader should now be informed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n96" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12196" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12241">After the departure of the friar, the three of them had spent some time in gloomy silence. Lucia was sadly preparing dinner; Renzo was trying to make up his mind to go home, away from the heartbroken sight she presented, but could not manage it. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n97" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12242" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12259">Agnese was to all appearance intent on her spinning-wheel; but she was really thinking out a plan. When it was ready, she broke the silence with these words: </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n98" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12260" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12261">‘Listen, children! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n99" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12262" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12300">If you’ll show you’ve got a stout heart and a quick hand; if you’ll trust your mother, both of you’ – the words ‘mother’ and ‘both of you’ made Lucia jump – ‘I’ll undertake to get you out of this trouble, better and quicker perhaps than Father Cristoforo, wonderful man as he is.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n100" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12301" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12333">Lucia stood still, and looked her with an expression that showed more amazement than belief in so splendid a promise. Renzo quickly said ‘Stout heart? quick hand? Go on – tell us what we can do.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n101" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12334" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12348">‘Well then; don’t you agree’, said Agnese, ‘that if you two were married it would be quite a step forward? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n102" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12349" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12359">Wouldn’t the rest be easier afterwards?’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n103" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12360" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12387">‘No doubt about that,’ said Renzo. ‘Once we’re married … we’d have the world to choose from; and there’s the territory of Bergamo, not far from here at all, where silk workers are welcomed with open arms. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n104" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12388" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12426">You know how many times my cousin Bortolo has said I ought to join him there and make my fortune, like he has. The only reason I’ve never gone is … well, because of Lucia here. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n105" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12427" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12453">If we were married we could all go together, and set up house there, and live in God’s own peace, out of the clutches of that blackguard, away from the temptation to do anything silly. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n106" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12454" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12456">Isn’t that true, now, Lucia?’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n107" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12457" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12461">‘It’s true, right enough,’ said Lucia, ‘but how in the world …’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n108" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12462" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12476">‘It’s the way I said just now,’ replied her mother. ‘With a stout heart and a quick hand, it’ll be easy.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n109" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12477" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12492">‘Easy?’ said Renzo and Lucia together, thinking how strangely and painfully difficult the whole thing had become. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n110" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12493" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12498">‘Yes, easy, once you see how to do it,’ replied Agnese. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n111" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12499" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12505">‘Listen carefully, and I’ll try to explain. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n112" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12506" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12541">This is something I’ve heard from people who know what they’re talking about, and in fact I’ve seen a case of it myself. If you want to have a wedding, you must have a priest, but he doesn’t have to agree to it; it’s enough for him to be there.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n113" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12542" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12547">‘Whatever do you mean?’ asked Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n114" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12548" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12550">‘Listen – I’ll tell you then. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n115" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12551" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12559">You need two witnesses – quick-witted, willing lads. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n116" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12560" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12575">You go to the curé’s house – and the thing is to catch him when he isn’t expecting you, so that he can’t get away. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n117" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12576" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12592">The man says “Your Reverence, this is my wife”, and the woman says “Your Reverence, this is my husband.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n118" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12593" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12614">As long as the curé hears the words, and the witnesses hear them too, it’s a valid marriage, just as sacred as if the Pope had done it for you. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n119" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12615" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12633">Once the words have been said, the curé can scream and shout as much as he likes; it doesn’t alter the fact that you’re man and wife.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n120" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12634" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12636">‘Can it really be true?’ cried Lucia. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n121" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12637" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12660">‘Why,’ said Agnese, ‘do you think that I never learnt anything at all in the thirty years I spent in this world before either of you were born? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n122" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12661" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12693">It’s the truth I’m telling you, and to prove it, one of my friends wanted to marry a man whose parents wouldn’t agree to it, and it worked all right for her. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n123" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12694" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12736">The curé suspected what they had in mind, and was on his guard; but those two clever devils managed so well, that they caught him at the right moment, said their piece, and became man and wife; though the poor girl was sorry enough for what she had done only three days later.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n124" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12737" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12815">Agnese was quite right about it being possible, and also about it being dangerous if it went wrong. For the only people who tried this route to matrimony were those who had met with some obstacle or been denied passage by the ordinary one; and consequently the priests did their very best to avoid being caught up in any such forced cooperation. If a curé was surprised by one of those couples and their witnesses, he always struggled furiously to get out of it, like Proteus escaping from the hands of those who wanted to compel him to prophesy. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n125" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12816" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12826">‘If only it were true, Lucia!’ said Renzo, with a pleading, expectant look. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n126" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12827" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12832">‘What do you mean, “If it were true”?’ demanded Agnese. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n127" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12833" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12838">‘So you think I’m talking nonsense too! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n128" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12839" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12858">I do my best for you, and you won’t even believe what I say. All right then – get out of your troubles by yourselves! I wash my hands of the whole thing.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n129" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12859" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12865">‘No, no; don’t do that,’ said Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n130" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12866" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12874">‘I only said what I did because it sounded too good to be true. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n131" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12875" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12886">I’m in your hands; I look on you as if you were really my own mother.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n132" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12887" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12905">At these words Agnese recovered from her fit of pique, and forgot her vow to leave them to their fate, which was never a very serious one anyway. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n133" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12906" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12927">‘But why didn’t Father Cristoforo think of this way out, then?’ said Lucia, in her gentle, submissive way. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n134" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12928" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12939">‘He’ll have thought of it, right enough,’ said Agnese. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n135" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12940" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12945">‘But he wouldn’t want to tell us about it.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n136" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12946" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12953">‘Why not?’ said Lucia and Renzo together. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n137" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12954" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12970">‘Because … because … if you must know, the clergy say that it isn’t really right to do that.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n138" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12971" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12986">‘How can it be wrong to do something, if it’s right when it’s done?’ asked Renzo.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n139" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12987" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12993">‘How should I know?’ said Agnese. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n140" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_12994" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13009">‘They make the rules to suit themselves; and we poor folk can’t understand them all. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n141" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13010" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13013">There are so many things like that. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n142" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13014" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13023">Look, it’s like giving someone a punch on the jaw. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n143" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13024" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13039">You shouldn’t do it at all; but once you’ve done it, not even the Pope can undo it again.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n144" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13040" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13051">‘If it isn’t really right,’ said Lucia, ‘we’d better not do it.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n145" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13052" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13065">‘Nonsense!’ said Agnese. ‘Do you think I’d give you a piece of advice that hadn’t the fear of God in it? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n146" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13066" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13099">If it were against the wishes of your parents, now, so that you could marry some good-for-nothing fellow … but as it is, I’m happy about it; and it’s Renzo here you want to marry; and the man who’s making the difficulties is that blackguard; and the curé…’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n147" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13100" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13106">‘Anyone would understand why we’d had to do it,’ said Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n148" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13107" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13150">‘We mustn’t tell Father Cristoforo about this until after we’ve done it,’ said Agnese. ‘But once it’s done and turned out all right, what do you suppose the good father will say to you? “Ah, my dear daughter, that was very wrong of you! You’ve let me down!” The clergy have to talk like that. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n149" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13151" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13161">But you can be quite sure that in his own heart he’ll be very pleased about it.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n150" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13162" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13185">Though Lucia could not find any answer to this argument, she did not seem convinced. But Renzo was greatly heartened, and said, ‘Well, if it’s really true, the thing’s as good as done.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n151" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13186" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13188">‘Steady a moment now!’ said Agnese. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n152" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13189" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13191">‘What about the witnesses? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n153" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13192" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13201">How are you going to find two of them with courage to do the job and enough sense to keep quiet about it in the meantime? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n154" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13202" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13217">And how are you going to get hold of the priest, who’s locked himself up in his own house this last couple of days? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n155" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13218" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13251">And then you’ve got to get him to stay put – for though he’s a heavy man, he’ll be as nimble as a kitten when he sees the four of you arrive, and you won’t see him for dust.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n156" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13252" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13274">‘I’ve got it !’ said Renzo, bringing his fist down on the table, and jingling the cutlery which lay there ready for dinner. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n157" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13275" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13288">And he told them his plan, which Agnese fully approved. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n158" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13289" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13296">‘It’s a trick,’ said Lucia. ‘It’s not … straightforward. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n159" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13297" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13313">Up to now we’ve been honest about this; let’s have faith, and go on in the same way. God will help us; Father Cristoforo said so. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n160" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13314" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13317">Let’s listen to his advice.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n161" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13318" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13331">‘Be guided by those who know more than you do,’ said Agnese with a grave expression. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n162" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13332" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13337">‘What do you need more advice for? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n163" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13338" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13342">God’s message is: “I help those who help themselves.” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n164" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13343" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13349">We’ll tell Father Cristoforo about it after it’s done.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n165" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13350" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13356">‘Lucia,’ said Renzo, ‘surely you won’t let me down now? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n166" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13357" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13366">We’ve done everything we should have done, like good Christians. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n167" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13367" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13373">Isn’t it true that we ought by rights to be man and wife already? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n168" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13374" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13398">The curé fixed the day for our wedding himself … and whose fault is it if we’ve got to use a bit of cunning now? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n169" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13399" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13402">No, I know you won’t let me down. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n170" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13403" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13408">I’ll be back presently with some news for you.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n171" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13409" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13424">He bade farewell to Lucia with an imploring look, and to Agnese with a glance of complicity; and hurried away. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n172" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13425" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13467">Tribulations sharpen the wits. In the straight and narrow path which his life had previously followed, Renzo had never had occasion to put much of an extra edge on his mental faculties. But on this occasion he had thought up a scheme which would have done credit to a lawyer. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n173" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13468" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13518">His plan took him straight to the cottage of his friend Tonio, who lived near by. He found him in his kitchen, with one knee on the fender; on the hot coals in front of him was a round pan, which he held by the rim with one hand, while he stirred its contents – a small grey buckwheat polenta – with a curved wooden spoon which he held in the other. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n174" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13519" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13552">Tonio’s mother, brother and wife were sitting at the table, and three or four little boys were standing round their father, with their eyes fixed on the pan, waiting for him to dish up. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n175" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13553" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13572">But the scene lacked the gaiety which the sight of dinner normally imparts to a group of people who have earned it by their labours. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n176" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13573" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13612">The size of the polenta was proportionate to the quality of the harvest, not to the number and the enthusiasm of the assembled company. They were all staring at the communal dish with a grim look of rabid desire, every one of them obviously thinking of the amount of hunger that would still be with him after the meal. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n177" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13613" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13644">While Renzo exchanged greetings with the family, Tonio ladled the polenta on to the beechwood platter which was ready to receive it. The polenta looked like a very small moon surrounded by a large nimbus of vapour. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n178" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13645" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13692">Yet the women still said politely to Renzo, ‘Will you do us the honour of joining us at table?’ – words which the peasants of Lombardy, and of many other lands, will always say to anyone who finds them at dinner, even if he is a wealthy glutton and they are down to their last mouthful. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n179" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13693" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13722">‘Thank you,’ said Renzo, ‘but I only came to have a quick word with Tonio. Look, Tonio, we don’t want to disturb the womenfolk, let’s go and eat at the inn, and we can talk there.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n180" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13723" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13763">Tonio found this a surprising suggestion, but all the more welcome-for that. Both the children (for children understand these things from a very early age) and the women were far from sorry to see the polenta relieved from one of the claims outstanding against it – the most formidable of those claims in fact. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n181" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13764" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13773">Tonio asked no questions, but went off with Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n182" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13774" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13832">They reached the inn; they sat down in perfect solitude, for poverty had weaned all the customers of that haven of delight from the habit of going there; they ordered up the little that the place had to offer; they drank a glass of wine apiece; and then Renzo said mysteriously to Tonio: ‘If you’ll do a little thing for me, I’ll do a big thing for you.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n183" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13833" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13839">‘Just name it,’ said Tonio, pouring out another glass. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n184" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13840" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13846">‘There’s nothing I wouldn’t do for you today.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n185" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13847" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13865">‘Well, you owe the curé twenty-five lire rent for that field you hired from him last year.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n186" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13866" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13872">‘Ah, Renzo, Renzo, you’re spoiling my treat. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n187" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13873" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13885">Why bring that up, just when I was beginning to feel better?’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n188" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13886" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13905">‘The only reason I mentioned the debt’, said Renzo, ‘is that I’ve got it in mind to give you a chance of paying it.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n189" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13906" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13907">‘Do you mean it?’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n190" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13908" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13908">‘I do. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n191" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13909" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13911">D’you like the idea?’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n192" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13912" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13912">‘Do I like it? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n193" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13913" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13917">I should think I do! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n194" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13918" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13941">If it was only so that I wouldn’t have to see the reverend gentleman grimace and shake his head at me any more, every time he’d be meeting me in the road! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n195" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13942" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13953">With his “Don’t forget now, Tonio!” – and his “Tonio, when are you coming to see me about that little matter?” </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n196" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13954" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13980">It’s got to the point where if he happens to look at me while he’s preaching, I’m afraid he’ll take twenty-five lire as the text of his sermon! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n197" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13981" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13986">To hell with his twenty-five lire! </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n198" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_13987" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14003">Besides he’d have to give me back my wife’s gold necklace, and I’d soon turn that into good polenta. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n199" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14004" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14004">But …’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n200" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14005" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14018">‘There’s no buts about it. If you’ll give me a little bit of help, the money’s in your pocket.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n201" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14019" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14020">‘Go on – tell me what it is, then.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n202" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14021" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14028">‘Not a word to anyone, mind!’ said Renzo, putting a finger to his lips. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n203" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14029" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14036">‘No need to say that. You know me well enough.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n204" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14037" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14059">‘His Reverence keeps on bringing up a lot of silly excuses for putting off my wedding, and I don’t want to wait any longer. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n205" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14060" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14090">Now I’m told that it’s quite certain that if my girl and I appear in front of him with two witnesses, and I say “This is my wife” and she says “This is my husband”, we’ll be as truly man and wife as if he’d married us in church. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n206" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14091" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14093">Do you follow me?’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n207" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14094" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14099">‘You want me to be a witness for you?’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n208" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14100" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14101">‘That’s it.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n209" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14102" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14108">‘And you’ll pay off the twenty-five lire for me?’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n210" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14109" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14113">‘I will.’ ‘Done, then!’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n211" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14114" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14119">‘But we’ll have to find a second witness.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n212" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14120" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14121">‘I’ve found one already. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n213" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14122" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14133">My fool of a brother Gervaso will do whatever I tell him. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n214" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14134" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14138">You’ll buy him a drink, of course?’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n215" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14139" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14143">‘And a meal,’ said Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n216" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14144" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14154">‘We’ll bring him here and have a party for the three of us … but can he do what’s wanted?’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n217" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14155" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14168">‘I’ll tell him what to do; you know I’ve got his share of brains as well as my own.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n218" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14169" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14169">‘Tomorrow then.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n219" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14170" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14170">‘Good.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n220" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14171" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14172">‘Towards evening.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n221" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14173" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14173">‘Better still.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n222" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14174" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14183">‘And remember!’ said Renzo, putting his finger to his lips again. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n223" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14184" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14205">‘Bah!’ said Tonio, drooping his head towards his right shoulder, and raising his left hand, with a look on his face which said ‘You’re doing me wrong.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n224" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14206" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14216">‘But what if your wife asks you a lot of questions, as she probably will …?’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n225" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14217" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14238">‘I’ll tell her some lies then. I owe her a good few over the years; so many, in fact, that I don’t think I’ll ever catch up with her. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n226" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14239" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14248">I’ll find some story that’ll quieten her down.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n227" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14249" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14260">‘We can have a longer talk about it tomorrow morning’, said Renzo, ‘and arrange all the details.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n228" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14261" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14284">They left the inn, and Tonio walked home, trying to think of a good story for his womenfolk, while Renzo went off to tell Agnese and Lucia what had been agreed. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n229" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14285" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14295">In the meantime Agnese had tried hard to win her daughter over, but in vain. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n230" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14296" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14328">Lucia met every argument with one or other of her pair of logical alternatives: either the whole thing is wrong and we shouldn’t do it, she said, or else it isn’t wrong and why not tell Father Cristoforo about it? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n231" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14329" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14365">Renzo came back glowing with triumph, and told them what he had done, ending with the words ‘What d’you think of that?’, in a tone of voice which conveyed: Haven’t I played the part of a man? and Could there be a better answer? and Would you ever have thought of that for yourselves? and a dozen other similar messages. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n232" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14366" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14414">Lucia gently shook her head, but the other two enthusiasts took no notice of her, as if she were a child, who could not be expected to understand the ins and outs of what was going on, but could be cajoled or compelled to do what was required of her later on. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n233" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14415" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14426">‘That’s fine,’ said Agnese, ‘that’s fine; but there’s one thing you haven’t thought of.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n234" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14427" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14431">‘What’s that, then?’ said Renzo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n235" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14432" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14438">‘You haven’t thought about Perpetua. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n236" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14439" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14467">She’ll let in Tonio and his brother all right, but not you two! She’ll have orders to keep you away from his Reverence as if you were small boys and he were a pear-tree.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n237" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14468" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14474">‘What shall we do, then?’ said Renzo, slightly confused. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n238" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14475" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14479">‘Listen – I’ve thought of something. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n239" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14480" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14503">I’ll come with you myself; there’s something only I know that’ll draw her like a magnet, and put such a spell on her that she won’t even see you’re there, and you can go straight in. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n240" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14504" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14512">I’ll call her to me, and I’ll touch the right string … you’ll see.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n241" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14513" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14525">‘Bless you for it!’ cried Renzo. ‘I’ve always said you were our best help in everything.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n242" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14526" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14547">‘But all this is no good,’ said Agnese, ‘if we can’t persuade Lucia here that it isn’t a sin.’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n243" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14548" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14562">Renzo added his eloquence to Agnese’s, but Lucia would not budge an inch. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n244" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14563" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14593">‘I can’t answer all these arguments of yours,’ she said, ‘but I can see that if it’s your way we take, every yard of it’s paved with tricks, lies and deceit. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n245" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14594" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14599">Oh Renzo! that’s not the way we started out together. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n246" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14600" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14636">I want to be your wife’ – she still couldn’t say the word, or express the wish, without a blush – ‘but I want it to be in an honest, God-fearing way, in front of the altar. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n247" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14637" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14641">Leave it to God to find the way. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n248" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14642" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14660">Don’t you think he knows how to help us, better than we can help ourselves with all those lying tricks? </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n249" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14661" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14667">And why keep Father Cristoforo in the dark about it?’ </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n250" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14668" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14707">The argument was still going on, and showed no signs of being near its end, when a rapid clatter of sandalled feet, and a sound of flapping robes like the wind in a slackened sail, announced the arrival of Father Cristoforo. </note>
        <note xml:id="english_1972_cap6-n251" type="comm" target="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14708" targetEnd="quarantana/cap6.xml#c6_14727">They all fell silent, and Agnese scarcely had time to whisper in Lucia’s ear: ‘Mind you don’t tell him anything now!’ </note>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>